[
  {
    "id": "nPwDAPpBUUrYKsRB",
    "question": "The power factor of $$AC$$ circuit having resistance $$(R)$$ and inductance $$(L)$$ connected in series and an angular velocity $$\\omega $$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$R/\\omega L$$ ",
      "$$R/{\\left( {{R^2} + {\\omega ^2}{L^2}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$ ",
      "$$\\omega L/R$$ ",
      "$$R/{\\left( {{R^2} - {\\omega ^2}{L^2}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$R/{\\left( {{R^2} + {\\omega ^2}{L^2}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "lydY8ehUtKC26aZ0",
    "question": "In an $$LCR$$ series $$a.c.$$ circuit, the voltage across each of the components, $$L,C$$ and $$R$$ is $$50V$$. The voltage across the $$L.C$$ combination will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$100V$$ ",
      "$$50\\sqrt 2 $$ ",
      "$$50$$ $$V$$ ",
      "$$0$$ $$V$$ (zero) "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$0$$ $$V$$ (zero) "
  },
  {
    "id": "SmqZd8MnGBgCzzBp",
    "question": "In a $$LCR$$ circuit capacitance is changed from $$C$$ to $$2$$ $$C$$. For the resonant frequency to remain unchaged, the inductance should be changed from $$L$$ to ",
    "options": [
      "$$L/2$$ ",
      "$$2L$$ ",
      "$$4L$$ ",
      "$$L/4$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$L/2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "oi26w9o1iXOCTXgv",
    "question": "Alternating current can not be measured by $$D.C.$$ ammeter because ",
    "options": [
      "Average value of current for complete cycle is zero ",
      "$$A.C.$$ Changes direction ",
      "$$A.C.$$  can not pass through $$D.C.$$ Ammeter ",
      "$$D.C.$$ Ammeter will get damaged. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "Average value of current for complete cycle is zero "
  },
  {
    "id": "YEww4HpdQL4O8otA",
    "question": "The self inductance of the motor of an electric fan is $$10$$ $$H$$. In order to impart maximum power at $$50$$ $$Hz$$, it should be connected to a capacitance of ",
    "options": [
      "$$8\\mu F$$ ",
      "$$4\\mu F$$",
      "$$2\\mu F$$",
      "$$1\\mu F$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$1\\mu F$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "iLTAg7jdqZg8KmtF",
    "question": "A circuit has a resistance of $$12$$ $$ohm$$ and an impedance of $$15$$ $$ohm$$. The power factor of the circuit will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.4$$ ",
      "$$0.8$$ ",
      "$$0.125$$ ",
      "$$1.25$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$0.8$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "uRbFUgJGpog2DiZu",
    "question": "The phase difference between the alternating current and $$emf$$ is $${\\pi  \\over 2}.$$ Which of the following cannot be the constituent of the circuit? ",
    "options": [
      "$$R,L$$ ",
      "$$C$$ alone ",
      "$$L$$ alone ",
      "$$L, C$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$R,L$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ASzIjiBCgAA6c2TN",
    "question": "In a series resonant $$LCR$$ circuit, the voltage across $$R$$ is $$100$$ volts and $$R = 1\\,k\\Omega $$ with $$C = 2\\mu F.$$ The resonant frequency $$\\omega $$ is $$200$$ $$rad/s$$. At resonance the voltage across $$L$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$2.5 \\times {10^{ - 2}}V$$ ",
      "$$40$$ $$V$$ ",
      "$$250$$ $$V$$ ",
      "$$4 \\times {10^{ - 3}}V$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$250$$ $$V$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "cW8qYk6sz4VQ7ASe",
    "question": "In an $$a.c.$$ circuit the voltage applied is $$E = {E_0}\\,\\sin \\,\\omega t.$$ The resulting current in the circuit is $$I = {I_0}\\sin \\left( {\\omega t - {\\pi  \\over 2}} \\right).$$ The power consumption in the circuit is given by ",
    "options": [
      "$$P = \\sqrt 2 {E_0}{I_0}$$ ",
      "$$P = {{{E_0}{I_0}} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "$$P=zero$$ ",
      "$$P = {{{E_0}{I_0}} \\over 2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$P=zero$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "thulUeTMEHlNKBZ2",
    "question": "In a series $$LCR$$ circuit $$R = 200\\Omega $$ and the voltage and the frequency of the main supply is $$220V$$ and $$50$$ $$Hz$$ respectively. On taking out the capacitance from the circuit the current lags behind the voltage by $${30^ \\circ }.$$ On taking out the inductor from the circuit the current leads the voltage by $${30^ \\circ }.$$ The power dissipated in the $$LCR$$ circuit is ",
    "options": [
      "$$305$$ $$W$$ ",
      "$$210$$ $$W$$ ",
      "$$zero$$ $$W$$ ",
      "$$242$$ $$W$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$242$$ $$W$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "qbVVQJ5xx7tlSAN0",
    "question": "A fully charged capacitor $$C$$ with initial charge $${q_0}$$ is connected to a coil of self inductance $$L$$ at $$t=0.$$ The time at which the energy is stored equally between the electric and the magnetic fields is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${\\pi  \\over 4}\\sqrt {LC} $$ ",
      "$$2\\pi \\sqrt {LC} $$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt {LC} $$ ",
      "$$\\pi \\sqrt {LC} $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$${\\pi  \\over 4}\\sqrt {LC} $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "h17MQANUOWM7bVSn9Bq9s",
    "question": "An arc lamp requires a direct current of\n10 A at 80 V to function. If it is connected\nto a 220 V (rms), 50 Hz AC supply, the\nseries inductor needed for it to work is\nclose to :",
    "options": [
      "0.044 H",
      "0.065 H",
      "80 H",
      "0.08 H"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "0.065 H"
  },
  {
    "id": "wwtanXWySkKGKkJvWaaD7",
    "question": "A sinusoidal voltage of peak value 283 V and angular frequency 320/s is applied to a series LCR circuit. Given that R=5 $$\\Omega $$, L=25 mH and C=1000 $$\\mu $$F. The total impedance, and phase difference between the voltage across the source and the current will respectively be :",
    "options": [
      "10 $$\\Omega $$ and tan<sup>$$-$$1</sup> $$\\left( {{5 \\over 3}} \\right)$$",
      "$$7\\,\\Omega $$  and 45<sup>o</sup> ",
      "$$10\\,\\Omega $$ and tan<sup>$$-$$1</sup>$$\\left( {{8 \\over 3}} \\right)$$",
      "$$7\\,\\Omega $$ and tan<sup>$$-$$1</sup>$$\\left( {{5 \\over 3}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$7\\,\\Omega $$  and 45<sup>o</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "wfr9c3vxd7eO8KhD",
    "question": "In an a.c. circuit, the instantaneous e.m.f. and current are given by <br/>\ne = 100 sin 30 t<br/>\ni = 20 sin $$\\left( {30t - {\\pi  \\over 4}} \\right)$$<br/>\nIn one cycle of a.c., the average power consumed by the circuit and the wattless current are, respectively ",
    "options": [
      "50, 0 ",
      "50, 10 ",
      "$${{1000} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }},10$$ ",
      "$${{50} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$${{1000} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }},10$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "LErmRAs7aPfk9kZnjbEJN",
    "question": "An ideal capacitor of capacitance $$0.2\\,\\mu F$$ is charged to a potential difference of $$10$$ $$V.$$ The charging battery is then disconnected. The capacitor is then connected to an ideal inductor of self inductance $$0.5$$ $$mH.$$ The current at a time when the potential difference across the capacitor is $$5$$ $$V,$$ is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.34\\,\\,A$$ ",
      "$$0.25\\,\\,A$$",
      "$$0.17\\,\\,A$$",
      "$$0.15\\,\\,A$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$0.17\\,\\,A$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "qfDj6DNEGPaAx4oS19SbE",
    "question": "A circuit connected to an ac source of emf\ne = e<sub>0</sub>sin(100t) with t in seconds, gives a phase\ndifference of $$\\pi $$/4 between the emf e and\ncurrent i. Which of the following circuits will\nexhibit this ?",
    "options": [
      "RC circuit with R = 1 k$$\\Omega $$ and C = 1μF",
      "RL circuit with R = 1k$$\\Omega $$ and L = 1mH",
      "RC circuit with R = 1k$$\\Omega $$ and C = 10 μF",
      "RL circuit with R = 1 k$$\\Omega $$ and L = 10 mH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "RC circuit with R = 1k$$\\Omega $$ and C = 10 μF"
  },
  {
    "id": "SxYBTBePrEFrTUvxCfLI5",
    "question": "An alternating voltage v(t) = 220 sin 100 $$\\pi $$t volt\nis applied to a purely resistance load of 50$$\\Omega $$ .\nThe time taken for the current to rise from half\nof the peak value to the peak value is :",
    "options": [
      "5 ms",
      "2.2 ms",
      "3.3 ms",
      "7.2 ms"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "3.3 ms"
  },
  {
    "id": "kOvprkYFwIeXUlt3fP03J",
    "question": "A series AC circuit containing an inductor (20 mH), a capacitor (120 $$\\mu $$F) and a resistor (60 $$\\Omega $$) is driven by an AC source of 24V/50 Hz. The energy dissipated in the circuit in 60 s is : ",
    "options": [
      "5.65 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>2</sup>J ",
      "2.26 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup>J",
      "5.17 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>2</sup> J",
      "3.39 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup> J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "5.17 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>2</sup> J"
  },
  {
    "id": "daWQCwZz5379riDFnM7k9k2k5dolaqg",
    "question": "A LCR circuit behaves like a damped harmonic oscillator. Comparing it with a physical spring-mass damped oscillator having damping constant 'b', the correct equivalence would be:",
    "options": [
      "L $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ k, C $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ b, R $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ m",
      "L $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ m, C $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ k, R $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ b",
      "L $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ m, C $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ $${1 \\over k}$$, R $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ b",
      "L $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ $${1 \\over b}$$, C $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ $${1 \\over m}$$, R $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ $${1 \\over k}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "L $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ m, C $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ $${1 \\over k}$$, R $$ \\leftrightarrow $$ b"
  },
  {
    "id": "qefVorS2uEXC7q9z647k9k2k5l5yars",
    "question": "In LC circuit the inductance L = 40 mH and\n<br/>capacitance C = 100 $$\\mu $$F. If a voltage\n<br/>V(t) = 10sin(314t) is applied to the circuit, the\n<br/>current in the circuit is given as :",
    "options": [
      "0.52 cos 314 t",
      "5.2 cos 314 t",
      "0.52 sin 314 t",
      "10 cos 314 t"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "0.52 cos 314 t"
  },
  {
    "id": "VEEt9YXhR16lconjbojgy2xukexwg41v",
    "question": "An inductance coil has a reactance of 100 $$\\Omega $$.\nWhen an AC signal of frequency 1000 Hz is\napplied to the coil, the applied voltage leads\nthe current by 45<sup>o</sup>. The self-inductance of the\ncoil is",
    "options": [
      "6.7 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–7</sup> H",
      "1.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–1</sup> H",
      "5.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–5</sup> H",
      "1.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–2</sup> H"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "1.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–2</sup> H"
  },
  {
    "id": "44MzeCC1nuPxzqf3q5jgy2xukf15pezu",
    "question": "A 750 Hz, 20 V (rms) source is connected to a\nresistance of 100 $$\\Omega $$, an inductance of 0.1803 H\nand a capacitance of 10 $$\\mu $$F all in series. The\ntime in which the resistance (heat capacity\n2 J/<sup>o</sup>C) will get heated by 10<sup>o</sup>C. (assume no loss\nof heat to the surroudnings) is close to :",
    "options": [
      "348 s",
      "418 s",
      "245 s",
      "365 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "348 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "ssDfoVbytyEM2abSbb1klt249qz",
    "question": "An LCR circuit contains resistance of 110$$\\Omega$$ and a supply of 220 V at 300 rad/s angular frequency. If only capacitance is removed from the circuit, current lags behind the voltage by 45$$^\\circ$$. If on the other hand, only inductor is removed the current leads by 45$$^\\circ$$ with the applied voltage. The rms current flowing in the circuit will be :",
    "options": [
      "1 A",
      "2.5 A",
      "2 A",
      "1.5 A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "2 A"
  },
  {
    "id": "8OGOKavxUO7OfLwZaI1klt2p82o",
    "question": "Match List I with List II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Rectifier</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Used either for stepping up or stepping down the a.c. voltage</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Stabilizer</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Used to convert a.c. voltage into d.c. voltage</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Transformer</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Used to remove any ripple in the rectified output voltage</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Filter</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Used for constant output voltage even when the input voltage or load current change</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iii), (d)-(iv)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "azQBwvklhqtxqqn4pP1kltha5wu",
    "question": "An alternating current is given by the equation i = i<sub>1</sub> sin $$\\omega$$t + i<sub>2</sub> cos $$\\omega$$t. The rms current will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{\\left( {i_1^2 + i_2^2} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}({i_1} + {i_2})$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{({i_1} + {i_2})^2}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}{\\left( {i_1^2 + i_2^2} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{\\left( {i_1^2 + i_2^2} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "MPaJt6x2pBRCtKDVY91kmj28zdc",
    "question": "An AC current is given by I = I<sub>1</sub> sin$$\\omega$$t + I<sub>2</sub> cos$$\\omega$$t. A hot wire ammeter will give a reading :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{I_1} + {I_2}} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{I_1^2 - I_2^2} \\over 2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{I_1^2 + I_2^2} \\over 2}} $$",
      "$${{{I_1} + {I_2}} \\over {2\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{I_1^2 + I_2^2} \\over 2}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "AGqwpL0lU8CIIAjX7R1kmk8acf3",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Phase difference between current and voltage in a purely resistive AC circuit</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>$${\\pi  \\over 2}$$; current leads voltage</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Phase difference between current and voltage in a pure inductive AC circuit</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>zero</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Phase difference between current and voltage in a pure capacitive AC circuit</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>$${\\pi  \\over 2}$$; current lags voltage</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Phase difference between current and voltage in an LCR series circuit</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{{X_C} - {X_L}} \\over R}} \\right)$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(iii), (d)-(i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)"
  },
  {
    "id": "LQAcqTOc0HtLHUGrvo1kmkalj6z",
    "question": "What happens to the inductive reactance and the current in a purely inductive circuit if the frequency is halved?",
    "options": [
      "Both, inducting reactance and current will be doubled.",
      "Inductive reactance will be doubled and current will be halved.",
      "Both, inductive reactance and current will be halved.",
      "Inductive reactance will be halved and current will be doubled."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "Inductive reactance will be halved and current will be doubled."
  },
  {
    "id": "VF3xHLQMu4uzx3s5Dr1kmkrhkv9",
    "question": "In a series LCR resonance circuit, if we change the resistance only, from a lower to higher value :",
    "options": [
      "The bandwidth of resonance circuit will increase.",
      "The resonance frequency will increase.",
      "The quality factor will increase.",
      "The quality factor and the resonance frequency will remain constant."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "The bandwidth of resonance circuit will increase."
  },
  {
    "id": "gQhRMzmtxQbTm9HQHU1kmkrijd1",
    "question": "An AC source rated 220 V, 50 Hz is connected to a resistor. The time taken by the current to change from its maximum to the rms value is :",
    "options": [
      "2.5 ms",
      "25 ms",
      "2.5 s",
      "0.25 ms"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "2.5 ms"
  },
  {
    "id": "drcpQeI6nE0zuYmBRD1kmlvm9lc",
    "question": "In a series LCR circuit, the inductive reactance (X<sub>L</sub>) is 10$$\\Omega$$ and the capacitive reactance (X<sub>C</sub>) is 4$$\\Omega$$. The resistance (R) in the circuit is 6$$\\Omega$$. The power factor of the circuit is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {2\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krpnqvvj",
    "question": "AC voltage V(t) = 20 sin$$\\omega$$t of frequency 50 Hz is applied to a parallel plate capacitor. The separation between the plates is 2 mm and the area is 1 m<sup>2</sup>. The amplitude of the oscillating displacement current for the applied AC voltage is _________. [Take $$\\varepsilon $$<sub>0</sub> = 8.85 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$12</sup> F/m]",
    "options": [
      "55.58 $$\\mu$$A",
      "21.14 $$\\mu$$A",
      "27.79 $$\\mu$$A",
      "83.37 $$\\mu$$A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "27.79 $$\\mu$$A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqbc8pz",
    "question": "For a series LCR circuit with R = 100 $$\\Omega$$, L = 0.5 mH and C = 0.1 pF connected across 220V$$-$$50 Hz AC supply, the phase angle between current and supplied voltage and the nature of the circuit is :",
    "options": [
      "0$$^\\circ$$, resistive circuit",
      "$$ \\approx $$ 90$$^\\circ$$, predominantly inductive circuit",
      "0$$^\\circ$$, resonance circuit",
      "$$ \\approx $$ 90$$^\\circ$$, predominantly capacitive circuit"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$ \\approx $$ 90$$^\\circ$$, predominantly capacitive circuit"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsv7oe0",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>$$\\omega L &gt; {1 \\over {\\omega C}}$$</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Current is in phase with emf</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>$$\\omega L = {1 \\over {\\omega C}}$$</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Current lags behind the applied emf</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>$$\\omega L &lt; {1 \\over {\\omega C}}$$</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Maximum current occurs</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Resonant frequency</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Current leads the emf</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below ",
    "options": [
      "a(ii), b(i), c(iv), d(iii)",
      "a(ii), b(i), c(iii), d(iv)",
      "a(iii), b(i), c(iv), d(ii)",
      "a(iv), b(iii), c(ii), d(i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "a(ii), b(i), c(iv), d(iii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw8vbh1",
    "question": "A 10 $$\\Omega$$ resistance is connected across 220V $$-$$ 50 Hz AC supply. The time taken by the current to change from its maximum value to the rms value is :",
    "options": [
      "2.5 ms",
      "1.5 ms",
      "3.0 ms",
      "4.5 ms"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "2.5 ms"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kryx1618",
    "question": "A 0.07 H inductor and a 12$$\\Omega$$ resistor are connected in series to a 220V, 50 Hz ac source. The approximate current in the circuit and the phase angle between current and source voltage are respectively. [Take $$\\pi$$ as $${{22} \\over 7}$$]",
    "options": [
      "8.8 A and $${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{11} \\over 6}} \\right)$$",
      "88 A and $${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{11} \\over 6}} \\right)$$",
      "0.88 A and $${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{11} \\over 6}} \\right)$$",
      "8.8 A and $${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{6} \\over 11}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "8.8 A and $${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{11} \\over 6}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks17s7bk",
    "question": "A 100$$\\Omega$$ resistance, a 0.1 $$\\mu$$F capacitor and an inductor are connected in series across a 250 V supply at variable frequency. Calculate the value of inductance of inductor at which resonance will occur. Given that the resonant frequency is 60 Hz.",
    "options": [
      "0.70 H",
      "70.3 mH",
      "7.03 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> H",
      "70.3 H"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "70.3 H"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktabwe96",
    "question": "A series LCR circuit driven by 300 V at a frequency of 50 Hz contains a resistance R = 3 k$$\\Omega$$, an inductor of inductive reactance X<sub>L</sub> = 250 $$\\pi$$$$\\Omega$$ and an unknown capacitor. The value of capacitance to maximize the average power should be : (Take $$\\pi$$<sup>2</sup> = 10)",
    "options": [
      "4 $$\\mu$$F",
      "25 $$\\mu$$F",
      "400 $$\\mu$$F",
      "40 $$\\mu$$F"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "4 $$\\mu$$F"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth5cv9x",
    "question": "In an ac circuit, an inductor, a capacitor and a resistor are connected in series with X<sub>L</sub> = R = X<sub>C</sub>. Impedance of this circuit is :",
    "options": [
      "2R<sup>2</sup>",
      "Zero",
      "R",
      "R$$\\sqrt 2 $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "R"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59p78c8",
    "question": "<p>A sinusoidal voltage V(t) = 210 sin 3000 t volt is applied to a series LCR circuit in which L = 10 mH, C = 25 $$\\mu$$F and R = 100 $$\\Omega$$. The phase difference ($$\\Phi $$) between the applied voltage and resultant current will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "tan<sup>$$-$$1</sup>(0.17)",
      "tan<sup>$$-$$1</sup>(9.46)",
      "tan<sup>$$-$$1</sup>(0.30)",
      "tan<sup>$$-$$1</sup>(13.33)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "tan<sup>$$-$$1</sup>(0.17)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5aknwm4",
    "question": "<p>If wattless current flows in the AC circuit, then the circuit is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Purely Resistive circuit",
      "Purely Inductive circuit",
      "LCR series circuit",
      "RC series circuit only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "Purely Inductive circuit"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbu66y",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The reactance of an ac circuit is zero. It is possible that the circuit contains a capacitor and an inductor.</p>\n<p>Statement II : In ac circuit, the average power delivered by the source never becomes zero.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c3toi9",
    "question": "<p>A resistance of 40 $$\\Omega$$ is connected to a source of alternating current rated 220 V, 50 Hz. Find the time taken by the current to change from its maximum value to the rms value :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.5 ms",
      "1.25 ms",
      "2.5 s",
      "0.25 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "2.5 ms"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w325pc",
    "question": "<p>In series RLC resonator, if the self inductance and capacitance become double, the new resonant frequency (f<sub>2</sub>) and new quality factor (Q<sub>2</sub>) will be :</p>\n<p>(f<sub>1</sub> = original resonant frequency, Q<sub>1</sub> = original quality factor)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${f_2} = {{{f_1}} \\over 2}$$ and $${Q_2} = {Q_1}$$",
      "$${f_2} = {f_1}$$ and $${Q_2} = {{{Q_1}} \\over {{Q_2}}}$$",
      "$${f_2} = 2{f_1}$$ and $${Q_2} = {Q_1}$$",
      "$${f_2} = {f_1}$$ and $${Q_2} = 2{Q_1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$${f_2} = {{{f_1}} \\over 2}$$ and $${Q_2} = {Q_1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dyqydu",
    "question": "<p>To increase the resonant frequency in series LCR circuit,</p>",
    "options": [
      "source frequency should be increased.",
      "another resistance should be added in series with the first resistance.",
      " another capacitor should be added in series with the first capacitor.",
      " the source frequency should be decreased."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": " another capacitor should be added in series with the first capacitor."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f4u1ke",
    "question": "<p>When you walk through a metal detector carrying a metal object in your pocket, it raises an alarm. This phenomenon works on :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Electromagnetic induction",
      "Resonance in ac circuits",
      "Mutual induction in ac circuits",
      "Interference of electromagnetic waves"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "Resonance in ac circuits"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gmfkts",
    "question": "<p>In a series $$L R$$ circuit $$X_{L}=R$$ and power factor of the circuit is $$P_{1}$$. When capacitor with capacitance $$C$$ such that $$X_{L}=X_{C}$$ is put in series, the power factor becomes $$P_{2}$$. The ratio $$\\frac{P_{1}}{P_{2}}$$ is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{\\sqrt{2}}$$",
      "2 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6ji7zez",
    "question": "<p>A direct current of $$4 \\mathrm{~A}$$ and an alternating current of peak value $$4 \\mathrm{~A}$$ flow through resistance of $$3\\, \\Omega$$ and $$2\\,\\Omega$$ respectively. The ratio of heat produced in the two resistances in same interval of time will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 : 2",
      "3 : 1",
      "3 : 4",
      "4 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "3 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6knirm5",
    "question": "<p>A series LCR circuit has $$\\mathrm{L}=0.01\\, \\mathrm{H}, \\mathrm{R}=10\\, \\Omega$$ and $$\\mathrm{C}=1 \\mu \\mathrm{F}$$ and it is connected to ac voltage of amplitude $$\\left(\\mathrm{V}_{\\mathrm{m}}\\right) 50 \\mathrm{~V}$$. At frequency $$60 \\%$$ lower than resonant frequency, the amplitude of current will be approximately :</p>",
    "options": [
      "466 mA",
      "312 mA",
      "238 mA",
      "196 mA"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "238 mA"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mao9vk",
    "question": "<p>The equation of current in a purely inductive circuit is $$5 \\sin \\left(49\\, \\pi t-30^{\\circ}\\right)$$. If the inductance is $$30 \\,\\mathrm{mH}$$ then the equation for the voltage across the inductor, will be :</p>\n<p>$$\\left\\{\\right.$$ Let $$\\left.\\pi=\\frac{22}{7}\\right\\}$$\n</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1.47 \\sin \\left(49 \\pi t-30^{\\circ}\\right)$$",
      "$$1.47 \\sin \\left(49 \\pi t+60^{\\circ}\\right)$$",
      "$$23.1 \\sin \\left(49 \\pi t-30^{\\circ}\\right)$$",
      "$$23.1 \\sin \\left(49 \\pi t+60^{\\circ}\\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$23.1 \\sin \\left(49 \\pi t+60^{\\circ}\\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p51yr7",
    "question": "<p>An alternating emf $$\\mathrm{E}=440 \\sin 100 \\pi \\mathrm{t}$$ is applied to a circuit containing an inductance of $$\\frac{\\sqrt{2}}{\\pi} \\mathrm{H}$$. If an a.c. ammeter is connected in the circuit, its reading will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4.4 A",
      "1.55 A",
      "2.2 A",
      "3.11 A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "2.2 A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rgzf86",
    "question": "<p>A circuit element $$\\mathrm{X}$$ when connected to an a.c. supply of peak voltage $$100 \\mathrm{~V}$$ gives a peak current of $$5 \\mathrm{~A}$$ which is in phase with the voltage. A second element $$\\mathrm{Y}$$ when connected to the same a.c. supply also gives the same value of peak current which lags behind the voltage by $$\\frac{\\pi}{2}$$. If $$\\mathrm{X}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Y}$$ are connected in series to the same supply, what will be the rms value of the current in ampere?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{10}{\\sqrt{2}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{5}{\\sqrt{2}}$$",
      "$$5 \\sqrt{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{5}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{5}{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo77jpr",
    "question": "An alternating voltage source $\\mathrm{V}=260 \\sin (628 \\mathrm{t}$ ) is connected across a pure inductor of $5 \\mathrm{mH}$ Inductive reactance in the circuit is :",
    "options": [
      "$6.28 \\Omega$",
      "$0.318 \\Omega$",
      "$0.5 \\Omega$",
      "$3.14 \\Omega$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$3.14 \\Omega$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpm229z",
    "question": "<p>If $$\\mathrm{R}, \\mathrm{X}_{\\mathrm{L}}$$, and $$\\mathrm{X}_{\\mathrm{C}}$$ represent resistance, inductive reactance and capacitive reactance. Then which of the following is dimensionless :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{R}{X_{L} X_{C}}$$",
      "$$R X_{L}  X_{C}$$",
      "$$\\frac{R}{\\sqrt{X_{L} X_{C}}}$$",
      "$$R \\frac{X_{L}}{X_{C}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{R}{\\sqrt{X_{L} X_{C}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr2rai3",
    "question": "<p>In a series LR circuit with $$\\mathrm{X_L=R}$$, power factor P<sub>1</sub>. If a capacitor of capacitance C with $$\\mathrm{X_C=X_L}$$ is added to the circuit the power factor becomes P<sub>2</sub>. The ratio of P<sub>1</sub> to P<sub>2</sub> will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : $$\\sqrt2$$",
      "1 : 3",
      "1 : 2",
      "1 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "1 : $$\\sqrt2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldui18qn",
    "question": "<p>In an LC oscillator, if values of inductance and capacitance become twice and eight times, respectively, then the resonant frequency of oscillator becomes $$x$$ times its initial resonant frequency $$\\omega_0$$. The value of $$x$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1/4",
      "1/16",
      "4",
      "16"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "1/4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp0cep6",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : An AC circuit undergoes electrical resonance if it contains either a capacitor or an inductor.</p>\n<p>Statement II : An AC circuit containing a pure capacitor or a pure inductor consumes high power due to its non-zero power factor.</p>\n<p>In the light of above statements, choose the correct answer form the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrjkmq5",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : When the frequency of an a.c source in a series LCR circuit increases, the current in the circuit first increases, attains a maximum value and then decreases.</p>\n<p>Statement II : In a series LCR circuit, the value of power factor at resonance is one.</p>\n<p>In the light of given statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are False.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyf3l3z",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Maximum power is dissipated in a circuit containing an inductor, a capacitor and a resistor connected in series with an AC source, when resonance occurs</p>\n<p>Statement II : Maximum power is dissipated in a circuit containing pure resistor due to zero phase difference between current and voltage.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh2zyj8b",
    "question": "<p>A capacitor of capacitance $$150.0 ~\\mu \\mathrm{F}$$ is connected to an alternating source of emf given by $$\\mathrm{E}=36 \\sin (120 \\pi \\mathrm{t}) \\mathrm{V}$$. The maximum value of current in the circuit is approximately equal to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} A$$",
      "$$2 \\sqrt{2} A$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{2} A$$",
      "$$2 A$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$2 A$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbl0864",
    "question": "A parallel plate capacitor has a capacitance $\\mathrm{C}=200~ \\mathrm{pF}$. It is connected to $230 \\mathrm{~V}$ ac supply with an angular frequency $300~ \\mathrm{rad} / \\mathrm{s}$. The rms value of conduction current in the circuit and displacement current in the capacitor respectively are :",
    "options": [
      "$14.3 ~\\mu \\mathrm{A}$ and $143 ~\\mu \\mathrm{A}$",
      "$13.8 ~\\mu \\mathrm{A}$ and $13.8 ~\\mu \\mathrm{A}$",
      "$13.8 ~\\mu \\mathrm{A}$ and $138 ~\\mu \\mathrm{A}$",
      "$1.38 ~\\mu \\mathrm{A}$ and $1.38 ~\\mu \\mathrm{A}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$13.8 ~\\mu \\mathrm{A}$ and $13.8 ~\\mu \\mathrm{A}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbl8966",
    "question": "In series LCR circuit, the capacitance is changed from $C$ to $4 C$. To keep the resonance frequency unchanged, the new inductance should be:",
    "options": [
      "increased by $2 \\mathrm{~L}$",
      "reduced by $\\frac{1}{4} \\mathrm{~L}$",
      "reduced by $\\frac{3}{4} \\mathrm{~L}$",
      "increased to $4 \\mathrm{~L}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "reduced by $\\frac{3}{4} \\mathrm{~L}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd7vbge",
    "question": "<p>An AC voltage $$V=20 \\sin 200 \\pi t$$ is applied to a series LCR circuit which drives a current $$I=10 \\sin \\left(200 \\pi t+\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right)$$. The average power dissipated is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "21.6 W",
      "200 W",
      "173.2 W",
      "50 W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "50 W"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsflvkm7",
    "question": "<p>In an a.c. circuit, voltage and current are given by:</p>\n<p>$$V=100 \\sin (100 t) V$$ and\n$$I=100 \\sin \\left(100 t+\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\right) \\mathrm{mA}$$ respectively.</p>\n<p>The average power dissipated in one cycle is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "5 W",
      "25 W",
      "2.5 W",
      "10 W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "2.5 W"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg5jie1",
    "question": "<p>An alternating voltage $$V(t)=220 \\sin 100 \\pi t$$ volt is applied to a purely resistive load of $$50 \\Omega$$. The time taken for the current to rise from half of the peak value to the peak value is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "7.2 ms",
      "3.3 ms",
      "5 ms",
      "2.2 ms"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "3.3 ms"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgd2r5a",
    "question": "<p>A series L.R circuit connected with an ac source $$E=(25 \\sin 1000 t) V$$ has a power factor of $$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}$$. If the source of emf is changed to $$\\mathrm{E}=(20 \\sin 2000 \\mathrm{t}) \\mathrm{V}$$, the new power factor of the circuit will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{5}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{7}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{5}}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2u3rd",
    "question": "<p>A bulb and a capacitor are connected in series across an ac supply. A dielectric is then placed between the plates of the capacitor. The glow of the bulb :</p>",
    "options": [
      "becomes zero\n",
      "remains same\n",
      "increases\n",
      "decreases"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "increases\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxltl",
    "question": "<p>In an ac circuit, the instantaneous current is zero, when the instantaneous voltage is maximum. In this case, the source may be connected to :</p>\n<p>A. pure inductor.</p>\n<p>B. pure capacitor.</p>\n<p>C. pure resistor.</p>\n<p>D. combination of an inductor and capacitor.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B and C only\n",
      "A and B only\n",
      "A, B and D only\n",
      "B, C and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "A, B and D only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3ve9g6",
    "question": "<p>A coil of negligible resistance is connected in series with $$90 \\Omega$$ resistor across $$120 \\mathrm{~V}, 60 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$ supply. A voltmeter reads $$36 \\mathrm{~V}$$ across resistance. Inductance of the coil is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.91 H",
      "0.76 H",
      "2.86 H",
      "0.286 H"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "0.76 H"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gst30",
    "question": "<p>A LCR circuit is at resonance for a capacitor C, inductance L and resistance R. Now the value of resistance is halved keeping all other parameters same. The current amplitude at resonance will be now:</p>",
    "options": [
      "halved\n",
      "same\n",
      "Zero\n",
      "double"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "double"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3ofn",
    "question": "<p>An alternating voltage of amplitude $$40 \\mathrm{~V}$$ and frequency $$4 \\mathrm{~kHz}$$ is applied directly across the capacitor of $$12 \\mu \\mathrm{F}$$. The maximum displacement current between the plates of the capacitor is nearly :</p>",
    "options": [
      "10 A",
      "8 A",
      "13 A",
      "12 A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "12 A"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s20yo",
    "question": "<p>A series LCR circuit is subjected to an ac signal of $$200 \\mathrm{~V}, 50 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$. If the voltage across the inductor $$(\\mathrm{L}=10 \\mathrm{~mH})$$ is $$31.4 \\mathrm{~V}$$, then the current in this circuit is _______.</p>",
    "options": [
      "10 A",
      "10 mA",
      "68 A",
      "63 A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "10 A"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57cv4",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : In an LCR series circuit, current is maximum at resonance.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Current in a purely resistive circuit can never be less than that in a series LCR circuit when connected to same voltage source.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-circuits-and-power-in-ac-circuits",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "4607qdKnqCzVxh96",
    "question": "In a transformer, number of turns in the primary coil are $$140$$ and that in the secondary coil are $$280.$$ If current in primary coil is $$4A,$$ then that in the secondary coil is ",
    "options": [
      "$$4A$$ ",
      "$$2A$$ ",
      "$$6A$$ ",
      "$$10A$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-generator-and-transformer",
    "solution": "$$2A$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "6Ec6OxBh8BJj2TNa",
    "question": "The core of any transformer is laminated so as  to",
    "options": [
      "reduce the energy loss due to eddy currents",
      "make it light weight",
      "make it robust and strong",
      "increase the secondary voltage "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-generator-and-transformer",
    "solution": "reduce the energy loss due to eddy currents"
  },
  {
    "id": "miSvleiDv9GBrw0o",
    "question": "In an $$AC$$ generator, a coil with $$N$$ turns, all of the same area $$A$$ and total resistance $$R,$$ rotates with frequency $$\\omega $$ in a magnetic field $$B.$$ The maximum value of $$emf$$ generated in the coil is ",
    "options": [
      "$$N.A.B.R.$$$$\\omega $$ ",
      "$$N.A.B$$",
      "$$N.A.B.R.$$  ",
      "$$N.A.B.$$$$\\omega $$  "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-generator-and-transformer",
    "solution": "$$N.A.B.$$$$\\omega $$  "
  },
  {
    "id": "XwJxzLYmUSZz6swhWBbPV",
    "question": "A power transmission line feeds input power at 2300 V to a step down transformer with its primary windings having 4000 turns, giving the output  power at 230 V.  If the current in the primary of the transformer is 5 A,  and its efficiency is 90%,  the output current would be ; ",
    "options": [
      "50 A",
      "45 A",
      "25 A",
      "20 A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-generator-and-transformer",
    "solution": "45 A"
  },
  {
    "id": "kPyJ0TmCbYPBMTmJgIOhO",
    "question": "A power transmission line feeds input power at 2300 V to a srep down transformer with its primary windings having 4000 turns. The output power is delivered at 230 V by the transformer. If the current in the primary of the transformer is 5A and its efficiency is 90%, the output current would be : ",
    "options": [
      "50 A",
      "45 A",
      "35 A",
      "25 A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-generator-and-transformer",
    "solution": "45 A"
  },
  {
    "id": "2kCrUXgD1yzCfozAGg18hoxe66ijvzt10aj",
    "question": "A transformer consisting of 300 turns in the\nprimary and 150 turns in the secondary gives\noutput power of 2.2 kW. If the current in the\nsecondary coil is 10A, then the input voltage\nand current in the primary coil are :",
    "options": [
      "220 V and 20 A",
      "220 V and 10A",
      "440 V and 5A",
      "440 V and 20 A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-generator-and-transformer",
    "solution": "440 V and 5A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5akkd0b",
    "question": "<p>Match List-I with List-II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 789px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 62px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 195px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 80px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 452px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\">List -II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">AC generator</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Detects the presence of current in the circuit</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Galvanometer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Converts mechanical energy into electrical energy</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Transformer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Works on the principle of resonance in AC circuit</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Metal detector</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Changes an alternating voltage for smaller or greater value</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (I), (C) - (IV), (D) - (III)",
      "(A) - (II), (B) - (I), (C) - (III), (D) - (IV)",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (IV), (C) - (II), (D) - (I)",
      "(A) - (III), (B) - (I), (C) - (II), (D) - (IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-generator-and-transformer",
    "solution": "(A) - (II), (B) - (I), (C) - (IV), (D) - (III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nsrt1d",
    "question": "<p>A transformer operating at primary voltage $$8 \\,\\mathrm{kV}$$ and secondary voltage $$160 \\mathrm{~V}$$ serves a load of $$80 \\mathrm{~kW}$$. Assuming the transformer to be ideal with purely resistive load and working on unity power factor, the loads in the primary and secondary circuit would be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$800 \\,\\Omega$$ and $$1.06 \\,\\Omega$$",
      "$$10 \\,\\Omega$$ and $$500 \\,\\Omega$$",
      "$$800 \\,\\Omega$$ and $$0.32 \\,\\Omega$$",
      "$$1.06 \\,\\Omega$$ and $$500 \\,\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-generator-and-transformer",
    "solution": "$$800 \\,\\Omega$$ and $$0.32 \\,\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldof1u9u",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 532px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 223px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 214px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">AC generator</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Presence of both L and C</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Transformer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Electromagnetic Induction</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Resonance phenomenon to occur</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Quality factor</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Sharpness of resonance</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Mutual Induction</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-I, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-I, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-generator-and-transformer",
    "solution": "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscp19dg",
    "question": "<p>Primary side of a transformer is connected to $$230 \\mathrm{~V}, 50 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$ supply. Turns ratio of primary to secondary winding is $$10: 1$$. Load resistance connected to secondary side is $$46 \\Omega$$. The power consumed in it is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "11.5 W",
      "12.5 W",
      "10.0 W",
      "12.0 W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "ac-generator-and-transformer",
    "solution": "11.5 W"
  },
  {
    "id": "8CMiNsI8xNXYas3C",
    "question": "In an oscillating $$LC$$ circuit the maximum charge on the capacitor is $$Q$$. The charge on the capacitor when the energy is stored equally between the electric and magnetic field is ",
    "options": [
      "$${Q \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$${Q \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$ ",
      "$${Q \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "$$Q$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "growth-and-decay-of-current",
    "solution": "$${Q \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "2QQCcZVecU4BTX9W",
    "question": "A resistor $$'R'$$ and $$2\\mu F$$ capacitor in series is connected through a switch to $$200$$ $$V$$ direct supply. Across the capacitor is a neon bulb that lights up at $$120$$ $$V.$$ Calculate the value of $$R$$ to make the bulb light up $$5$$ $$s$$ after the switch has been closed. $$\\left( {{{\\log }_{10}}2.5 = 0.4} \\right)$$ ",
    "options": [
      "$$1.7 \\times {10^5}\\,\\Omega $$ ",
      "$$2.7 \\times {10^6}\\,\\Omega $$ ",
      "$$3.3 \\times {10^7}\\,\\Omega $$ ",
      "$$1.3 \\times {10^4}\\,\\Omega $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "growth-and-decay-of-current",
    "solution": "$$2.7 \\times {10^6}\\,\\Omega $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "K5I4kHCDK9VBY64KG53rsa0w2w9jwzhfdkz",
    "question": "A coil of self inductance 10 mH and resistance 0.1 $$\\Omega $$ is connected through a switch to a battery of internal\nresistance 0.9 $$\\Omega $$. After the switch is closed, the time taken for the current to attain 80% of the saturation\nvalue is: [take ln 5 = 1.6] \n",
    "options": [
      "0.324 s",
      "0.002 s",
      "0.103 s",
      "0.016 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "growth-and-decay-of-current",
    "solution": "0.016 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "wMxJsw83Tk4t09PURnjgy2xukfajdg43",
    "question": "A series L-R circuit is connected to a battery of emf V. If the circuit is switched on at t = 0, then\nthe time at which the energy stored in the inductor reaches $$\\left( {{1 \\over n}} \\right)$$  times of its maximum value, is :",
    "options": [
      "$${L \\over R}\\ln \\left( {{{\\sqrt n } \\over {\\sqrt n  + 1}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${L \\over R}\\ln \\left( {{{\\sqrt n } \\over {\\sqrt n  - 1}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${L \\over R}\\ln \\left( {{{\\sqrt n  + 1} \\over {\\sqrt n  - 1}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${L \\over R}\\ln \\left( {{{\\sqrt n  - 1} \\over {\\sqrt n }}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "growth-and-decay-of-current",
    "solution": "$${L \\over R}\\ln \\left( {{{\\sqrt n } \\over {\\sqrt n  - 1}}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "caUO97TMDmEHWY7vcf7k9k2k5f63fee",
    "question": "An emf of 20 V is applied at time t = 0 to a circuit containing in series 10 mH inductor and 5 $$\\Omega $$\nresistor. The ratio of the currents at time t = $$\\infty $$ and at t = 40 s is close to : (Take e<sup>2</sup> = 7.389)",
    "options": [
      "1.06",
      "0.84",
      "1.15",
      "1.46"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "growth-and-decay-of-current",
    "solution": "1.06"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56v40l0",
    "question": "<p>If L, C and R are the self inductance, capacitance and resistance respectively, which of the following does not have the dimension of time?</p>",
    "options": [
      "RC",
      "$${L \\over R}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{LC}$$",
      "$${L \\over C}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "growth-and-decay-of-current",
    "solution": "$${L \\over C}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57q0r56",
    "question": "<p>The current flowing through an ac circuit is given by</p>\n<p>I = 5 sin(120$$\\pi$$t)A</p>\n<p>How long will the current take to reach the peak value starting from zero?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {60}}$$ s",
      "60 s",
      "$${1 \\over {120}}$$ s",
      "$${1 \\over {240}}$$ s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "growth-and-decay-of-current",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {240}}$$ s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p56ir0",
    "question": "<p>A coil of inductance 1 H and resistance $$100 \\,\\Omega$$ is connected to a battery of 6 V. Determine approximately :</p>\n<p>(a) The time elapsed before the current acquires half of its steady - state value.</p>\n<p>(b) The energy stored in the magnetic field associated with the coil at an instant 15 ms after the circuit is switched on. (Given $$\\ln 2=0.693, \\mathrm{e}^{-3 / 2}=0.25$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "t = 10 ms; U = 2 mJ",
      "t = 10 ms; U = 1 mJ",
      "t = 7 ms; U = 1 mJ",
      "t = 7 ms; U = 2 mJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "growth-and-decay-of-current",
    "solution": "t = 7 ms; U = 1 mJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf15ms4",
    "question": "<p>A capacitor of capacitance $$100 \\mu \\mathrm{F}$$ is charged to a potential of $$12 \\mathrm{~V}$$ and connected to a $$6.4 \\mathrm{~mH}$$ inductor to produce oscillations. The maximum current in the circuit would be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.0 A",
      "3.2 A",
      "1.5 A",
      "1.2 A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "growth-and-decay-of-current",
    "solution": "1.5 A"
  },
  {
    "id": "rdKd8e6bBqQc6MiC",
    "question": "For an RLC circuit driven with voltage of amplitude vm and frequency $${\\omega _0}$$ = $${1 \\over {\\sqrt {LC} }}$$ the current exhibits resonance. The quality factor, Q is given by : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{CR} \\over {{\\omega _0}}}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\omega _0}L} \\over R}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\omega _0}R} \\over L}$$ ",
      "$${R \\over {\\left( {{\\omega _0}C} \\right)}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "quality-factor",
    "solution": "$${{{\\omega _0}L} \\over R}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "rqaFZ6jbWJ8liGdw1Djgy2xukfrpjmiy",
    "question": "An AC circuit has R= 100 $$\\Omega $$, C = 2 $$\\mu $$F and L = 80 mH, connected in series. The quality factor of the\ncircuit is :",
    "options": [
      "20",
      "2",
      "0.5",
      "400"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "alternating-current",
    "topic": "quality-factor",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "7j0rzgh4L20GoRNY",
    "question": "An $$\\alpha $$-particle of energy $$5$$ $$MeV$$ is scattered through $${180^ \\circ }$$ by a fixed uranium nucleus. The distance of closest approach is of the order of ",
    "options": [
      "$${10^{ - 12}}\\,cm$$ ",
      "$${10^{ - 10}}\\,cm$$ ",
      "$$1A$$ ",
      "$${10^{ - 15a}}\\,cm$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "alpha-particle-scattering-and-rutherford-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "$${10^{ - 12}}\\,cm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "t9gbrQZkmKlGCWl9",
    "question": "An alpha nucleus of energy $${1 \\over 2}m{v^2}$$ bombards a heavy nuclear target of charge $$Ze$$. Then the distance of closest approach for the alpha nucleus will be proportional to ",
    "options": [
      "$${v^2}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over m}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {{v^2}}}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {Ze}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "alpha-particle-scattering-and-rutherford-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {{v^2}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Mz2bMY7kQcZWsWlb",
    "question": "It is found that if a neutron suffers an elastic collinear collision with deuterium at rest, fractional loss of its\nenergy is p<sub>d</sub>; while for its similar collision with carbon nucleus at rest, fractional loss of energy is p<sub>c</sub>. The values of p<sub>d</sub> and p<sub>c</sub> are respectively : ",
    "options": [
      "(0, 1)",
      "(0.89, 0.28)",
      "(0.28, 0.89)",
      "(0, 0)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "alpha-particle-scattering-and-rutherford-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "(0.89, 0.28)"
  },
  {
    "id": "d3Ucn2JdtK89K0HxIijgy2xukf3vdpvr",
    "question": "Hydrogen ion and singly ionized helium atom are accelerated, from rest, through the same potential\ndifference. The ratio of final speeds of hydrogen and helium ions is close to :",
    "options": [
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 2",
      "5 : 7",
      "10 : 7"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "alpha-particle-scattering-and-rutherford-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c424zm",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct option from the following options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "In the ground state of Rutherford's model electrons are in stable equilibrium. While in Thomson's model electrons always experience a net-force.",
      "An atom has a nearly continuous mass distribution in a Rutherford's model but has a highly non-uniform mass distribution in Thomson's model.",
      "A classical atom based on Rutherford's model is doomed to collapse.",
      "The positively charged part of the atom possesses most of the mass in Rutherford's model but not in Thomson's model."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "alpha-particle-scattering-and-rutherford-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "A classical atom based on Rutherford's model is doomed to collapse."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswq2kx",
    "question": "<p>The energy of $$\\mathrm{He}^{+}$$ ion in its first excited state is, (The ground state energy for the Hydrogen atom is $$-13.6 ~\\mathrm{eV})$$ :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-13.6 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$",
      "$$-27.2 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$",
      "$$-3.4 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$",
      "$$-54.4 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "alpha-particle-scattering-and-rutherford-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "$$-13.6 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqnmnl",
    "question": "<p>The waves emitted when a metal target is bombarded with high energy electrons are</p>",
    "options": [
      " Infrared rays",
      "Radio Waves",
      "Microwaves",
      "X-rays"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "alpha-particle-scattering-and-rutherford-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "X-rays"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfm0ryi",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Most of the mass of the atom and all its positive charge are concentrated in a tiny nucleus and the electrons revolve around it, is Rutherford's model.</p>\n<p>Statement II : An atom is a spherical cloud of positive charges with electrons embedded in it, is a special case of Rutherford's model.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "alpha-particle-scattering-and-rutherford-model-of-atom",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "t5PziT3qZsxzNgR8",
    "question": "If $$13.6$$ $$eV$$ energy is required to ionize the hydrogen atom, then the energy required to remove an electron from $$n=2$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$10.2$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$0$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$3.4$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$6.8$$ $$eV.$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$3.4$$ $$eV$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "UcnBfSHIA5MpCd9G",
    "question": "The wavelengths involved in the spectrum of deuterium $$\\left( {{}_1^2\\,D} \\right)$$ are slightly different from that of hydrogen spectrum, because ",
    "options": [
      "the size of the two nuclei are different ",
      "the nuclear forces are different in the two cases ",
      "the masses of the two nuclei are different ",
      "the attraction between the electron and the nucleus is different in the two cases "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "the masses of the two nuclei are different "
  },
  {
    "id": "TRtLCaMnq9FLZ9zd",
    "question": "Which of the following atoms has the lowest ionization potential ? ",
    "options": [
      "$${}_7^{14}N$$ ",
      "$${}_{55}^{133}\\,Cs$$ ",
      "$${}_{18}^{40}\\,Ar$$ ",
      "$${}_8^{16}\\,O$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${}_{55}^{133}\\,Cs$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "aeFwtWYlFHKpp345",
    "question": "If the binding energy of the electron in a hydrogen atom is $$13.6eV,$$ the energy required to remove the electron from the first excited state of $$L{i^{ +  + }}$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$30.6$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$13.6$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$3.4$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$122.4$$ $$eV$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$30.6$$ $$eV$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "YQo15g0qID6qndlx",
    "question": "Which of the following transitions in hydrogen atoms emit photons of highest frequency ?",
    "options": [
      "$$n = 1$$ to $$n=2$$ ",
      "$$n = 2$$ to $$n=6$$ ",
      "$$n = 6$$ to $$n=2$$ ",
      "$$n = 2$$ to $$n=1$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$n = 2$$ to $$n=1$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "nA8jwc73aR0R2zBS",
    "question": "Suppose an electron is attracted towards the origin by a force $${k \\over r}$$ where $$'k'$$ is a constant and $$'r'$$ is the distance of the electron from the origin. By applying Bohr model to this system, the radius of the $${n^{th}}$$ orbital of the electron is found to be $$'{r_n}'$$ and the kinetic energy of the electron to be $$'{T_n}'.$$ \n<p>Then which of the following is true? </p>",
    "options": [
      "$${T_n} \\propto {1 \\over {{n^2}}},{r_n} \\propto {n^2}$$ ",
      "$${T_n}$$ independent of $$n,{r_n} \\propto n$$",
      "$${T_n} \\propto {1 \\over n},{r_n} \\propto n$$ ",
      "$${T_n} \\propto {1 \\over n},{r_n} \\propto {n^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${T_n}$$ independent of $$n,{r_n} \\propto n$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "s3BeYEZV7vNh9876",
    "question": "The transition from the state $$n=4$$  to $$n=3$$ in a hydrogen like atom result in ultra violet radiation. Infrared radiation will be obtained in the transition from : ",
    "options": [
      "$$3 \\to 2$$ ",
      "$$4 \\to 2$$",
      "$$5 \\to 4$$",
      "$$2 \\to 1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$5 \\to 4$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "vcMFHQ01FVRjO7lC",
    "question": "Energy required for the electron excitation in $$L{i^{ +  + }}$$ from the first to the third Bohr orbit is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$36.3$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$108.8$$ $$eV$$",
      "$$122.4$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$12.1$$ $$eV$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$108.8$$ $$eV$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "D0BrAVlk651aQ3Pd",
    "question": "Hydrogen atom is excited from ground state to another state with principal quantum number equal to $$4.$$ Then the number of spectral lines in the emission spectra will be : ",
    "options": [
      "$$2$$ ",
      "$$3$$ ",
      "$$5$$ ",
      "$$6$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$6$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "h4cMuNp7bssJ79B8",
    "question": "A diatomic molecule is made of two masses $${m_1}$$ and $${m_2}$$ which are separated by a distance $$r.$$ If we calculate its rotational energy by applying Bohr's rule of angular momentum quantization, its energy will be given by: ($$n$$ is an integer) ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{{\\left( {{m_1} + {m_2}} \\right)}^2}{n^2}{h^2}} \\over {2m_1^2m_2^2{r^2}}}$$ ",
      "$${{{n^2}{h^2}} \\over {2\\left( {{m_1} + {m_2}} \\right){r^2}}}$$ ",
      "$${{2{n^2}{h^2}} \\over {\\left( {{m_1} + {m_2}} \\right){r^2}}}$$ ",
      "$${{\\left( {{m_1} + {m_2}} \\right){n^2}{h^2}} \\over {2{m_1}{m_2}{r^2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${{\\left( {{m_1} + {m_2}} \\right){n^2}{h^2}} \\over {2{m_1}{m_2}{r^2}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "EMS4NwMsxXTATMl3",
    "question": "In a hydrogen like atom electron make transition from an energy level with quantum number $$n$$ to another with quantum number $$\\left( {n - 1} \\right)$$. If $$n &gt;  &gt; 1,$$ the frequency of radiation emitted is proportional  to : ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over n}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {{n^{{3 \\over 2}}}}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {{n^3}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {{n^3}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "GRStPOuEY8L8EZaW",
    "question": "The radiation corresponding to $$3 \\to 2$$ transition of hydrogen atom falls on a metal surface to produce photoelectrons. These electrons are made to enter a magnetic field $$3 \\times {10^{ - 4}}\\,T.$$ If the radius of the larger circular path followed by these electrons is $$10.0$$ $$mm$$, the work function of the metal is close to: ",
    "options": [
      "$$1.8$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$1.1$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$0.8$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$1.6$$ $$eV$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$1.1$$ $$eV$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "X6C549hC3b9UUpwC",
    "question": "Hydrogen $$\\left( {{}_1{H^1}} \\right)$$, Deuterium $$\\left( {{}_1{H^2}} \\right)$$, singly ionised Helium $${\\left( {{}_2H{e^4}} \\right)^ + }$$ and doubly ionised lithium $${\\left( {{}_3L{i^6}} \\right)^{ +  + }}$$ all have one electron around the nucleus. Consider an electron transition from $$n=2$$ to $$n=1.$$ If the wavelengths of emitted radiation are $${\\lambda _1},{\\lambda _2},{\\lambda _3}$$ and $${\\lambda _4}$$ respectively then approximately which one of the following is correct?",
    "options": [
      "$$4{\\lambda _1} = 2{\\lambda _2} = 2{\\lambda _3} = {\\lambda _4}$$ ",
      "$${\\lambda _1} = 2{\\lambda _2} = 2{\\lambda _3} = {\\lambda _4}$$ ",
      "$${\\lambda _1} = {\\lambda _2} = 4{\\lambda _3} = 9{\\lambda _4}$$ ",
      "$${\\lambda _1} = 2{\\lambda _2} = 3{\\lambda _3} = 4{\\lambda _4}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${\\lambda _1} = {\\lambda _2} = 4{\\lambda _3} = 9{\\lambda _4}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "f1VCtY5QI3pxZNBP",
    "question": "As an electron makes a transition from an excited state to the ground state of a hydrogen - like atom/ion : ",
    "options": [
      "kinetic energy decreases, potential energy increases but total energy remains same ",
      "kinetic energy and total energy decrease but potential energy increases ",
      "its kinetic energy increases but potential energy and total energy decrease",
      "kinetic energy, potential energy and total energy decrease "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "its kinetic energy increases but potential energy and total energy decrease"
  },
  {
    "id": "nJ7izufyR29BNU7Sikprv",
    "question": "A hydrogen atom makes a transition from n = 2 to n = 1 and emits a photon. This photon strikes a doubly ionized lithium atom (z = 3) in excited state and completely removes the orbiting electron. The least quantum number for the excited state of the ion for the process is :",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "3",
      "4",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "4Z7EBmzMEEHC9RcXJc6tZ",
    "question": "The acceleration of an electron in the first orbit of the hydrogen atom (n = 1) is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{h^2}} \\over {{\\pi ^2}{m^2}{r^3}}}$$",
      "$${{{h^2}} \\over {{8\\pi ^2}{m^2}{r^3}}}$$",
      "$${{{h^2}} \\over {{4\\pi ^2}{m^2}{r^3}}}$$",
      "$${{{h^2}} \\over {{4\\pi }{m^2}{r^3}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${{{h^2}} \\over {{4\\pi ^2}{m^2}{r^3}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "J0N3KwLGZxT2gBT4GnmmY",
    "question": "According to Bohr’s theory, the time averaged magnetic field at the centre (i.e. nucleus) of a hydrogen atom due to the motion of electrons in the n<sup>th</sup> orbit is proportional to : (n = principal  quantum number)\n",
    "options": [
      "$${n^{ - 4}}$$ ",
      "$${n^{ - 5}}$$ ",
      "n<sup>$$-$$3</sup> ",
      "n<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${n^{ - 5}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "1LvjgkZaOgSrgOKXTShwX",
    "question": "Muon ($$\\mu $$<sup>$$-$$</sup>) is a negatively charged (|q| = |e|) particle with a mass m<sub>$$\\mu $$</sub> = 200 m<sub>e</sub>, where m<sub>e</sub> is the mass of the electron and e is the electronic charge. If $$\\mu $$<sup>$$-$$</sup> is bond to a proton to form a hydrogen like atom,  identify the correct statements.\n<br/>(A)   Radis of the muonic orbit is 200 times smaller than that of the electron. \n<br/>(B)   The speed of the $$\\mu $$<sup>$$-$$</sup> in the n<sup>th</sup> orbit is $${1 \\over {200}}$$ times that of the electron in the n<sup>th</sup> orbit.\n<br/>(C)   The ionization energy of muonic atom is 200 timesmore than of an hydroen atom. \n<br/>(D)   The momentum of the muon in the n<sup>th</sup> orbit is 200 times more than that of the electron. ",
    "options": [
      "(A), &nbsp;&nbsp; (B), &nbsp;&nbsp; (D)",
      "(A), &nbsp;&nbsp; (C), &nbsp;&nbsp; (D)",
      "(B), &nbsp;&nbsp; (D)",
      "(C), &nbsp;&nbsp; (D)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "(A), &nbsp;&nbsp; (C), &nbsp;&nbsp; (D)"
  },
  {
    "id": "PavhhsYmKCP6uAqubzoe5",
    "question": "The energy required to remove the electron from a singly ionized Helium atom is $$2.2$$ times the energies required to remove an electron from Helium atom. The total energy required to ionize the Helium atom completely is :",
    "options": [
      "$$20$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$34$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$79$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$109$$ $$eV$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$79$$ $$eV$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Pirx9xZT9W7Gitl2",
    "question": "If the series limit frequency of the Lyman series is $${\\nu _L}$$, then the series limit frequency of the Pfund series is: ",
    "options": [
      "$${\\nu _L}/25$$ ",
      "$$25{\\nu _L}$$",
      "$$16{\\nu _L}$$ ",
      "$${\\nu _L}/16$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${\\nu _L}/25$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "keWq8KI8WjGXxYdp",
    "question": "An electron from various excited states of hydrogen atom emit radiation to come to the ground state. Let\n$${\\lambda _n}$$, $${\\lambda _g}$$ be the de Broglie wavelength of the electron in the n<sup>th</sup> state and the ground state respectively. Let\n$${\\Lambda _n}$$ be the wavelength of the emitted photon in the transition from the n<sup>th</sup> state to the ground state. For large n, (A, B are constants)",
    "options": [
      "$${\\Lambda _n} \\approx A + {B \\over {\\lambda _n^2}}$$",
      "$${\\Lambda _n} \\approx A + B{\\lambda _n}$$ ",
      "$$\\Lambda _n^2 \\approx A + B\\lambda _n^2$$ ",
      "$$\\Lambda _n^2 \\approx \\lambda$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${\\Lambda _n} \\approx A + {B \\over {\\lambda _n^2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "YvwRcQgcrtD5hs3MO63rsa0w2w9jx7eqe54",
    "question": "The electron in a hydrogen atom first jumps from the third excited state to the second excited state and\nsubsequently to the first excited state. The ratio of the respective wavelengths, $${{{\\lambda _1}} \\over {{\\lambda _2}}}$$, of the photons emitted\nin this process is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{22} \\over 5}$$",
      "$${7 \\over 5}$$",
      "$${9 \\over 7}$$",
      "$${{20} \\over 7}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${{20} \\over 7}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "rzTPPFCfSfjSKFadMd3rsa0w2w9jx7eb8bl",
    "question": "Consider an electron in a hydrogen atom revolving in its second excited state (having radius 4.65 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$). The\nde-Broglie wavelength of this electron is :",
    "options": [
      "6.6 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$",
      "3.5 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$",
      "9.7 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$",
      "12.9 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "9.7 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "m36uRrsid8FtIZs81N3rsa0w2w9jx3s6kye",
    "question": "An excited He<sup>+</sup>\n ion emits two photons in succession, with wavelengths 108.5 nm and 30.4 nm, in making a\ntransition to ground state. The quantum number n, corresponding to its initial excited state is (for photon of\nwavelength $$\\lambda $$, energy $$E = {{1240\\,eV} \\over {\\lambda (in\\,nm)}}$$) :",
    "options": [
      "n = 4",
      "n = 7",
      "n = 5",
      "n = 6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "n = 5"
  },
  {
    "id": "sqTJR4KA0vY7X8KRFx3rsa0w2w9jwzjc02d",
    "question": "In Li<sup>+ +</sup>, electron in first Bohr orbit is excited to a level by a radiation of wavelength $$\\lambda $$. When the ion gets\ndeexcited to the ground state in all possible ways (including intermediate emissions), a total of six spectral\nlines are observed. What is the value of $$\\lambda $$?\n<br/>(Given : H = 6.63 × 10<sup>–34</sup> Js; c = 3 × 10<sup>8</sup>\n ms\n<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "10.8 nm",
      "12.3 nm",
      "9.4 nm",
      "11.4 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "10.8 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "Zaa8Cu2inmA2ALjqH6aMK",
    "question": "Taking the wavelength of first Balmer line in\nhydrogen spectrum (n = 3 to n = 2) as 660 nm,\nthe wavelength of the 2nd Balmer line (n = 4 to\nn = 2) will be :",
    "options": [
      "642.7 nm",
      "488.9 nm",
      "889.2 nm",
      "388.9 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "488.9 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "16y1MXImK4m6rKpp06JAz",
    "question": "Radiation coming from transitions\nn = 2 to n = 1 of hydrogen atoms fall on He<sup>+</sup>\nions in n = 1 and n = 2 states. The possible\ntransition of helium ions as they absorb energy\nfrom the radiation is :",
    "options": [
      "n = 1 $$ \\to $$ n = 4",
      "n = 2 $$ \\to $$ n = 5",
      "n = 2 $$ \\to $$ n = 4",
      "n = 2 $$ \\to $$ n = 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "n = 2 $$ \\to $$ n = 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "CSmROBamUkhdHJ1Oe1ewW",
    "question": "A particle of mass m moves in a circular orbit in a central potential field U(r) = $${1 \\over 2}$$ kr<sup>2</sup>. If Bohr 's\nquantization conditions are applied, radii of possible orbitls and energy levels vary with quantum number n as : \n",
    "options": [
      "r<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ $$\\sqrt n $$, E<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ n",
      "r<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ $$\\sqrt n $$, E<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ $${1 \\over n}$$",
      "r<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ n, E<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ n",
      "r<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ n<sup>2</sup>, E<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ $${1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "r<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ $$\\sqrt n $$, E<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ n"
  },
  {
    "id": "VDKk7Z1f4AiNiWyhELJ4I",
    "question": "In a hydrogen like atom, when an electron jumps from the M-shell to the L-shell, the wavelength of emitted radiation is $$\\lambda $$. If an electron jumps from N-shell to the L-shell, the wavelength of emitted radiation will be: ",
    "options": [
      "$${{25} \\over {16}}$$ $$\\lambda $$",
      "$${{27} \\over {20}}$$ $$\\lambda $$",
      "$${{16} \\over {25}}$$ $$\\lambda $$",
      "$${{20} \\over {27}}$$ $$\\lambda $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${{20} \\over {27}}$$ $$\\lambda $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "FIrQrz66tHF8UYbcftTQC",
    "question": "A hydrogen atom, initially in the ground state is excited by absorbing a photon of wavelength 980$$\\mathop A\\limits^ \\circ  $$. The radius of the atom in the excited state, in terms of Bohr radius a<sub>0</sub> will be : (hc = 12500 eV$$\\mathop A\\limits^ \\circ  $$)",
    "options": [
      "4a<sub>0</sub>",
      "9a<sub>0</sub>",
      "25a<sub>0</sub>",
      "16a<sub>0</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "16a<sub>0</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "huPUPLVIjXYGZr30XjUD0",
    "question": "A He<sup>+</sup> ion is in its first excited state. Its\nionization energy is :-",
    "options": [
      "13.60 eV",
      "6.04 eV",
      "48.36 eV",
      "54.40 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "13.60 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "qHvrWxRT4A6DGYIGXN7k9k2k5dl1t8p",
    "question": "The time period of revolution of electron in its ground state orbit in a hydrogen atom is 1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-16</sup> s. The frequency of revolution of the electron in its first excited state (in s<sup>-1</sup>) is :\n",
    "options": [
      "5.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>12</sup>",
      "1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup>",
      "7.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup>",
      "6.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>15</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "7.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "0HchujemsojpIz4Qci7k9k2k5l9kfbd",
    "question": "The energy required to ionise a hydrogen like\nion in its ground state is 9 Rydbergs. What is\nthe wavelength of the radiation emitted when\nthe electron in this ion jumps from the second\nexcited state to the ground state ?",
    "options": [
      "35.8 nm",
      "11.4 nm",
      "8.6 nm",
      "24.2 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "11.4 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "ytzgc8giNCiRqXJuIPjgy2xukexs9ya6",
    "question": "In a hydrogen atom the electron makes a\ntransition from (n + 1)<sup>th</sup> level to the n<sup>th</sup> level.\nIf n &gt;&gt; 1, the frequency of radiation emitted is\nproportional to :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over n}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {{n^3}}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {{n^4}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {{n^3}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "d2ySfBgbnFTePmpauK1klroo58e",
    "question": "According to Bohr atomic model, in which of the following transitions will the frequency be maximum?",
    "options": [
      "n = 2 to n = 1",
      "n = 3 to n = 2",
      "n = 4 to n = 3",
      "n = 5 to n = 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "n = 2 to n = 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldWYWX064gd7GPEDzu1klt2u91x",
    "question": "The wavelength of the photon emitted by a hydrogen atom when an electron makes a transition from n = 2 to n = 1 state is :",
    "options": [
      "194.8 nm",
      "490.7 nm",
      "913.3 nm",
      "121.8 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "121.8 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "Zyqnpg3XXS9z2CjBVr1kltjcayj",
    "question": "If $$\\lambda$$<sub>1</sub> and $$\\lambda$$<sub>2</sub> are the wavelengths of the third member of Lyman and first member of the Paschen series respectively, then the value of $$\\lambda$$<sub>1</sub> : $$\\lambda$$<sub>2</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "7 : 135",
      "7 : 108",
      "1 : 9",
      "1 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "7 : 135"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ku3f7NOWoEVufpImbq1kmj1e3vm",
    "question": "If an electron is moving in the n<sup>th</sup> orbit of the hydrogen atom, then its velocity (v<sub>n</sub>) for the n<sup>th</sup> orbit is given as :",
    "options": [
      "$${v_n} \\propto {1 \\over n}$$",
      "v<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ n<sup>2</sup>",
      "v<sub>n</sub> $$ \\propto $$ n",
      "$${v_n} \\propto {1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$${v_n} \\propto {1 \\over n}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "txvpfizTT1K3LQq3xX1kmj3t6ql",
    "question": "Which level of the single ionized carbon has the same energy as the ground state energy of hydrogen atom?",
    "options": [
      "8",
      "6",
      "1",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "6"
  },
  {
    "id": "o9VorCr6eZN0xXMKZA1kmka86pl",
    "question": "The atomic hydrogen emits a line spectrum consisting of various series. Which series of hydrogen atomic spectra is lying in the visible region?",
    "options": [
      "Brackett series",
      "Balmer series",
      "Paschen series",
      "Lyman series"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "Balmer series"
  },
  {
    "id": "8KP7rLahTFLiWpJbQ71kmkqwv4e",
    "question": "Imagine that the electron in a hydrogen atom is replaced by a muon ($$\\mu$$). The mass of muon particle is 207 times that of an electron and charge is equal to the charge of an electron. The ionization potential of this hydrogen atom will be :",
    "options": [
      "13.6 eV",
      "2815.2 eV",
      "331.2 eV",
      "27.2 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "2815.2 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktac194x",
    "question": "A particular hydrogen like ion emits radiation of frequency 2.92 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup> Hz when it makes transition from n = 3 to n = 1. The frequency in Hz of radiation emitted in transition from n = 2 to n = 1 will be :",
    "options": [
      "0.44 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup>",
      "6.57 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup>",
      "4.38 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup>",
      "2.46 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "2.46 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56vfq7c",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : In hydrogen atom, the frequency of radiation emitted when an electron jumps from lower energy orbit (E<sub>1</sub>) to higher energy orbit (E<sub>2</sub>), is given as hf = E<sub>1</sub> $$-$$ E<sub>2</sub></p>\n<p>Statement II : The jumping of electron from higher energy orbit (E<sub>2</sub>) to lower energy orbit (E<sub>1</sub>) is associated with frequency of radiation given as f = (E<sub>2</sub> $$-$$ E<sub>1</sub>)/h</p>\n<p>This condition is Bohr's frequency condition.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57qgiqx",
    "question": "<p>A hydrogen atom in its ground state absorbs 10.2 eV of energy. The angular momentum of electron of the hydrogen atom will increase by the value of :</p>\n<p>(Given, Planck's constant = 6.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js).</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.10 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js",
      "1.05 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js",
      "3.15 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js",
      "4.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "1.05 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5akyfa2",
    "question": "<p>The ratio for the speed of the electron in the 3<sup>rd</sup> orbit of He<sup>+</sup> to the speed of the electron in the 3<sup>rd</sup> orbit of hydrogen atom will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "1 : 2",
      "4 : 1",
      "2 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bcb0bc",
    "question": "<p>In Bohr's atomic model of hydrogen, let K, P and E are the kinetic energy, potential energy and total energy of the electron respectively. Choose the correct option when the electron undergoes transitions to a higher level :</p>",
    "options": [
      "All K, P and E increase.",
      "K decreases, P and E increase.",
      "P decreases, K and E increase.",
      "K increases, P and E decrease."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "K decreases, P and E increase."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w38ipy",
    "question": "<p>A hydrogen atom in ground state absorbs 12.09 eV of energy. The orbital angular momentum of the electron is increased by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.05 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js",
      "2.11 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js",
      "3.16 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js",
      "4.22 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "2.11 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dzacr6",
    "question": "<p>The momentum of an electron revolving in $$\\mathrm{n}^{\\text {th }}$$ orbit is given by :</p>\n<p>(Symbols have their usual meanings)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{nh}}{2 \\pi \\mathrm{r}}$$",
      "$$\n\\frac{n h}{2 r}\n$$",
      "$$\n\\frac{\\mathrm{nh}}{2 \\pi}\n$$",
      "$$\\frac{2 \\pi r}{\\mathrm{nh}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{nh}}{2 \\pi \\mathrm{r}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dzbteg",
    "question": "<p>The magnetic moment of an electron (e) revolving in an orbit around nucleus with an orbital angular momentum is given by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\n\\vec{\\mu}_{\\mathrm{L}}=\\frac{\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{eL}}}{2 \\mathrm{~m}}\n$$",
      "$$\\vec{\\mu}_{\\mathrm{L}}=-\\frac{\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{eL}}}{2 \\mathrm{~m}}$$",
      "$$\\vec{\\mu}_{l}=-\\frac{\\overrightarrow{e L}}{\\mathrm{~m}}$$",
      "$$\n\\vec{\\mu}_{l}=\\frac{2 \\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{eL}}}{\\mathrm{m}}\n$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\vec{\\mu}_{\\mathrm{L}}=-\\frac{\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{eL}}}{2 \\mathrm{~m}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f5efaj",
    "question": "<p>Hydrogen atom from excited state comes to the ground state by emitting a photon of wavelength $$\\lambda$$. The value of principal quantum number '$$n$$' of the excited state will be : ($$\\mathrm{R}:$$ Rydberg constant)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{\\lambda \\mathrm{R}}{\\lambda-1}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{\\lambda \\mathrm{R}}{\\lambda \\mathrm{R}-1}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{\\lambda}{\\lambda \\mathrm{R}-1}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{\\lambda R^{2}}{\\lambda R-1}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{\\lambda \\mathrm{R}}{\\lambda \\mathrm{R}-1}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p5g0cg",
    "question": "<p>Find the ratio of energies of photons produced due to transition of an electron of hydrogen atom from its (i) second permitted energy level to the first level, and (ii) the highest permitted energy level to the first permitted level.</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 : 4",
      "4 : 3",
      "1 : 4",
      "4 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "3 : 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldny12o3",
    "question": "<p>An electron of a hydrogen like atom, having $$Z=4$$, jumps from $$4^{\\text {th }}$$ energy state to $$2^{\\text {nd }}$$ energy state. The energy released in this process, will be :</p>\n<p>(Given Rch = $$13.6~\\mathrm{eV}$$)</p>\n<p>Where R = Rydberg constant</p>\n<p>c = Speed of light in vacuum</p>\n<p>h = Planck's constant</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$10.5 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$",
      "$$40.8 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$",
      "$$13.6 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$",
      "$$3.4 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$40.8 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo66r5d",
    "question": "The radius of electron's second stationary orbit in Bohr's atom is R. The radius of 3rd orbit will be",
    "options": [
      "2.25R",
      "$3 \\mathrm{R}$",
      "$\\frac{\\mathrm{R}}{3}$",
      "$9 \\mathrm{R}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "2.25R"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr1y5cy",
    "question": "<p>Speed of an electron in Bohr's $$7^{\\text {th }}$$ orbit for Hydrogen atom is $$3.6 \\times 10^{6} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. The corresponding speed of the electron in $$3^{\\text {rd }}$$ orbit, in $$\\mathrm{m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left(1.8 \\times 10^{6}\\right)$$",
      "$$\\left(7.5 \\times 10^{6}\\right)$$",
      "$$\\left(8.4 \\times 10^{6}\\right)$$",
      "$$\\left(3.6 \\times 10^{6}\\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\left(8.4 \\times 10^{6}\\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwrn00y",
    "question": "<p>A photon is emitted in transition from n = 4 to n = 1 level in hydrogen atom. The corresponding wavelength for this transition is (given, h = 4 $$\\times$$ 10$$^{-15}$$ eVs) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "99.3 nm",
      "94.1 nm",
      "974 nm",
      "941 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "94.1 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrjh1y3",
    "question": "<p>A $$12.5 \\mathrm{~eV}$$ electron beam is used to bombard gaseous hydrogen at room temperature. The number of spectral lines emitted will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "4",
      "3",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyf0gm1",
    "question": "<p>The angular momentum for the electron in Bohr's orbit is L. If the electron is assumed to revolve in second orbit of hydrogen atom, then the change in angular momentum will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "L",
      "$$\\frac{L}{2}$$",
      "zero",
      "2 L"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "L"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh30r2ot",
    "question": "<p>A small particle of mass $$m$$ moves in such a way that its potential energy $$U=\\frac{1}{2} m ~\\omega^{2} r^{2}$$ where $$\\omega$$ is constant and $$r$$ is the distance of the particle from origin. Assuming Bohr's quantization of momentum and circular orbit, the radius of $$n^{\\text {th }}$$ orbit will be proportional to,</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{n}$$",
      "$$n^{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{n}$$",
      "$$n$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{n}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsamb8bl",
    "question": "From the statements given below :<br/><br/>\n(A) The angular momentum of an electron in $n^{\\text {th }}$ orbit is an integral multiple of $\\hbar$.<br/><br/>\n(B) Nuclear forces do not obey inverse square law.<br/><br/>\n(C) Nuclear forces are spin dependent.<br/><br/>\n(D) Nuclear forces are central and charge independent.<br/><br/>\n(E) Stability of nucleus is inversely proportional to the value of packing fraction.\n<br/><br/>\nChoose the <b>correct</b> answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(B), (C), (D), (E) only",
      "(A), (C), (D), (E) only",
      "(A), (B), (C), (E) only",
      "(A), (B), (C), (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "(A), (B), (C), (E) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbkxrye",
    "question": "The minimum energy required by a hydrogen atom in ground state to emit radiation in Balmer series is nearly :",
    "options": [
      "$13.6 \\mathrm{eV}$",
      "$1.5 \\mathrm{eV}$",
      "$12.1 \\mathrm{eV}$",
      "$1.9 \\mathrm{eV}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$12.1 \\mathrm{eV}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3gmgr",
    "question": "<p>The radius of third stationary orbit of electron for Bohr's atom is R. The radius of fourth stationary orbit will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{4}{3} \\mathrm{R}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{16}{9} R$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{3}{4} R$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{9}{16} \\mathrm{R}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{16}{9} R$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse6f47l",
    "question": "<p>If the wavelength of the first member of Lyman series of hydrogen is $$\\lambda$$. The wavelength of the second member will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{27}{5} \\lambda$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{5}{27} \\lambda$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{27}{32} \\lambda$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{32}{27} \\lambda$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{27}{32} \\lambda$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg5gkdv",
    "question": "<p>An electron revolving in $$n^{\\text {th }}$$ Bohr orbit has magnetic moment $$\\mu_n$$. If $$\\mu_n \\propto n^x$$, the value of $$x$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "0",
      "3",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgcx4ob",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of the magnitude of the kinetic energy to the potential energy of an electron in the 5<sup>th</sup> excited state of a hydrogen atom is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "1",
      "$$\\frac{1}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwco24",
    "question": "<p>A hydrogen atom in ground state is given an energy of $$10.2 \\mathrm{~eV}$$. How many spectral lines will be emitted due to transition of electrons?</p>",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "6",
      "10",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2es2v5",
    "question": "<p>According to Bohr's theory, the moment of momentum of an electron revolving in $$4^{\\text {th }}$$ orbit of hydrogen atom is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2 \\frac{h}{\\pi}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{h}{2 \\pi}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{h}{\\pi}$$\n",
      "$$8 \\frac{h}{\\pi}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$2 \\frac{h}{\\pi}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3tw0",
    "question": "<p>An electron rotates in a circle around a nucleus having positive charge $$\\mathrm{Ze}$$. Correct relation between total energy (E) of electron to its potential energy (U) is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2 \\mathrm{E}=3 \\mathrm{U}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{E}=\\mathrm{U}$$\n",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{E}=\\mathrm{U}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{E}=2 \\mathrm{U}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$2 \\mathrm{E}=\\mathrm{U}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s23rt",
    "question": "<p>The angular momentum of an electron in a hydrogen atom is proportional to : (Where $$\\mathrm{r}$$ is the radius of orbit of electron)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{r}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{\\mathrm{r}}}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{r}}$$",
      "r"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{r}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29eed",
    "question": "<p>The longest wavelength associated with Paschen series is : (Given $$\\mathrm{R}_{\\mathrm{H}}=1.097 \\times 10^7 \\mathrm{SI}$$ unit)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2.973 \\times 10^{-6} \\mathrm{~m}$$\n",
      "$$1.876 \\times 10^{-6} \\mathrm{~m}$$\n",
      "$$1.094 \\times 10^{-6} \\mathrm{~m}$$\n",
      "$$3.646 \\times 10^{-6} \\mathrm{~m}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$1.876 \\times 10^{-6} \\mathrm{~m}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc587n8",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of the shortest wavelength of Balmer series to the shortest wavelength of Lyman series for hydrogen atom is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: 2$$\n",
      "$$1: 4$$\n",
      "$$2: 1$$\n",
      "$$4: 1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "bohr's-model-and-hydrogen-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$4: 1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "YnV25A2VbItpU38U",
    "question": "In the nuclear fusion reaction \n$$${}_1^2H + {}_1^3H \\to {}_2^4He + n$$$\n<br/>given that the repulsive potential energy between the two nuclei is $$ \\sim 7.7 \\times {10^{ - 14}}J$$, the temperature at which the gases must be heated to initiate the reaction is nearly \n<br/>[ Boltzmann's Constant $$k = 1.38 \\times {10^{ - 23}}\\,J/K$$ ]",
    "options": [
      "$${10^7}\\,\\,K$$ ",
      "$${10^5}\\,\\,K$$ ",
      "$${10^3}\\,\\,K$$ ",
      "$${10^9}\\,\\,K$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$${10^9}\\,\\,K$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "1BXDWJYutoMAJLBe",
    "question": "The binding energy per nucleon of deuteron $$\\left( {{}_1^2\\,H} \\right)$$ and helium nucleus $$\\left( {{}_2^4\\,He} \\right)$$ is $$1.1$$ $$MeV$$ and $$7$$ $$MeV$$ respectively. If two deuteron nuclei react to form a single helium nucleus, then the energy released is ",
    "options": [
      "$$23.6\\,\\,MeV$$ ",
      "$$26.9\\,\\,MeV$$",
      "$$13.9\\,\\,MeV$$",
      "$$19.2\\,\\,MeV$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$$23.6\\,\\,MeV$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "94qQQCVosZrezE7R",
    "question": "A nuclear transformation is denoted by $$X\\left( {n,\\alpha } \\right)\\matrix{\n   7  \\cr \n   3  \\cr \n\n } Li.$$ Which of the following is the nucleus of element $$X$$ ?  ",
    "options": [
      "$${}_5^{10}B$$ ",
      "$${}^{12}{C_6}$$ ",
      "$${}_4^{11}Be$$ ",
      "$${}_5^9B$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$${}_5^{10}B$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "jWgpEmdreM2ZVJUe",
    "question": "When $${}_3L{i^7}$$ nuclei are bombarded by protons, and the resultant nuclei are $${}_4B{e^8}$$, the emitted particles will be ",
    "options": [
      "alpha particles ",
      "beta particles ",
      "gamma photons ",
      "neutrons "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "gamma photons "
  },
  {
    "id": "lSthkiS5WymUs0th",
    "question": "If the binding energy per nucleon in $${}_3^7Li$$ and $${}_2^4He$$ nuclei are $$5.60$$ $$MeV$$ and $$7.06$$ $$MeV$$ respectively, then in the reaction \n$$$p + {}_3^7Li \\to 2\\,{}_2^4He$$$\n<br/>energy of proton must be",
    "options": [
      "$$28.24$$ $$MeV$$ ",
      "$$17.28$$ $$MeV$$ ",
      "$$1.46$$ $$MeV$$ ",
      "$$39.2$$ $$MeV$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$$17.28$$ $$MeV$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "N2Mpt56VPTA7TUtF",
    "question": "If $${M_O}$$ is the mass of an oxygen isotope $${}_8{O^{17}}$$ , $${M_p}$$ and $${M_N}$$ are the masses of a proton and neutron respectively, the nuclear binding energy of the isotope is ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {{M_O} - 17{M_N}} \\right){C^2}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {{M_O} - 8{M_P}} \\right){C^2}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {{M_O} - 8{M_P} - 9{M_N}} \\right){C^2}$$ ",
      "$${{M_O}{c^2}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {{M_O} - 8{M_P} - 9{M_N}} \\right){C^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "tJBu2OaCdd3mAKfO",
    "question": "This question contains Statement- 1 and  Statement- 2. Of the four choices given after the statements,  choose the one that best describes the two statements: \n<br/><b>Statement- 1:</b>\n<br/>Energy is released when heavy nuclei undergo fission or light nuclei undergo fusion and \n<p><b>Statement- 2:</b>\n<br/>For heavy nuclei, binding energy per nucleon increases with increasing $$Z$$  while for light nuclei it decreases with increasing $$Z.$$ </p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement - $$1$$ is false, Statement - $$2$$ is true ",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true; Statement - $$2$$ is a correct explanation for Statement - $$1$$ ",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true; Statement - $$2$$ is not a correct explanation for Statement - $$1$$ ",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "Hs6rDLDFbOs0tuUh",
    "question": "A nucleus of mass $$M+$$$$\\Delta m$$ is at rest and decays into two daughter nuclei of equal mass $${M \\over 2}$$ each. Speed of light is $$c.$$ \n<br/><br/><p>The binding energy per nucleon for the parent nucleus is $${E_1}$$ and that for the daughter nuclei is $${E_2}.$$ Then </p>",
    "options": [
      "$${E_2} = 2{E_1}$$ ",
      "$${E_1} &gt; {E_2}$$ ",
      "$${E_2} &gt; {E_1}$$ ",
      "$${E_1} = 2{E_2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$${E_2} &gt; {E_1}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "bLLjw7KFn61oLENm",
    "question": "A nucleus of mass $$M+$$$$\\Delta m$$ is at rest and decays into two daughter nuclei of equal mass $${M \\over 2}$$ each. Speed of light is $$c.$$ \n<br/><br/><p>The speed of daughter nuclei is </p>",
    "options": [
      "$$c{{\\Delta m} \\over {M + \\Delta m}}$$ ",
      "$$c\\sqrt {{{2\\Delta m} \\over M}} $$ ",
      "$$c\\sqrt {{{\\Delta m} \\over M}} $$ ",
      "$$c\\sqrt {{{\\Delta m} \\over {M + \\Delta m}}} $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$$c\\sqrt {{{2\\Delta m} \\over M}} $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "e4iI1qyGqr7MvABX",
    "question": "Assume that a neutron breaks into a proton and an electron.  The energy released during this process is : (mass of neutron $$ = 1.6725 \\times {10^{ - 27}}kg,$$ mass of proton $$ = 1.6725 \\times {10^{ - 27}}\\,kg,$$ mass of electron $$ = 9 \\times {10^{ - 31}}\\,kg$$ ).",
    "options": [
      "$$0.51$$ $$MeV$$ ",
      "$$7.10\\,MeV$$ ",
      "$$6.30\\,MeV$$",
      "$$5.4\\,MeV$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$$0.51$$ $$MeV$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ibbQ63XVYABiB0w04ZycX",
    "question": "Imagine that a reactor converts all given mass into energy and that it operates at a power level of 10<sup>9</sup>  watt. The mass of the fuel consumed per hour in the reactor will be : (velocity of light, c is \n3×10<sup>8</sup>  m/s)\n",
    "options": [
      "0.96 gm",
      "0.8 gm ",
      "4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> gm",
      "6.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> gm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> gm"
  },
  {
    "id": "8kutpMFkVMoimP8wXnAsk",
    "question": "Two deuterons undergo nuclear fusion to form a Helium nucleus. Energy released in this process is : (given binding energy per nucleon for deuteron = 1.1 MeV and for helium = 7.0 MeV)\n",
    "options": [
      "30.2 MeV",
      "32.4 MeV",
      "23.6 MeV",
      "25.8 MeV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "23.6 MeV"
  },
  {
    "id": "E5VoaWfI1qQHQgOntLuRH",
    "question": "Consider the nuclear fission\n<br/><br/>Ne<sup>20</sup> $$ \\to $$ 2He<sup>4</sup> + C<sup>12</sup>\n<br/><br/>Given that the binding energy/ nucleon of Ne<sup>20</sup>, He<sup>4</sup>  and C<sup>12</sup> are, respectively, 8.03 MeV, 7.07 MeV and 7.86 MeV, identify the correct statement - \n",
    "options": [
      "8.3 MeV energy will be released",
      "energy of 11.9 MeV has to be supplied",
      "energy of 12.4 MeV will be supplied",
      "energy of 3.6 MeV will be released"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "energy of 11.9 MeV has to be supplied"
  },
  {
    "id": "EYrwmp6O68sfZomj7bjgy2xukev384om",
    "question": "In a reactor, 2 kg of <sub>92</sub>U<sup>235</sup> fuel is fully used up\nin 30 days. The energy released per fission is\n200 MeV. Given that the Avogadro number,\nN = 6.023 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>26</sup> per kilo mole and 1 eV =\n1.6 × 10<sup>–19</sup> J. The power output of the reactor is\nclose to",
    "options": [
      "125 MW",
      "60 MW",
      "54 MW",
      "35 MW"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "60 MW"
  },
  {
    "id": "38RYFv8N6PByPCAYlfjgy2xukfakyrna",
    "question": "Find the Binding energy per neucleon for $${}_{50}^{120}Sn$$. Mass of proton m<sub>p</sub>\n = 1.00783 U, mass of neutron\nm<sub>n</sub>\n = 1.00867 U and mass of tin nucleus m<sub>Sn</sub> = 119.902199 U. (take 1U = 931 MeV)",
    "options": [
      "9.0 MeV",
      "8.5 MeV",
      "8.0 MeV",
      "7.5 MeV\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "8.5 MeV"
  },
  {
    "id": "NnxEMtzu85vK9Mat50jgy2xukfrnqxbb",
    "question": "You are given that Mass of $${}_3^7Li$$ = 7.0160u,\n<br/>Mass of $${}_2^4He$$ = 4.0026u\n<br/>and Mass of $${}_1^1H$$ = 1.0079u.\n<br/>When 20 g of $${}_3^7Li$$ is converted into $${}_2^4He$$ by proton capture, the energy liberated, (in kWh), is :\n<br/>[Mass of nucleon = 1 GeV/c<sup>2</sup>]\n",
    "options": [
      "6.82 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup>",
      "4.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup>",
      "8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup>",
      "1.33 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "1.33 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "LcnA0r5yQ4XacLMF8o1krpna7dr",
    "question": "A nucleus of mass M emits $$\\gamma$$ -ray photon of frequency 'v'. The loss of internal energy by the nucleus is :<br/><br/>[Take 'c' as the speed of electromagnetic wave]",
    "options": [
      "hv",
      "$$hv\\left[ {1 + {{hv} \\over {2M{c^2}}}} \\right]$$",
      "$$hv\\left[ {1 - {{hv} \\over {2M{c^2}}}} \\right]$$",
      "0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$$hv\\left[ {1 + {{hv} \\over {2M{c^2}}}} \\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsuqw9c",
    "question": "A nucleus with mass number 184 initially at rest emits an $$\\alpha$$-particle. If the Q value of the reaction is 5.5 MeV, calculate the kinetic energy of the $$\\alpha$$-particle.",
    "options": [
      "5.5 MeV",
      "5.0 MeV",
      "5.38 MeV",
      "0.12 MeV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "5.38 MeV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l569n6dx",
    "question": "<p>The Q-value of a nuclear reaction and kinetic energy of the projectile particle, K<sub>p</sub> are related as :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Q = K<sub>p</sub>",
      "(K<sub>p</sub> + Q) < 0",
      "Q < K<sub>p</sub>",
      "(K<sub>p</sub> + Q) > 0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "(K<sub>p</sub> + Q) > 0"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c43tt2",
    "question": "<p>Nucleus A is having mass number 220 and its binding energy per nucleon is 5.6 MeV. It splits in two fragments 'B' and 'C' of mass numbers 105 and 115. The binding energy of nucleons in 'B' and 'C' is 6.4 MeV per nucleon. The energy Q released per fission will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.8 MeV",
      "275 MeV",
      "220 MeV",
      "176 MeV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "176 MeV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i0yn6o",
    "question": "<p>A nucleus of mass $$M$$ at rest splits into two parts having masses $$\\frac{M^{\\prime}}{3}$$ and $${{2M'} \\over 3}(M' &lt; M)$$. The ratio of de Broglie wavelength of two parts will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 2",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 1",
      "2 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "1 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldogd6pr",
    "question": "<p>The mass of proton, neutron and helium nucleus are respectively $$1.0073~u,1.0087~u$$ and $$4.0015~u$$. The binding energy of helium nucleus is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$28.4~\\mathrm{MeV}$$",
      "$$56.8~\\mathrm{MeV}$$",
      "$$7.1~\\mathrm{MeV}$$",
      "$$14.2~\\mathrm{MeV}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$$28.4~\\mathrm{MeV}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq2ec05",
    "question": "<p>$$_{92}^{238}A \\to _{90}^{234}B + _2^4D + Q$$</p>\n<p>In the given nuclear reaction, the approximate amount of energy released will be:</p>\n<p>[Given, mass of $${ }_{92}^{238} \\mathrm{~A}=238.05079 \\times 931.5 ~\\mathrm{MeV} / \\mathrm{c}^{2},$$</p>\n<p>mass of $${ }_{90}^{234} B=234 \\cdot 04363 \\times 931 \\cdot 5 ~\\mathrm{MeV} / \\mathrm{c}^{2},$$</p>\n<p>mass of $$\\left.{ }_{2}^{4} D=4 \\cdot 00260 \\times 931 \\cdot 5 ~\\mathrm{MeV} / \\mathrm{c}^{2}\\right]$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.12 MeV",
      "4.25 MeV",
      "3.82 MeV",
      "5.9 MeV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "4.25 MeV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh022hep",
    "question": "<p>For a nucleus $${ }_{\\mathrm{A}}^{\\mathrm{A}} \\mathrm{X}$$ having mass number $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and atomic number $$\\mathrm{Z}$$</p>\n<p>A. The surface energy per nucleon $$\\left(b_{\\mathrm{s}}\\right)=-a_{1} A^{2 / 3}$$.</p>\n<p>B. The Coulomb contribution to the binding energy $$\\mathrm{b}_{\\mathrm{c}}=-a_{2} \\frac{Z(Z-1)}{A^{4 / 3}}$$</p>\n<p>C. The volume energy $$\\mathrm{b}_{\\mathrm{v}}=a_{3} A$$</p>\n<p>D. Decrease in the binding energy is proportional to surface area.</p>\n<p>E. While estimating the surface energy, it is assumed that each nucleon interacts with 12 nucleons. ( $$a_{1}, a_{2}$$ and $$a_{3}$$ are constants)</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "C, D only",
      "B, C, E only",
      "B, C only",
      "A, B, C, D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "C, D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscp9q8q",
    "question": "<p>The atomic mass of $${ }_6 \\mathrm{C}^{12}$$ is $$12.000000 \\mathrm{~u}$$ and that of $${ }_6 \\mathrm{C}^{13}$$ is $$13.003354 \\mathrm{~u}$$. The required energy to remove a neutron from $${ }_6 \\mathrm{C}^{13}$$, if mass of neutron is $$1.008665 \\mathrm{~u}$$, will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "62.5 MeV",
      "6.25 MeV",
      "4.95 MeV",
      "49.5 MeV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "4.95 MeV"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1zpzt",
    "question": "<p>The explosive in a Hydrogen bomb is a mixture of $${ }_1 \\mathrm{H}^2,{ }_1 \\mathrm{H}^3$$ and $${ }_3 \\mathrm{Li}^6$$ in some condensed form. The chain reaction is given by</p>\n<p>$$\\begin{aligned}\n&amp; { }_3 \\mathrm{Li}^6+{ }_0 \\mathrm{n}^1 \\rightarrow{ }_2 \\mathrm{He}^4+{ }_1 \\mathrm{H}^3 \\\\\n&amp; { }_1 \\mathrm{H}^2+{ }_1 \\mathrm{H}^3 \\rightarrow{ }_2 \\mathrm{He}^4+{ }_0 \\mathrm{n}^1\n\\end{aligned}$$</p>\n<p>During the explosion the energy released is approximately</p>\n<p>[Given ; $$\\mathrm{M}(\\mathrm{Li})=6.01690 \\mathrm{~amu}, \\mathrm{M}\\left({ }_1 \\mathrm{H}^2\\right)=2.01471 \\mathrm{~amu}, \\mathrm{M}\\left({ }_2 \\mathrm{He}^4\\right)=4.00388$$ $$\\mathrm{amu}$$, and $$1 \\mathrm{~amu}=931.5 \\mathrm{~MeV}]$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "22.22 MeV",
      "28.12 MeV",
      "16.48 MeV",
      "12.64 MeV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "22.22 MeV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg5y8yo",
    "question": "<p>In a nuclear fission reaction of an isotope of mass $$M$$, three similar daughter nuclei of same mass are formed. The speed of a daughter nuclei in terms of mass defect $$\\Delta M$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$c \\sqrt{\\frac{3 \\Delta M}{M}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\Delta M c^2}{3}$$\n",
      "$$c \\sqrt{\\frac{2 \\Delta M}{M}}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{2 c \\Delta M}{M}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$$c \\sqrt{\\frac{2 \\Delta M}{M}}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwdqsr",
    "question": "<p>A nucleus at rest disintegrates into two smaller nuclei with their masses in the ratio of $$2: 1$$. After disintegration they will move :</p>",
    "options": [
      "in opposite directions with speed in the ratio of $$1: 2$$ respectively.\n",
      "in the same direction with same speed.\n",
      "in opposite directions with speed in the ratio of $$2: 1$$ respectively.\n",
      "in opposite directions with the same speed."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "in opposite directions with speed in the ratio of $$1: 2$$ respectively.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwem1b",
    "question": "<p>The energy released in the fusion of $$2 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ of hydrogen deep in the sun is $$E_H$$ and the energy released in the fission of $$2 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ of $${ }^{235} \\mathrm{U}$$ is $$E_U$$. The ratio $$\\frac{E_H}{E_U}$$ is approximately:\n(Consider the fusion reaction as $$4_1^1H+2 \\mathrm{e}^{-} \\rightarrow{ }_2^4 \\mathrm{He}+2 v+6 \\gamma+26.7 \\mathrm{~MeV}$$, energy released in the fission reaction of $${ }^{235} \\mathrm{U}$$ is $$200 \\mathrm{~MeV}$$ per fission nucleus and $$\\mathrm{N}_{\\mathrm{A}}= 6.023 \\times 10^{23})$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "7.62",
      "25.6",
      "9.13",
      "15.04"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "7.62"
  },
  {
    "id": "luyita3e",
    "question": "<p>The energy equivalent of $$1 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of substance is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$5.6 \\times 10^{26} \\mathrm{~MeV}$$\n",
      "$$5.6 \\times 10^{12} \\mathrm{~MeV}$$\n",
      "$$5.6 \\mathrm{~eV}$$\n",
      "$$11.2 \\times 10^{24} \\mathrm{~MeV}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$$5.6 \\times 10^{26} \\mathrm{~MeV}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxlw8",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following nuclear fragments corresponding to nuclear fission between neutron $$\\left({ }_0^1 \\mathrm{n}\\right)$$ and uranium isotope $$\\left({ }_{92}^{235} \\mathrm{U}\\right)$$ is correct :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${ }_{56}^{140} \\mathrm{Xe}+{ }_{38}^{94} \\mathrm{Sr}+3{ }_0^1 \\mathrm{n}$$\n",
      "$${ }_{51}^{153} \\mathrm{Sb}+{ }_{41}^{99} \\mathrm{Nb}+3{ }_0^1 \\mathrm{n}$$\n",
      "$${ }_{56}^{144} \\mathrm{Ba}+{ }_{36}^{89} \\mathrm{Kr}+4{ }_0^1 \\mathrm{n}$$\n",
      "$${ }_{56}^{144} \\mathrm{Ba}+{ }_{36}^{89} \\mathrm{Kr}+3{ }_0^1 \\mathrm{n}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$${ }_{56}^{144} \\mathrm{Ba}+{ }_{36}^{89} \\mathrm{Kr}+3{ }_0^1 \\mathrm{n}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3veetz",
    "question": "<p>If $$M_0$$ is the mass of isotope $${ }_5^{12} B, M_p$$ and $$M_n$$ are the masses of proton and neutron, then nuclear binding energy of isotope is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(5 M_p+7 M_n-M_o) C^2$$\n",
      "$$(M_o-5 M_p-7 M_n) C^2$$\n",
      "$$(M_o-5 M_p) C^2$$\n",
      "$$(M_0-12 M_n) C^2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "$$(5 M_p+7 M_n-M_o) C^2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3vefuq",
    "question": "<p>In a hypothetical fission reaction</p>\n<p>$${ }_{92} X^{236} \\rightarrow{ }_{56} \\mathrm{Y}^{141}+{ }_{36} Z^{92}+3 R$$</p>\n<p>The identity of emitted particles (R) is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Proton",
      "Neutron",
      "Electron",
      "$$\\gamma$$-radiations"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "Neutron"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gt1y4",
    "question": "<p>Binding energy of a certain nucleus is $$18 \\times 10^8 \\mathrm{~J}$$. How much is the difference between total mass of all the nucleons and nuclear mass of the given nucleus:</p>",
    "options": [
      "20 $$\\mu$$g",
      "2 $$\\mu$$g",
      "10 $$\\mu$$g",
      "0.2 $$\\mu$$g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nuclear-fission-and-fusion-and-binding-energy",
    "solution": "20 $$\\mu$$g"
  },
  {
    "id": "gbwbvYz5vmma2a3j",
    "question": "If $${N_0}$$ is the original mass of the substance of half-life period $${t_{1/2}} = 5$$ years, then the amount of substance left after $$15$$ years is ",
    "options": [
      "$${N_0}/8$$ ",
      "$${N_0}/16$$",
      "$${N_0}/2$$",
      "$${N_0}/4$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$${N_0}/8$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "pfUEG7Y8Eq3AWTy2",
    "question": "At a specific instant emission of radioactive compound is deflected in a magnetic field. The compound can emit \n<br/>$$\\eqalign{\n  &amp; \\left( i \\right)\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,electrons\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\left( {ii} \\right)\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,protons  \\cr \n  &amp; \\left( {iii} \\right)\\,\\,\\,H{e^{2 + }}\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\left( {iv} \\right)\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,neutrons \\cr} $$\n<p>The emission at instant can be </p>",
    "options": [
      "$$i, ii, iii$$ ",
      "$$i, ii, iii, iv$$ ",
      "$$iv$$ ",
      "$$ii, iii$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$i, ii, iii$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "KXogbFqXErl6uVYK",
    "question": "When a $${U^{238}}$$ nucleus originally at rest, decays by emitting an alpha particle having a speed $$'u',$$ the recoil speed of the residual nucleus is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{4\\mu } \\over {238}}$$ ",
      "$$ - {{4\\mu } \\over {234}}$$ ",
      "$$  {{4\\mu } \\over {234}}$$",
      "$$ - {{4\\mu } \\over {238}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$  {{4\\mu } \\over {234}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "OdNgqZS2YUNA9KjY",
    "question": "A radioactive sample at any instant has its disintegration rate $$5000$$ disintegrations per minute. After $$5$$ minutes, the rate is $$1250$$ disintegrations per minute. Then, the decay constant (per minute) is ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.4$$ $$ln2$$ ",
      "$$0.2$$ $$ln2$$ ",
      "$$0.1$$ $$ln2$$ ",
      "$$0.8$$ $$ln2$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$0.4$$ $$ln2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "mXyckVcJOkEzCcNx",
    "question": "A nucleus with $$Z=92$$ emits the following in a sequence: \n$$$\\alpha ,{\\beta ^ - },{\\beta ^ - },\\alpha ,\\alpha ,\\alpha ,\\alpha ,\\alpha ,{\\beta ^ - },{\\beta ^ - },\\alpha ,{\\beta ^ + },{\\beta ^ + },\\alpha $$$\n<p>Then $$Z$$ of the resulting nucleus is </p> ",
    "options": [
      "$$76$$ ",
      "$$78$$ ",
      "$$82$$ ",
      "$$74$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$78$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "tC5L2rf3jjTIWp2q",
    "question": "Which of the following cannot be emitted by radioactive substances during their decay ? ",
    "options": [
      "Protons ",
      "Neutrinoes ",
      "Helium nuclei ",
      "Electrons "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "Protons "
  },
  {
    "id": "W9RH3682luKjAzCu",
    "question": "Which of the following radiations has the least wavelength ? ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\gamma $$ - rays ",
      "$$\\beta $$ - rays ",
      "$$\\alpha $$ - rays",
      "$$X$$ - rays "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$\\gamma $$ - rays "
  },
  {
    "id": "N9HRUTVrw1p0QpSP",
    "question": "A nucleus disintegrated into two nuclear parts which have their velocities in the ratio of $$2:1.$$ The ratio of their nuclear sizes will be",
    "options": [
      "$${3^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}}}:1$$ ",
      "$$1:{2^{1/3}}$$ ",
      "$${2^{1/3}}:1$$ ",
      "$$1:{3^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$1:{2^{1/3}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "7Yok3u8SgkYgKY5q",
    "question": "If radius of the $$\\matrix{\n   {27}  \\cr \n   {13}  \\cr \n\n } $$ $$Al$$ nucleus is estimated to be $$3.6$$ fermi then the radius of $$\\matrix{\n   {125}  \\cr \n   {52}  \\cr \n\n } \\,Te$$ nucleus is estimated to be nearly ",
    "options": [
      "$$8$$  fermi ",
      "$$6$$  fermi ",
      "$$5$$  fermi ",
      "$$4$$  fermi "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$6$$  fermi "
  },
  {
    "id": "gFbeq2tekhrcrxhu",
    "question": "Starting with a sample of pure $${}^{66}Cu,{7 \\over 8}$$ of it decays into $$Zn$$ in $$15$$ minutes. The corresponding half life is ",
    "options": [
      "$$15$$ minutes ",
      "$$10$$ minutes ",
      "$$7{1 \\over 2}$$ minutes ",
      "$$5$$ minutes"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$5$$ minutes"
  },
  {
    "id": "WOUKKCA8AnBiof9A",
    "question": "The intensity of gamma radiation from a given source is $$L$$. On passing through $$36$$ $$mm$$ of lead, it is reduced to $${{\\rm I} \\over 8}.$$ The thickness of lead which will reduce the intensity to $${{\\rm I} \\over 2}$$ will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$9mm$$ ",
      "$$6mm$$ ",
      "$$12mm$$ ",
      "$$18mm$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$12mm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "rRMlAiKhdCSM3BaD",
    "question": "The $$'rad'$$ is the correct unit used to report the measurement of ",
    "options": [
      "the ability of a beam of gamma ray photons to produce ions in a target ",
      "the energy delivered by radiation to a target ",
      "the biological effect of radiation ",
      "the rate of decay of radioactive source "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "the biological effect of radiation "
  },
  {
    "id": "kHqs3QBgfq1sxHkG",
    "question": "In gamma ray emission from a nucleus",
    "options": [
      "only the proton number changes ",
      "both the neutron number and the proton number change ",
      "there is no change in the proton number and the neutron number ",
      "only the neutron number changes "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "there is no change in the proton number and the neutron number "
  },
  {
    "id": "MO2qF4ispfIO8i8E",
    "question": "The half-life period of a ratio-active element $$X$$ is same as the mean life time of another ratio-active element $$Y.$$ Initially they have the same number of atoms. Then ",
    "options": [
      "$$X$$ and $$Y$$ decay at same rate always ",
      "$$X$$ will decay faster than $$Y$$ ",
      "$$Y$$ will decay faster than $$X$$ ",
      "$$X$$ and $$Y$$ have same decay rate initially "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$Y$$ will decay faster than $$X$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "xFdm9vHuxpcBCazi",
    "question": "A radioactive nucleus (initial mass number $$A$$ and atomic number $$Z$$ emits $$3\\,\\alpha $$- particles and $$2$$ positrons. The ratio of number of neutrons to that of protons in the final nucleus will be ",
    "options": [
      "$${{A - Z - 8} \\over {Z - 4}}$$ ",
      "$${{A - Z - 4} \\over {Z - 8}}$$ ",
      "$${{A - Z - 12} \\over {Z - 4}}$$ ",
      "$${{A - Z - 4} \\over {Z - 2}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$${{A - Z - 4} \\over {Z - 8}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "xvat97DTKRC07MRS",
    "question": "The half life of a radioactive substance is $$20$$ minutes. The approximate time interval $$\\left( {{t_2} - {t_1}} \\right)$$ between the time $${{t_2}}$$ when $${2 \\over 3}$$ of it had decayed and time $${{t_1}}$$ when $${1 \\over 3}$$ of it had decayed is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$14$$ min ",
      "$$20$$ min ",
      "$$28$$ min ",
      "$$7$$ min "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$20$$ min "
  },
  {
    "id": "tKd2dCc3kT7LtJzy",
    "question": "Half-lives of two radioactive elements $$A$$ and $$B$$ are $$20$$ minutes and $$40$$ minutes, respectively. Initially, the samples have equal number of nuclei. After $$80$$ minutes, the ratio of decayed number of $$A$$ and $$B$$ nuclei will be: ",
    "options": [
      "$$1:4$$ ",
      "$$5:4$$ ",
      "$$1:16$$ ",
      "$$4:1$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$5:4$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "9udS0dofmfXrIqDe",
    "question": "A radioactive nucleus A with a half life T, decays into a nucleus B. At t = 0, there is no nucleus B. At\nsometime t, the ratio of the number of B to that of A is 0.3. Then, t is given by : ",
    "options": [
      "$$t = {T \\over {\\log (1.3)}}$$ ",
      "$$t = T\\log (1.3)$$  ",
      "$$t = {T \\over 2}{{\\log 2} \\over {\\log 1.3}}$$ ",
      "$$t = T{{\\log 1.3} \\over {\\log 2}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$t = T{{\\log 1.3} \\over {\\log 2}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "klyqpQNdPaWCYJRWhONTr",
    "question": "A solution containing active cobalt $${^{60}_{27}}Co$$ having activity of $$0.8$$ $$\\mu Ci$$ and decay constant $$\\lambda $$ is injected in an animal's body. If $$1\\,c{m^3}$$ of blood is drawn from the animal's body after $$10$$ hrs of injection, the activity found was $$300$$ decays per minute What is the volume of blood that is flowing in the body ? $$\\left( {\\,\\,Ci = 3.7 \\times {{10}^{10}}\\,} \\right.$$ decays per second and at $$t=10$$ hrs $$\\left. {{e^{ - \\lambda t}} = 0.84} \\right)$$",
    "options": [
      "$$6$$ liters",
      "$$7$$ liters",
      "$$4$$ liters",
      "$$5$$ liters"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$5$$ liters"
  },
  {
    "id": "0uhgHoPX8uRa15yU1mKaY",
    "question": "An unstable heavy nucleus at rest breaks into two nuclei which move away with velocities in the ratio of 8 : 27. The ratio of the radii of the nuclei (assumed to be spherical) is : ",
    "options": [
      "8 : 27",
      "4 : 9",
      "3 : 2",
      "2 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "3 : 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "BjZAZ3WPz7saUAmnGCMbv",
    "question": "At some instant,  a radioactive sample S<sub>1</sub> having an activity 5 $$\\mu $$Ci has twice the number of nuclei as another sample S<sub>2</sub> which has an activity of 10 $$\\mu $$Ci. The half lives of S<sub>1</sub> and S<sub>2</sub> are : ",
    "options": [
      "20 years and 5 years,  respectively ",
      "20 years and 10years,  respectively ",
      "5 years and 20 years, respectively ",
      "10 years and 20 years,  respectively"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "20 years and 5 years,  respectively "
  },
  {
    "id": "ufB55eRLFOuOWldW8U3rsa0w2w9jx7grwdi",
    "question": "Half lives of two radioactive nuclei A and B are 10 minutes and 20 minutes, respectively, If initially a sample\nhas equal number of nuclei, then after 60 minutes, the ratio of decayed numbers of nuclei A and B will be :\n",
    "options": [
      "9 : 8",
      "1 : 8",
      "8 : 1",
      "3 : 8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "9 : 8"
  },
  {
    "id": "NlbbE5WpPNAY4GRkyN3rsa0w2w9jwzipjr0",
    "question": "Two radioactive substances A and B have decay constants 5$$\\lambda $$ and $$\\lambda $$ respectively. At t = 0, a sample has the\nsame number of the two nuclei. The time taken for the ratio of the number of nuclei to become $${\\left( {{1 \\over e}} \\right)^2}$$\n will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${2 \\over \\lambda }$$",
      "$${1 \\over {4\\lambda }}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {2\\lambda }}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\lambda }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {2\\lambda }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "af9hMpX7iSonKAohfTNck",
    "question": "Using a nuclear counter the count rate of emitted particles from a radioactive source is measured. At t = 0 it was 1600 counts per second and t = 8 seconds it was 100 counts per second. The count rate observed, as counts per second, at t = 6 seconds is close to -\n",
    "options": [
      "200",
      "150",
      "400",
      "360"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "200"
  },
  {
    "id": "FjcX4DtArwI1Qn68wl18hoxe66ijvztgcko",
    "question": "Two radioactive materials A and B have decay\nconstants 10$$\\lambda $$ and $$\\lambda $$, respectively. It initially\nthey have the same number of nuclei, then the\nratio of the number of nuclei of A to that of B\nwill be 1/e after a time :",
    "options": [
      "1/9$$\\lambda $$",
      "11/10$$\\lambda $$",
      "1/10$$\\lambda $$",
      "1/11$$\\lambda $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "1/9$$\\lambda $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "YZoXYcmEfMUcCC1WKrRjE",
    "question": "In a radioactive decay chain, the initial nucleus is $${}_{90}^{232}$$Th. At the end there are 6 $$\\alpha $$-particles and 4 $$\\beta $$-particles which are emitted. If the end nucleus is $${}_Z^A$$X, A and Z are given by : ",
    "options": [
      "A = 208; Z = 80",
      "A = 208; Z = 82",
      "A  = 200; Z = 81 ",
      "A = 202; Z = 80"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "A = 208; Z = 82"
  },
  {
    "id": "UrX1dBuDzRM0r7lAhAEbf",
    "question": "At a given instant, say t = 0, two radioactive substance A and B have  equal activities. the ratio $${{{R_B}} \\over {{R_A}}}$$ of their activities after time t itself decays with time t as e<sup>$$-$$3t</sup>. If the half-life of A is ln<sup>2</sup>, the half-life of B is : ",
    "options": [
      "4ln2",
      "$${{\\ln 2} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{\\ln 2} \\over 4}$$",
      "2ln2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$${{\\ln 2} \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "160d07KInIQ2dmyL1Ykxm",
    "question": "A sample of radioactive material A, that has an activity of 10 mCi(1 Ci = 3.7 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>10</sup> decays/s), has twice the number of nuclei as another sample of a different radioactive materail B which has an activity of 20 mCi. The correct choices for half-lives of A and B would then be respectively : ",
    "options": [
      "5 days and 10 days",
      "10 days and 40 days",
      "20 days and 5 days",
      "20 days and 10 days"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "20 days and 5 days"
  },
  {
    "id": "8ujCIhDzis1vgjc8Puefo",
    "question": "The ratio of mass densities of nuclei of <sup>40</sup>Ca\nand <sup>16</sup>O is close to :-",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "5",
      "0.1",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "HiECt2eLjPlGBJY7Gs7k9k2k5f4r8b3",
    "question": "The activity of a radioactive sample falls from 700 s<sup>–1</sup> to 500 s<sup>–1</sup> in 30 minutes. Its half life is close\nto:\n",
    "options": [
      "62 min",
      "66 min",
      "72 min",
      "52 min"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "62 min"
  },
  {
    "id": "0Zn1aBpQemDUqte27djgy2xukf15vama",
    "question": "In a radioactive material, fraction of active\nmaterial remaining after time t is 9/16. The\nfraction that was remaining after t/2 is\n",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 4}$$",
      "$${4 \\over 5}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 5}$$",
      "$${7 \\over 8}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "UDljbalqZMZ4U44li4jgy2xukf3uo6t9",
    "question": "The radius R of a nucleus of mass number A can be estimated by the formula<br/> R = (1.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–15</sup>)A<sup>1/3</sup> m.\n<br/>It follows that the mass density of a nucleus is of the order of :\n<br/><br/>(M<sub>prot.</sub> $$ \\cong $$ M<sub>neut</sub> $$ \\simeq $$ 1.67 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–27</sup> kg)",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>24</sup> kg m<sup>–3</sup>",
      "10<sup>10</sup> kg m<sup>–3</sup>",
      "10<sup>17</sup> kg m<sup>–3</sup>",
      "10<sup>3</sup> kg m<sup>–3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "10<sup>17</sup> kg m<sup>–3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "0emef2jIkxyeI8ZQyXjgy2xukfl37s3m",
    "question": "A radioactive nucleus decays by two different\nprocesses. The half life for the first process is\n10 s and that for the second is 100 s. The\neffective half life of the nucleus is close to :",
    "options": [
      "12 sec",
      "9 sec",
      "55 sec",
      "6 sec"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "9 sec"
  },
  {
    "id": "MPH3hdGxfeQZjSoDxxjgy2xukg0i5sfh",
    "question": "Given the masses of various atomic particles\n<br/>m<sub>p</sub> = 1.0072 u, m<sub>n</sub> = 1.0087 u, m<sub>e</sub> = 0.000548 u,\n<br/>$${m_{\\overline v }}$$ = 0, m<sub>d</sub> = 2.0141 u, where p $$ \\equiv $$ proton,\nn $$ \\equiv $$ neutron, <br/>e $$ \\equiv $$ electron, $$\\overline v $$ $$ \\equiv $$ antineutrino and\nd $$ \\equiv $$ deuteron. Which of the following process is\nallowed by momentum and energy\nconservation?",
    "options": [
      "n + n $$ \\to $$ deuterium atom\n<br>(electron bound to the nucleus)",
      "n + p $$ \\to $$ d + $$\\gamma $$",
      "p $$ \\to $$ n + e<sup>+</sup> + $$\\overline v $$",
      "e<sup>+</sup> + e<sup>-</sup> $$ \\to $$ $$\\gamma $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "n + p $$ \\to $$ d + $$\\gamma $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "6qKuSPF2JCosrabfIb1klrxavxo",
    "question": "Two radioactive substances X and Y originally have N<sub>1</sub> and N<sub>2</sub> nuclei respectively. Half life of X is half of the half life of Y. After three half lives of Y, number of nuclei of both are equal. The ratio $${{{N_1}} \\over {{N_2}}}$$ will be equal to :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 8}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 1}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 3}$$",
      "$${8 \\over 1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$${8 \\over 1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "VCwfDV3vYMGiyFF62d1klukkixr",
    "question": "A radioactive sample is undergoing $$\\alpha$$ decay. At any time t<sub>1</sub>, its activity is A and another time t<sub>2</sub>, the activity is $${A \\over 5}$$. What is the average life time for the sample?",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\ln 5} \\over {{t_2} - {t_1}}}$$",
      "$${{\\ln ({t_2} + {t_1})} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{{t_1} - {t_2}} \\over {\\ln 5}}$$",
      "$${{{t_2} - {t_1}} \\over {\\ln 5}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$${{{t_2} - {t_1}} \\over {\\ln 5}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "QBV5RAkdNsJZoAbhxE1kmiovh2j",
    "question": "Calculate the time interval between 33% decay and 67% decay if half-life of a substance is 20 minutes.",
    "options": [
      "40 minutes",
      "60 minutes",
      "13 minutes",
      "20 minutes"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "20 minutes"
  },
  {
    "id": "KXzo19ctsrQF7crqVk1kmip3ifx",
    "question": "The half-life of Au<sup>198</sup> is 2.7 days. The activity of 1.50 mg of Au<sup>198</sup> if its atomic weight is 198 g mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup> is, (N<sub>a</sub> = 6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>23</sup>/mol).",
    "options": [
      "240 Ci",
      "357 Ci",
      "252 Ci",
      "535 Ci"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "357 Ci"
  },
  {
    "id": "mcUKXSO1Y1mVP6Y6mI1kmlhsu3l",
    "question": "A radioactive sample disintegrates via two independent decay processes having half lives $$T_{1/2}^{(1)}$$ and $$T_{1/2}^{(2)}$$ respectively. The effective half-life T<sub>1/2</sub> of the nuclei is :",
    "options": [
      "None of the above",
      "$${T_{1/2}} = T_{1/2}^{(1)} + T_{1/2}^{(2)}$$",
      "$${T_{1/2}} = {{T_{1/2}^{(1)}T_{1/2}^{(2)}} \\over {T_{1/2}^{(1)} + T_{1/2}^{(2)}}}$$",
      "$${T_{1/2}} = {{T_{1/2}^{(1)} + T_{1/2}^{(2)}} \\over {T_{1/2}^{(1)} - T_{1/2}^{(2)}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$${T_{1/2}} = {{T_{1/2}^{(1)}T_{1/2}^{(2)}} \\over {T_{1/2}^{(1)} + T_{1/2}^{(2)}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "guiz8db8Hl7p2nGFw71kmlvyl3v",
    "question": "The decay of a proton to neutron is :",
    "options": [
      "always possible as it is associated only with $$\\beta$$<sup>+</sup> decay",
      "possible only inside the nucleus",
      "not possible as proton mass is less than the neutron mass",
      "not possible but neutron to proton conversation is possible"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "possible only inside the nucleus"
  },
  {
    "id": "mSwUCZDhHNAgD0SsqN1krpmvvl6",
    "question": "A radioactive material decays by simultaneous emissions of two particles with half lives of 1400 years and 700 years respectively. What will be the time after which one third of the material remains ? (Take ln 3 = 1.1)",
    "options": [
      "740 years",
      "1110 years",
      "700 years",
      "340 years"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "740 years"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krueyi4t",
    "question": "Some nuclei of a radioactive material are undergoing radioactive decay. The time gap between the instances when a quarter of the nuclei have decayed and when half of the nuclei have decayed is given as :<br/><br/>(where $$\\lambda$$ is the decay constant)",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 2}{{\\ln 2} \\over \\lambda }$$",
      "$${{\\ln 2} \\over \\lambda }$$",
      "$${{2\\ln 2} \\over \\lambda }$$",
      "$${{\\ln {3 \\over 2}} \\over \\lambda }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$${{\\ln {3 \\over 2}} \\over \\lambda }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krukk6c4",
    "question": "The half-life of $${}^{198}Au$$ is 3 days. If atomic weight of $${}^{198}Au$$ is 198 g/mol then the activity of 2 mg of $${}^{198}Au$$ is [in disintegration/second] :",
    "options": [
      "2.67 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>12</sup>",
      "6.06 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>18</sup>",
      "32.36 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>12</sup>",
      "16.18 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>12</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "16.18 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>12</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krywmd9h",
    "question": "If 'f' denotes the ratio of the number of nuclei decayed (N<sub>d</sub>) to the number of nuclei at t = 0 (N<sub>0</sub>) then for a collection of radioactive nuclei, the rate of change of 'f' with respect to time is given as :<br/><br/>[$$\\lambda$$ is the radioactive decay constant]",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$ $$\\lambda$$ (1 $$-$$ e<sup>$$-$$$$\\lambda$$t</sup>)",
      "$$\\lambda$$ (1 $$-$$ e<sup>$$-$$$$\\lambda$$t</sup>)",
      "$$\\lambda$$e<sup>$$-$$$$\\lambda$$t</sup>",
      "$$-$$ $$\\lambda$$e<sup>$$-$$$$\\lambda$$t</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda$$e<sup>$$-$$$$\\lambda$$t</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks18m3oj",
    "question": "Consider the following statements :<br/><br/>A. Atoms of each element emit characteristics spectrum.<br/><br/>B. According to Bohr's Postulate, an electron in a hydrogen atom, revolves in a certain stationary orbit.<br/><br/>C. The density of nuclear matter depends on the size of the nucleus.<br/><br/>D. A free neutron is stable but a free proton decay is possible.<br/><br/>E. Radioactivity is an indication of the instability of nuclei.<br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "A, B, C, D and E",
      "A, B and E only",
      "B and D only",
      "A, C and E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "A, B and E only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktdycxoc",
    "question": "There are 10<sup>10</sup> radioactive nuclei in a given radioactive element, its half-life time is 1 minute. How many nuclei will remain after 30 seconds? $$\\left( {\\sqrt 2  = 1.414} \\right)$$",
    "options": [
      "2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup>",
      "7 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup>",
      "10<sup>5</sup>",
      "4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "7 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktmofoon",
    "question": "The half life period of radioactive element x is same as the mean life time of another radioactive element y. Initially they have the same number of atoms. Then :",
    "options": [
      "x-will decay faster than y.",
      "y-will decay faster than x.",
      "x and y have same decay rate initially and later on different decay rate.",
      "x and y decay at the same rate always."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "y-will decay faster than x."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l546vpll",
    "question": "<p>The activity of a radioactive material is 2.56 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> Ci. If the half life of the material is 5 days, after how many days the activity will become 2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> Ci ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "30 days",
      "35 days",
      "40 days",
      "25 days"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "35 days"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54urzkk",
    "question": "<p>In the following nuclear reaction,</p>\n<p>$$D\\buildrel \\alpha  \\over\n \\longrightarrow {D_1}\\buildrel {{\\beta ^ - }} \\over\n \\longrightarrow {D_2}\\buildrel \\alpha  \\over\n \\longrightarrow {D_3}\\buildrel \\gamma  \\over\n \\longrightarrow {D_4}$$</p>\n<p>Mass number of D is 182 and atomic number is 74. Mass number and atomic number of D<sub>4</sub> respectively will be _________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "174 and 71",
      "174 and 69",
      "172 and 69",
      "172 and 71"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "174 and 71"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55lkgaa",
    "question": "<p>Following statements related to radioactivity are given below :</p>\n<p>(A) Radioactivity is a random and spontaneous process and is dependent on physical and chemical conditions.</p>\n<p>(B) The number of un-decayed nuclei in the radioactive sample decays exponentially with time.</p>\n<p>(C) Slope of the graph of log<sub>e</sub> (no. of undecayed nuclei) Vs. time represents the reciprocal of mean life time ($$\\tau$$).</p>\n<p>(D) Product of decay constant ($$\\lambda$$) and half-life time (T<sub>1/2</sub>) is not constant.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) and (B) only",
      "(B) and (D) only",
      "(B) and (C) only",
      "(C) and (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "(B) and (C) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58c8yho",
    "question": "<p>How many alpha and beta particles are emitted when Uranium <sub>92</sub>U<sup>238</sup> decays to lead <sub>82</sub>Pb<sup>206</sup> ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 alpha particles and 5 beta particles",
      "6 alpha particles and 4 beta particles",
      "4 alpha particles and 5 beta particles",
      "8 alpha particles and 6 beta particles"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "8 alpha particles and 6 beta particles"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58i851u",
    "question": "<p>A radioactive nucleus can decay by two different processes. Half-life for the first process is 3.0 hours while it is 4.5 hours for the second process. The effective half-life of the nucleus will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "3.75 hours",
      "0.56 hours",
      "0.26 hours",
      "1.80 hours"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "1.80 hours"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gjzb1w",
    "question": "<p>The disintegration rate of a certain radioactive sample at any instant is 4250 disintegrations per minute. 10 minutes later, the rate becomes 2250 disintegrations per minute. The approximate decay constant is :</p>\n<p>$$\\left(\\right.$$Take $$\\left.\\log _{10} 1.88=0.274\\right)$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$0.02 \\min ^{-1}$$",
      "$$2.7 \\min ^{-1}$$",
      "$$0.063 \\min ^{-1}$$",
      "$$6.3 \\min ^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$0.063 \\min ^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i1poyw",
    "question": "<p>Mass numbers of two nuclei are in the ratio of $$4: 3$$. Their nuclear densities will be in the ratio of</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 : 3",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{3}{4}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{3}}$$",
      "1 : 1",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{4}{3}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{3}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "1 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jikx3u",
    "question": "<p>What is the half-life period of a radioactive material if its activity drops to $$1 / 16^{\\text {th }}$$ of its initial value in 30 years?</p>",
    "options": [
      "9.5 years",
      "8.5 years",
      "7.5 years",
      "10.5 years"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "7.5 years"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6knqoec",
    "question": "<p>The activity of a radioactive material is $$6.4 \\times 10^{-4}$$ curie. Its half life is 5 days. The activity will become $$5 \\times 10^{-6}$$ curie after :</p>",
    "options": [
      "7 days",
      "15 days",
      "25 days",
      "35 days"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "35 days"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mayrhu",
    "question": "<p>The half life period of a radioactive substance is 60 days. The time taken for $$\\frac{7}{8}$$th of its original mass to disintegrate will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "120 days",
      "130 days",
      "180 days",
      "20 days"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "180 days"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nszg99",
    "question": "<p>A radioactive sample decays $$\\frac{7}{8}$$ times its original quantity in 15 minutes. The half-life of the sample is</p>",
    "options": [
      "5 min",
      "7.5 min",
      "15 min",
      "30 min"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "5 min"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rh7dh6",
    "question": "<p>Read the following statements :</p>\n<p>(A) Volume of the nucleus is directly proportional to the mass number.</p>\n<p>(B) Volume of the nucleus is independent of mass number.</p>\n<p>(C) Density of the nucleus is directly proportional to the mass number.</p>\n<p>(D) Density of the nucleus is directly proportional to the cube root of the mass number.</p>\n<p>(E) Density of the nucleus is independent of the mass number.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct option from the following options.</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) and (D) only.",
      "(A) and (E) only.",
      "(B) and (E) only.",
      "(A) and (C) only."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "(A) and (E) only."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldplzf4r",
    "question": "<p>A free neutron decays into a proton but a free proton does not decay into neutron. This is because</p>",
    "options": [
      "neutron is an uncharged particle",
      "neutron has larger rest mass than proton",
      "neutron is a composite particle made of a proton and an electron",
      "proton is a charged particle"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "neutron has larger rest mass than proton"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqvcnt8",
    "question": "Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $\\mathbf{A}$ and the other is labelled as Reason $\\mathbf{R}$\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Assertion A:</b> The nuclear density of nuclides ${ }_{5}^{10} \\mathrm{~B},{ }_{3}^{6} \\mathrm{Li},{ }_{26}^{56} \\mathrm{Fe},{ }_{10}^{20} \\mathrm{Ne}$ and ${ }_{83}^{209} \\mathrm{Bi}$ can be arranged as $\\rho_{\\mathrm{Bi}}^{\\mathrm{N}}&gt;\\rho_{\\mathrm{Fe}}^{\\mathrm{N}}&gt;\\rho_{\\mathrm{Ne}}^{\\mathrm{N}}&gt;\\rho_{\\mathrm{B}}^{\\mathrm{N}}&gt;\\rho_{\\mathrm{Li}}^{\\mathrm{N}}$\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Reason R:</b> The radius $R$ of nucleus is related to its mass number $A$ as $R=R_{0} A^{1 / 3}$, where $R_{0}$ is a constant.\n<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below",
    "options": [
      "${Both ~\\mathbf{A}}$ and $\\mathbf{R}$ are true and $\\mathbf{R}$ is the correct explanation of $\\mathbf{A}$",
      "Both $\\mathbf{A}$ and $\\mathbf{R}$ are true but $\\mathbf{R}$ is NOT the correct explanation of $\\mathbf{A}$",
      "$\\mathbf{A}$ is false but $\\mathbf{R}$ is true",
      "$\\mathbf{A}$ is true but $\\mathbf{R}$ is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$\\mathbf{A}$ is false but $\\mathbf{R}$ is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lds9s2is",
    "question": "<p>Substance A has atomic mass number 16 and half life of 1 day. Another substance B has atomic mass number 32 and half life of $$\\frac{1}{2}$$ day. If both A and B simultaneously start undergo radio activity at the same time with initial mass 320 g each, how many total atoms of A and B combined would be left after 2 days.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1.69\\times10^{24}$$",
      "$$3.38\\times10^{24}$$",
      "$$6.76\\times10^{23}$$",
      "$$6.76\\times10^{24}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$3.38\\times10^{24}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsoitcb",
    "question": "<p>If a radioactive element having half-life of $$30 \\mathrm{~min}$$ is undergoing beta decay, the fraction of radioactive element remains undecayed after $$90 \\mathrm{~min}$$. will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{16}$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{8}$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{8}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduhhs4l",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of the density of oxygen nucleus ($$_8^{16}O$$) and helium nucleus ($$_2^{4}\\mathrm{He}$$) is</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 : 1",
      "1 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "8 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "1 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldydsmry",
    "question": "<p>Consider the following radioactive decay process</p>\n<p>$$_{84}^{218}A\\buildrel \\alpha  \\over\n \\longrightarrow {A_1}\\buildrel {{\\beta ^ - }} \\over\n \\longrightarrow {A_2}\\buildrel \\gamma  \\over\n \\longrightarrow {A_3}\\buildrel \\alpha  \\over\n \\longrightarrow {A_4}\\buildrel {{\\beta ^ + }} \\over\n \\longrightarrow {A_5}\\buildrel \\gamma  \\over\n \\longrightarrow {A_6}$$</p>\n<p>The mass number and the atomic number of A$$_6$$ are given by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "210 and 84",
      "210 and 80",
      "211 and 80",
      "210 and 82"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "210 and 80"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnygjbo",
    "question": "The half-life of a radioactive nucleus is 5 years. The fraction of the original sample that would decay in 15 years is:",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{1}{8}$",
      "$\\frac{3}{4}$",
      "$\\frac{7}{8}$",
      "$\\frac{1}{4}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$\\frac{7}{8}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgoybtwf",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A : The binding energy per nucleon is practically independent of the atomic number for nuclei of mass number in the range 30 to 170 .</p>\n<p>Reason R : Nuclear force is short ranged.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is true",
      "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is false",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguxq9ko",
    "question": "<p>Two radioactive elements A and B initially have same number of atoms. The half life of A is same as the average life of B. If $$\\lambda_{A}$$ and $$\\lambda_{B}$$ are decay constants of A and B respectively, then choose the correct relation from the given options.<p></p></p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda_{\\mathrm{A}}=\\lambda_{\\mathrm{B}} \\ln 2$$",
      "$$\\lambda_{\\mathrm{A}} \\ln 2=\\lambda_{\\mathrm{B}}$$",
      "$$\\lambda_{\\mathrm{A}}=2 \\lambda_{\\mathrm{B}}$$",
      "$$\\lambda_{\\mathrm{A}}=\\lambda_{\\mathrm{B}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda_{\\mathrm{A}}=\\lambda_{\\mathrm{B}} \\ln 2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvr9a97",
    "question": "<p>The half life of a radioactive substance is T. The time taken, for disintegrating $$\\frac{7}{8}$$th part of its original mass will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "8T",
      "3T",
      "T",
      "2T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "3T"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqhy15",
    "question": "<p>A radio active material is reduced to $$1 / 8$$ of its original amount in 3 days. If $$8 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~kg}$$ of the material is left after 5 days the initial amount of the material is</p>",
    "options": [
      "64 g",
      "256 g",
      "32 g",
      "40 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "256 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd5kg87",
    "question": "<p>The mass number of nucleus having radius equal to half of the radius of nucleus with mass number 192 is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "32",
      "24",
      "20",
      "40"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "atoms-and-nuclei",
    "topic": "nucleus-and-radioactivity",
    "solution": "24"
  },
  {
    "id": "BO76lbuZXnP0sLUH",
    "question": "Capacitance (in $$F$$) of a spherical conductor with radius $$1$$ $$m$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$1.1 \\times {10^{ - 10}}$$ ",
      "$${10^{ - 6}}$$ ",
      "$$9 \\times {10^{ - 9}}$$ ",
      "$${10^{ - 3}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitance",
    "solution": "$$1.1 \\times {10^{ - 10}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "gbs27J8Hl751F28nwfjgy2xukexwq8ar",
    "question": "A 10 $$\\mu $$F capacitor is fully charged to a potential\ndifference of 50 V. After removing the source\nvoltage it is connected to an uncharged\ncapacitor in parallel. Now the potential\ndifference across them becomes 20 V. The\ncapacitance of the second capacitor is :",
    "options": [
      "20 $$\\mu $$F",
      "15 $$\\mu $$F",
      "10 $$\\mu $$F",
      "30 $$\\mu $$F"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitance",
    "solution": "15 $$\\mu $$F"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks0klvx5",
    "question": "Match List I with List II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Capacitance, C</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>$${M^1}{L^1}{T^{ - 3}}{A^{ - 1}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Permittivity of free space, $${\\varepsilon _0}$$</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>$${M^{ - 1}}{L^{ - 3}}{T^4}{A^2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Permeability of free space, $${\\mu _0}$$</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>$${M^{ - 1}}{L^{ - 2}}{T^4}{A^2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Electric field, E</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>$${M^1}{L^1}{T^{ - 2}}{A^{ - 2}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below ",
    "options": [
      "(a) $$\\to$$ (iii), (b) $$\\to$$ (ii), (c) $$\\to$$ (iv), (d) $$\\to$$ (i)",
      "(a) $$\\to$$ (iii), (b) $$\\to$$ (iv), (c) $$\\to$$ (ii), (d) $$\\to$$ (i)",
      "(a) $$\\to$$ (iv), (b) $$\\to$$ (ii), (c) $$\\to$$ (iii), (d) $$\\to$$ (i)",
      "(a) $$\\to$$ (iv), (b) $$\\to$$ (iii), (c) $$\\to$$ (ii), (d) $$\\to$$ (i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitance",
    "solution": "(a) $$\\to$$ (iii), (b) $$\\to$$ (ii), (c) $$\\to$$ (iv), (d) $$\\to$$ (i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f4kiud",
    "question": "<p>Capacitance of an isolated conducting sphere of radius R<sub>1</sub> becomes n times when it is enclosed by a concentric conducting sphere of radius R<sub>2</sub> connected to earth. The ratio of their radii $$\\left( {{{{R_2}} \\over {{R_1}}}} \\right)$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${n \\over {n - 1}}$$",
      "$${{2n} \\over {2n + 1}}$$",
      "$${{n + 1} \\over n}$$",
      "$${{2n + 1} \\over n}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitance",
    "solution": "$${n \\over {n - 1}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnwkn50",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: One is labeled as Assertion A and the other is labeled as Reason R.</p>\n<p><b>Assertion A :</b> Two metallic spheres are charged to the same potential. One of them is hollow and another is solid, and both have the same radii. Solid sphere will have lower charge than the hollow one.</p>\n<p><b>Reason R :</b> Capacitance of metallic spheres depend on the radii of spheres</p>\n<p>In light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is not the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is true",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitance",
    "solution": "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "2L4gBqTcmw5pPLaM",
    "question": "A capacitance of 2 $$\\mu $$F is required in an electrical circuit across a potential difference of 1.0 kV. A large\nnumber of 1 $$\\mu $$F capacitors are available which can withstand a potential difference of not more than 300 V.\nThe minimum number of capacitors required to achieve this is: ",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "16",
      "32",
      "24"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitor-in-circuit",
    "solution": "32"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krywprsj",
    "question": "Two capacitors of capacities 2C and C are joined in parallel and charged up to potential V. The battery is removed and the capacitor of capacity C is filled completely with a medium of dielectric constant K. The potential difference across the capacitors will now be :",
    "options": [
      "$${V \\over {K + 2}}$$",
      "$${V \\over K}$$",
      "$${{3V} \\over {K + 2}}$$",
      "$${{3V} \\over K}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitor-in-circuit",
    "solution": "$${{3V} \\over {K + 2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "yv9bwg3OJELXJL4K",
    "question": "A sheet of aluminium foil of negligible thickness is introduced between the plates of a capacitor. The capacitance of the capacitor ",
    "options": [
      "decreases ",
      "remains unchanged ",
      "becomes infinite ",
      "increases "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "remains unchanged "
  },
  {
    "id": "Gq1uYqgcrJNWiydf",
    "question": "A parallel plate capacitor with air between the plates has capacitance of $$9$$ $$pF.$$ The separation between its plates is $$'d'.$$ The space between the plates has dielectric constant $${k_1}$$ $$=3$$ and thickness $${d \\over 3}$$ while the other one has dielectric constant $${k_2} = 6$$ and thickness $${{2d} \\over 3}$$. Capacitance of the capacitor is now ",
    "options": [
      "$$1.8$$ $$pF$$ ",
      "$$45$$ $$pF$$ ",
      "$$40.5$$ $$pF$$ ",
      "$$20.25$$ $$pF$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "$$40.5$$ $$pF$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "wtYxiZj40C8pK7cQ",
    "question": "A parallel plate capacitor is made of two circular plates separated by a distance $$5$$ $$mm$$ and with a dielectric of dielectric constant $$2.2$$ between them. When the electric field in the dielectric is $$3 \\times {10^4}\\,V/m$$ the charge density of the positive plate will be close to: ",
    "options": [
      "$$6 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\,\\,C/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$$3 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\,\\,C/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$$3 \\times {10^4}\\,\\,C/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$$6 \\times {10^4}\\,\\,C/{m^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "$$6 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\,\\,C/{m^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "fvaGJwNGLcoazjij",
    "question": "A parallel plate capacitor of capacitance 90 pF is connected to a battery of emf 20 V. If a dielectric material\nof dielectric constant K = 5/3 is inserted between the plates, the magnitude of the induced charge will be :",
    "options": [
      "0.9 n C",
      "1.2 n C",
      "0.3 n C",
      "2.4 n C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "1.2 n C"
  },
  {
    "id": "Hqztj32RwUv4gdbjQCirt",
    "question": "The parallel combination of two air filled\nparallel plate capacitors of capacitance C and\nnC is connected to a battery of voltage, V. When\nthe capacitors are fully charged, the battery is\nremoved and after that a dielectric material of\ndielectric constant K is placed between the two\nplates of the first capacitor. The new potential\ndifference of the combined system is :-",
    "options": [
      "V",
      "$${V \\over {K + n}}$$",
      "$${{(n+1)V} \\over {K + n}}$$",
      "$${{nV} \\over {K + n}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "$${{(n+1)V} \\over {K + n}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xbp6HGKNkllEQXwKNxCoM",
    "question": "Voltage rating of a parallel plate capacitor is\n500V. Its dielectric can withstand a maximum\nelectric field of 10<sup>6</sup> V/m. The plate area is\n10<sup>–4</sup> m<sup>2</sup>. What is the dielectric constant is the\ncapacitance is 15 pF?\n(given $$\\varepsilon $$<sub>0</sub> = 8.86 × 10<sup>–12</sup> C<sup>2</sup>/Nm<sup>2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "8.5",
      "4.5",
      "3.8",
      "6.2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "8.5"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ws750gZXbfcNAbVTbt2LD",
    "question": "A parallel plate capacitor having capacitance 12 pF is charged by a battery to a potential difference of 10 V between its plates. The charging battery is now disconnected and a porcelain slab of dielectric constant 6.5 is slipped between the plates. The work done by the capacitor on the slab is :",
    "options": [
      "508 pJ",
      "692 pJ",
      "560 pJ",
      "600 pJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "508 pJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "QH8rxhAsavOKu3h89djgy2xukfl3zjob",
    "question": "A parallel plate capacitor has plate of length\n'l', width ‘w’ and separation of plates is ‘d’. It\nis connected to a battery of emf V. A dielectric\nslab of the same thickness ‘d’ and of dielectric\nconstant k = 4 is being inserted between the\nplates of the capacitor. At what length of the\nslab inside plates, will the energy stored in the\ncapacitor be two times the initial energy\nstored?",
    "options": [
      "$${l \\over 4}$$",
      "$${l \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{2l} \\over 3}$$",
      "$${l \\over 3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "$${l \\over 3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "keWX4d3EehQ4aRsXhq1kmhoh7pt",
    "question": "For changing the capacitance of a given parallel plate capacitor, a dielectric material of dielectric constant K is used, which has the same area as the plates of the capacitor. The thickness of the dielectric slab is $${3 \\over 4}$$d, where 'd' is the separation between the plates of parallel plate capacitor. The new capacitance (C') in terms of original capacitance (C<sub>0</sub>) is given by the following relation :",
    "options": [
      "$$C' = {{3 + K} \\over {4K}}{C_0}$$",
      "$$C' = {{4 + K} \\over {3}}{C_0}$$",
      "$$C' = {{4K} \\over {K + 3}}{C_0}$$",
      "$$C' = {{4} \\over {3 + K}}{C_0}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "$$C' = {{4K} \\over {K + 3}}{C_0}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krujwtkb",
    "question": "A parallel plate capacitor with plate area 'A' and distance of separation 'd' is filled with a dielectric. What is the capacity of the capacitor when permittivity of the dielectric varies as :<br/><br/>$$\\varepsilon (x) = {\\varepsilon _0} + kx$$, for $$\\left( {0 &lt; x \\le {d \\over 2}} \\right)$$<br/><br/>$$\\varepsilon (x) = {\\varepsilon _0} + k(d - x)$$, for $$\\left( {{d \\over 2} \\le x \\le d} \\right)$$",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left( {{\\varepsilon _0} + {{kd} \\over 2}} \\right)^{2/kA}}$$",
      "$${{kA} \\over {2\\ln \\left( {{{2{\\varepsilon _0} + kd} \\over {2{\\varepsilon _0}}}} \\right)}}$$",
      "0",
      "$${{kA} \\over 2}\\ln \\left( {{{2{\\varepsilon _0}} \\over {2{\\varepsilon _0} - kd}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "$${{kA} \\over {2\\ln \\left( {{{2{\\varepsilon _0} + kd} \\over {2{\\varepsilon _0}}}} \\right)}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw932h9",
    "question": "If q<sub>f</sub> is the free charge on the capacitor plates and q<sub>b</sub> is the bound charge on the dielectric slab of dielectric constant k placed between the capacitor plates, then bound charge q<sub>b</sub> an be expressed as :",
    "options": [
      "$${q_b} = {q_f}\\left( {1 - {1 \\over {\\sqrt k }}} \\right)$$",
      "$${q_b} = {q_f}\\left( {1 - {1 \\over k}} \\right)$$",
      "$${q_b} = {q_f}\\left( {1 + {1 \\over {\\sqrt k }}} \\right)$$",
      "$${q_b} = {q_f}\\left( {1 + {1 \\over k}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "$${q_b} = {q_f}\\left( {1 - {1 \\over k}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l547ofns",
    "question": "<p>A parallel plate capacitor filled with a medium of dielectric constant 10, is connected across a battery and is charged. The dielectric slab is replaced by another slab of dielectric constant 15. Then the energy of capacitor will :</p>",
    "options": [
      "increase by 50%",
      "decrease by 15%",
      "increase by 25%",
      "increase by 33%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "increase by 50%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59maqgz",
    "question": "<p>Two metallic plates form a parallel plate capacitor. The distance between the plates is 'd'. A metal sheet of thickness $${d \\over 2}$$ and of area equal to area of each plate is introduced between the plates. What will be the ratio of the new capacitance to the original capacitance of the capacitor?</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 2",
      "1 : 4",
      "4 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6ma2gc4",
    "question": "<p>Two capacitors, each having capacitance $$40 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{F}$$ are connected in series. The space between one of the capacitors is filled with dielectric material of dielectric constant $$\\mathrm{K}$$ such that the equivalence capacitance of the system became $$24 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{F}$$. The value of $$\\mathrm{K}$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.5",
      "2.5",
      "1.2",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "1.5"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nrkg0z",
    "question": "<p>A slab of dielectric constant $$\\mathrm{K}$$ has the same cross-sectional area as the plates of a parallel plate capacitor and thickness $$\\frac{3}{4} \\mathrm{~d}$$, where $$\\mathrm{d}$$ is the separation of the plates. The capacitance of the capacitor when the slab is inserted between the plates will be :</p>\n<p>(Given $$\\mathrm{C}_{0}$$ = capacitance of capacitor with air as medium between plates.)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{4 K C_{0}}{3+K}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3 K C_{0}}{3+K}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3+K}{4 K C_{0}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{K}{4+K}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{4 K C_{0}}{3+K}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldugmb5c",
    "question": "<p>A parallel plate capacitor has plate area 40 cm$$^2$$ and plates separation 2 mm. The space between the plates is filled with a dielectric medium of a thickness 1 mm and dielectric constant 5. The capacitance of the system is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{10\\varepsilon_0~F}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{24\\varepsilon_0~F}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{\\frac{3}{10}\\varepsilon_0~F}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{\\frac{10}{3}\\varepsilon_0~F}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{\\frac{10}{3}\\varepsilon_0~F}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvs3ne8",
    "question": "<p>The distance between two plates of a capacitor is $$\\mathrm{d}$$ and its capacitance is $$\\mathrm{C}_{1}$$, when air is the medium between the plates. If a metal sheet of thickness $$\\frac{2 d}{3}$$ and of the same area as plate is introduced between the plates, the capacitance of the capacitor becomes $$\\mathrm{C}_{2}$$. The ratio $$\\frac{\\mathrm{C}_{2}}{\\mathrm{C}_{1}}$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "3 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "4 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "3 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3veewk",
    "question": "<p>A capacitor has air as dielectric medium and two conducting plates of area $$12 \\mathrm{~cm}^2$$ and they are $$0.6 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ apart. When a slab of dielectric having area $$12 \\mathrm{~cm}^2$$ and $$0.6 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ thickness is inserted between the plates, one of the conducting plates has to be moved by $$0.2 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ to keep the capacitance same as in previous case. The dielectric constant of the slab is : (Given $$\\epsilon_0=8.834 \\times 10^{-12} \\mathrm{~F} / \\mathrm{m}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.50",
      "0.66",
      "1.33",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "capacitors-with-dielectric",
    "solution": "1.50"
  },
  {
    "id": "iKPC6fPZN6En8nK4",
    "question": "A fully charged capacitor has a capacitance $$'C'$$. It is discharged through a small coil of resistance wire embedded in a thermally insulated block of specific heat capacity $$'s'$$ and mass $$'m'.$$ If the temperature of the block is raised by $$'\\Delta T',$$ the potential difference $$'v'$$ across the capacitance is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{mCAT} \\over s}$$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{2mCAT} \\over s}} $$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{2msAT} \\over C}} $$ ",
      "$${{ms\\Delta T} \\over C}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "combination-of-capacitors",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{2msAT} \\over C}} $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "AbtgcF7VNunrO7sO",
    "question": "A parallel plate capacitor is made by stacking $$n$$ equally spaced plates connected alternatively. If the capacitance between any two adjacent plates is $$'C'$$ then the resultant capacitance is ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {n + 1} \\right)C$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {n - 1} \\right)C$$ ",
      "$$nC$$ ",
      "$$C$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "combination-of-capacitors",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {n - 1} \\right)C$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "b26FDjxWYnZBwJ5B",
    "question": "Two capacitors $${C_1}$$ and $${C_2}$$ are charged to $$120$$ $$V$$ and $$200$$ $$V$$ respectively. It is found that connecting them together the potential on each one can be made zero. Then ",
    "options": [
      "$$5{C_1} = 3{C_2}$$ ",
      "$$3{C_1} = 5{C_2}$$ ",
      "$$3{C_1} + 5{C_2} = 0$$ ",
      "$$9{C_1} = 4{C_2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "combination-of-capacitors",
    "solution": "$$3{C_1} = 5{C_2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "m46LAUbOqynP20ys935wA",
    "question": "Three capacitors each of 4 $$\\mu $$F are to be connected in such a way that the effective capacitance is 6 $$\\mu $$F. This can be done by connecting them :",
    "options": [
      "all in series",
      "two in series and one in parallel\n",
      "all in parallel",
      "two in parallel and one in series"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "combination-of-capacitors",
    "solution": "two in series and one in parallel\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "sOnP4Jn4DRemgv4oqt7k9k2k5gy26s4",
    "question": "Effective capacitance of parallel combination\nof two capacitors C<sub>1</sub> and C<sub>2</sub> is 10 μF. When\nthese capacitors are individually connected to\na voltage source of 1V, the energy stored in the\ncapacitor C<sub>2</sub> is 4 times that of C<sub>1</sub>. If these\ncapacitors are connected in series, their\neffective capacitance will be :",
    "options": [
      "4.2 μF",
      "8.4 μF",
      "1.6 μF",
      "3.2 μF"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "combination-of-capacitors",
    "solution": "1.6 μF"
  },
  {
    "id": "kTuGSfbhwGMLqOtALhjgy2xukff4pjif",
    "question": "Two capacitors of capacitances C and 2C are\ncharged to potential differences V and 2V,\nrespectively. These are then connected in\nparallel in such a manner that the positive\nterminal of one is connected to the negative\nterminal of the other. The final energy of this\nconfiguration is :",
    "options": [
      "Zero",
      "$${3 \\over 2}C{V^2}$$",
      "$${9 \\over 2}C{V^2}$$",
      "$${{25} \\over 6}C{V^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "combination-of-capacitors",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 2}C{V^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "usia2yeY7zUov0GDFR1klribci5",
    "question": "Two equal capacitors are first connected in series and then in parallel. The ratio of the equivalent capacities in the two cases will be :",
    "options": [
      "4 : 1",
      "1 : 2",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "combination-of-capacitors",
    "solution": "1 : 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "zJfSF6XvoLbexyqqhM1klth5e6m",
    "question": "Consider the combination of 2 capacitors C<sub>1</sub> and C<sub>2</sub> with C<sub>2</sub> &gt; C<sub>1</sub>, when connected in parallel, the equivalent capacitance is $${{15} \\over 4}$$ times the equivalent capacitance of the same connected in series. Calculate the ratio of capacitors, $${{{C_2}} \\over {{C_1}}}$$.",
    "options": [
      "$${{15} \\over {11}}$$",
      "No Solutions",
      "$${{29} \\over {15}}$$",
      "$${{15} \\over {4}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "combination-of-capacitors",
    "solution": "No Solutions"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gmpfsx",
    "question": "<p>The total charge on the system of capacitors $$C_{1}=1 \\mu \\mathrm{F}, C_{2}=2 \\mu \\mathrm{F}, \\mathrm{C}_{3}=4 \\mu \\mathrm{F}$$ and $$\\mathrm{C}_{4}=3 \\mu \\mathrm{F}$$ connected in parallel is :</p>\n<p>(Assume a battery of $$20 \\mathrm{~V}$$ is connected to the combination)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$200 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "200 C",
      "$$10 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "10 C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "combination-of-capacitors",
    "solution": "$$200 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "TLiB6Zt2Pky3CshH",
    "question": "If there are $$n$$ capacitors in parallel connected to $$V$$ volt source, then the energy stored is equal to ",
    "options": [
      "$$CV$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}nC{V^2}$$ ",
      "$$C{V^2}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {2n}}C{V^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "electric-energy-stored-by-capacitor",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}nC{V^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ATq5YUf6zKjfi4zD",
    "question": "The work done in placing a charge of $$8 \\times {10^{ - 18}}$$ coulomb on a condenser of capacity $$100$$ micro-farad is ",
    "options": [
      "$$16 \\times {10^{ - 32}}\\,\\,joule$$ ",
      "$$3.1 \\times {10^{ - 26}}\\,\\,joule$$",
      "$$4 \\times {10^{ - 10}}\\,\\,joule$$",
      "$$32 \\times {10^{ - 32}}\\,\\,joule$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "electric-energy-stored-by-capacitor",
    "solution": "$$32 \\times {10^{ - 32}}\\,\\,joule$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "4gKcYdKAcylRDCPo",
    "question": "A battery is used to charge a parallel plate capacitor till the potential difference between the plates becomes equal to the electromotive force of the battery. The ratio of the energy stored in the capacitor and the work done by the battery will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$1/2$$ ",
      "$$1$$ ",
      "$$2$$ ",
      "$$1/4$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "electric-energy-stored-by-capacitor",
    "solution": "$$1/2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "IR7UpTJU5ifGk8SbKs0WT",
    "question": "The energy stored in the electric field produced by a metal sphere is 4.5 J. If the sphere contains 4 $$\\mu $$C charge, its radius will be :\n<br/>[ Take : $${1 \\over {4\\,\\pi { \\in _0}}} = $$ 9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>9</sup>  N $$-$$ m<sup>2</sup>/C<sup>2</sup> ]",
    "options": [
      "20 mm",
      "32 mm",
      "28 mm",
      "16 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "electric-energy-stored-by-capacitor",
    "solution": "16 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "cj8kuYoLnyBRwJZPzYS3u",
    "question": "A capacitor with capacitance 5μF is charged to\n5μC. If the plates are pulled apart to reduce the\ncapacitance to 2μF, how much work is done ?",
    "options": [
      "2.16 × 10<sup>–6</sup> J",
      "2.55 × 10<sup>–6</sup> J",
      "3.75 × 10<sup>–6</sup> J",
      "6.25 × 10<sup>–6</sup> J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "electric-energy-stored-by-capacitor",
    "solution": "3.75 × 10<sup>–6</sup> J"
  },
  {
    "id": "WZn2bepXulzyRgAsdAjgy2xukfakors2",
    "question": "A capacitor C is fully charged with voltage V<sub>0</sub>. After disconnecting the voltage source, it is connected\nin parallel with another uncharged capacitor of capacitance $${C \\over 2}$$. The energy loss in the process\nafter the charge is distributed between the two capacitors is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 2}CV_0^2$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}CV_0^2$$",
      "$${1 \\over 3}CV_0^2$$",
      "$${1 \\over 6}CV_0^2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "electric-energy-stored-by-capacitor",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 6}CV_0^2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bc2c6a",
    "question": "<p>If the charge on a capacitor is increased by 2 C, the energy stored in it increases by 44%. The original charge on the capacitor is (in C)</p>",
    "options": [
      "10",
      "20",
      "30",
      "40"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "electric-energy-stored-by-capacitor",
    "solution": "10"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguxupxd",
    "question": "<p>A parallel plate capacitor of capacitance $$2 \\mathrm{~F}$$ is charged to a potential $$\\mathrm{V}$$, The energy stored in the capacitor is $$E_{1}$$. The capacitor is now connected to another uncharged identical capacitor in parallel combination. The energy stored in the combination is $$\\mathrm{E}_{2}$$. The ratio $$\\mathrm{E}_{2} / \\mathrm{E}_{1}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 2",
      "2 : 3",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "electric-energy-stored-by-capacitor",
    "solution": "1 : 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbl4bgb",
    "question": "Two identical capacitors have same capacitance $C$. One of them is charged to the potential $V$ and other to the potential $2 \\mathrm{~V}$. The negative ends of both are connected together. When the positive ends are also joined together, the decrease in energy of the combined system is :",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{1}{4} \\mathrm{CV}^2$",
      "$\\frac{3}{4} \\mathrm{CV}^2$",
      "$\\frac{1}{2} \\mathrm{CV}^2$",
      "$2 \\mathrm{CV}^2$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "electric-energy-stored-by-capacitor",
    "solution": "$\\frac{1}{4} \\mathrm{CV}^2$"
  },
  {
    "id": "e6AD5TmcSOt28q1g",
    "question": "A parallel plate condenser with a dielectric of dielectric constant $$K$$ between the plates has a capacity $$C$$ and is charged to a potential $$V$$ volt. The dielectric slab is slowly removed from between the plates and then reinserted. The net work done by the system in this process is ",
    "options": [
      "zero ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}\\,\\left( {K - 1} \\right)\\,C{V^2}$$ ",
      "$${{C{V^2}\\left( {K - 1} \\right)} \\over K}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {K - 1} \\right)\\,C{V^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "parallel-plate-capacitor",
    "solution": "zero "
  },
  {
    "id": "gr7JyZIT9ApQgH5ZRtR2i",
    "question": "A parallel plate capacitor with area 200 cm<sup>2</sup> and separation between the plates 1.5 cm,  is connected across a battery of emf V. If the force of attraction between the plates is $$25 \\times {10^{ - 6}}N,$$ the value of V is approximately : $$\\left( {{ \\in _o} = 8.85 \\times {{10}^{ - 12}}{{{C^2}} \\over {N.{m^2}}}} \\right)$$",
    "options": [
      "250 V",
      "100 V",
      "300 V",
      "150 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "parallel-plate-capacitor",
    "solution": "250 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "QR0yg1kEIJGexqv0gRpbT",
    "question": "A parallel plate capacitor with plates of area 1 m<sup>2</sup> each, are at a separation of 0.1 m. If the electric field between the plates is 100 N/C, the magnitude of charge on each plate is : \n<br/><br/>(Take $$\\varepsilon $$<sub>0</sub> = 8.85 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$12</sup> $${{{C^2}} \\over {N - {m^2}}}$$)",
    "options": [
      "9.85 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–10</sup> C",
      "8.85 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–10</sup> C",
      "6.85 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–10</sup> C",
      "7.85 × 10<sup>–10</sup> C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "parallel-plate-capacitor",
    "solution": "8.85 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–10</sup> C"
  },
  {
    "id": "4a4aSrK9P4kgAF3cTie36",
    "question": "A parallel plate capacitor has 1μF capacitance.\nOne of its two plates is given +2μC charge and\nthe other plate, +4μC charge. The potential\ndifference developed across the capacitor is:-",
    "options": [
      "1V",
      "5V",
      "2V",
      "3V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "parallel-plate-capacitor",
    "solution": "1V"
  },
  {
    "id": "8mMYaSEC4GjYUZ5vUt1klt27t1f",
    "question": "An electron with kinetic energy K<sub>1</sub> enters between parallel plates of a capacitor at an angle '$$\\alpha$$' with the plates. It leaves the plates at angle '$$\\beta$$' with kinetic energy K<sub>2</sub>. Then the ratio of kinetic energies K<sub>1</sub> : K<sub>2</sub> will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{{\\cos }^2}\\beta } \\over {{{\\cos }^2}\\alpha }}$$",
      "$${{\\cos \\beta } \\over {\\cos \\alpha }}$$",
      "$${{{{\\sin }^2}\\beta } \\over {{{\\cos }^2}\\alpha }}$$",
      "$${{\\cos \\beta } \\over {\\sin \\alpha }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "parallel-plate-capacitor",
    "solution": "$${{{{\\cos }^2}\\beta } \\over {{{\\cos }^2}\\alpha }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57q90xt",
    "question": "<p>A force of 10 N acts on a charged particle placed between two plates of a charged capacitor. If one plate of capacitor is removed, then the force acting on that particle will be.</p>",
    "options": [
      "5 N",
      "10 N",
      "20 N",
      "Zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "parallel-plate-capacitor",
    "solution": "5 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c4a0nd",
    "question": "<p>A parallel plate capacitor is formed by two plates each of area 30$$\\pi$$ cm<sup>2</sup> separated by 1 mm. A material of dielectric strength 3.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup> is filled between the plates. If the maximum charge that can be stored on the capacitor without causing any dielectric breakdown is 7 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup>C, the value of dielectric constant of the material is :</p>\n<p>[Use $${1 \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}} = 9 \\times {10^9}$$ Nm<sup>2</sup> C<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.66",
      "1.75",
      "2.25",
      "2.33"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "parallel-plate-capacitor",
    "solution": "2.33"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rgj5f7",
    "question": "<p>Two identical thin metal plates has charge $$q_{1}$$ and $$q_{2}$$ respectively such that $$q_{1}&gt;q_{2}$$. The plates were brought close to each other to form a parallel plate capacitor of capacitance C. The potential difference between them is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\left(q_{1}+q_{2}\\right)}{C}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\left(q_{1}-q_{2}\\right)}{C}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\left(q_{1}-q_{2}\\right)}{2 C}$$",
      "$$\\frac{2\\left(q_{1}-q_{2}\\right)}{C}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "parallel-plate-capacitor",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\left(q_{1}-q_{2}\\right)}{2 C}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswsttc",
    "question": "<p>A capacitor of capacitance $$\\mathrm{C}$$ is charged to a potential V. The flux of the electric field through a closed surface enclosing the positive plate of the capacitor is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Zero",
      "$$\\frac{C V}{\\varepsilon_{0}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{C V}{2 \\varepsilon_{0}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{2 C V}{\\varepsilon_{0}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "parallel-plate-capacitor",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{C V}{\\varepsilon_{0}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "HtWT6Zb6CiRWcsU2",
    "question": "Let $$C$$ be the capacitance of a capacitor discharging through a resistor $$R.$$ Suppose $${t_1}$$ is the time taken for the energy stored in the capacitor to reduce  to half its initial value and $${t_2}$$ is the time taken for the charge to reduce to one-fourth its initial value. Then the ratio $${t_1}/{t_2}$$ will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$1$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 4}$$ ",
      "$$2$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "rc-circuit",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 4}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktafge1u",
    "question": "The material filled between the plates of a parallel plate capacitor has resistivity 200 $$\\Omega$$m. The value of capacitance of the capacitor is 2 pF. If a potential difference of 40 V is applied across the plates of the capacitor, then the value of leakage current flowing out of the capacitor is : (given the value of relative permittivity of material is 50) ",
    "options": [
      "9.0 $$\\mu$$A",
      "9.0 mA",
      "0.9 mA",
      "0.9 $$\\mu$$A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "rc-circuit",
    "solution": "0.9 mA"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktmpgub8",
    "question": "A capacitor is connected to a 20 V battery through a resistance of 10$$\\Omega$$. It is found that the potential difference across the capacitor rises to 2 V in 1 $$\\mu$$s. The capacitance of the capacitor is __________ $$\\mu$$F. Given : $$\\ln \\left( {{{10} \\over 9}} \\right) = 0.105$$",
    "options": [
      "9.52",
      "0.95",
      "0.105",
      "1.85"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "rc-circuit",
    "solution": "0.95"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54uvv2l",
    "question": "<p>A capacitor is discharging through a resistor R. Consider in time t<sub>1</sub>, the energy stored in the capacitor reduces to half of its initial value and in time t<sub>2</sub>, the charge stored reduces to one eighth of its initial value. The ratio t<sub>1</sub>/t<sub>2</sub> will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "1/2",
      "1/3",
      "1/4",
      "1/6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "capacitor",
    "topic": "rc-circuit",
    "solution": "1/6"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ze1uZpWlVA7Tw6eN",
    "question": "A circular disc of radius $$R$$ is removed from a bigger circular disc of radius $$2R$$ such that the circumferences of the discs coincide. The center of mass of the new disc is $$\\alpha R$$ form the center of the bigger disc. The value of $$\\alpha $$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$1/4$$ ",
      "$$1/3$$ ",
      "$$1/2$$ ",
      "$$1/6$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "cavity-problems",
    "solution": "$$1/3$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "DTbqjQLkohJDnpSy",
    "question": "A body $$A$$ of mass $$M$$ while falling vertically downloads under gravity breaks into two-parts; a body $$B$$ of mass $${1 \\over 3}$$ $$M$$ and a body $$C$$ of mass $${2 \\over 3}$$ $$M.$$ The center of mass of bodies $$B$$ and $$C$$ taken together shifts compared to that of bodies $$B$$ and $$C$$ taken together shifts compared to that of body $$A$$ towards ",
    "options": [
      "does not shift ",
      "depends on height of breaking ",
      "body $$B$$ ",
      "body $$C$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "center-of-mass-of-continuous-mass-distribution",
    "solution": "does not shift "
  },
  {
    "id": "xgq9perk5vcVZ7Xu",
    "question": "Distance of the center of mass of a solid uniform cone from its vertex is $$z{}_0$$. If the radius of its base is $$R$$ and its height is $$h$$ then $$z{}_0$$ is equal to : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{5h} \\over 8}$$ ",
      "$${{3{h^2}} \\over {8R}}$$ ",
      "$${{{h^2}} \\over {4R}}$$ ",
      "$${{3h} \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "center-of-mass-of-continuous-mass-distribution",
    "solution": "$${{3h} \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "u9CwJJkzFTx8gwZ5IU7k9k2k5kv9tjp",
    "question": "A rod of length L has non-uniform linear mass\n<br/>density given by $$\\rho $$(x) = $$a + b{\\left( {{x \\over L}} \\right)^2}$$\n, where a\n<br/>and b are constants and 0 $$ \\le $$ x $$ \\le $$ L. The value\n<br/>of x for the centre of mass of the rod is at :",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 2}\\left( {{{a + b} \\over {2a + b}}} \\right)L$$",
      "$${4 \\over 3}\\left( {{{a + b} \\over {2a + 3b}}} \\right)L$$",
      "$${3 \\over 4}\\left( {{{2a + b} \\over {3a + b}}} \\right)L$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}\\left( {{{2a + b} \\over {3a + b}}} \\right)L$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "center-of-mass-of-continuous-mass-distribution",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 4}\\left( {{{2a + b} \\over {3a + b}}} \\right)L$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "VLHK6KOaUxPayjKB",
    "question": "Consider a two particle system with particles having masses $${m_1}$$ and $${m_2}$$. If the first particle is pushed towards the center of mass through a distance $$d,$$ by what distance should the second particle is moved, so as to keep the center of mass at the same position? ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{m_2}} \\over {{m_1}}}\\,\\,d$$  ",
      "$${{{m_1}} \\over {{m_1} + {m_2}}}d$$ ",
      "$${{{m_1}} \\over {{m_2}}}d$$ ",
      "$$d$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "center-of-mass-of-discrete-particles",
    "solution": "$${{{m_1}} \\over {{m_2}}}d$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57pqga0",
    "question": "<p>Two blocks of masses 10 kg and 30 kg are placed on the same straight line with coordinates (0, 0) cm and (x, 0) cm respectively. The block of 10 kg is moved on the same line through a distance of 6 cm towards the other block. The distance through which the block of 30 kg must be moved to keep the position of centre of mass of the system unchanged is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 cm towards the 10 kg block",
      "2 cm away from the 10 kg block",
      "2 cm towards the 10 kg block",
      "4 cm away from the 10 kg block"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "center-of-mass-of-discrete-particles",
    "solution": "2 cm towards the 10 kg block"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p4a8py",
    "question": "<p>Two bodies of mass $$1 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ and $$3 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ have position vectors $$\\hat{i}+2 \\hat{j}+\\hat{k}$$ and $$-3 \\hat{i}-2 \\hat{j}+\\hat{k}$$ respectively. The magnitude of position vector of centre of mass of this system will be similar to the magnitude of vector :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\hat{i}+2 \\hat{j}+\\hat{k}$$",
      "$$-3 \\hat{i}-2 \\hat{j}+\\hat{k}$$",
      "$$-2 \\hat{i}+2 \\hat{k}$$",
      "$$2 \\hat{i}-\\hat{j}+2 \\hat{k}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "center-of-mass-of-discrete-particles",
    "solution": "$$\\hat{i}+2 \\hat{j}+\\hat{k}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "pnDHZ821HAXsBq7V",
    "question": "A block of mass $$0.50$$ $$kg$$ is moving with a speed of $$2.00$$ $$m{s^{ - 1}}$$ on a smooth surface. It strike another mass of $$1.0$$ $$kg$$ and then they move together as a single body. The energy loss during the collision is :",
    "options": [
      "$$0.16J$$ ",
      "$$1.00J$$ ",
      "$$0.67J$$ ",
      "$$0.34$$  $$J$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "$$0.67J$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "xnNKC9egwPygXHiy",
    "question": "<b>Statement - 1 : </b> Two particles moving in the same direction do not lose all their energy in a completely inelastic collision. \n<br/><br/><b>Statement - 2 :</b> Principle of conservation of momentum holds true for all kinds of collisions.",
    "options": [
      "Statement - 1 is true, Statement - 2 is true; Statement - 2 is the correct explanation of Statement -  1  ",
      "Statement - 1 is true, Statement - 2 is true; Statement - 2 is <b>not</b> the correct explanation of Statement -  1  ",
      "Statement - 1 is false, Statement - 2 is true ",
      "Statement - 1 is true, Statement - 2 is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "Statement - 1 is true, Statement - 2 is true; Statement - 2 is the correct explanation of Statement -  1  "
  },
  {
    "id": "ItHLBj1wfhKlo13J",
    "question": "This question has statement $${\\rm I}$$ and statement $${\\rm I}$$$${\\rm I}$$. Of the four choices given after the statements, choose the one that best describes the two statements.\n<p><b>Statement - $${\\rm I}$$:</b> A point particle of mass $$m$$ moving with speed $$\\upsilon $$ collides with stationary point particle of mass $$M.$$ If the maximum energy loss possible is given as $$f\\left( {{1 \\over 2}m{v^2}} \\right)$$, then $$f = \\left( {{m \\over {M + m}}} \\right).$$\n<br/><br/><b>Statement - $${\\rm II}$$:</b> Maximum energy loss occurs when the particles get stuck together as a result of the collision. </p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ is true, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is true; Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is the correct explanation of Statement - $${\\rm I}$$.",
      "Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ is true, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is true; Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is not the correct explanation of Statement - $${\\rm I}$$.",
      "Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ is true, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is false ",
      "Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ is false, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ is false, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ true."
  },
  {
    "id": "zAeid4s9T1Uzjbdo",
    "question": "A particle of mass $$m$$ moving in the $$x$$ direction with speed $$2v$$ is hit by another particle of mass $$2m$$  moving in the $$y$$ direction with speed $$v.$$  If the collision is perfectly inelastic, the percentage loss in the energy during the collision is close to: ",
    "options": [
      "$$56\\% $$ ",
      "$$62\\% $$",
      "$$44\\% $$",
      "$$50\\% $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "$$56\\% $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "a1h7IOVtcxppkBerBLJqC",
    "question": "A neutron moving with a speed ‘v’ makes a head on collision with a stationary\nhydrogen atom in ground state. The minimum kinetic energy of the neutron for\nwhich inelastic collision will take place is :",
    "options": [
      "10.2 eV",
      "16.8 eV",
      "12.1 eV",
      "20.4 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "20.4 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "UFc8CWHpJzGXSvF9",
    "question": "The mass of a hydrogen molecule is 3.32 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-27</sup> kg. If 10<sup>23</sup> hydrogen molecules strike, per second, a fixed wall of area 2 cm<sup>2</sup> at an angle of 45<sup>o</sup> to the normal, and rebound elastically with a speed of 10<sup>3</sup> m/s, then the pressure on the wall is nearly: ",
    "options": [
      "2.35 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> N m<sup>-2</sup>",
      "4.70 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> N m<sup>-2</sup>",
      "2.35 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>2</sup> N m<sup>-2</sup>",
      "4.70 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>2</sup> N m<sup>-2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "2.35 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> N m<sup>-2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "MX7f8MTbmBWWmGKZdy3BO",
    "question": "A proton of mass m collides elastically with a particle of unknown mass at rest. After the collision,  the proton and the unknown particle are seen moving at an angle of 90<sup>o</sup> with respect to each other. The mass of unknown particle is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${m \\over 2}$$",
      "m",
      "$${m \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$",
      "2 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "m"
  },
  {
    "id": "6ZE9CfSVinM7H5g2",
    "question": "In a collinear collision, a particle with an initial speed v<sub>0</sub> strikes a stationary particle of the same mass. If\nthe final total kinetic energy is 50% greater than the original kinetic energy, the magnitude of the relative\nvelocity between the two particles, after collision, is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{v_0}} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "$${{v_0}} \\over 4$$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 {v_0}$$",
      "$${{v_0}} \\over 2$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt 2 {v_0}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "VQNAfJ0JwW46dhyKi6RYv",
    "question": "If 10<sup>22</sup> gas molecules each of mass 10<sup>–26</sup> kg\ncollide with a surface (perpendicular to it)\nelastically per second over an area 1 m<sup>2</sup> with\na speed 10<sup>4</sup> m/s, the pressure exerted by the gas\nmolecules will be of the order of :",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>8</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup>",
      "10<sup>16</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup>",
      "10<sup>4</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup>",
      "2 N/m<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "2 N/m<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "RdT8iUaE0q90yW6aBNDmT",
    "question": "A particle of mass 'm' is moving with speed '2v'\nand collides with a mass '2m' moving with\nspeed 'v' in the same direction. After collision,\nthe first mass is stopped completely while the\nsecond one splits into two particles each of\nmass 'm', which move at angle 45° with respect\nto the origianl direction.\nThe speed of each of the moving particle will\nbe :-",
    "options": [
      "2 $$\\sqrt2$$v",
      "v / (2 $$\\sqrt2$$ )",
      "v / $$\\sqrt2$$",
      "$$\\sqrt2$$v"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "2 $$\\sqrt2$$v"
  },
  {
    "id": "BQVxm3CHxJjC3vPE0HQaI",
    "question": "A body of mass 2 kg makes an eleastic collision\nwith a second body at rest and continues to move\nin the original direction but with one fourth of its\noriginal speed. What is the mass of the second\nbody ?",
    "options": [
      "1.2 kg",
      "1.0 kg",
      "1.8 kg",
      "1.5 kg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "1.2 kg"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZIcXfjv1T8bgwjEoT07tL",
    "question": "A body of mass m<sub>1</sub> moving with an unknown\nvelocity of $${v_1}\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge  $$, undergoes a collinear collision\nwith a body of mass m<sub>2</sub> moving with a velocity\n$${v_2}\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge  $$ . After collision, m<sub>1</sub> and m<sub>2</sub> move with\nvelocities of $${v_3}\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge  $$ and $${v_4}\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge  $$ , respectively.\nIf m<sub>2</sub> = 0.5 m<sub>1</sub> and v<sub>3</sub> = 0.5 v<sub>1</sub>, then v<sub>1</sub> is :-",
    "options": [
      "$${v_4} - {{{v_2}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${v_4} - {{{v_2}} \\over 4}$$",
      "$${v_4} - {v_2}$$",
      "$${v_4} + {v_2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "$${v_4} - {v_2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ffzhAQk3xQj3WUBZfz4ac",
    "question": "An alpha-particle of mass m suffers 1-dimensional elastic collision with a nucleus at rest of unknown mass. It is scattered directly backwards losing, 64% of its initial kinetic energy. The mass of the nucleus is ",
    "options": [
      "2m",
      "4m",
      "1.5m",
      "3.5m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "4m"
  },
  {
    "id": "xOFjq4w5TNhYpRHQdk7JK",
    "question": "A simple pendulum, made of a string of length $$\\ell $$ and a bob of mass m, is released from a small angle $${{\\theta _0}}$$. It strikes a block of mass M, kept on a horizontal surface at its lowest point of oscillations, elastically. It\nbounces back and goes up to an angle $${{\\theta _1}}$$. Then M is given by : ",
    "options": [
      "$${m \\over 2}\\left( {{{{\\theta _0} + {\\theta _1}} \\over {{\\theta _0} - {\\theta _1}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${m \\over 2}\\left( {{{{\\theta _0} - {\\theta _1}} \\over {{\\theta _0} + {\\theta _1}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$$m\\left( {{{{\\theta _0} + {\\theta _1}} \\over {{\\theta _0} - {\\theta _1}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$$m\\left( {{{{\\theta _0} - {\\theta _1}} \\over {{\\theta _0} + {\\theta _1}}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "$$m\\left( {{{{\\theta _0} + {\\theta _1}} \\over {{\\theta _0} - {\\theta _1}}}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "RyQ4T0YCkL3iEzw2JKL8p",
    "question": "A body of mass 1 kg falls freely from a height of 100 m, on a platform mass 3 kg which is mounted on a spring having spring constant k = 1.25 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup>  N/m. The body sticks to the platform and the spring's maximum compression is found to be x. Given that g = 10 ms<sup>–2</sup>\n, the value of x will be close to : ",
    "options": [
      "8 cm",
      "4 cm",
      "40 cm",
      "80 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "4 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "yOqMeIm73bAqkicZ6LtId",
    "question": "A piece of wood of mass 0.03 kg is dropped from the top of a 100 m height building. At the same time, a bullet of mass 0.02 kg is fired vertically upward, with a velocity 100 ms<sup>–1</sup>, from the ground. The bullet gets embedded in the wood. Then the maximum height to which the combined system reaches above the top of the building before falling below is - (g = 10 ms<sup>–2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "30 m ",
      "40 m",
      "20 m",
      "10 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "40 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "VKhgwb5YmY7b9fMoRCjgy2xukf3ufgfj",
    "question": "A block of mass 1.9 kg is at rest at the edge of a table, of height 1 m. A bullet of mass 0.1 kg\ncollides with the block and sticks to it. If the velocity of the bullet is 20 m/s in the horizontal\ndirection just before the collision then the kinetic energy just before the combined system strikes\nthe floor, is [Take g = 10 m/s<sup>2</sup>\n . Assume there is no rotational motion and loss of energy after the\ncollision is negligable.]",
    "options": [
      "23 J",
      "21 J",
      "20 J",
      "19 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "21 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "5rx54d66X0ne3oXiZz7k9k2k5l9guhg",
    "question": "A particle of mass m is projected with a speed\nu from the ground at an angle\n$$\\theta  = {\\pi  \\over 3}$$ w.r.t.\nhorizontal (x-axis). When it has reached its\nmaximum height, it collides completely\ninelastically with another particle of the same\nmass and velocity $$u\\widehat i$$ . The horizontal distance\ncovered by the combined mass before reaching\nthe ground is:",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\sqrt 2 {{{u^2}} \\over g}$$",
      "$${{3\\sqrt 3 } \\over 8}{{{u^2}} \\over g}$$",
      "$${{3\\sqrt 2 } \\over 4}{{{u^2}} \\over g}$$",
      "$${5 \\over 8}{{{u^2}} \\over g}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "$${{3\\sqrt 3 } \\over 8}{{{u^2}} \\over g}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "P83tb12mV8X5UKg6k47k9k2k5ietaoz",
    "question": "Two particles of equal mass m have respective\n<br/>initial velocities $$u\\widehat i$$ and $$u\\left( {{{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over 2}} \\right)$$.\n<br/>They collide\ncompletely inelastically. The energy lost in the\nprocess is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 3}m{u^2}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 8}m{u^2}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 4}m{u^2}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{2 \\over 3}} m{u^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 8}m{u^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "kMziWJoYrtTekb2JBj7k9k2k5hhc2hz",
    "question": "A particle of mass m is dropped from a height\nh above the ground. At the same time another\nparticle of the same mass is thrown vertically\nupwards from the ground with a speed of $$\\sqrt {2gh} $$. If they collide head-on completely\ninelastically, the time taken for the combined\nmass to reach the ground, in units of $$\\sqrt {{h \\over g}} $$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{1 \\over 2}} $$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over 2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over 4}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over 2}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "63epoaj6Pbm53RjYHOjgy2xukev2td6f",
    "question": "A particle of mass m with an initial velocity $$u\\widehat i$$\ncollides perfectly elastically with a mass 3 m at\nrest. It moves with a velocity $$v\\widehat j$$ after collision,\nthen, v is given by :",
    "options": [
      "$$v = \\sqrt {{2 \\over 3}} u$$",
      "$$v = {u \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$",
      "$$v = {u \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$$v = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 6 }}u$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "$$v = {u \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "LJLtggkvzeGoqA59qc1kltj841t",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.<br/><br/>Assertion A : Body 'P' having mass M moving with speed 'u' has head-on collision elastically with another body 'Q' having mass 'm' initially at rest. If m &lt;&lt; M, body 'Q' will have a maximum speed equal to '2u' after collision.<br/><br/>Reason R : During elastic collision, the momentum and kinetic energy are both conserved.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "A is correct but R is not correct.",
      "A is not correct but R is correct.",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "fvjQ8RvFfiVc4SVLEM1kmlvgugm",
    "question": "An object of mass m<sub>1</sub> collides with another object of mass m<sub>2</sub>, which is at rest. After the collision the objects move with equal speeds in opposite direction. The ratio of the masses m<sub>2</sub> : m<sub>1</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "3 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "3 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth2w92x",
    "question": "A body of mass M moving at speed V<sub>0</sub> collides elastically with a mass 'm' at rest. After the collision, the two masses move at angles $$\\theta$$<sub>1</sub> and $$\\theta$$<sub>2</sub> with respect to the initial direction of motion of the body of mass M. The largest possible value of the ratio M/m, for which the angles $$\\theta$$<sub>1</sub> and $$\\theta$$<sub>2</sub> will be equal, is :",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "1",
      "3",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l546u8pk",
    "question": "<p>A body of mass M at rest explodes into three pieces, in the ratio of masses 1 : 1 : 2. Two smaller pieces fly off perpendicular to each other with velocities of 30 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup> and 40 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup> respectively. The velocity of the third piece will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "15 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "25 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "35 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "50 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "25 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57pusel",
    "question": "<p>What percentage of kinetic energy of a moving particle is transferred to a stationary particle when it strikes the stationary particle of 5 times its mass?</p>\n<p>(Assume the collision to be head-on elastic collision)</p>",
    "options": [
      "50.0%",
      "66.6%",
      "55.6%",
      "33.3%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "55.6%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f4foje",
    "question": "<p>Two billiard balls of mass 0.05 kg each moving in opposite directions with 10 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup> collide and rebound with the same speed. If the time duration of contact is t = 0.005 s, then what is the force exerted on the ball due to each other?</p>",
    "options": [
      "100 N",
      "200 N",
      "300 N",
      "400 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "200 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyff41o",
    "question": "<p>A particle of mass m moving with velocity v collides with a stationary particle of mass 2m. After collision, they stick together and continue to move together with velocity</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$v$$",
      "$$\\frac{v}{3}$$",
      "$$\\frac{v}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{v}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{v}{3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gsdz6",
    "question": "<p>A stationary particle breaks into two parts of masses $$m_A$$ and $$m_B$$ which move with velocities $$v_A$$ and $$v_B$$ respectively. The ratio of their kinetic energies $$\\left(K_B: K_A\\right)$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$v_B: v_A$$\n",
      "$$1: 1$$\n",
      "$$m_B v_B: m_A v_A$$\n",
      "$$m_B: m_A$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "collision",
    "solution": "$$v_B: v_A$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lNQBy7v8fsuRC7Kx",
    "question": "Consider the following two statements : \n<br/><br>$$A.$$ Linear momentum of a system of particles is zero\n<br/><br>$$B.$$ Kinetic energy of a system of particles is zero.\n<br/><br>then </br></br></br>",
    "options": [
      "$$A$$ does not imply $$B$$ and $$B$$ does not imply $$A$$",
      "$$A$$ implies $$B$$ but $$B$$ does not imply $$A$$ ",
      "$$A$$ does not imply $$B$$ but $$B$$ implies $$A$$ ",
      "$$A$$ implies $$B$$ and $$B$$ implies $$A$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "$$A$$ does not imply $$B$$ and $$B$$ does not imply $$A$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "gnHchs5vfh53bMk9",
    "question": "A machine gun fires a bullet of mass $$40$$ $$g$$ with a velocity  $$1200m{s^{ - 1}}.$$ The man holding it can exert a maximum force of $$144$$ $$N$$ on the gun. How many bullets can he fire per second at the most? ",
    "options": [
      "Two ",
      "Four ",
      "One ",
      "Three "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "Three "
  },
  {
    "id": "amEaHEve22kHcp18",
    "question": "A player caught a cricket ball of mass $$150$$ $$g$$ moving at a rate of $$20$$ $$m/s.$$  If the catching process is completed in $$0.1s,$$ the force of the blow exerted by the ball on the hand of the player is equal to ",
    "options": [
      "$$150$$ $$N$$ ",
      "$$3$$ $$N$$ ",
      "$$30$$ $$N$$ ",
      "$$300$$ $$N$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "$$30$$ $$N$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "0vCAeFI4lhK6kSEF",
    "question": "A bomb of mass $$16kg$$ at rest explodes into two pieces of masses $$4$$ $$kg$$ and $$12$$ $$kg.$$ The velocity of the $$12$$ $$kg$$ mass is $$4\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}.$$ The kinetic energy of the other mass is ",
    "options": [
      "$$144$$ $$J$$ ",
      "$$288$$ $$J$$ ",
      "$$192$$ $$J$$ ",
      "$$96$$ $$J$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "$$288$$ $$J$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "bx5j2aS78IdEAxCatbPUM",
    "question": "A particle of mass m is moving in a straight line with momentum p. Starting at time t = 0, a force F = kt acts in the same direction on the moving particle during time interval T so that its momentum changes from p to 3p. Here k is a constant. The value of T is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\sqrt {{k \\over p}} $$",
      "$$2\\sqrt {{p \\over k}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{2p} \\over 2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{2k} \\over p}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "$$2\\sqrt {{p \\over k}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Xzv5EQELrubBDoHCOLTW1",
    "question": "A wedge of mass M = 4m lies on a frictionless\nplane. A particle of mass m approaches the\nwedge with speed v. There is no friction\nbetween the particle and the plane or between\nthe particle and the wedge. The maximum\nheight climbed by the particle on the wedge is\ngiven by :-",
    "options": [
      "$${{{v^2}} \\over {g}}$$",
      "$${{2{v^2}} \\over {7g}}$$",
      "$${{{v^2}} \\over {2g}}$$",
      "$${{2{v^2}} \\over {5g}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "$${{2{v^2}} \\over {5g}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "kIjnqKIosJlYQlKYU63rsa0w2w9jx3pnzgb",
    "question": "A man (mass = 50 kg) and his son (mass = 20 kg) are standing on a frictionless surface facing each other. The\nman pushes his son so that he starts moving at a speed of 0.70 ms<sup>–1</sup> with respect to the man. The speed of the\nman with respect to the surface is :",
    "options": [
      "0.28 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "0.47 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "0.20 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "0.14 ms<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "0.20 ms<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "l13Df72BzP6e5PtSKUjgy2xukfyy8d0f",
    "question": "Particle A of mass m<sub>1</sub>\n moving with velocity $$\\left( {\\sqrt3\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\right)m{s^{ - 1}}$$ collides with another particle B of mass m<sub>2</sub>\nwhich is at rest initially. Let $$\\overrightarrow {{V_1}} $$\n and $$\\overrightarrow {{V_2}} $$\n be the velocities of particles A and B after collision\nrespectively. If m<sub>1</sub>\n = 2m<sub>2</sub>\n and after<br/> collision $$\\overrightarrow {{V_1}}  = $$$$\\left( {\\widehat i + \\sqrt 3 \\widehat j} \\right)$$\n, the angle between $$\\overrightarrow {{V_1}} $$\n and $$\\overrightarrow {{V_2}} $$\n is :",
    "options": [
      "105<sup>o</sup>",
      "15<sup>o</sup>",
      "-45<sup>o</sup>",
      "60<sup>o</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "105<sup>o</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqa585y",
    "question": "If the Kinetic energy of a moving body becomes four times its initial Kinetic energy, then the percentage change in its momentum will be :",
    "options": [
      "100%",
      "200%",
      "300%",
      "400%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "100%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsuvhom",
    "question": "A bullet of '4 g' mass is fired from a gun of mass 4 kg. If the bullet moves with the muzzle speed of 50 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, the impulse imparted to the gun and velocity of recoil of gun are :",
    "options": [
      "0.2 kg ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, 0.1 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "0.4 kg ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, 0.05 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "0.2 kg ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, 0.05 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "0.4 kg ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, 0.1 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "0.2 kg ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, 0.05 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58bcavr",
    "question": "<p>An object is thrown vertically upwards. At its maximum height, which of the following quantity becomes zero?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Momentum",
      "Potential Energy",
      "Acceleration",
      "Force"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "Momentum"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w28aiq",
    "question": "<p>Two bodies A and B of masses 5 kg and 8 kg are moving such that the momentum of body B is twice that of the body A. The ratio of their kinetic energies will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 : 5",
      "2 : 5",
      "5 : 4",
      "5 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "2 : 5"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i0cv9h",
    "question": "<p>A ball of mass $$0.15 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ hits the wall with its initial speed of $$12 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ and bounces back without changing its initial speed. If the force applied by the wall on the ball during the contact is $$100 \\mathrm{~N}$$, calculate the time duration of the contact of ball with the wall.</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.018 s",
      "0.036 s",
      "0.009 s",
      "0.072 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "0.036 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i0e14v",
    "question": "<p>A body of mass $$8 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ and another of mass $$2 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ are moving with equal kinetic energy. The ratio of their respective momentum will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 4",
      "4 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kmefbq",
    "question": "<p>A body of mass $$10 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is projected at an angle of $$45^{\\circ}$$ with the horizontal. The trajectory of the body is observed to pass through a point $$(20,10)$$. If $$\\mathrm{T}$$ is the time of flight, then its momentum vector, at time $$\\mathrm{t}=\\frac{\\mathrm{T}}{\\sqrt{2}}$$, is _____________.</p>\n<p>[Take $$\\mathrm{g}=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$ ]</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\n100 \\hat{i}+(100 \\sqrt{2}-200) \\hat{j}$$",
      "$$100 \\sqrt{2} \\hat{i}+(100-200 \\sqrt{2}) \\hat{j}$$",
      "$$100 \\hat{i}+(100-200 \\sqrt{2}) \\hat{j}$$",
      "$$100 \\sqrt{2} \\hat{i}+(100 \\sqrt{2}-200) \\hat{j}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "$$100 \\sqrt{2} \\hat{i}+(100 \\sqrt{2}-200) \\hat{j}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6m9py5f",
    "question": "<p>In two different experiments, an object of mass $$5 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ moving with a speed of $$25 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ hits two different walls and comes to rest within (i) 3 second, (ii) 5 seconds, respectively. Choose the correct option out of the following :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Impulse and average force acting on the object will be same for both the cases.",
      "Impulse will be same for both the cases but the average force will be different.",
      "Average force will be same for both the cases but the impulse will be different.",
      "Average force and impulse will be different for both the cases."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "Impulse will be same for both the cases but the average force will be different."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rhg0hg",
    "question": "<p>If momentum of a body is increased by 20%, then its kinetic energy increases by</p>",
    "options": [
      "36%",
      "40%",
      "44%",
      "48%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "44%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpkmvgy",
    "question": "<p>100 balls each of mass $$\\mathrm{m}$$ moving with speed $$v$$ simultaneously strike a wall normally and reflected back with same speed, in time $$\\mathrm{t ~s}$$. The total force exerted by the balls on the wall is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{200 m v}{t}$$",
      "$$\\frac{100 m v}{t}$$",
      "$$\\frac{m v}{100 t}$$",
      "$$200 m v t$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{200 m v}{t}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldquy4x0",
    "question": "A machine gun of mass $10 \\mathrm{~kg}$ fires $20 \\mathrm{~g}$ bullets at the rate of 180 bullets per minute with a speed of $100 \\mathrm{~m} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$ each. The recoil velocity of the gun is",
    "options": [
      "$ 0.02 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$",
      "$1.5 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$",
      "$2.5 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$",
      "$0.6 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "$0.6 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr2fn46",
    "question": "<p>A ball of mass $$200 \\mathrm{~g}$$ rests on a vertical post of height $$20 \\mathrm{~m}$$. A bullet of mass $$10 \\mathrm{~g}$$, travelling in horizontal direction, hits the centre of the ball. After collision both travels independently. The ball hits the ground at a distance $$30 \\mathrm{~m}$$ and the bullet at a distance of $$120 \\mathrm{~m}$$ from the foot of the post. The value of initial velocity of the bullet will be (if $$g=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "120 m/s",
      "360 m/s",
      "400 m/s",
      "60 m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "360 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq1a943",
    "question": "<p>A bullet of $$10 \\mathrm{~g}$$ leaves the barrel of gun with a velocity of $$600 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. If the barrel of gun is $$50 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ long and mass of gun is $$3 \\mathrm{~kg}$$, then value of impulse supplied to the gun will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "12 Ns",
      "3 Ns",
      "6 Ns",
      "36 Ns"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "6 Ns"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguxz2s9",
    "question": "<p>An average force of $$125 \\mathrm{~N}$$ is applied on a machine gun firing bullets each of mass $$10 \\mathrm{~g}$$ at the speed of $$250 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ to keep it in position. The number of bullets fired per second by the machine gun is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "25",
      "50",
      "5",
      "100"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "50"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3a3qt",
    "question": "<p>Two bodies of mass $$4 \\mathrm{~g}$$ and $$25 \\mathrm{~g}$$ are moving with equal kinetic energies. The ratio of magnitude of their linear momentum is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3: 5$$\n",
      "$$5: 4$$\n",
      "$$2: 5$$\n",
      "$$4: 5$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "$$2: 5$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3p10j",
    "question": "<p>A body of mass $$1000 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is moving horizontally with a velocity $$6 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. If $$200 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ extra mass is added, the final velocity (in $$\\mathrm{m} / \\mathrm{s}$$) is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "6",
      "2",
      "3",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "5"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse684ye",
    "question": "<p>An artillery piece of mass $$M_1$$ fires a shell of mass $$M_2$$ horizontally. Instantaneously after the firing, the ratio of kinetic energy of the artillery and that of the shell is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$M_1 /\\left(M_1+M_2\\right)$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{M_2}{M_1}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{M_1}{M_2}$$\n",
      "$$M_2 /\\left(M_1+M_2\\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{M_2}{M_1}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgx468k",
    "question": "<p>A spherical body of mass $$100 \\mathrm{~g}$$ is dropped from a height of $$10 \\mathrm{~m}$$ from the ground. After hitting the ground, the body rebounds to a height of $$5 \\mathrm{~m}$$. The impulse of force imparted by the ground to the body is given by : (given, $$\\mathrm{g}=9.8 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$43.2 \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$2.39 \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$4.32 \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$23.9 \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "impulse-momentum-theorem",
    "solution": "$$2.39 \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "pgWvSIEXyKTkCNra",
    "question": "Two identical particles move towards each other with velocity $$2v$$ and $$v$$ respectively. The velocity of center of mass is ",
    "options": [
      "$$v$$ ",
      "$$v/3$$ ",
      "$$v/2$$ ",
      "zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "center-of-mass",
    "topic": "motion-of-center-of-mass",
    "solution": "$$v/2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "1l568h81v",
    "question": "<p>A particle of mass m is moving in a circular path of constant radius r such that its centripetal acceleration (a) is varying with time t as a = k<sup>2</sup>rt<sup>2</sup>, where k is a constant. The power delivered to the particle by the force acting on it is given as</p>",
    "options": [
      "zero",
      "mk<sup>2</sup>r<sup>2</sup>t<sup>2</sup>",
      "mk<sup>2</sup>r<sup>2</sup>t",
      "mk<sup>2</sup>rt"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "non-uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "mk<sup>2</sup>r<sup>2</sup>t"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56ukhcs",
    "question": "<p>A stone tide to a spring of length L is whirled in a vertical circle with the other end of the spring at the centre. At a certain instant of time, the stone is at its lowest position and has a speed u. The magnitude of change in its velocity, as it reaches a position where the string is horizontal, is $$\\sqrt {x({u^2} - gL)} $$. The value of x is -</p>",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "2",
      "1",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "non-uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "9XwDckxIh9qNOdxb",
    "question": "The minimum velocity (in $$m{s^{ - 1}}$$) with which a car driver must traverse a flat curve of radius 150 m and coefficient of friction $$0.6$$ to avoid skidding is ",
    "options": [
      "$$60$$ ",
      "$$30$$ ",
      "$$15$$ ",
      "$$25$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$$30$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "t24lssV0vCNG1oNS",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is <b>FALSE</b> for a particle moving in a circle with a constant\nangular speed?   ",
    "options": [
      "The velocity vector is tangent to the circle.",
      "The acceleration vector is tangent to the circle.",
      "The acceleration vector points to the centre of the circle.",
      "The velocity and acceleration vectors are perpendicular to each other."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "The acceleration vector is tangent to the circle."
  },
  {
    "id": "CYX8eg1ZwaGiHPvR",
    "question": "For a particle in uniform circular motion the acceleration $$\\overrightarrow a $$ at a point P(R, θ) on the circle of radius R is (here θ is measured from the x–axis)",
    "options": [
      "$$ - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\cos \\theta \\widehat i + {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\sin \\theta \\widehat j$$",
      "$$ - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\sin \\theta \\widehat i + {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\cos \\theta \\widehat j$$",
      "$$ - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\cos \\theta \\widehat i - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\sin \\theta \\widehat j$$",
      "$${{{v^2}} \\over R}\\widehat i + {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\widehat j$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$$ - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\cos \\theta \\widehat i - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\sin \\theta \\widehat j$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "QUTOe3ixMeVyWi9A",
    "question": "Two cars of masses m<sub>1</sub> and m<sub>2</sub> are moving in circles of radii r<sub>1</sub> and r<sub>2</sub>, respectively. Their speeds are such that they make complete circles in the same time t. The ratio of their centripetal acceleration is",
    "options": [
      "m<sub>1</sub>r<sub>1</sub> : m<sub>2</sub>r<sub>2</sub>",
      "m<sub>1</sub> : m<sub>2</sub>",
      "r<sub>1</sub> : r<sub>2</sub>",
      "1 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "r<sub>1</sub> : r<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "PJBY3ec0cow284JnDLWaD",
    "question": "A disc rotates about its axis of symmetry in a horizontal plane at a steady rate of $$3.5$$ revolutions per second. A coin placed at a distnce of 1.25 cm from the axis of rotation remains at rest on the disc. The coefficient of friction between the coin and the disc is : (g = 10 m/s<sup>2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "0.5",
      "0.3",
      "0.7",
      "0.6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "0.6"
  },
  {
    "id": "VdYTnxX0JjVZXsi6weoRM",
    "question": "A particle is moving along a circular path with a constant speed of 10 ms<sup>–1</sup>. What is the magnitude of the change in velocity of the particle, when it moves through an angle of 60<sup>o</sup> around the centre of the circle? ",
    "options": [
      "zero ",
      "10 m/s",
      "$$10\\sqrt 2 m/s$$",
      "$$10\\sqrt 3 m/s$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "10 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "NqvTe2S7LfrbBiP8jttgK",
    "question": "A body is projected at t = 0 with a velocity 10 ms<sup>–1</sup>\n at an angle of 60<sup>o</sup> with the horizontal. The radius of curvature of its trajectory at t = 1s is R. neglecting air resistance and taking acceleration due to gravity g = 10 ms<sup>–2</sup>, the value of R is : ",
    "options": [
      "2.8 m",
      "5.1 m",
      "2.5 m",
      "10.3 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "2.8 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "SB95hGshHFXpQ73VH97k9k2k5gxsc7e",
    "question": "A particle of mass m is fixed to one end of a\nlight spring having force constant k and\nunstretched length $$\\ell $$. The other end is fixed. The\nsystem is given an angular speed $$\\omega $$ about the\nfixed end of the spring such that it rotates in a\ncircle in gravity free space. Then the stretch in\nthe spring is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{m\\ell {\\omega ^2}} \\over {k - m{\\omega ^2}}}$$",
      "$${{m\\ell {\\omega ^2}} \\over {k - m{\\omega}}}$$",
      "$${{m\\ell {\\omega ^2}} \\over {k + m{\\omega ^2}}}$$",
      "$${{m\\ell {\\omega ^2}} \\over {k + m{\\omega}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$${{m\\ell {\\omega ^2}} \\over {k - m{\\omega ^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "0sTInJTxtvGaHbK3TUjgy2xukfro4ykf",
    "question": "A clock has a continuously moving second's hand of 0.1 m length. The average acceleration of the\ntip of the hand (in units of ms<sup>–2</sup>) is of the order of :",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>-3</sup>",
      "10<sup>-1</sup>",
      "10<sup>-2</sup>",
      "10<sup>-4</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "10<sup>-3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "yeOAPlBsskllmodDsi1kltipn9x",
    "question": "A particle is moving with uniform speed along the circumference of a circle of radius R under the action of a central fictitious force F which is inversely proportional to R<sup>3</sup>. Its time period of revolution will be given by :",
    "options": [
      "$$T \\propto {R^{{4 \\over 3}}}$$",
      "$$T \\propto {R^{{5 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$$T \\propto {R^{{3 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$$T \\propto {R^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$$T \\propto {R^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "JTeCJURXbnCUArkIRP1kmhnrlv6",
    "question": "A block of 200 g mass moves with a uniform speed in a horizontal circular groove, with vertical side walls of radius 20 cm. If the block takes 40 s to complete one round, the normal force by the side walls of the groove is :",
    "options": [
      "9.859 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> N",
      "0.0314 N",
      "9.859 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> N",
      "6.28 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "9.859 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> N"
  },
  {
    "id": "EHIIk9UkGtVApYd4mN1kmiopld3",
    "question": "Statement I : A cyclist is moving on an unbanked road with a speed of 7 kmh<sup>$$-$$1</sup> and takes a sharp circular turn along a path of radius of 2m without reducing the speed. The static friction coefficient is 0.2. The cyclist will not slip and pass the curve. (g = 9.8 m/s<sup>2</sup>)<br/><br/>Statement II : If the road is banked at an angle of 45$$^\\circ$$, cyclist can cross the curve of 2m radius with the speed of 18.5 kmh<sup>$$-$$1</sup> without slipping.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect and statement II is correct",
      "Both statement I and statement II are true",
      "Statement I is correct and statement II is incorrect",
      "Both statement I and statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "Both statement I and statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "S5lZvUCZYGi9u6LbmG1krpljzgn",
    "question": "The normal reaction 'N' for a vehicle of 800 kg mass, negotiating a turn on a 30$$^\\circ$$ banked road at maximum possible speed without skidding is ____________ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> kg m/s<sup>2</sup>. [Given cos30$$^\\circ$$ = 0.87, $$\\mu$$<sub>s</sub> = 0.2]",
    "options": [
      "12.4",
      "7.2",
      "6.96",
      "10.2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "10.2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktbncda8",
    "question": "A particle of mass m is suspended from a ceiling through a string of length L. The particle moves in a horizontal circle of radius r such that $$r = {L \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$. The speed of particle will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\sqrt {rg} }$$",
      "$${\\sqrt {2rg} }$$",
      "$${2\\sqrt {rg} }$$",
      "$${\\sqrt {{{rg} \\over 2}} }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$${\\sqrt {rg} }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktdz96vv",
    "question": "A huge circular arc of length 4.4 ly subtends an angle '4s' at the centre of the circle. How long it would take for a body to complete 4 revolution if its speed is 8 AU per second?<br/><br/>Given : 1 ly = 9.46 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup> m<br/><br/>1 AU = 1.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>11</sup> m",
    "options": [
      "4.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> s",
      "4.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup> s",
      "3.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>6</sup> s",
      "7.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "4.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup> s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59lxvo1",
    "question": "<p>A disc with a flat small bottom beaker placed on it at a distance R from its center is revolving about an axis passing through the center and perpendicular to its plane with an angular velocity $$\\omega$$. The coefficient of static friction between the bottom of the beaker and the surface of the disc is $$\\mu$$. The beaker will revolve with the disc if :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$R \\le {{\\mu g} \\over {2{\\omega ^2}}}$$",
      "$$R \\le {{\\mu g} \\over {{\\omega ^2}}}$$",
      "$$R \\ge {{\\mu g} \\over {2{\\omega ^2}}}$$",
      "$$R \\ge {{\\mu g} \\over {{\\omega ^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$$R \\le {{\\mu g} \\over {{\\omega ^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59m92bx",
    "question": "<p>For a particle in uniform circular motion, the acceleration $$\\overrightarrow a $$ at any point P(R, $$\\theta$$) on the circular path of radius R is (when $$\\theta$$ is measured from the positive x-axis and v is uniform speed) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$ - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\sin \\theta \\widehat i + {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\cos \\theta \\widehat j$$",
      "$$ - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\cos \\theta \\widehat i + {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\sin \\theta \\widehat j$$",
      "$$ - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\cos \\theta \\widehat i - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\sin \\theta \\widehat j$$",
      "$$ - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\widehat i + {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\widehat j$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$$ - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\cos \\theta \\widehat i - {{{v^2}} \\over R}\\sin \\theta \\widehat j$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbi2oh",
    "question": "<p>A stone of mass m, tied to a string is being whirled in a vertical circle with a uniform speed. The tension in the string is</p>",
    "options": [
      "the same throughout the motion.",
      "minimum at the highest position of the circular path.",
      "minimum at the lowest position of the circular path.",
      "minimum when the rope is in the horizontal position. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "minimum at the highest position of the circular path."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbzc2e",
    "question": "<p>A fly wheel is accelerated uniformly from rest and rotates through 5 rad in the first second. The angle rotated by the fly wheel in the next second, will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "7.5 rad",
      "15 rad",
      "20 rad",
      "30 rad"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "15 rad"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c2yhy3",
    "question": "<p>A boy ties a stone of mass 100 g to the end of a 2 m long string and whirls it around in a horizontal plane. The string can withstand the maximum tension of 80 N. If the maximum speed with which the stone can revolve is $${K \\over \\pi }$$ rev./min. The value of K is :</p>\n<p>(Assume the string is massless and unstretchable)</p>",
    "options": [
      "400",
      "300",
      "600",
      "800"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "600"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo7c3jq",
    "question": "A stone of mass $1 \\mathrm{~kg}$ is tied to end of a massless string of length $1 \\mathrm{~m}$. If the breaking tension of the string is $400 \\mathrm{~N}$, then maximum linear velocity, the stone can have without breaking the string, while rotating in horizontal plane, is :",
    "options": [
      "$20 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$",
      "$40 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$",
      "$400 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$",
      "$10 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$20 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo7daud",
    "question": "A body is moving with constant speed, in a circle of radius $10 \\mathrm{~m}$. The body completes one revolution in $4 \\mathrm{~s}$. At the end of 3rd second, the displacement of body (in $\\mathrm{m}$ ) from its starting point is :",
    "options": [
      "$15 \\pi$",
      "30",
      "$10 \\sqrt{2}$",
      "$5 \\pi$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$10 \\sqrt{2}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsal8zn",
    "question": "<p>An object moves at a constant speed along a circular path in a horizontal plane with center at the origin. When the object is at $$x=+2~\\mathrm{m}$$, its velocity is $$\\mathrm{ - 4\\widehat j}$$ m/s. The object's velocity (v) and acceleration (a) at $$x=-2~\\mathrm{m}$$ will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$v=4\\mathrm{\\widehat i~m/s},a=8\\mathrm{\\widehat j~m/s^2}$$",
      "$$v=4\\mathrm{\\widehat j~m/s},a=8\\mathrm{\\widehat i~m/s^2}$$",
      "$$v=-4\\mathrm{\\widehat i~m/s},a=-8\\mathrm{\\widehat j~m/s^2}$$",
      "$$v=-4\\mathrm{\\widehat j~m/s},a=8\\mathrm{\\widehat i~m/s^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$$v=4\\mathrm{\\widehat j~m/s},a=8\\mathrm{\\widehat i~m/s^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsp8hcq",
    "question": "<p>A car is moving on a horizontal curved road with radius 50 m. The approximate maximum speed of car will be, if friction between tyres and road is 0.34. [take g = 10 ms$$^{-2}$$]</p>",
    "options": [
      "3.4 ms$$^{-1}$$",
      "13 ms$$^{-1}$$",
      "22.4 ms$$^{-1}$$",
      "17 ms$$^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "13 ms$$^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldui3641",
    "question": "<p>A car is moving with a constant speed of 20 m/s in a circular horizontal track of radius 40 m. A bob is suspended from the roof of the car by a massless string. The angle made by the string with the vertical will be : (Take g = 10 m/s$$^2$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{6}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\pi}{4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwrt6cw",
    "question": "<p>A body of mass 200g is tied to a spring of spring constant 12.5 N/m, while the other end of spring is fixed at point O. If the body moves about O in a circular path on a smooth horizontal surface with constant angular speed 5 rad/s. Then the ratio of extension in the spring to its natural length will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 2",
      "2 : 3",
      "2 : 5",
      "1 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "2 : 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgozv6yz",
    "question": "<p>A vehicle of mass $$200 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is moving along a levelled curved road of radius $$70 \\mathrm{~m}$$ with angular velocity of $$0.2 ~\\mathrm{rad} / \\mathrm{s}$$. The centripetal force acting on the vehicle is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$560 \\mathrm{~N}$$",
      "$$14 \\mathrm{~N}$$",
      "$$2800 \\mathrm{~N}$$",
      "$$2240 \\mathrm{~N}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$$560 \\mathrm{~N}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguxs3kl",
    "question": "<p>A coin placed on a rotating table just slips when it is placed at a distance of $$1 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ from the center. If the angular velocity of the table in halved, it will just slip when placed at a distance of _________ from the centre :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 cm",
      "8 cm",
      "4 cm",
      "2 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "4 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh247dhr",
    "question": "<p>A particle is moving with constant speed in a circular path. When the particle turns by an angle $$90^{\\circ}$$, the ratio of instantaneous velocity to its average velocity is $$\\pi: x \\sqrt{2}$$. The value of $$x$$ will be -</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "7",
      "5",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh24hwif",
    "question": "<p>A small block of mass $$100 \\mathrm{~g}$$ is tied to a spring of spring constant $$7.5 \\mathrm{~N} / \\mathrm{m}$$ and length $$20 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. The other end of spring is fixed at a particular point A. If the block moves in a circular path on a smooth horizontal surface with constant angular velocity $$5 ~\\mathrm{rad} / \\mathrm{s}$$ about point $$\\mathrm{A}$$, then tension in the spring is -</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.50 N",
      "1.5 N",
      "0.75 N",
      "0.25 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "0.75 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh30s344",
    "question": "<p>A child of mass $$5 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is going round a merry-go-round that makes 1 rotation in $$3.14 \\mathrm{~s}$$. The radius of the merry-go-round is $$2 \\mathrm{~m}$$. The centrifugal force on the child will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "50 N",
      "80 N",
      "100 N",
      "40 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "40 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbkstf7",
    "question": "A ball of mass $0.5 \\mathrm{~kg}$ is attached to a string of length $50 \\mathrm{~cm}$. The ball is rotated on a horizontal circular path about its vertical axis. The maximum tension that the string can bear is $400 \\mathrm{~N}$. The maximum possible value of angular velocity of the ball in $\\mathrm{rad} / \\mathrm{s}$ is, :",
    "options": [
      "1600",
      "20",
      "40",
      "1000"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "40"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbla2py",
    "question": "A particle moving in a circle of radius $\\mathrm{R}$ with uniform speed takes time $\\mathrm{T}$ to complete one revolution.<br/><br/>\nIf this particle is projected with the same speed at an angle $\\theta$ to the horizontal, the maximum height attained by it is equal to $4 R$. The angle of projection $\\theta$ is then given by :",
    "options": [
      "$\\sin ^{-1}\\left[\\frac{2 \\mathrm{gT}^2}{\\pi^2 \\mathrm{R}}\\right]^{\\frac{1}{2}}$",
      "$\\sin ^{-1}\\left[\\frac{\\pi^2 \\mathrm{R}}{2 \\mathrm{gT}^2}\\right]^{\\frac{1}{2}}$",
      "$\\cos ^{-1}\\left[\\frac{\\pi \\mathrm{R}}{2 \\mathrm{gT}^2}\\right]^{\\frac{1}{2}}$",
      "$\\cos ^{-1}\\left[\\frac{2 \\mathrm{gT}^2}{\\pi^2 \\mathrm{R}}\\right]^{\\frac{1}{2}}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$\\sin ^{-1}\\left[\\frac{2 \\mathrm{gT}^2}{\\pi^2 \\mathrm{R}}\\right]^{\\frac{1}{2}}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc35sf0",
    "question": "<p>A train is moving with a speed of $$12 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ on rails which are $$1.5 \\mathrm{~m}$$ apart. To negotiate a curve radius $$400 \\mathrm{~m}$$, the height by which the outer rail should be raised with respect to the inner rail is (Given, $$g=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2)$$ :</p>",
    "options": [
      "6.0 cm",
      "5.4 cm",
      "4.8 cm",
      "4.2 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "5.4 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse6hrcw",
    "question": "<p>A coin is placed on a disc. The coefficient of friction between the coin and the disc is $$\\mu$$. If the distance of the coin from the center of the disc is $$r$$, the maximum angular velocity which can be given to the disc, so that the coin does not slip away, is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{r}{\\mu g}}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{\\mu g}{r}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mu g}{r}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mu}{\\sqrt{r g}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{\\mu g}{r}}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1k2mp",
    "question": "<p>If the radius of curvature of the path of two particles of same mass are in the ratio $$3: 4$$, then in order to have constant centripetal force, their velocities will be in the ratio of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: \\sqrt{3}$$\n",
      "$$2: \\sqrt{3}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{3}: 2$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{3}: 1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{3}: 2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfln4re",
    "question": "<p>A stone of mass $$900 \\mathrm{~g}$$ is tied to a string and moved in a vertical circle of radius $$1 \\mathrm{~m}$$ making $$10 \\mathrm{~rpm}$$. The tension in the string, when the stone is at the lowest point is (if $$\\pi^2=9.8$$ and $$g=9.8 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$$) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "17.8 N",
      "97 N",
      "9.8 N",
      "8.82 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "9.8 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gsxza",
    "question": "<p>A clock has $$75 \\mathrm{~cm}, 60 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ long second hand and minute hand respectively. In 30 minutes duration the tip of second hand will travel $$x$$ distance more than the tip of minute hand. The value of $$x$$ in meter is nearly (Take $$\\pi=3.14$$) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "118.9",
      "140.5",
      "139.4",
      "220.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "139.4"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s20xk",
    "question": "<p>A man carrying a monkey on his shoulder does cycling smoothly on a circular track of radius $$9 \\mathrm{~m}$$ and completes 120 resolutions in 3 minutes. The magnitude of centripetal acceleration of monkey is (in $$\\mathrm{m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$$ ) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4 \\pi^2 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$\n",
      "$$16 \\pi^2 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$\n",
      "$$57600 \\pi^2 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$\n",
      "Zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "$$16 \\pi^2 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2955q",
    "question": "<p>A car of $$800 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is taking turn on a banked road of radius $$300 \\mathrm{~m}$$ and angle of banking $$30^{\\circ}$$. If coefficient of static friction is 0.2 then the maximum speed with which car can negotiate the turn safely: $$(\\mathrm{g}=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2, \\sqrt{3}=1.73)$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "51.4 m/s",
      "102.8 m/s",
      "70.4 m/s",
      "264 m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "circular-motion",
    "topic": "uniform-circular-motion",
    "solution": "51.4 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "sfLB2JRpKsBNbp75",
    "question": "Consider telecommunication through optical fibres. Which of the following statements is <b>not</b> true? ",
    "options": [
      "Optical fibres can be of graded refractive index",
      "Optical fibres are subject to electromagnetic interference from outside ",
      "Optical fibres have extremely low transmission loss ",
      "Optical fibres may have homogeneous core with a suitable cladding. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "Optical fibres are subject to electromagnetic interference from outside "
  },
  {
    "id": "wSTcKrPWSaJwXk7o",
    "question": "This question has Statement - $$1$$ and Statement - $$2$$. Of the four choices given after the statements, choose the one that best describes the two statements.\n<br/><b>Statement -$$1$$ :</b> Sky wave signals are used for long distance radio communication. These signals are in general, less stable then ground wave signals.\n<br/><b>Statement -$$2$$ :</b> The state of ionosphere varies from hour to hour, day to day and season to season. ",
    "options": [
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is the correct explanation of Statement - $$1$$.",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is not the correct explanation of Statement - $$1$$.",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is false, Statement - $$2$$ is true ",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is not the correct explanation of Statement - $$1$$."
  },
  {
    "id": "YJfS2N6BUi79xvE7",
    "question": "A radar has a power of $$1kW$$ and is operating at a frequency of $$10$$ $$GHz.$$ It is located on a mountain top of height $$500$$ $$m.$$ The maximum distance upto which it can detect object located on the surface of the earth (Radius of earth $$ = 6.4 \\times {10^6}m$$) is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$80$$ $$km$$ ",
      "$$16$$ $$km$$ ",
      "$$40$$ $$km$$ ",
      "$$64$$ $$km$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "$$80$$ $$km$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "UhPPnhFnvgkUJB08YfxUy",
    "question": "A signal is to be transmitted through a wave of wavelength $$\\lambda $$, using a linear antenna. The length l of the antenna and effective power radiated P<sub>eff</sub> will be given respectively as :\n<br/><br/>(K is a constant of proportionality)\n",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda $$, P<sub>eff</sub> = K $$\\left( {{1 \\over \\lambda }} \\right)$$<sup>2</sup>",
      "$${{\\lambda  \\over 8}}$$, P<sub>eff</sub> = K $$\\left( {{1 \\over \\lambda }} \\right)$$",
      "$${{\\lambda  \\over 16}}$$, P<sub>eff</sub> = K $$\\left( {{1 \\over \\lambda }} \\right)$$<sup>3</sup>",
      "$${{\\lambda  \\over 5}}$$, P<sub>eff</sub> = K $$\\left( {{1 \\over \\lambda }} \\right)$$$${\\left( {{1 \\over \\lambda }} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda $$, P<sub>eff</sub> = K $$\\left( {{1 \\over \\lambda }} \\right)$$<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "lbc1eczRhGSFNJG8",
    "question": "A telephonic communication service is working at carrier frequency of 10 GHz. Only 10% of it is utilized\nfor transmission. How many telephonic channels can be transmitted simultaneously if each channel\nrequires a bandwidth of 5 kHz ?",
    "options": [
      "2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>6</sup>",
      "2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup>",
      "2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>",
      "2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "XY5oHkFzD8cJbjpgdNRy3",
    "question": "In a communication system operating at wavelength 800 nm, only one percent of source frequency is available as signal bandwith. The number of channels accomodated for transmitting TV signals of band width 6 MHz are (Take velocity of light c = 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>8</sup>m/s, h = 6.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> J-s)",
    "options": [
      "3.75 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup>",
      "3.86 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup>",
      "6.25 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup>",
      "4.87 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "6.25 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "xWfKfyF8DZZhtEBdzWB9U",
    "question": "A TV transmission tower has a height of 140 m and the height of the receiving antenna is 40 m. What is the maximum distance upto which signals can be broadcasted from this tower is LOS (Line of Sight) mode ? (Given : radius of earth = 6.4 × 10<sup>6</sup> m). ",
    "options": [
      "40 km",
      "65 km",
      "48 km",
      "80 km"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "65 km"
  },
  {
    "id": "dLxH6Mvqz41KHVUUnF6VE",
    "question": "To double the covering range of a TV transmittion tower, its height should be multiplied by :",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "2",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "o9kDJjw1iiuS0Lc5957MG",
    "question": "The wavelength of the carrier waves in a\nmodern optical fiber communication network\nis close to :",
    "options": [
      "1500 nm",
      "2400 nm",
      "600 nm",
      "900 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "1500 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "AbyExxF0GdOnsWyadlFpp",
    "question": "In a line of sight radio communication, a\ndistance of about 50 km is kept between the\ntransmitting and receiving antennas. If the\nheight of the receiving antenna is 70m, then the\nminimum height of the transmitting antenna\nshould be :<br/>\n(Radius of the Earth = 6.4 × 10<sup>6</sup> m).",
    "options": [
      "40 m",
      "20 m",
      "51 m",
      "32 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "32 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "5xydr3OdDN6Ihpn7iIZCR",
    "question": "The physical sizes of the transmitter and\nreceiver antenna in a communication system\nare :-",
    "options": [
      "proportional to carrier frequency",
      "inversely proportional to carrier frequency",
      "inversely proportional to modulation\nfrequency",
      "independent of both carrier and modulation\nfrequency"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "inversely proportional to carrier frequency"
  },
  {
    "id": "JV5dotDpVil9I3VlYK18hoxe66ijvzttrrz",
    "question": "Given below in the the left column are different\nmodes of communication using the kinds of\nwaves given the right column.\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width: 100%}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-hgcj{font-weight:bold;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-s268{text-align:left}\n.tg .tg-xk68{font-weight:bold;color:#fe0000;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-hgcj\">A</th>\n<th class=\"tg-s268\">Optical Fibre<br/>communication</th>\n<th class=\"tg-xk68\">P</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\">Ultrasound</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-hgcj\">B</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s268\">Radar</td>\n<td class=\"tg-xk68\">Q</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Infrared Light</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-hgcj\">C</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s268\">Sonar</td>\n<td class=\"tg-xk68\">R</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Microwaves</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-hgcj\">D</td>\n<td class=\"tg-s268\">Mobile Phones</td>\n<td class=\"tg-xk68\">S</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Radio Waves</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "A-Q, B-S, C-R, D-P",
      "A-Q, B-S, C-P, D-R",
      "A-S, B-Q, C-R, D-P",
      "A-R, B-P, C-S, D-Q"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "A-Q, B-S, C-P, D-R"
  },
  {
    "id": "UvVPwu9BXBwe5poWCQ1kmhnbkz9",
    "question": "A 25 m long antenna is mounted on an antenna tower. The height of the antenna tower is 75 m. The wavelength (in meter) of the signal transmitted by this antenna would be :",
    "options": [
      "200",
      "400",
      "100",
      "300"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "100"
  },
  {
    "id": "cbu15v1cs1dnU7avgZ1kmior527",
    "question": "Two identical antennas mounted on identical towers are separated from each other by a distance of 45 km. What should nearly be the minimum height of receiving antenna to receive the signals in line of sight? (Assume radius of earth is 6400 km)",
    "options": [
      "158.2 m",
      "79.1 m",
      "19.77 m",
      "39.55 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "39.55 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "EsDEDVxBXUUytVfVJg1kmkqve23",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/>List - I<br/><br/>(a) 10 km height over earth's surface<br/><br/>(b) 70 km height over earth's surface<br/><br/>(c) 180 km height over earth's surface<br/><br/>(d) 270 km height over earth's surface<br/><br/>List - II<br/><br/>(i) Thermosphere<br/><br/>(ii) Mesosphere<br/><br/>(iii) Stratosphere<br/><br/>(iv) Troposphere",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iv), (c)-(iii), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(iii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsvs6g7",
    "question": "What should be the height of transmitting antenna and the population covered if the television telecast is to cover a radius of 150 km? The average population density around the tower is 2000/km<sup>2</sup> and the value of R<sub>e</sub> = 6.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>6</sup> m.",
    "options": [
      "Height = 1241 m<br><br>Population covered = 7 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>",
      "Height = 1731 m<br><br>Population covered = 1413 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>",
      "Height = 1800 m<br><br>Population covered = 1413 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup>",
      "Height = 1600 m<br><br>Population covered = 2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "Height = 1731 m<br><br>Population covered = 1413 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktbqwwqo",
    "question": "A transmitting antenna at top of a tower has a height of 50 m and the height of receiving antenna is 80 m. What is range of communication for Line of Sight (LoS) mode?<br/><br/>[use radius of earth = 6400 km]",
    "options": [
      "45.5 km",
      "80.2 km",
      "144.1 km",
      "57.28 km"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "57.28 km"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfluwou",
    "question": "An antenna is mounted on a 400 m tall building. What will be the wavelength of signal that can be radiated effectively by the transmission tower upto a range of 44 km?",
    "options": [
      "37.8 m",
      "605 m",
      "75.6 m",
      "302 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "605 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54v2pq2",
    "question": "<p>The TV transmission tower at a particular station has a height of 125 m. For doubling the coverage of its range, the height of the tower should be increased by</p>",
    "options": [
      "125 m",
      "250 m",
      "375 m",
      "500 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "375 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l569wd1g",
    "question": "<p>Match List-I with List-II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 577px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 43px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 277px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 205px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Television signal</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">03 KHz</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Radio signal</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">20 KHz</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">High Quality Music</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">02 MHz</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Human speech</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">06 MHz</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-I, B-II, C-IV, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56vkbk3",
    "question": "<p>We do not transmit low frequency signal to long distances because-</p>\n<p>(a) The size of the antenna should be comparable to signal wavelength which is unreal solution for a signal of longer wavelength.</p>\n<p>(b) Effective power radiated by a long wavelength baseband signal would be high.</p>\n<p>(c) We want to avoid mixing up signals transmitted by different transmitter simultaneously.</p>\n<p>(d) Low frequency signal can be sent to long distances by superimposing with a high frequency wave as well.</p>\n<p>Therefore, the most suitable option will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "All statements are true",
      "(a), (b) and (c) are true only",
      "(a), (c) and (d) are true only",
      "(b), (c) and (d) are true only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "(a), (c) and (d) are true only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5al1g80",
    "question": "<p>A signal of 100 THz frequency can be transmitted with maximum efficiency by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Coaxial cable",
      "Optical fibre",
      "Twisted pair of copper wires",
      "Water"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "Optical fibre"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jiocdy",
    "question": "<p>At a particular station, the TV transmission tower has a height of 100 m. To triple its coverage range, height of the tower should be increased to</p>",
    "options": [
      "200 m",
      "300 m",
      "600 m",
      "900 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "900 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldofb88n",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following frequencies does not belong to FM broadcast ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$106 ~\\mathrm{MHz}$$",
      "$$89 ~\\mathrm{MHz}$$",
      "$$64 ~\\mathrm{MHz}$$",
      "$$99 ~\\mathrm{MHz}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "$$64 ~\\mathrm{MHz}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldspsli2",
    "question": "<p>If the height of transmitting and receiving antennas are 80 m each, the maximum line of sight distance will be:</p>\n<p>Given : Earth's radius $$=6.4\\times10^6$$ m</p>",
    "options": [
      "28 km",
      "64 km",
      "32 km",
      "36 km"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "64 km"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtxrfri",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 607px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 263px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Troposphere</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Approximate 65-75 km over Earth's surface</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">E-Part of Stratosphere</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Approximate 300 km over Earth's surface</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">F$$_2$$-Part of Thermosphere</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Approximate 10 km over Earth's surface</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D-Part of Stratosphere</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Approximate 100 km over Earth's surface</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I",
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-I, B-IV, C-III, D-II",
      "A-I, B-II, C-IV, D-III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwqw52m",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 668px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 248px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List-I<br/></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List-II<br/></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">AM Broadcast</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">88-108 MHz</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">FM Broadcast</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">540-1600 kHz</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Television</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">3.7-4.2 GHz</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Satellite Communication</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">54MHz - 890MHz</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-I, B-III, C-II, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgny32wf",
    "question": "The height of transmitting antenna is $180 \\mathrm{~m}$ and the height of the receiving antenna is $245 \\mathrm{~m}$. The maximum distance between them for satisfactory communication in line of sight will be :<br/><br/>(given $\\mathrm{R}=6400 \\mathrm{~km})$",
    "options": [
      "$104 \\mathrm{~km}$",
      "$56 \\mathrm{~km}$",
      "$48 \\mathrm{~km}$",
      "$96 \\mathrm{~km}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "$104 \\mathrm{~km}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgoztiqi",
    "question": "<p>To radiate EM signal of wavelength $$\\lambda$$ with high efficiency, the antennas should have a minimum size equal to:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\lambda}{2}$$",
      "$$\\lambda$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\lambda}{4}$$",
      "$$2 \\lambda$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\lambda}{4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq18bgf",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 554px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 159px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 295px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List - I<br/>(Layer of atmosphere)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List - II<br/>(Approximate height over earth's surface)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{F_1}$$ - Layer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">10 km</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{D}$$ - Layer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">170 - 190 km</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Troposphere</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">100 km</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{E}$$ - Layer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">65 - 75 km</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A - II, B - IV, C - III, D - I",
      "A - II, B-I, C - IV, D - III",
      "A - II, B - IV, C - I, D - III",
      "A - III, B - IV, C - I, D - II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "A - II, B - IV, C - I, D - III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsx1izi",
    "question": "<p>In satellite communication, the uplink frequency band used is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3.7-4.2 \\mathrm{~GHz}$$",
      "$$5.925-6.425 \\mathrm{~GHz}$$",
      "$$76-88 \\mathrm{~MHz}$$",
      "$$420-890 \\mathrm{~MHz}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "$$5.925-6.425 \\mathrm{~GHz}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguy5qu6",
    "question": "<p>A transmitting antenna is kept on the surface of the earth. The minimum height of receiving antenna required to receive the signal in line of sight at $$4 \\mathrm{~km}$$ distance from it is $$x \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{~m}$$. The value of $$x$$ is __________.</p>\n<p>(Let, radius of earth $$\\mathrm{R}=6400 \\mathrm{~km}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.25",
      "125",
      "1250",
      "12.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "125"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqlpcj",
    "question": "<p>The power radiated from a linear antenna of length $$l$$ is proportional to</p>\n<p>(Given, $$\\lambda=$$ Wavelength of wave):</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left(\\frac{l}{\\lambda}\\right)^{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{l}{\\lambda^{2}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{l^{2}}{\\lambda}$$",
      "$$\\frac{l}{\\lambda}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "$$\\left(\\frac{l}{\\lambda}\\right)^{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh023yn3",
    "question": "<p>A TV transmitting antenna is $$98 \\mathrm{~m}$$ high and the receiving antenna is at the ground level. If the radius of the earth is $$6400 \\mathrm{~km}$$, the surface area covered by the transmitting antenna is approximately:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4868 \\mathrm{~km}^{2}$$",
      "$$1240 \\mathrm{~km}^{2}$$",
      "$$3942 \\mathrm{~km}^{2}$$",
      "$$1549 \\mathrm{~km}^{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "$$3942 \\mathrm{~km}^{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh24v2j5",
    "question": "<p>By what percentage will the transmission range of a TV tower be affected when the height of the tower is increased by $$21 \\%$$ ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "12%",
      "15%",
      "10%",
      "14%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "elements-of-communication-system-&-propagation-of-em-wave",
    "solution": "10%"
  },
  {
    "id": "xG2RNOrnUQUCyg2v",
    "question": "A signal of $$5$$ $$kHz$$ frequency is amplitude modulated on a carrier wave of frequency $$2$$ $$MHz.$$ The frequencies of the resultant signal is/are : ",
    "options": [
      "$$2005$$ $$kHz, 2000$$ $$kHz$$ and $$1995$$ $$kHz$$",
      "$$2000$$ $$kHz$$ and $$1995$$ $$kHz$$ ",
      "$$2$$ $$MHz$$ only ",
      "$$2005$$ $$kHz$$ and $$1995$$ $$kHz$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "$$2005$$ $$kHz, 2000$$ $$kHz$$ and $$1995$$ $$kHz$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "CO61bwbkzmBMahH6",
    "question": "Choose the correct statement : ",
    "options": [
      "In amplitude modulation the amplitude of the high frequency carrier wave is make to vary in proportion to the amplitude of the audio signal. ",
      "In amplitude modulation the frequency of the high frequency carrier wave is made to vary in proportion to the amplitude of the audio signal.",
      "In frequency modulation the amplitude of the high frequency carrier wave is made to vary in proportion to the amplitude of the audio  signal. ",
      "In frequency modulation the amplitude of the high frequency carrier wave is made to vary in proportion to the frequency of the audio signal."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "In amplitude modulation the amplitude of the high frequency carrier wave is make to vary in proportion to the amplitude of the audio signal. "
  },
  {
    "id": "V9gU7UPbeKWHlj8lDTRsz",
    "question": "A modulated signal C<sub>m</sub>(t) has the form C<sub>m</sub>(t) = 30 sin 300 $$\\pi $$t + 10 (cos 200 $$\\pi $$t −cos 400 $$\\pi $$t). The carrier frequency c, the modulating frequency (message frequency) f<sub>$$\\omega $$</sub>, and the modulation index $$\\mu $$ are respectively given by :",
    "options": [
      "f<sub>c</sub> = 200 Hz; f<sub>$$\\omega $$</sub> = 50 Hz; $$\\mu $$ = $${1 \\over 2}$$",
      "f<sub>c</sub> = 150 Hz; f<sub>$$\\omega $$</sub> = 50 Hz; $$\\mu $$ = $${2 \\over 3}$$  ",
      "f<sub>c</sub> = 150 Hz; f<sub>$$\\omega $$</sub> = 30 Hz; $$\\mu $$ = $${1 \\over 3}$$",
      "f<sub>c</sub> = 200 Hz; f<sub>$$\\omega $$</sub> = 30 Hz; $$\\mu $$ = $${1 \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "f<sub>c</sub> = 150 Hz; f<sub>$$\\omega $$</sub> = 50 Hz; $$\\mu $$ = $${2 \\over 3}$$  "
  },
  {
    "id": "11D8X5Nnuug2dQM4CjUKT",
    "question": "An audio signal consists of two distinct sounds : one a human speech signal in the frequency band of 200 Hz to 2700 Hz, while the other is a high frequency music signal in the frequency band of 10200 Hz to 15200 Hz. The ratio of the AM signal bandwidth required to send both the signals together to the AM signal bandwidth required to send just the human speech is :",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "5",
      "6",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "6"
  },
  {
    "id": "Z1o1XZ0inG8g4ug4ExWzq",
    "question": "A signal of frequency 20 kHz and peak voltage of 5 Volt is used to modulate a carrier wave of frequency 1.2 MHz and peak voltage 25 Volts. Choose the correct statement.",
    "options": [
      "Modulation index = 5, side frequency bands are at 1400 kHz and 1000 kHz",
      "Modulation index = 5, side frequency bands are at 21.2 kHz and 18.8 kHz\n",
      "Modulation index = 0.8, side frequency bands are at 1180 kHz and 1220 kHz",
      "Modulation index = 0.2, side frequency bands are at 1220 kHz and 1180 kHz\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "Modulation index = 0.2, side frequency bands are at 1220 kHz and 1180 kHz\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "QjJAfqj6WY7YnolI",
    "question": "In amplitude modulation, sinusoidal carrier frequency used is denoted by $${\\omega _c}$$ and the signal frequency is\ndenoted by $${\\omega _m}$$. The bandwidth ($$\\Delta {\\omega _m}$$) of the signal is such that $$\\Delta {\\omega _m}$$ &lt; &lt; $$\\omega _c$$. Which of the following frequencies is not contained in the modulated wave?",
    "options": [
      "$${\\omega _m}$$",
      "$${\\omega _c}$$ ",
      "$${\\omega _m}$$ + $${\\omega _c}$$",
      "$${\\omega _c}$$ - $${\\omega _m}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "$${\\omega _m}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "qSPuzFWLll3PAk0IKi4ns",
    "question": "A carrier wave of peak voltage 14 V is used for transmitting a message signal. The peak voltage of modulating signal given to achieve a modulation index  of 80% will be : ",
    "options": [
      "7 V",
      "28 V",
      "11.2 V",
      "22.4 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "11.2 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "Si5UroIW6vHo2aUr5JFxv",
    "question": "The number of amplitude modulted broadcast stations that can be accomodated in a $$300$$ $$kHz$$ band width for the highest modulating frequency $$15$$ $$kHz$$ will be : ",
    "options": [
      "$$20$$",
      "$$15$$ ",
      "$$10$$ ",
      "$$8$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "$$10$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "knx0rfvNUZ6NWBgsaaEJw",
    "question": "The carrier frequency of a transmitter is provided by a tank circuit of a coil of inductance 49 $$\\mu $$H and a capacitance of 2.5 nF. It is modulated by an audio signal of $$12$$ $$kHz.$$ The frequency range occupied by the side bands is : ",
    "options": [
      "13482 kHz $$-$$ 13494 kHz",
      "442 kHz $$-$$ 466 kHz",
      "63 kHz $$-$$ 75 kHz",
      "18 kHz $$-$$ 30 kHz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "442 kHz $$-$$ 466 kHz"
  },
  {
    "id": "tZkq2UIc2P8evijYkrIEo",
    "question": "The modulation frequency of an AM radio station is 250 kHz, which is 10% of the carrier wave. If another AM station approaches you for license what broadcast frequency will you allot ?",
    "options": [
      "2900 kHz",
      "2750 kHz",
      "2250 kHz",
      "2000 kz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "2000 kz"
  },
  {
    "id": "X5uluzuvgznLaRyL8OTF8",
    "question": "An amplitude modulated signal is given by V(t) = 10[1 + 0.3cos(2.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup>\nt)] sin(5.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup>\nt). Here t is in\nseconds. The sideband frequencies (in kHz) are, [Given $$\\pi $$ = 22/7]\n",
    "options": [
      "892.5 and 857.5",
      "89.25 and 85.75",
      "1785 and 1715",
      "178.5 and 171.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "89.25 and 85.75"
  },
  {
    "id": "EcjLKq094KTSGZyr2M7rP",
    "question": "A 100 V carrier wave is made to vary between 160 V and 40 V by a modulating signal. What is the modulation index ? \n",
    "options": [
      "0.5 ",
      "0.6",
      "0.4",
      "0.3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "0.6"
  },
  {
    "id": "nmzSejiMMpSYBUCfgarGT",
    "question": "A signal Acoswt is transmitted using v<sub>0</sub> sin $$\\omega $$<sub>0</sub>t\nas carrier wave. The correct amplitude\nmodulated (AM) signal is",
    "options": [
      "v<sub>0</sub>  sin $$\\omega $$<sub>0</sub>t + Acos$$\\omega $$t",
      "(v<sub>0</sub> + A)cos$$\\omega $$t sin$$\\omega $$<sub>0</sub> t",
      "v<sub>0</sub> sin[$$\\omega $$<sub>0</sub> (1+ 0.01Asin$$\\omega $$t)t]",
      "$${v_0}\\sin {\\omega _0}t + {{\\rm A} \\over 2}\\sin ({\\omega _0} - \\omega )t + {A \\over 2}\\sin ({\\omega _0} + \\omega )t$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "$${v_0}\\sin {\\omega _0}t + {{\\rm A} \\over 2}\\sin ({\\omega _0} - \\omega )t + {A \\over 2}\\sin ({\\omega _0} + \\omega )t$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "n3lKE5A9wcQJ2cCTAp18hoxe66ijvzsvb6g",
    "question": "A message signal of frequency 100 MHz and\npeak voltage 100 V is used to execute\namplitude modulation on a carrier wave of\nfrequency 300 GHz and peak voltage 400 V.\nThe modulation index and difference between\nthe two side band frequencies are :",
    "options": [
      "0.25; 1 × 10<sup>8</sup> Hz",
      "4; 2 × 10<sup>8</sup> Hz",
      "4; 1 × 10<sup>8</sup> Hz",
      "0.25; 2 × 10<sup>8</sup> Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "0.25; 2 × 10<sup>8</sup> Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "bmWBmlwB381aUWfKNg3rsa0w2w9jx7efdda",
    "question": "In an amplitude modulator circuit, the carrier wave is given by, C(t) = 4 sin(20000 $$\\pi $$t) while modulating signal\nis given by, m(t) = 2 sin (2000 $$\\pi $$t). The values of modulation index and lower side band frequency are :",
    "options": [
      "0.3 and 9 kHz",
      "0.5 and 10 kHz",
      "0.4 and 10 kHz",
      "0.5 and 9 kHz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "0.5 and 9 kHz"
  },
  {
    "id": "zZVQAsn00aRVZjQ74Hjgy2xukeuu8boy",
    "question": "An amplitude modulated wave is represented\nby the expression<br/> v<sub>m</sub> = 5(1 + 0.6 cos 6280t)\nsin(211 × 10<sup>4</sup> t) volts\n<br/>The minimum and maximum amplitudes of the\namplitude modulated wave are, respectively",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$ V, 5 V",
      "$${5 \\over 2}$$ V, 8 V",
      "5 V, 8 V",
      "3 V, 5 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "$${5 \\over 2}$$ V, 8 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "oqikjGn7NvOIuvVumf1klry50o4",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : A speech signal of 2 kHz is used to modulate a carrier signal of 1 MHz. The bandwidth requirement for the signal is 4 kHz.<br/><br/>Statement II : The side band frequencies are 1002 kHz and 998 kHz.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "o0MUdF2K79pGVog0oH1klt1tdi7",
    "question": "If a message signal of frequency 'f<sub>m</sub>' is amplitude modulated with a carrier signal of frequency 'f<sub>c</sub>' and radiated through an antenna, the wavelength of the corresponding signal in air is :",
    "options": [
      "$${c \\over {{f_c} + {f_m}}}$$",
      "$${c \\over {{f_c}}}$$",
      "$${c \\over {{f_c} - {f_m}}}$$",
      "$${c \\over {{f_m}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "$${c \\over {{f_c}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "iLEYTwRISqPWd0Iw6y1kmk825wo",
    "question": "A carrier signal C(t) = 25 sin(2.512 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup>t) is amplitude modulated by a message signal m(t) = 5 sin(1.57 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup>t) and transmitted through an antenna. What will be the bandwidth of the modulated signal?",
    "options": [
      "50 MHz",
      "8 GHz",
      "1987.5 MHz",
      "2.01 GHz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "50 MHz"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krum7riw",
    "question": "In amplitude modulation, the message signal<br/><br/>V<sub>m</sub>(t) = 10 sin (2$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>t) volts and <br/><br/>Carrier signal<br/><br/>V<sub>C</sub>(t) = 20 sin(2$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> t) volts<br/><br/>The modulated signal now contains the message signal with lower side band and upper side band frequency, therefore the bandwidth of modulated signal is $$\\alpha$$ kHz. The value of $$\\alpha$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "200 kHz",
      "50 kHz",
      "100 kHz ",
      "0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "200 kHz"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l547tivn",
    "question": "<p>Only 2% of the optical source frequency is the available channel bandwidth for an optical communicating system operating at 1000 nm. If an audio signal requires a bandwidth of 8 kHz, how many channels can be accommodated for transmission :</p>",
    "options": [
      "375 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup>",
      "75 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup>",
      "375 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup>",
      "75 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "75 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55lokh4",
    "question": "<p>Amplitude modulated wave is represented by $${V_{AM}} = 10\\,[1 + 0.4\\cos (2\\pi  \\times {10^4}t)]\\cos (2\\pi  \\times {10^7}t)$$. The total bandwidth of the amplitude modulated wave is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "10 kHz",
      "20 MHz",
      "20 kHz",
      "10 MHz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "20 kHz"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58ccjy6",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct statement for amplitude modulation :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Amplitude of modulating signal is varied in accordance  with the information signal.",
      "Amplitude of modulated signal is varied in accordance  with the information signal.",
      "Amplitude of carrier signal is varied in accordance  with the information signal.",
      "Amplitude of modulated signal is varied in accordance  with the modulating signal."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "Amplitude of carrier signal is varied in accordance  with the information signal."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58ibixt",
    "question": "<p>A sinusoidal wave y(t) = 40sin(10 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>6</sup> $$\\pi$$t) is amplitude modulated by another sinusoidal wave x(t) = 20sin (1000 $$\\pi$$t). The amplitude of minimum frequency component of modulated signal is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.5",
      "0.25",
      "20",
      "10"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "10"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59pmled",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 629px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 62px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 251px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 80px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 236px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0lax\">List -II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Facsimile</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Static Document Image</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Guided media Channel</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Local Broadcast Radio</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Frequency Modulation</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Rectangular wave</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Digital Signal</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Optical Fiber</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the following options:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-I, B-IV, C-II, D-III",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-III, D-I",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "A-I, B-IV, C-II, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c457ob",
    "question": "<p>A baseband signal of 3.5 MHz frequency is modulated with a carrier signal of 3.5 GHz frequency using amplitude modulation method. What should be the minimum size of antenna required to transmit the modulated signal?</p>",
    "options": [
      "42.8 m",
      "42.8 mm",
      "21.4 mm",
      "21.4 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "21.4 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w379rv",
    "question": "<p>A speech signal given by 11 sin(2200 $$\\pi$$t) V is used for amplitude modulation with a carrier signal given by 44 sin(6600 $$\\pi$$t) V. The minimum amplitude of modulated wave will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "33 V",
      "55 V",
      "8.25 V",
      "13.75 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "33 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f478rh",
    "question": "<p>In AM modulation, a signal is modulated on a carrier wave such that maximum and minimum amplitudes are found to be 6 V and 2 V respectively. The modulation index is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "100%",
      "80%",
      "60%",
      "50%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "50%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gjwbo3",
    "question": "<p>A radio can tune to any station in $$6 \\,\\mathrm{MHz}$$ to $$10 \\,\\mathrm{MHz}$$ band. The value of corresponding wavelength bandwidth will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 m",
      "20 m",
      "30 m",
      "50 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "20 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i0vaz7",
    "question": "<p>The maximum and minimum voltage of an amplitude modulated signal are $$60 \\mathrm{~V}$$ and $$20 \\mathrm{~V}$$ respectively. The percentage modulation index will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.5%",
      "50%",
      "2%",
      "30%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "50%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mb111e",
    "question": "<p>In the case of amplitude modulation to avoid distortion the modulation index $$(\\mu)$$ should be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mu \\leq 1$$",
      "$$\\mu \\geq 1$$",
      "$$\\mu = 2$$",
      "$$\\mu = 0$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "$$\\mu \\leq 1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nt20q5",
    "question": "<p>A FM Broadcast transmitter, using modulating signal of frequency 20 kHz has a deviation ratio of 10. The Bandwidth required for transmission is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "220 kHz",
      "180 kHz",
      "360 kHz",
      "440 khz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "440 khz"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p5hrin",
    "question": "<p>Find the modulation index of an AM wave having $$8 \\mathrm{~V}$$ variation where maximum amplitude of the AM wave is $$9 \\mathrm{~V}$$.</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.8",
      "0.5",
      "0.2",
      "0.1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "0.8"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnvuri2",
    "question": "<p>In an amplitude modulation, a modulating signal having amplitude of X Volt is superimposed with a carrier signal of amplitude Y Volt in first case. Then, in second case, the same modulating signal is superimposed with different carrier signal of amplitude 2Y Volt. The ratio of modulation index in the two cases respectively will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 1",
      "4 : 1",
      "1 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo6rhnb",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p><b>Statement I : </b>For transmitting a signal, size of antenna ( $l$ ) should be comparable to wavelength of signal (at least $l=\\frac{\\lambda}{4}$ in dimension)</p>\n<p><b>Statement II:</b> In amplitude modulation, amplitude of carrier wave remains constant (unchanged).</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      " Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": " Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpk6s1h",
    "question": "<p>The amplitude of $$15 \\sin (1000 \\pi \\mathrm{t})$$ is modulated by $$10 \\sin (4 \\pi \\mathrm{t})$$ signal. The amplitude modulated signal contains frequency (ies) of</p>\n<p>A. $$500 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$</p>\n<p>B. $$2 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$</p>\n<p>C. $$250 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$</p>\n<p>D. $$498 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$</p>\n<p>E. $$502 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "B only",
      "A only",
      "A, D and E only",
      "A and B only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "A, D and E only"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqv6hr5",
    "question": "Match List <b>I</b> with List <b>II</b>:\n<br/><br/>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"><b>List I</b></th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"><b>List II</b></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A. Attenuation</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I. Combination of a receiver and transmitter.</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B. Transducer</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II. process of retrieval of information from the carrier wave at receiver</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C. Demodulation</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III. converts one form of energy into another</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D. quad Repeater</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV. Loss of strength of a signal while propagating through a medium.</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr1iwim",
    "question": "<p>A sinusoidal carrier voltage is amplitude modulated. The resultant amplitude modulated wave has maximum and minimum amplitude of $$120 \\mathrm{~V}$$ and $$80 \\mathrm{~V}$$ respectively. The amplitude of each sideband is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "15 V",
      "20 V",
      "5 V",
      "10 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "10 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsa0gr4",
    "question": "<p>The modulation index for an A.M. wave having maximum and minimum peak-to-peak voltages of 14 mV and 6 mV respectively is-</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.4",
      "0.6",
      "1.4",
      "0.2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "0.4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduhnwsf",
    "question": "<p>A message signal of frequency 5 kHz is used to modulate a carrier signal of frequency 2 MHz. The bandwidth for amplitude modulation is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "10 kHz",
      "2.5 kHz",
      "20 kHz",
      "5 kHz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "10 kHz"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrjjauf",
    "question": "<p>The amplitude of $$15 \\sin (1000 \\pi \\mathrm{t})$$ is modulated by $$10 \\sin (4 \\pi \\mathrm{t})$$ signal. The amplitude modulated signal contains frequencies of</p>\n<p>A. $$500 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$</p>\n<p>B. $$2 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$</p>\n<p>C. $$250 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$</p>\n<p>D. $$498 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$</p>\n<p>E. $$502 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and C only",
      "A and B only",
      "A and D only",
      "A, D and E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "A, D and E only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvs231a",
    "question": "<p>A message signal of frequency $$3 ~\\mathrm{kHz}$$ is used to modulate a carrier signal of frequency $$1.5 ~\\mathrm{MHz}$$. The bandwidth of the amplitude modulated wave is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$6 ~\\mathrm{MHz}$$",
      "$$6 ~\\mathrm{kHz}$$",
      "$$3 ~\\mathrm{MHz}$$",
      "$$3 ~\\mathrm{kHz}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "$$6 ~\\mathrm{kHz}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgxwv754",
    "question": "<p>A carrier wave of amplitude 15 V is modulated by a sinusoidal base band signal of magnitude 3 V. The ratio of maximum amplitude to minimum amplitude in an amplitude modulated wave is</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "5",
      "2",
      "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh30tspu",
    "question": "<p>For an amplitude modulated wave the minimum amplitude is $$3 \\mathrm{~V}$$, while the modulation index is $$60 \\%$$. The maximum amplitude of the modulated wave is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "5 V",
      "12 V",
      "10 V",
      "15 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "communication-systems",
    "topic": "modulation-&-demodulation",
    "solution": "12 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "cYZfAZLyahGGq6g75aFU1",
    "question": "A 200 $$\\Omega $$  resistor has a certain color code. If one\nreplaces the red color by green in the code, the\nnew resistance will be :",
    "options": [
      "500 $$\\Omega $$",
      "100 $$\\Omega $$",
      "200 $$\\Omega $$",
      "300 $$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "color-coding-of-resistance",
    "solution": "500 $$\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Wr8HjdC3se066k06",
    "question": "The resistance of the series combination of two resistances is $$S.$$ When they are jointed in parallel the total resistance is $$P.$$ If $$S = nP$$ then the Minimum possible value of $$n$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$2$$ ",
      "$$3$$ ",
      "$$4$$ ",
      "$$1$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "combination-of-resistances",
    "solution": "$$4$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "hYGjyeHl2OTqO98KEbvkk",
    "question": "A uniform metallic wire has a resistance of 18 $$\\Omega $$ and is bent into an equilateral triangle. Then, the resistance between any two vertices of the triangle is -\n",
    "options": [
      "12 $$\\Omega $$",
      "2 $$\\Omega $$",
      "4 $$\\Omega $$",
      "8 $$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "combination-of-resistances",
    "solution": "4 $$\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktaey9sd",
    "question": "What equal length of an iron wire and a copper-nickel alloy wire, each of 2 mm diameter connected parallel to give an equivalent resistance of 3$$\\Omega$$ ?<br/><br/>(Given resistivities of iron and copper-nickel alloy wire are 12 $$\\mu$$$$\\Omega$$ and 51 $$\\mu$$$$\\Omega$$ cm respectively)",
    "options": [
      "82 m",
      "97 m",
      "110 m",
      "90 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "combination-of-resistances",
    "solution": "97 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktbo0umg",
    "question": "If you are provided a set of resistances 2$$\\Omega$$, 4$$\\Omega$$, 6$$\\Omega$$ and 8$$\\Omega$$. Connect these resistances so as to obtain an equivalent resistance of $${{46} \\over 3}$$$$\\Omega$$.",
    "options": [
      "4$$\\Omega$$ and 6$$\\Omega$$ are in parallel with 2$$\\Omega$$ and 8$$\\Omega$$ in series",
      "6$$\\Omega$$ and 8$$\\Omega$$ are in parallel with 2$$\\Omega$$ and 4$$\\Omega$$ in series",
      "2$$\\Omega$$ and 6$$\\Omega$$ are in parallel with 4$$\\Omega$$ and 8$$\\Omega$$ in series",
      "2$$\\Omega$$ and 4$$\\Omega$$ are in parallel with 6$$\\Omega$$ and 8$$\\Omega$$ in series"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "combination-of-resistances",
    "solution": "2$$\\Omega$$ and 4$$\\Omega$$ are in parallel with 6$$\\Omega$$ and 8$$\\Omega$$ in series"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kte6mrk0",
    "question": "Five identical cells each of internal resistance 1$$\\Omega$$ and emf 5V are connected in series and in parallel with an external resistance 'R'. For what value of 'R', current in series and parallel combination will remain the same?",
    "options": [
      "1 $$\\Omega$$",
      "25 $$\\Omega$$ ",
      "5 $$\\Omega$$",
      "10 $$\\Omega$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "combination-of-resistances",
    "solution": "1 $$\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktmoalrp",
    "question": "Two resistors R<sub>1</sub> = (4 $$\\pm$$ 0.8) $$\\Omega$$ and R<sub>2</sub> = (4 $$\\pm$$ 0.4) $$\\Omega$$ are connected in parallel. The equivalent resistance of their parallel combination will be :",
    "options": [
      "(4 $$\\pm$$ 0.4) $$\\Omega$$",
      "(2 $$\\pm$$ 0.4) $$\\Omega$$",
      "(2 $$\\pm$$ 0.3) $$\\Omega$$",
      "(4 $$\\pm$$ 0.3) $$\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "combination-of-resistances",
    "solution": "(2 $$\\pm$$ 0.3) $$\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbp882",
    "question": "<p>What will be the most suitable combination of three resistors A = 2$$\\Omega$$, B = 4$$\\Omega$$, C = 6$$\\Omega$$ so that $$\\left( {{{22} \\over 3}} \\right)$$$$\\Omega$$ is equivalent resistance of combination?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Parallel combination of A and C connected in series with B.",
      "Parallel combination of A and B connected in series with C.",
      "Series combination of A and C connected in parallel with B.",
      "Series combination of B and C connected in parallel with A."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "combination-of-resistances",
    "solution": "Parallel combination of A and B connected in series with C."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w2z0ak",
    "question": "<p>An electric cable of copper has just one wire of radius 9 mm. Its resistance is 14 $$\\Omega$$. If this single copper wire of the cable is replaced by seven identical well insulated copper wires each of radius 3 mm connected in parallel, then the new resistance of the combination will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "9 $$\\Omega$$",
      "18 $$\\Omega$$",
      "28 $$\\Omega$$",
      "126 $$\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "combination-of-resistances",
    "solution": "18 $$\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnw6r4n",
    "question": "<p>Equivalent resistance between the adjacent corners of a regular n-sided polygon of uniform wire of resistance R would be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{(\\mathrm{n}-1) \\mathrm{R}}{\\mathrm{n}^{2}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{n^{2} R}{n-1}$$",
      "$$\\frac{(n-1) R}{(2 n-1)}$$",
      "$$\\frac{(n-1) R}{n}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "combination-of-resistances",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{(\\mathrm{n}-1) \\mathrm{R}}{\\mathrm{n}^{2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnyljm0",
    "question": "Given below are two statements:\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement I</b> : The equivalent resistance of resistors in a series combination is smaller than least resistance used in the combination.\n<br/><br/>\n<b>Statement II</b> : The resistivity of the material is independent of temperature.\n<br/><br/>\nIn the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "combination-of-resistances",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3x2ws",
    "question": "<p>A wire of resistance $$\\mathrm{R}$$ and length $$\\mathrm{L}$$ is cut into 5 equal parts. If these parts are joined parallely, then resultant resistance will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{25} \\mathrm{R}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{5} R$$",
      "25 R",
      "5 R"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "combination-of-resistances",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{25} \\mathrm{R}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "gGJqUVwUc1dlDP3s",
    "question": "The mass of product liberated on anode in an electrochemical cell depends on  (where $$t$$ is the time period for which the current is passed). ",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left( {It} \\right)^{1/2}}$$",
      "$$It$$ ",
      "$$I/t$$ ",
      "$${I^2}t$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-cell-or-battery-and-combination-of-batteries",
    "solution": "$$It$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "OC1Wl3iCwlWoYzF3",
    "question": "The nagative $$Zn$$ pole of a Daniell cell, sending a constant current through a circuit, decreases in mass by $$0.13g$$ in $$30$$ minutes. If the electrochemical equivalent of $$Zn$$ and $$Cu$$ are $$32.5$$ and $$31.5$$ respectively, the increase in the mass of the positive $$Cu$$ pole in this time is ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.180$$ $$g$$ ",
      "$$0.141$$ $$g$$ ",
      "$$0.126$$ $$g$$ ",
      "$$0.242$$ $$g$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-cell-or-battery-and-combination-of-batteries",
    "solution": "$$0.126$$ $$g$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54vh8us",
    "question": "<p>The combination of two identical cells, whether connected in series or parallel combination provides the same current through an external resistance of 2$$\\Omega$$. The value of internal resistance of each cell is</p>",
    "options": [
      "2$$\\Omega$$",
      "4$$\\Omega$$",
      "6$$\\Omega$$",
      "8$$\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-cell-or-battery-and-combination-of-batteries",
    "solution": "2$$\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59mc468",
    "question": "<p>Two cells of same emf but different internal resistances r<sub>1</sub> and r<sub>2</sub> are connected in series with a resistance R. The value of resistance R, for which the potential difference across second cell is zero, is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "r<sub>2</sub> $$-$$ r<sub>1</sub>",
      "r<sub>1</sub> $$-$$ r<sub>2</sub>",
      "r<sub>1</sub>",
      "r<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-cell-or-battery-and-combination-of-batteries",
    "solution": "r<sub>2</sub> $$-$$ r<sub>1</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6ji1tti",
    "question": "<p>Two sources of equal emfs are connected in series. This combination is connected to an external resistance R. The internal resistances of the two sources are $$r_{1}$$ and $$r_{2}$$ $$\\left(r_{1}&gt;r_{2}\\right)$$. If the potential difference across the source of internal resistance $$r_{1}$$ is zero, then the value of R will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$r_{1}-r_{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{r_{1} r_{2}}{r_{1}+r_{2}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{r_{1}+r_{2}}{2}$$",
      "$$r_{2}-r_{1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-cell-or-battery-and-combination-of-batteries",
    "solution": "$$r_{1}-r_{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "gOyCKb1pbFGV1tyk",
    "question": "A thermocouple is made from two metals, Antimony and Bismuth. If one junction of the couple is kept hot and the other is kept cold, then, an electric current will ",
    "options": [
      "flow from Antimony to Bismuth at the hot junction ",
      "flow from Bismuth to Antimony at the cold junction ",
      "now flow through the thermocouple ",
      "flow from Antimony to Bismuth at the cold junction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-current,-current-density-and-drift-velocity",
    "solution": "flow from Antimony to Bismuth at the cold junction"
  },
  {
    "id": "0pfaa66idpGct060y36tc",
    "question": "A copper rod of cross-sectional area A carries a uniform current I through it. At temperature T, if the volume charge density of the rod is $$\\rho $$,  how long will the changes take to travel a distance d ? ",
    "options": [
      "$${{2\\rho \\,d\\,A} \\over {\\rm I}}$$",
      "$${{2\\rho \\,d\\,A} \\over {{\\rm I}\\,T}}$$",
      "$${{\\rho \\,d\\,A} \\over {{\\rm I}\\,}}$$",
      "$${{\\rho \\,d\\,A} \\over {{\\rm I}\\,T}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-current,-current-density-and-drift-velocity",
    "solution": "$${{\\rho \\,d\\,A} \\over {{\\rm I}\\,}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "KFdEQ3srMBl8wIzd3GdEJ",
    "question": "Drift speed of electrons, when 1.5 A of current flows in a copper wire of cross section 5 mm<sup>2</sup>, is $$\\upsilon $$. If the electron density in copper is 9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>28</sup>/m<sup>3</sup> the value of $$\\upsilon $$. in mm/s is close to (Take charge of electron to be = 1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$19</sup>C)",
    "options": [
      "0.02",
      "3",
      "2",
      "0.2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-current,-current-density-and-drift-velocity",
    "solution": "0.02"
  },
  {
    "id": "lP6alCHw21SjYHWeAl1klrh1w76",
    "question": "A current through a wire depends on time as <br/><br/>i = $$\\alpha$$<sub>0</sub>t + $$\\beta$$t<sup>2</sup><br/><br/>where $$\\alpha$$<sub>0</sub> = 20 A/s and $$\\beta$$ = 8 As<sup>$$-$$2</sup>. Find the charge crossed through a section of the wire in 15 s.",
    "options": [
      "2250 C",
      "2100 C",
      "260 C",
      "11250 C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-current,-current-density-and-drift-velocity",
    "solution": "11250 C"
  },
  {
    "id": "80wYG2HdaixLuTwhLh1kmj3riu6",
    "question": "A current of 10A exists in a wire of cross-sectional area of 5 mm<sup>2</sup> with a drift velocity of 2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. The number of free electrons in each cubic meter of the wire is ___________.",
    "options": [
      "625 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>25</sup>",
      "1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>23</sup>",
      "2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>25</sup>",
      "2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>6</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-current,-current-density-and-drift-velocity",
    "solution": "625 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>25</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "xpWIIvBgrgxysqhEjq1krpli03n",
    "question": "A current of 5 A is passing through a non-linear magnesium wire of cross-section 0.04 m<sup>2</sup>. At every point the direction of current density is at an angle of 60$$^\\circ$$ with the unit vector of area of cross-section. The magnitude of electric field at every point of the conductor is :<br/><br/>(Resistivity of magnesium $$\\rho$$ = 44 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> $$\\Omega$$m)",
    "options": [
      "11 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> V/m",
      "11 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> V/m",
      "11 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> V/m",
      "11 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> V/m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-current,-current-density-and-drift-velocity",
    "solution": "11 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> V/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dxt71y",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following physical quantities have the same dimensions?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Electric displacement $$(\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{D}})$$ and surface charge density",
      "Displacement current and electric field",
      "Current density and surface charge density",
      "Electric potential and energy"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-current,-current-density-and-drift-velocity",
    "solution": "Electric displacement $$(\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{D}})$$ and surface charge density"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kn6rwa",
    "question": "<p>(A) The drift velocity of electrons decreases with the increase in the temperature of conductor.</p>\n<p>(B) The drift velocity is inversely proportional to the area of cross-section of given conductor.</p>\n<p>(C) The drift velocity does not depend on the applied potential difference to the conductor.</p>\n<p>(D) The drift velocity of electron is inversely proportional to the length of the conductor.</p>\n<p>(E) The drift velocity increases with the increase in the temperature of conductor.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) and (B) only",
      "(A) and (D) only",
      "(B) and (E) only",
      "(B) and (C) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-current,-current-density-and-drift-velocity",
    "solution": "(A) and (D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpk8tj4",
    "question": "<p>The drift velocity of electrons for a conductor connected in an electrical circuit is $$\\mathrm{V}_{\\mathrm{d}}$$. The conductor in now replaced by another conductor with same material and same length but double the area of cross section. The applied voltage remains same. The new drift velocity of electrons will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{V_{d}}{4}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{V}_{\\mathrm{d}}$$",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~V}_{\\mathrm{d}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{V_{d}}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-current,-current-density-and-drift-velocity",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{V}_{\\mathrm{d}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr17hf1",
    "question": "<p>The charge flowing in a conductor changes with time as $$\\mathrm{Q}(\\mathrm{t})=\\alpha \\mathrm{t}-\\beta \\mathrm{t}^{2}+\\gamma \\mathrm{t}^{3}$$. Where $$\\alpha, \\beta$$ and $$\\gamma$$ are constants. Minimum value of current is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\beta-\\frac{\\alpha^{2}}{3 \\gamma}$$",
      "$$\\alpha-\\frac{3 \\beta^{2}}{\\gamma}$$",
      "$$\\alpha-\\frac{\\beta^{2}}{3 \\gamma}$$",
      "$$\\alpha-\\frac{\\gamma^{2}}{3 \\beta}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-current,-current-density-and-drift-velocity",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha-\\frac{\\beta^{2}}{3 \\gamma}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1v1sw",
    "question": "<p>The electric current through a wire varies with time as $$I=I_0+\\beta t$$, where $$I_0=20 \\mathrm{~A}$$ and $$\\beta=3 \\mathrm{~A} / \\mathrm{s}$$. The amount of electric charge crossed through a section of the wire in $$20 \\mathrm{~s}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "80 C",
      "800 C",
      "1000 C",
      "1600 C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-current,-current-density-and-drift-velocity",
    "solution": "1000 C"
  },
  {
    "id": "B6JootYK7CfkeBOL",
    "question": "If $${\\theta _1},$$ is the inversion temperature, $${\\theta _n}$$ is the neutral temperature, $${\\theta _c}$$  is the temperature of the cold junction, then ",
    "options": [
      "$${\\theta _i} + {\\theta _c} = {\\theta _n}$$ ",
      "$${\\theta _i} - {\\theta _c} = 2{\\theta _n}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\theta _i} + {\\theta _C}} \\over 2} = {\\theta _n}$$ ",
      "$${\\theta _c} - {\\theta _i} = 2{\\theta _n}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$${{{\\theta _i} + {\\theta _C}} \\over 2} = {\\theta _n}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "5M7EROC16wZRTCRZ",
    "question": "A wire when connected to $$220$$ $$V$$ mains supply has power dissipation $${P_1}.$$ Now the wire is cut into two equal pieces which are connected in parallel to the same supply. Power dissipation in this case is $${P_2}.$$ Then $${P_2}:{P_1}$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$1$$ ",
      "$$4$$ ",
      "$$2$$ ",
      "$$3$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$$4$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Cy7fSXIy2UPkikqw",
    "question": "A $$220$$ volt, $$1000$$ watt bulb is connected across a $$110$$ $$volt$$ mains supply. The power consumed will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$750$$ watt ",
      "$$500$$ watt ",
      "$$250$$ watt ",
      "$$1000$$ watt "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$$250$$ watt "
  },
  {
    "id": "n45THVOLm0IPeJTq",
    "question": "The electrochemical equivalent of a metal is $${3.35109^{ - 7}}$$ $$kg$$ per Coulomb. The mass of the metal liberated at the cathode when a $$3A$$ current is passed for $$2$$ seconds will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$6.6 \\times {10^{57}}/kg$$ ",
      "$$9.9 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\,kg$$ ",
      "$$19.8 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\,kg$$ ",
      "$$1.1 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\,kg$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$$19.8 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\,kg$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "plnK8UfkILcELtWx",
    "question": "The thermo $$emf$$ of a thermocouple varies with temperature  $$\\theta $$ of the hot junction as $$E = a\\theta  + b{\\theta ^2}$$ in volts where the ratio $$a/b$$ is $${700^ \\circ }C.$$ If the cold junction is kept at $${0^ \\circ }C,$$ then the neutral temperature is ",
    "options": [
      "$${1400^ \\circ }C$$ ",
      "$${350^ \\circ }C$$",
      "$${700^ \\circ }C$$",
      "No neutral temperature is possible for this termocouple."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "No neutral temperature is possible for this termocouple."
  },
  {
    "id": "tS1RMmmalhvW3BQI",
    "question": "A heater coil is cut into two equal parts and only one part is now used in the heater. The heat generated will now be ",
    "options": [
      "four times ",
      "doubled ",
      "halved ",
      "one fourth "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "doubled "
  },
  {
    "id": "ZiHpAhp6kbYElwTC",
    "question": "The resistance of hot tungsten filament is about $$10$$ times the cold resistance. What will be resistance of $$100$$ $$W$$ and $$200$$ $$V$$ lamp when not in use ? ",
    "options": [
      "$$20\\Omega $$ ",
      "$$40\\Omega $$",
      "$$200\\Omega $$",
      "$$400\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$$40\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "LeIK1aAr1ED4jkSx",
    "question": "An electric bulb is rated $$220$$ volt - $$100$$ watt. The power consumed by it when operated on $$110$$ volt will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$75$$ watt ",
      "$$40$$ watt",
      "$$25$$ Watt ",
      "$$50$$ Watt"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$$25$$ Watt "
  },
  {
    "id": "eDjbNrFk51ERIpfm",
    "question": "The resistance of bulb filmanet is $$100\\Omega $$ at a temperature of $${100^ \\circ }C.$$ If its temperature coefficient of resistance be $$0.005$$ per $$^ \\circ C$$, its resistance will become $$200\\,\\Omega $$ at a temperature of ",
    "options": [
      "$${300^ \\circ }C$$ ",
      "$${400^ \\circ }C$$",
      "$${500^ \\circ }C$$",
      "$${200^ \\circ }C$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$${400^ \\circ }C$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "VBqTK6O2O9Uz2MNA",
    "question": "The resistance of a wire is $$5$$ ohm at $${50^ \\circ }C$$ and $$6$$ ohm at $${100^ \\circ }C.$$ The resistance of the wire at $${0^ \\circ }C$$ will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$3$$ ohm",
      "$$2$$ ohm ",
      "$$1$$ ohm ",
      "$$4$$ ohm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$$4$$ ohm"
  },
  {
    "id": "d64YIQxOUC6xmXcw",
    "question": "Two conductors have the same resistance at $${0^ \\circ }C$$ but their temperature coefficients of resistance are $${\\alpha _1}$$ and $${\\alpha _2}.$$ The respective temperature coefficients of their series and parallel combinations are nearly",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2}} \\over 2},\\,{\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2}$$ ",
      "$${\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2},\\,{{{\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2}} \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$${\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2},\\,{{{\\alpha _1}{\\alpha _2}} \\over {{\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2}}}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2}} \\over 2},\\,{{{\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2}} \\over 2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$${{{\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2}} \\over 2},\\,{{{\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2}} \\over 2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Q1GSThHcgtCd6Pu7",
    "question": "Two electric bulbs marked $$25W$$ $$-$$ $$220$$ $$V$$ and $$100W$$ $$-$$ $$220V$$ are connected in series to a $$440$$ $$V$$ supply. Which of the bulbs will fuse?",
    "options": [
      "Both ",
      "$$100$$ $$W$$ ",
      "$$25$$ $$W$$ ",
      "Neither "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$$25$$ $$W$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Zz73Qo0XAcyd5G1N",
    "question": "The supply voltage to room is $$120V.$$ The resistance of the lead wires is $$6\\Omega $$. A $$60$$ $$W$$ bulb is already switched on. What is the decrease of voltage  across the bulb, when a $$240$$ $$W$$ heater is switched on in parallel to the bulb? ",
    "options": [
      "zero ",
      "$$2.9$$ Volt",
      "$$13.3$$  Volt",
      "$$10.04$$ Volt "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$$10.04$$ Volt "
  },
  {
    "id": "LklwnUiSpSO9Zkmh",
    "question": "In a large building, three are $$15$$ bulbs of $$40$$ $$W$$, $$5$$ bulbs of $$100$$ $$W$$, $$5$$ fans of $$80$$ $$W$$ and $$1$$ heater of $$1$$ $$kW.$$ The voltage of electric mains is $$220$$ $$V.$$ The minimum capacity of the main fuse of the building will be: ",
    "options": [
      "$$8$$ $$A$$ ",
      "$$10$$ $$A$$ ",
      "$$12$$ $$A$$ ",
      "$$14$$ $$A$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$$12$$ $$A$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "bSrBLnM5jeXcZRl0QFD5X",
    "question": "The resistance of an electrical toaster has a temperature dependence given by R(T) = R<sub>0</sub> [1 + $$\\alpha $$(T − T<sub>0</sub>)] in its range of operation. At T<sub>0</sub> = 300 K, R = 100 $$\\Omega $$ and at T = 500 K, R = 120 $$\\Omega $$. The toaster is connected to a voltage source at 200 V and its temperature is raised at a constant rate\nfrom 300 to 500 K in 30 s. The total work done in raising the temperature is :",
    "options": [
      "400 $$\\ln \\,{{1.5} \\over {1.3}}\\,J$$",
      "200 $$\\ln \\,{{2} \\over {3}}\\,J$$",
      "60000 $$\\ln \\,{{6} \\over {5}}\\,J$$",
      "300 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "60000 $$\\ln \\,{{6} \\over {5}}\\,J$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "0FnGOyrhSQdUbYWKbkYry",
    "question": "A constant voltages is applied between two ends of a metallic wire. If the length is halved and the radius of the wire is doubled, the rate of heat developed in the wire will be : ",
    "options": [
      "Doubled ",
      "Halved",
      "Unchanged",
      "Increased 8 times "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "Increased 8 times "
  },
  {
    "id": "HjtiIsdBTEsslnqP90qZF",
    "question": "A heating element has a resistance of 100 $$\\Omega $$ at room temperature.  When it is connected to a supply of 220 V, a steady current of 2 A passes in it and temperature is 500<sup>o</sup>C more than room temperature. what is the temperature coefficient of resistance of the heating element ? ",
    "options": [
      "0.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> <sup>o</sup>C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> <sup>o</sup>C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> <sup>o</sup>C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> <sup>o</sup>C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> <sup>o</sup>C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "QGvTEfImdjpnMoMOsUGMj",
    "question": "A 2 W carbon resistor is color coded with green, black, red and brown respectively. The maximum current which can be passed through this resistor is -",
    "options": [
      "0.4 mA",
      "20 mA",
      "63 mA",
      "100 mA"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "20 mA"
  },
  {
    "id": "YtHzseqCepostZcVqd6l3",
    "question": "A current of 2 mA was passed through an unknown resistor which dissipated a power of 4.4 W. Dissipated power when an ideal power supply of 11 V is connected across it is -",
    "options": [
      "11 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–5</sup> W",
      "11 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> W",
      "11 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup> W",
      "11 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup> W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "11 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–5</sup> W"
  },
  {
    "id": "4jjWHrnKr4IKDRK4E0lUh",
    "question": "Two equal resistances when connected in series to a battery, consume electric power of 60 W. If these resistances are now connected in parallel combination to the same battery, the electric power consumed will be : \n",
    "options": [
      "240 W",
      "60 W",
      "30 W",
      "120 W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "240 W"
  },
  {
    "id": "TDAQw6Br20fMX5WWviih2",
    "question": "Two electric bulbs, rated at (25 W, 220 V) and (100 W, 220 V), are connected in series across a 220 V voltage source. If the 25 W and 100 W bulbs draw powers P<sub>1</sub> and P<sub>2</sub> respectively, then : \n",
    "options": [
      "P<sub>1</sub> = 4W, P<sub>2</sub> = 16 W",
      "P<sub>1</sub> = 16W, P<sub>2</sub> = 4 W",
      "P<sub>1</sub> = 9W, P<sub>2</sub> = 16 W",
      "P<sub>1</sub> = 16W, P<sub>2</sub> = 9 W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "P<sub>1</sub> = 16W, P<sub>2</sub> = 4 W"
  },
  {
    "id": "JlybRSy5VmrfmBLdret67",
    "question": "A cell of internal resistance r drives current\nthrough an external resistance R. The power\ndelivered by the cell to the external resistance\nwill be maximum when :-",
    "options": [
      "R = 1000 r",
      "R = r",
      "R = 2r",
      "R = 0.001 r"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "R = r"
  },
  {
    "id": "Iq5eDmMxk6JKGrBLncjgy2xukfdqit5p",
    "question": "An electrical power line, having a total\nresistance of 2 $$\\Omega $$, delivers 1 kW at 220 V. The\nefficiency of the transmission line is\napproximately :",
    "options": [
      "85%",
      "96%",
      "72%",
      "91%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "96%"
  },
  {
    "id": "40hnYKxW0rROM846gS7k9k2k5f7hmp6",
    "question": "In a building there are 15 bulbs of 45 W, 15 bulbs of 100 W, 15 small fans of 10 W and 2 heaters\nof 1 kW. The voltage of electric main is 220 V. The minimum fuse capacity (rated value) of the\nbuilding will be :",
    "options": [
      "15 A",
      "20 A",
      "25 A",
      "10 A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "20 A"
  },
  {
    "id": "MHbXmErNaaT1l5yvVHjgy2xukeu2jla2",
    "question": "A battery of 3.0 V is connected to a resistor dissipating 0.5 W of power. If the terminal voltage of the battery is 2.5 V, the power dissipated within the internal resistance is :",
    "options": [
      "0.50 W",
      "0.072 W",
      "0.10 W",
      "0.125 W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "0.10 W"
  },
  {
    "id": "oDf2IL8d2d7FVXnwsv1kmipckqw",
    "question": "A resistor develops 500 J of thermal energy in 20 s when a current of 1.5A is passed through it. If the current is increased from 1.5A to 3A, what will be the energy developed in 20 s.",
    "options": [
      "1000 J",
      "2000 J",
      "1500 J",
      "500 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "2000 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks19va2d",
    "question": "The resistance of a conductor at 15$$^\\circ$$C is 16$$\\Omega$$ and at 100$$^\\circ$$C is 20$$\\Omega$$. What will be the temperature coefficient of resistance of the conductor?",
    "options": [
      "0.010$$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "0.033$$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "0.003$$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "0.042$$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "0.003$$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktbr1p8k",
    "question": "An electric bulb of 500 watt at 100 volt is used in a circuit having a 200 V supply. Calculate the resistance R to be connected in series with the bulb so that the power delivered by the bulb is 500 W.",
    "options": [
      "20 $$\\Omega$$",
      "30 $$\\Omega$$",
      "5 $$\\Omega$$",
      "10 $$\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "20 $$\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktmnw0xt",
    "question": "Due to cold weather a 1 m water pipe of cross-sectional area 1 cm<sup>2</sup> is filled with ice at $$-$$10$$^\\circ$$C. Resistive heating is used to melt the ice. Current of 0.5A is passed through 4 k$$\\Omega$$ resistance. Assuming that all the heat produced is used for melting, what is the minimum time required? (Given latent heat of fusion for water/ice = 3.33 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> J kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, specific heat of ice = 2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> J kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup> and density of ice = 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup>",
    "options": [
      "0.353 s",
      "35.3 s",
      "3.53 s",
      "70.6 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "35.3 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55k5jwd",
    "question": "<p>Resistance of the wire is measured as 2 $$\\Omega$$ and 3 $$\\Omega$$ at 10$$^\\circ$$C and 30$$^\\circ$$C respectively. Temperature co-efficient of resistance of the material of the wire is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.033 $$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "$$-$$0.033 $$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "0.011 $$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "0.055 $$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "0.033 $$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nsjma0",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : A uniform wire of resistance $$80 \\,\\Omega$$ is cut into four equal parts. These parts are now connected in parallel. The equivalent resistance of the combination will be $$5 \\,\\Omega$$.</p>\n<p>Statement II: Two resistances 2R and 3R are connected in parallel in a electric circuit. The value of thermal energy developed in 3R and 2R will be in the ratio $$3: 2$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the option given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both statement I and statement II are correct",
      "Both statement I and statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo6lxz4",
    "question": "The $\\mathrm{H}$ amount of thermal energy is developed by a resistor in $10 \\mathrm{~s}$ when a current of $4 \\mathrm{~A}$ is passed through it. If the current is increased to $16 \\mathrm{~A}$, the thermal energy developed by the resistor in $10 \\mathrm{~s}$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{\\mathrm{H}}{4}$",
      "$16 \\mathrm{H}$",
      "H",
      "$4 \\mathrm{H}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$16 \\mathrm{H}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsprd15",
    "question": "<p>Ratio of thermal energy released in two resistors R and 3R connected in parallel in an electric circuit is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "1 : 27",
      "1 : 3",
      "3 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "3 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguy6qmk",
    "question": "<p>Two identical heater filaments are connected first in parallel and then in series. At the same applied voltage, the ratio of heat produced in same time for parallel to series will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 : 1",
      "1 : 4",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "4 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd5tt5u",
    "question": "<p>By what percentage will the illumination of the lamp decrease if the current drops by 20%?</p>",
    "options": [
      "26%",
      "36%",
      "46%",
      "56%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "36%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg5t1zl",
    "question": "<p>When a potential difference $$V$$ is applied across a wire of resistance $$R$$, it dissipates energy at a rate $$W$$. If the wire is cut into two halves and these halves are connected mutually parallel across the same supply, the energy dissipation rate will become:</p>",
    "options": [
      "1/2W",
      "4W",
      "1/4W",
      "2W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "4W"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgx2n14",
    "question": "<p>An electric toaster has resistance of $$60 \\Omega$$ at room temperature $$\\left(27^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}\\right)$$. The toaster is connected to a $$220 \\mathrm{~V}$$ supply. If the current flowing through it reaches $$2.75 \\mathrm{~A}$$, the temperature attained by toaster is around : ( if $$\\alpha=2 \\times 10^{-4}$$/$$^\\circ  \\mathrm{C}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "1235 $$^\\circ$$C",
      "1667 $$^\\circ$$C",
      "694 $$^\\circ$$C",
      "1694 $$^\\circ$$C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "1694 $$^\\circ$$C"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2es2na",
    "question": "<p>An electric bulb rated $$50 \\mathrm{~W}-200 \\mathrm{~V}$$ is connected across a $$100 \\mathrm{~V}$$ supply. The power dissipation of the bulb is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "100 W",
      "50 W",
      "12.5 W",
      "25 W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "12.5 W"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3ve9dw",
    "question": "<p>Water boils in an electric kettle in 20 minutes after being switched on. Using the same main supply, the length of the heating element should be _________ to __________ times of its initial length if the water is to be boiled in 15 minutes.</p>",
    "options": [
      "increased, $$\\frac{3}{4}$$",
      "increased, $$\\frac{4}{3}$$",
      "decreased, $$\\frac{3}{4}$$",
      "decreased, $$\\frac{4}{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "decreased, $$\\frac{3}{4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb295ad",
    "question": "<p>The number of electrons flowing per second in the filament of a $$110 \\mathrm{~W}$$ bulb operating at $$220 \\mathrm{~V}$$ is : (Given $$\\mathrm{e}=1.6 \\times 10^{-19} \\mathrm{C}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1.25 \\times 10^{19}$$\n",
      "$$31.25 \\times 10^{17}$$\n",
      "$$6.25 \\times 10^{18}$$\n",
      "$$6.25 \\times 10^{17}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "electric-power-and-heating-effect-of-current",
    "solution": "$$31.25 \\times 10^{17}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "uiLFmxxbPDGgE81u",
    "question": "If an ammeter is to be used in place of a voltmeter, then we must connect with the ammeter a ",
    "options": [
      "low resistance in parallel ",
      "high resistance in parallel ",
      "high resistance in series ",
      "low resistance in series "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "high resistance in series "
  },
  {
    "id": "oCfPjGdX87Zk9NBi",
    "question": "The thermo $$e.m.f.$$ of a thermo -couple is $$25$$ $$\\mu V/{}^ \\circ C$$ at room temperature. A galvanometer of $$40$$ $$ohm$$ resistance, capable of detecting current as low as $${10^{ - 5}}\\,A,$$ is connected with the thermo couple. The smallest temperature difference that can be detected by this system is ",
    "options": [
      "$${16^0}C$$ ",
      "$${12^0}C$$",
      "$${8^0}C$$",
      "$${20^0}C$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$${16^0}C$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "uq9zqy6WgFx7CtG0",
    "question": "An ammeter reads upto $$1$$ ampere. Its internal resistance is $$0.81$$ $$ohm$$. To increase the range to $$10$$ $$A$$ the value of the required shunt is ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.03\\,\\Omega $$ ",
      "$$0.3\\,\\Omega $$ ",
      "$$0.9\\,\\Omega $$",
      "$$0.09\\,\\Omega $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$$0.09\\,\\Omega $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "cpZym95vLWxghTMx",
    "question": "A moving coil galvanometer has $$150$$ equal divisions. Its current sensitivity is $$10$$- divisions per milliampere and voltage sensitivity is $$2$$ divisions per millivolt. In order that each division reads $$1$$ volt, the resistance in $$ohms$$ needed to be connected in series with the coil will be - ",
    "options": [
      "$${10^5}$$ ",
      "$${10^3}$$",
      "$$9995$$ ",
      "$$99995$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$$9995$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "6SoJA5XIwlMKlyVQ",
    "question": "Two voltmeters, one of copper and another of silver, are joined in parallel. When a total charge $$q$$ flows through the voltmeters, equal amount of metals are deposited. If the electrochemical equivalents of copper and silver are $${Z_1}$$ and $${Z_2}$$ respectively the charge which flows through the silver voltmeter is ",
    "options": [
      "$${q \\over {1 + {{{Z_2}} \\over {{Z_1}}}}}$$ ",
      "$${q \\over {1 + {{{Z_1}} \\over {{Z_2}}}}}$$ ",
      "$$q{{{Z_2}} \\over {{Z_1}}}$$ ",
      "$$q{{{Z_1}} \\over {{Z_2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$${q \\over {1 + {{{Z_2}} \\over {{Z_1}}}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "EMaCvdCkcJFexPVY",
    "question": "This questions has Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ and Statement - $${\\rm I}$$$${\\rm I}$$. Of the four choices given after the Statements, choose the one that best describes into two Statements.\n<p><b>Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ : </b> Higher the range, greater is the resistance of ammeter. \n<br/><b>Statement - $${\\rm I}$$$${\\rm I}$$ :</b> To increase the range of ammeter, additional shunt needs to be used across it.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ is true, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is true, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is the correct explanation of statement - $${\\rm I}$$.",
      "Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ is true, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is true, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is not the correct explanation of statement - $${\\rm I}$$.",
      "Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ is true, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is false",
      "Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ is false, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "Statement - $${\\rm I}$$ is false, Statement - $${\\rm II}$$ is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "LC0K6IK81EzYqMbWH6iN1",
    "question": "A 50 $$\\Omega $$ resistance is connected to a battery of 5 V. A galvanometer of resistance 100 $$\\Omega $$ is to be used as an ammeter to measure current through the resistance, for this a resistance r<sub>s</sub> is connected to the galvanometer. Which of the following connections should be employed if the measured current is within 1% of thecurrent without the ammeter in the circuit ?",
    "options": [
      "r<sub>s</sub> = 0.5 $$\\Omega $$ in parallel with the galvanometer",
      "r<sub>s</sub> = 0.5 $$\\Omega $$ in series with the galvanometer",
      "r<sub>s</sub> = 1 $$\\Omega $$ in series with galvanometer",
      "r<sub>s</sub> =1 $$\\Omega $$ in parallel with galvanometer"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "r<sub>s</sub> = 0.5 $$\\Omega $$ in parallel with the galvanometer"
  },
  {
    "id": "OJAkST2XymZYeR9P",
    "question": "A galvanometer having a coil resistance of $$100\\,\\Omega $$ gives a full scale deflection, when a currect of $$1$$ $$mA$$ is passed through it. The value of the resistance, which can convert this galvanometer into ammeter giving a full scale deflection for a current of $$10$$ $$A,$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$$0.1\\,\\Omega $$ ",
      "$$3\\,\\Omega $$ ",
      "$$0.01\\,\\Omega $$",
      "$$2\\,\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$$0.01\\,\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "5aT5yJbIhnIdc8J8",
    "question": "When a current of 5 mA is passed through a galvanometer having a coil of resistance 15$$\\Omega $$, it shows full\nscale deflection. The value of the resistance to be put in series with the galvanometer to convert it into a\nvoltmeter of range 0 – 10V is:",
    "options": [
      "4.005 × 10<sup>3</sup> $$\\Omega $$",
      "1.985 × 10<sup>3</sup> $$\\Omega $$",
      "2.535 × 10<sup>3</sup> $$\\Omega $$",
      "2.045 × 10<sup>3</sup> $$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "1.985 × 10<sup>3</sup> $$\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "C9NxWuKFx68qorS2nifad",
    "question": "In a circuit for finding the resistance of a galvanometer  by half deflection method,  a 6 V battery and a high resistance of 11 k$$\\Omega $$ are used. The figure of merit of the galvanometer is 60 $$\\mu A/$$division.  In the absence of shunt resistance, the galvanometer produces a deflection of $$\\theta $$ = 9 divisions when current flows in the circuit. The value of the shunt resistance that can cause the deflection of $$\\theta /2,$$ is closest to :",
    "options": [
      "500 $$\\Omega $$",
      "220 $$\\Omega $$",
      "55 $$\\Omega $$",
      "110 $$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "110 $$\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "vzQHFuKMH5gDmq87s6WNr",
    "question": "A galvanometer with its coil resistance 25 $$\\Omega $$ requires a current of 1 mA for its full deflection. In order to construct an ammeter to read upto a current of 2 A,  the approximate value of the shunt resistance should be : ",
    "options": [
      "$$2.5 \\times {10^{ - 3}}\\,\\Omega $$ ",
      "$$1.25 \\times {10^{ - 2}}\\Omega $$",
      "$$1.25 \\times {10^{ - 3}}\\Omega $$",
      "$$2.5 \\times {10^{ - 2}}\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$$1.25 \\times {10^{ - 2}}\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "SSiE5nee84TR580txzma9",
    "question": "A moving coil galvanometer has resistance 50$$\\Omega $$\nand it indicates full deflection at 4mA current.\nA voltmeter is made using this galvanometer\nand a 5 k$$\\Omega $$ resistance. The maximum voltage,\nthat can be measured using this voltmeter, will\nbe close to :",
    "options": [
      "15 V",
      "10 V",
      "40 V",
      "20 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "20 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "R9SAZKwXxdLWzsVBun3rsa0w2w9jx7g1ya9",
    "question": "A moving coil galvanometer, having a resistance G, produces full scale deflection when a current Ig flows\nthrough it. This galvanometer can be converted into (i) an ammeter of range 0 to I<sub>0</sub>(I<sub>0</sub> &gt; I<sub>g</sub>) by connecting a\nshunt resistance R<sub>A</sub> to it and (ii) into a voltmeter of range 0 to V (V = GI<sub>0</sub>) by connecting a series resistance\nR<sub>V</sub> to it. Then,",
    "options": [
      "$${R_A}{R_V} = {G^2}$$ and $${{{R_A}} \\over {{R_V}}} = {{{I_g}} \\over {\\left( {{I_0} - {I_g}} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${R_A}{R_V} = {G^2}\\left( {{{{I_g}} \\over {{I_0} - {I_g}}}} \\right)$$ and $${{{R_A}} \\over {{R_V}}} = {\\left( {{{{I_0} - {I_g}} \\over {{I_g}}}} \\right)^2}$$",
      "$${R_A}{R_V} = {G^2}\\left( {{{{I_0} - {I_g}} \\over {{I_g}}}} \\right)$$ and $${{{R_A}} \\over {{R_V}}} = {\\left( {{{{I_g}} \\over {{I_0} - {I_g}}}} \\right)^2}$$",
      "$${R_A}{R_V} = {G^2}$$ and $${{{R_A}} \\over {{R_V}}} = {\\left( {{{{I_g}} \\over {{I_0} - {I_g}}}} \\right)^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$${R_A}{R_V} = {G^2}$$ and $${{{R_A}} \\over {{R_V}}} = {\\left( {{{{I_g}} \\over {{I_0} - {I_g}}}} \\right)^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "0RwKSwzaxYnS1NjJBT18hoxe66ijvztbapo",
    "question": "A moving coil galvanometer allows a full scale\ncurrent of 10<sup>–4</sup> A. A series resistance of 2 M$$\\Omega $$\nis required to convert the above galvanometer\ninto a voltmeter of range 0-5 V. Therefore the\nvalue of shunt resistance required to convert the\nabove galvanometer into an ammeter of range\n0.10 mA is :",
    "options": [
      "200 $$\\Omega $$",
      "500 $$\\Omega $$",
      "100 $$\\Omega $$",
      "None of the options are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "None of the options are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "Zo4UwXxVxxd17xakDSp73",
    "question": "The resistance of a galvanometer is 50 ohm and\nthe maximum current which can be passed\nthrough it is 0.002 A. What resistance must be\nconnected to it in order to convert it into an\nammeter of range 0 – 0.5 A ?",
    "options": [
      "0.02 ohm",
      "0.2 ohm",
      "0.002 ohm",
      "0.5 ohm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "0.2 ohm"
  },
  {
    "id": "jOqz53VZQQm7z1S2BiHUc",
    "question": "A galvanometer, whose resistance is 50 ohm, has 25 divisions in it. When a current of 4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup> A passes through it, its needle ( pointer) deflects by one division. To use this galvanometer as a voltmeter of range 2.5 V, it should be connected to a resistance of : ",
    "options": [
      "200 ohm",
      "250 ohm",
      "6200 ohm",
      "6250 ohm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "200 ohm"
  },
  {
    "id": "y6ZZO93FxMi6gRCvgSFJ3",
    "question": "A galvanometer having a resistance of 20 $$\\Omega $$ and 30 divisions on both sides has figure of merit 0.005 ampere/division. The resistance that should be connected in series such that it can be used as a voltmeter upto 15 volt, is:",
    "options": [
      "120 $$\\Omega $$",
      "125 $$\\Omega $$",
      "80 $$\\Omega $$",
      "100 $$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "80 $$\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "pc8M7D7DtnJbd4xoBbjgy2xukg0a1gfa",
    "question": "A circuit to verify Ohm's law uses ammeter and voltmeter in series or parallel connected correctly\nto the resistor. In the circuit :",
    "options": [
      "Ammeter is always connected in series and voltmeter in parallel",
      "Both ammeter and voltmeter must be connected in series",
      "Both ammeter and voltmeter must be connected in parallel",
      "Ammeter is always used in parallel and voltmeter is series"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "Ammeter is always connected in series and voltmeter in parallel"
  },
  {
    "id": "DAnXq686VdMsqgXco0jgy2xukfl4e626",
    "question": "A galvanometer is used in laboratory for\ndetecting the null point in electrical\nexperiments. If, on passing a current of 6 mA it\nproduces a deflection of 2<sup>o</sup>, its figure of merit\nis close to :",
    "options": [
      "6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> A/div",
      "666<sup>o</sup> A/div",
      "3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> A/div",
      "333<sup>o</sup> A/div"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> A/div"
  },
  {
    "id": "2iPRjBl8dAyZejKwENjgy2xukf3uaadv",
    "question": "Two resistors 400$$\\Omega $$  and 800$$\\Omega $$ are connected in series across a 6 V battery. The potential difference measured by a voltmeter of 10 k$$\\Omega $$ across 400 $$\\Omega $$ resistor is close to :\n",
    "options": [
      "2.05 V",
      "1.95 V",
      "2 V",
      "1.8 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "1.95 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "1yNqnTCFDtdFg02BWMjgy2xukfg9wky8",
    "question": "A galvanometer of resistance G is converted\ninto a voltmeter of range 0 – 1 V by connecting\na resistance R<sub>1</sub> in series with it. The additional\nresistance that should be connected in series\nwith R<sub>1</sub> to increase the range of the voltmeter\nto 0 – 2 V will be :",
    "options": [
      "G",
      "R<sub>1</sub>",
      "R<sub>1</sub> + G",
      "R<sub>1</sub> - G"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "R<sub>1</sub> + G"
  },
  {
    "id": "uFiuD4Rks8JQ2Ghhra7k9k2k5hgpxmr",
    "question": "A galvanometer having a coil resistance\n100 $$\\Omega $$ gives a full scale deflection when a\ncurrent of 1 mA is passed through it. What is\nthe value of the resistance which can convert\nthis galvanometer into a voltmeter giving full\nscale deflection for a potential difference of\n10 V?",
    "options": [
      "8.9 k$$\\Omega $$",
      "10 k$$\\Omega $$",
      "9.9 k$$\\Omega $$",
      "7.9 k$$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "9.9 k$$\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfm75yi",
    "question": "For full scale deflection of total 50 divisions, 50 mV voltage is required in galvanometer. The resistance of galvanometer if its current sensitivity is 2 div/mA will be :",
    "options": [
      "1$$\\Omega$$",
      "5$$\\Omega$$",
      "4$$\\Omega$$",
      "2$$\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "2$$\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth5jj8l",
    "question": "Consider a galvanometer shunted with 5$$\\Omega$$ resistance and 2% of current passes through it. What is the resistance of the given galvanometer ?",
    "options": [
      "300 $$\\Omega$$",
      "344 $$\\Omega$$",
      "245 $$\\Omega$$",
      "226 $$\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "245 $$\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57prg1l",
    "question": "<p>A 72 $$\\Omega$$ galvanometer is shunted by a resistance of 8 $$\\Omega$$. The percentage of the total current which passes through the galvanometer is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.1%",
      "10%",
      "25%",
      "0.25%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "10%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59poesd",
    "question": "<p>If n represents the actual number of deflections in a converted galvanometer of resistance G and shunt resistance S. Then the total current I when its figure of merit is K will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${{KS} \\over {(S + G)}}$$",
      "$${{(G + S)} \\over {nKS}}$$",
      "$${{nKS} \\over {(G + S)}}$$",
      "$${{nK(G + S)} \\over S}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$${{nK(G + S)} \\over S}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5al5y8m",
    "question": "<p>A teacher in his physics laboratory allotted an experiment to determine the resistance (G) of a galvanometer. Students took the observations for $${1 \\over 3}$$ deflection in the galvanometer. Which of the below is true for measuring value of G?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 3}$$ deflection method cannot be used for determining the resistance of the galvanometer.",
      "$${1 \\over 3}$$ deflection method can be used and in this case the G equals to twice the value of shunt resistances.",
      "$${1 \\over 3}$$ deflection method can be used and in this case, the G equals to three times the value of shunt resistances.",
      "$${1 \\over 3}$$ deflection method can be used and in this case the G value equals to the shunt resistances."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 3}$$ deflection method can be used and in this case the G equals to twice the value of shunt resistances."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c2qi47",
    "question": "<p>Two identical cells each of emf 1.5 V are connected in parallel across a parallel combination of two resistors each of resistance 20 $$\\Omega$$. A voltmeter connected in the circuit measures 1.2 V. The internal resistance of each cell is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.5 $$\\Omega$$",
      "4 $$\\Omega$$",
      "5 $$\\Omega$$",
      "10 $$\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "5 $$\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnw0rsa",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : For measuring the potential difference across a resistance of $$600 \\Omega$$, the voltmeter with resistance $$1000 \\Omega$$ will be preferred over voltmeter with resistance $$4000 \\Omega$$.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Voltmeter with higher resistance will draw smaller current than voltmeter with lower resistance.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is not correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is correct",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is not correct",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is not the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is not correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo69h0d",
    "question": "The number of turns of the coil of a moving coil galvanometer is increased in order to increase current sensitivity by $50 \\%$. The percentage change in voltage sensitivity of the galvanometer will be :",
    "options": [
      "$0 \\%$",
      "$75 \\%$",
      "$100 \\%$",
      "$50 \\%$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$0 \\%$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwqp8xy",
    "question": "<p>A cell of emf 90 V is connected across series combination of two resistors each of 100$$\\Omega$$ resistance. A voltmeter of resistance 400$$\\Omega$$ is used to measure the potential difference across each resistor. The reading of the voltmeter will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "40 V",
      "90 V",
      "45 V",
      "80 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "40 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguyc7b5",
    "question": "<p>The current sensitivity of moving coil galvanometer is increased by $$25 \\%$$. This increase is achieved only by changing in the number of turns of coils and area of cross section of the wire while keeping the resistance of galvanometer coil constant. The percentage change in the voltage sensitivity will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "+25%",
      "$$-$$50%",
      "$$-$$25%",
      "Zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "+25%"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsan7lov",
    "question": "In an ammeter, $5 \\%$ of the main current passes through the galvanometer. If resistance of the galvanometer is $\\mathrm{G}$, the resistance of ammeter will be :",
    "options": [
      "$199 \\mathrm{~G}$",
      "$200 \\mathrm{~G}$",
      "$\\frac{G}{20}$",
      "$\\frac{\\mathrm{G}}{199}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$\\frac{G}{20}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbkwr5w",
    "question": "A galvanometer has a resistance of $50 ~\\Omega$ and it allows maximum current of $5 \\mathrm{~mA}$. It can be converted into voltmeter to measure upto $100 \\mathrm{~V}$ by connecting in series a resistor of resistance :",
    "options": [
      "$19500 \\Omega$",
      "$5975 \\Omega$",
      "$20050 \\Omega$",
      "$19950 \\Omega$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$19950 \\Omega$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscpoor2",
    "question": "<p>A current of $$200 \\mu \\mathrm{A}$$ deflects the coil of a moving coil galvanometer through $$60^{\\circ}$$. The current to cause deflection through $$\\frac{\\pi}{10}$$ radian is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "120 $$\\mu$$A",
      "180 $$\\mu$$A",
      "30 $$\\mu$$A",
      "60 $$\\mu$$A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "60 $$\\mu$$A"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf144o3",
    "question": "<p>The deflection in moving coil galvanometer falls from 25 divisions to 5 division when a shunt of $$24 \\Omega$$ is applied. The resistance of galvanometer coil will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$48 \\Omega$$\n",
      "$$100 \\Omega$$\n",
      "$$96 \\Omega$$\n",
      "$$12 \\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$$96 \\Omega$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf18uwe",
    "question": "<p>A galvanometer having coil resistance $$10 \\Omega$$ shows a full scale deflection for a current of $$3 \\mathrm{~mA}$$. For it to measure a current of $$8 \\mathrm{~A}$$, the value of the shunt should be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3.75 \\times 10^{-3} \\Omega$$\n",
      "$$3 \\times 10^{-3} \\Omega$$\n",
      "$$4.85 \\times 10^{-3} \\Omega$$\n",
      "$$2.75 \\times 10^{-3} \\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$$3.75 \\times 10^{-3} \\Omega$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luy9clvj",
    "question": "<p>A galvanometer has a coil of resistance $$200 \\Omega$$ with a full scale deflection at $$20 \\mu \\mathrm{A}$$. The value of resistance to be added to use it as an ammeter of range $$(0-20) \\mathrm{mA}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$0.40\\Omega$$",
      "$$0.10\\Omega$$",
      "$$0.20\\Omega$$",
      "$$0.50\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "$$0.20\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s23u4",
    "question": "<p>A galvanometer of resistance $$100 \\Omega$$ when connected in series with $$400 \\Omega$$ measures a voltage of upto $$10 \\mathrm{~V}$$. The value of resistance required to convert the galvanometer into ammeter to read upto $$10 \\mathrm{~A}$$ is $$x \\times 10^{-2} \\Omega$$. The value of $$x$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "20",
      "800",
      "200"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "galvanometer,-voltmeter-and-ammeter",
    "solution": "20"
  },
  {
    "id": "BjQ6wonD4UOIAkoa",
    "question": "An electric current is passed through a circuit containing two wires of the same material, connected in parallel. If the lengths and radii are in the ratio of  $${4 \\over 3}$$ and $${2 \\over 3}$$, then the ratio of the current passing through the wires will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$8/9$$ ",
      "$$1/3$$ ",
      "$$3$$ ",
      "$$2$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "kirchhoff's-circuit-laws",
    "solution": "$$1/3$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "geSpm7i5JjpctjZq",
    "question": "The Kirchhoff's first law $$\\left( {\\sum i = 0} \\right)$$ and second law $$\\left( {\\sum iR = \\sum E} \\right),$$ where the symbols have their usual meanings, are respectively based on ",
    "options": [
      "conservation  of charge, conservation of momentum",
      "conservation of energy, conservation of charge ",
      "conservation of momentum, conservation of charge ",
      "conservation of charge, conservation of energy"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "kirchhoff's-circuit-laws",
    "solution": "conservation of charge, conservation of energy"
  },
  {
    "id": "kZl0WVkqCMamH0EY",
    "question": "Two sources of equal $$emf$$ are connected to an external resistance  $$R.$$ The internal resistance of the two sources are $${R_1}$$ and  $${R_2}\\left( {{R_1} &gt; {R_1}} \\right).$$ If the potential difference across the source having internal resistance $${R_2}$$ is zero, then ",
    "options": [
      "$$R = {R_2} - {R_1}$$ ",
      "$$R = {R_2} \\times \\left( {{R_1} + {R_2}} \\right)/\\left( {{R_2} - {R_1}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$R = {R_1}{R_2}/\\left( {{R_2} - {R_1}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$R = {R_1}{R_2}/\\left( {{R_1} - {R_2}} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "kirchhoff's-circuit-laws",
    "solution": "$$R = {R_2} - {R_1}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ACmTZs0L84nU9o5Z",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is <b>false</b>?",
    "options": [
      "Kirchhoff’s second law represents energy conservation.",
      "Wheatstone bridge is the most sensitive when all the four resistances are of the same order of\nmagnitude.",
      "In a balanced wheatstone bridge if the cell and the galvanometer are exchanged, the null point is\ndisturbed.",
      "A rheostat can be used as a potential divider."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "kirchhoff's-circuit-laws",
    "solution": "In a balanced wheatstone bridge if the cell and the galvanometer are exchanged, the null point is\ndisturbed."
  },
  {
    "id": "5NHEvSOiSFvXpiKu",
    "question": "Two batteries with e.m.f 12 V and 13 V are connected in parallel across a load resistor of 10 $$\\Omega $$. The\ninternal resistances of the two batteries are 1 $$\\Omega $$ and 2 $$\\Omega $$ respectively. The voltage across the load lies between :",
    "options": [
      "11.7 V and 11.8 V",
      "11.6 V and 11.7 V",
      "11.5 V and 11.6 V",
      "11.4 V and 11.5 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "kirchhoff's-circuit-laws",
    "solution": "11.5 V and 11.6 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "EMCCdeYAXjPF8mlv",
    "question": "In a meter bridge experiment null  point is obtained at $$20$$ $$cm$$, from one end of the wire when resistance $$X$$ is balanced against another resistance $$Y.$$ If $$X &lt; Y$$, then where will be the new position of the null point from the same end, if one decides to balance a resistance of $$4$$ $$X$$ against $$Y$$ ",
    "options": [
      "$$40$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$80$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$50$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$70$$ $$cm$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "meter-bridge",
    "solution": "$$50$$ $$cm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "hcIg5KV9z1Xl432I",
    "question": "On interchanging the resistances, the balance point of a meter bridge shifts to the left by 10 cm. The\nresistance of their series combination is 1 k$$\\Omega $$. How much was the resistance on the left slot before\ninterchanging the resistances?",
    "options": [
      "910 $$\\Omega $$",
      "990 $$\\Omega $$",
      "505 $$\\Omega $$",
      "550 $$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "meter-bridge",
    "solution": "550 $$\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsamtosf",
    "question": "In a metre-bridge when a resistance in the left gap is $2 \\Omega$ and unknown resistance in the right gap, the balance length is found to be $40 \\mathrm{~cm}$. On shunting the unknown resistance with $2 \\Omega$, the balance length changes by :",
    "options": [
      "$62.5 $ ",
      "$22.5 \\mathrm{~cm}$",
      "$20 \\mathrm{~cm}$",
      "$65 \\mathrm{~cm}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "meter-bridge",
    "solution": "$22.5 \\mathrm{~cm}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd7iy3r",
    "question": "<p>The resistance per centimeter of a meter bridge wire is $$r$$, with $$X \\Omega$$ resistance in left gap. Balancing length from left end is at $$40 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ with $$25 \\Omega$$ resistance in right gap. Now the wire is replaced by another wire of $$2 r$$ resistance per centimeter. The new balancing length for same settings will be at</p>",
    "options": [
      "10 cm",
      "80 cm",
      "40 cm",
      "20 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "meter-bridge",
    "solution": "40 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "V2UyxyJY4IwPWXSq",
    "question": "An energy source will supply a constant current into the load if its internal resistance is ",
    "options": [
      "very large as compared to the load resistance ",
      "equal to the resistance of the load ",
      "non-zero but less than the resistance of the load",
      "zero "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "ohm's-law",
    "solution": "zero "
  },
  {
    "id": "gwzftriO0loiJL7b",
    "question": "When $$5V$$ potential difference is applied across a wire of length $$0.1$$ $$m,$$ the drift speed of electrons is $$2.5 \\times {10^{ - 4}}\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}.$$ If the electron density in the wire is $$8 \\times {10^{28}}\\,\\,{m^{ - 3}},$$ the resistivity of the material is close to :",
    "options": [
      "$$1.6 \\times {10^{ - 6}}\\Omega m$$ ",
      "$$1.6 \\times {10^{ - 5}}\\Omega m$$ ",
      "$$1.6 \\times {10^{ - 8}}\\Omega m$$ ",
      "$$1.6 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\Omega m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "ohm's-law",
    "solution": "$$1.6 \\times {10^{ - 5}}\\Omega m$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ymIJC2KG7BBWBhm7nW1kmhorhu5",
    "question": "A conducting wire of length 'l', area of cross-section A and electric resistivity $$\\rho$$ is connected between the terminals of a battery. A potential difference V is developed between its ends, causing an electric current.<br/><br/>If the length of the wire of the same material is doubled and the area of cross-section is halved, the resultant current would be :",
    "options": [
      "$$4{{VA} \\over {\\rho l}}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 4}{{VA} \\over {\\rho l}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}{{VA} \\over {\\rho l}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}{{\\rho l} \\over {VA}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "ohm's-law",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 4}{{VA} \\over {\\rho l}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "PS7TbIqCesBO6stuhw1kmkre8bx",
    "question": "In the experiment of Ohm's law, a potential difference of 5.0 V is applied across the end of a conductor of length 10.0 cm and diameter of 5.00 mm. The measured current in the conductor is 2.00 A. The maximum permissible percentage error in the resistivity of the conductor is :",
    "options": [
      "3.9",
      "8.4",
      "7.5",
      "3.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "ohm's-law",
    "solution": "3.9"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduhr3zb",
    "question": "<p>A uniform metallic wire carries a current 2 A, when 3.4 V battery is connected across it. The mass of uniform metallic wire is 8.92 $$\\times$$ 10$$^{-3}$$ kg, density is 8.92 $$\\times$$ 10$$^{3}$$ kg/m$$^3$$ and resistivity is 1.7 $$\\times$$ 10$$^{-8}~\\Omega$$-$$\\mathrm{m}$$. The length of wire is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$l=100$$ m",
      "$$l=6.8$$ m",
      "$$l=5$$ m",
      "$$l=10$$ m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "ohm's-law",
    "solution": "$$l=10$$ m"
  },
  {
    "id": "mRe8l33BFkyzGwBW",
    "question": "The length of a wire of a potentiometer is $$100$$ $$cm$$, and the $$e.$$ $$m.$$ $$f.$$ of its standard cell is $$E$$ volt. It is employed to measure the $$e.m.f.$$ of a battery whose internal resistance in $$0.5\\Omega .$$ If the balance point is obtained at $$1=30$$ $$cm$$ from the positive end, the $$e.m.f.$$ of the battery is \n<p>where $$i$$ is the current in the potentiometer wire.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${{30E} \\over {100.5}}$$ ",
      "$${{30E} \\over {\\left( {100 - 0.5} \\right)}}$$  ",
      "$${{30\\left( {E - 0.5i} \\right)} \\over {100}}$$ ",
      "$${{30E} \\over {100}} - 0.5i$$,  where i is the current in the potentiometer\nwire"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "potentiometer",
    "solution": "$${{30E} \\over {100}} - 0.5i$$,  where i is the current in the potentiometer\nwire"
  },
  {
    "id": "V6wcr5zbUWy1dmJe",
    "question": "In a potentiometer experiment the balancing with a cell is at  length $$240$$ $$cm.$$ On shunting the cell with a resistance of $$2\\Omega ,$$ the balancing length becomes $$120$$ $$cm$$. The internal resistance of the cell is ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.5\\Omega $$ ",
      "$$1\\Omega $$",
      "$$2\\Omega $$",
      "$$4\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "potentiometer",
    "solution": "$$2\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "R9UdGikCD5CKM2yU",
    "question": "In a potentiometer experiment, it is found that no current passes through the galvanometer when the\nterminals of the cell are connected across 52 cm of the potentiometer wire. If the cell is shunted by a\nresistance of 5 $$\\Omega$$, a balance is found when the cell is connected across 40 cm of the wire. Find the internal\nresistance of the cell.",
    "options": [
      "2.5 $$\\Omega$$",
      "1 $$\\Omega$$",
      "1.5 $$\\Omega$$",
      "2 $$\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "potentiometer",
    "solution": "1.5 $$\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "r3rKRvu4wCsV4VHjXDf1k",
    "question": "An ideal battery of 4 V and resistance R are connected in series in the primary circuit of a potentiometer of length 1 m and  esistance 5 $$\\Omega $$. The value of R, to give a potential difference of 5 mV across 10 cm of potentiometer wire, is : ",
    "options": [
      "480 $$\\Omega $$",
      "495 $$\\Omega $$",
      "490 $$\\Omega $$",
      "395 $$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "potentiometer",
    "solution": "395 $$\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "aamzmExiqp1NE2DDqk7k9k2k5gv5a7t",
    "question": "The length of a potentiometer wire is 1200 cm\nand it carries a current of 60 mA. For a cell of\nemf 5V and internal resistance of 20$$\\Omega $$, the null\npoint on it is found to be a 1000 cm. The\nresistance of whole wire is :",
    "options": [
      "80$$\\Omega $$",
      "60$$\\Omega $$",
      "120$$\\Omega $$",
      "100$$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "potentiometer",
    "solution": "100$$\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lds9clec",
    "question": "<p>With the help of potentiometer, we can determine the value of emf of a given cell. The sensitivity of the potentiometer is</p>\n<p>(A) directly proportional to the length of the potentiometer wire</p>\n<p>(B) directly proportional to the potential gradient of the wire</p>\n<p>(C) inversely proportional to the potential gradient of the wire</p>\n<p>(D) inversely proportional to the length of the potentiometer wire</p>\n<p>Choose the correct option for the above statements :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A only",
      "B and D only",
      "A and C only",
      "inversely C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "potentiometer",
    "solution": "A and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxzxs",
    "question": "<p>To measure the internal resistance of a battery, potentiometer is used. For $$R=10 \\Omega$$, the balance point is observed at $$l=500 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ and for $$\\mathrm{R}=1 \\Omega$$ the balance point is observed at $$l=400 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. The internal resistance of the battery is approximately :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$0.1 \\Omega$$\n",
      "$$0.3 \\Omega$$\n",
      "$$0.2 \\Omega$$\n",
      "$$0.4 \\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "potentiometer",
    "solution": "$$0.3 \\Omega$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "TXWeNjjwXkpJKaG4",
    "question": "The length of a given cylindrical wire is increased by $$100\\% $$. Due to the consequent decrease in diameter the change in the resistance of the wire will be",
    "options": [
      "$$200\\% $$",
      "$$100\\% $$ ",
      "$$50\\% $$",
      "$$300\\% $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "$$300\\% $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "WB8X5uHFdgLImheC",
    "question": "Thermistors are usually made of ",
    "options": [
      "metal oxides with high temperature coefficient of resistivity ",
      "metals with high temperature coefficient of resistivity ",
      "metals with low temperature coefficient of resistivity ",
      "semiconducting materials having low temperature "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "metal oxides with high temperature coefficient of resistivity "
  },
  {
    "id": "W0Yp4gh8gzh7pFgV",
    "question": "A material $$'B'$$ has twice the specific resistance of $$'A'.$$ A circular wire made of $$'B'$$ has twice the diameter of a wire made of $$'A'$$. Then for the two wires to have the same resistance, the ratio $${l \\over B}/{l \\over A}$$ of their respective lengths must be",
    "options": [
      "$$1$$ ",
      "$${l \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$${l \\over 4}$$ ",
      "$$2$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "$$2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "A2NHsLe1CqC2BD2t",
    "question": "If a wire is stretched to make it $$0.1\\% $$ longer, its resistance will: ",
    "options": [
      "increase by $$0.2\\% $$",
      "decrease by $$0.2\\% $$",
      "decrease by $$0.05\\% $$",
      "increase by $$0.05\\% $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "increase by $$0.2\\% $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "sgUjbwzNCmrOI2y6lNHln",
    "question": "A uniform wire of length 1 and radius r has a resistance of 100 $$\\Omega $$. It is recast into a wire of radius $${r  \\over 2}.$$  The resistance of new wire will be : ",
    "options": [
      "1600 $$\\Omega $$ ",
      "400 $$\\Omega $$",
      "200 $$\\Omega $$",
      "100 $$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "1600 $$\\Omega $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "pZX3OApbxTGvUBepqcLb6",
    "question": "A metal wire of resistance 3 $$\\Omega $$  is elongated to\nmake a uniform wire of double its previous\nlength. This new wire is now bent and the ends\njoined to make a circle. If two points on this\ncircle make an angle 60° at the centre, the\nequivalent resistance between these two points\nwill be :-",
    "options": [
      "5 /2 $$\\Omega $$",
      "12/5 $$\\Omega $$",
      "7/2 $$\\Omega $$",
      "5 / 3 $$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "5 / 3 $$\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "MNHy91FwKSD3f1uwlCAO6",
    "question": "In a conductor, if the number of conduction\nelectrons per unit volume is 8.5 × 10<sup>28</sup> m<sup>–3</sup> and\nmean free time is 25ƒs (femto second), it's\napproximate resistivity is :-<br/>\n(m<sub>e</sub> = 9.1 × 10<sup>–31</sup> kg)",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>–8</sup> $$\\Omega $$m",
      "10<sup>–7</sup> $$\\Omega $$m",
      "10<sup>–5</sup> $$\\Omega $$m",
      "10<sup>–6</sup> $$\\Omega $$m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "10<sup>–8</sup> $$\\Omega $$m"
  },
  {
    "id": "ylwu9ATRfrMmV19byR18hoxe66ijvwwkzsm",
    "question": "A current of 5 A passes through a copper\nconductor (resistivity = 1.7 × 10<sup>–8</sup> $$\\Omega $$m) of radius\nof cross-section 5 mm. Find the mobility of the\ncharges if their drift velocity is 1.1 × 10<sup>–3</sup> m/s.",
    "options": [
      "1.3 m<sup>2</sup>/Vs",
      "1.0 m<sup>2</sup>/Vs",
      "1.8 m<sup>2</sup>/Vs",
      "1.5 m<sup>2</sup>/Vs"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "1.0 m<sup>2</sup>/Vs"
  },
  {
    "id": "98vIQwSQdX5DxVcjkS3rsa0w2w9jwzhx53v",
    "question": "Space between two concentric conducting spheres of radii a and b (b &gt; a) is filled with a medium of\nresistivity $$\\rho $$. The resistance between the two spheres will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\rho  \\over {2\\pi }}\\left( {{1 \\over a} + {1 \\over b}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\rho  \\over {4\\pi }}\\left( {{1 \\over a} + {1 \\over b}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\rho  \\over {2\\pi }}\\left( {{1 \\over a} - {1 \\over b}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\rho  \\over {4\\pi }}\\left( {{1 \\over a} - {1 \\over b}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "$${\\rho  \\over {4\\pi }}\\left( {{1 \\over a} - {1 \\over b}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "A2kPmvArT3fBp9ggf3jgy2xukev21dnd",
    "question": "Consider four conducting materials copper,\ntungsten, mercury and aluminium with\nresistivity $$\\rho $$<sub>C</sub>, $$\\rho $$<sub>T</sub>, $$\\rho $$<sub>M</sub> and $$\\rho $$<sub>A</sub> respectively. Then :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\rho $$<sub>C</sub> &gt;  $$\\rho $$<sub>A</sub> &gt;  $$\\rho $$<sub>T</sub>",
      "$$\\rho $$<sub>M</sub> &gt;  $$\\rho $$<sub>A</sub> &gt;  $$\\rho $$<sub>C</sub>",
      "$$\\rho $$<sub>A</sub> &gt;  $$\\rho $$<sub>T</sub> &gt;  $$\\rho $$<sub>C</sub>",
      "$$\\rho $$<sub>A</sub> &gt;  $$\\rho $$<sub>M</sub> &gt;  $$\\rho $$<sub>C</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "$$\\rho $$<sub>M</sub> &gt;  $$\\rho $$<sub>A</sub> &gt;  $$\\rho $$<sub>C</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "k7H73ooaxw5SRjDAoH1klulf7ut",
    "question": "A wire of 1$$\\Omega$$ has a length of 1 m. It is stretched till its length increases by 25%. The percentage change in resistance to the nearest integer is :",
    "options": [
      "76%",
      "12.5%",
      "25%",
      "56%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "56%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58bvl9r",
    "question": "<p>An aluminium wire is stretched to make its length, 0.4% larger. The percentage change in resistance is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.4%",
      "0.2%",
      "0.8%",
      "0.6%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "0.8%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6ma3lde",
    "question": "<p>A wire of resistance R<sub>1</sub> is drawn out so that its length is increased by twice of its original length. The ratio of new resistance to original resistance is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "9 : 1",
      "1 : 9",
      "4 : 1",
      "3 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "9 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p50ibg",
    "question": "<p>Two metallic wires of identical dimensions are connected in series. If $$\\sigma_{1}$$ and $$\\sigma_{2}$$ are the conductivities of the these wires respectively, the effective conductivity of the combination is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\n\\frac{\\sigma_{1} \\sigma_{2}}{\\sigma_{1}+\\sigma_{2}}\n$$",
      "$$\n\\frac{2 \\sigma_{1} \\sigma_{2}}{\\sigma_{1}+\\sigma_{2}}\n$$",
      "$$\n\\frac{\\sigma_{1}+\\sigma_{2}}{2 \\sigma_{1} \\sigma_{2}}\n$$",
      "$$\n\\frac{\\sigma_{1}+\\sigma_{2}}{\\sigma_{1} \\sigma_{2}}\n$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "$$\n\\frac{2 \\sigma_{1} \\sigma_{2}}{\\sigma_{1}+\\sigma_{2}}\n$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rgmc4r",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A: Alloys such as constantan and manganin are used in making standard resistance coils.</p>\n<p>Reason R: Constantan and manganin have very small value of temperature coefficient of resistance.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rgp9n8",
    "question": "<p>A $$1 \\mathrm{~m}$$ long wire is broken into two unequal parts $$\\mathrm{X}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Y}$$. The $$\\mathrm{X}$$ part of the wire is streched into another wire W. Length of $$W$$ is twice the length of $$X$$ and the resistance of $$\\mathrm{W}$$ is twice that of $$\\mathrm{Y}$$. Find the ratio of length of $$\\mathrm{X}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Y}$$.</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 4",
      "1 : 2",
      "4 : 1",
      "2 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "1 : 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtyrs3j",
    "question": "<p>The resistance of a wire is 5 $$\\Omega$$. It's new resistance in ohm if stretched to 5 times of it's original length will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "25",
      "625",
      "5",
      "125"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "125"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgriitoy",
    "question": "<p>A wire of resistance $$160 ~\\Omega$$ is melted and drawn in a wire of one-fourth of its length. The new resistance of the wire will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$640 ~\\Omega$$",
      "$$40 ~\\Omega$$",
      "$$16 ~\\Omega$$",
      "$$10 ~\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "$$10 ~\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscpqh3c",
    "question": "<p>Wheatstone bridge principle is used to measure the specific resistance $$\\left(S_1\\right)$$ of given wire, having length $$L$$, radius $$r$$. If $$X$$ is the resistance of wire, then specific resistance is ; $$S_1=X\\left(\\frac{\\pi r^2}{L}\\right)$$. If the length of the wire gets doubled then the value of specific resistance will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{S_1}{4}$$\n",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~S}_1$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{S}_1}{2}$$\n",
      "$$S_1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "$$S_1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse6jbrc",
    "question": "<p>Two conductors have the same resistances at $$0^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ but their temperature coefficients of resistance are $$\\alpha_1$$ and $$\\alpha_2$$. The respective temperature coefficients for their series and parallel combinations are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\alpha_1+\\alpha_2, \\frac{\\alpha_1 \\alpha_2}{\\alpha_1+\\alpha_2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\alpha_1+\\alpha_2}{2}, \\frac{\\alpha_1+\\alpha_2}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\alpha_1+\\alpha_2, \\frac{\\alpha_1+\\alpha_2}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\alpha_1+\\alpha_2}{2}, \\alpha_1+\\alpha_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "resistance-and-resistivity",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\alpha_1+\\alpha_2}{2}, \\frac{\\alpha_1+\\alpha_2}{2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "97IUgmaetUoTy92U",
    "question": "In a Wheatstone's bridge, three resistance $$P, Q$$ and $$R$$ connected in the three arms and the fourth arm is formed by two resistances $${S_1}$$ and $${S_2}$$ connected in parallel. The condition for the bridge to be balanced will be ",
    "options": [
      "$${P \\over Q} = {{2R} \\over {{S_1} + {S_2}}}$$ ",
      "$${P \\over Q} = {{R\\left( {{S_1} + {S_2}} \\right)} \\over {{S_1}{S_2}}}$$ ",
      "$${P \\over Q} = {{R\\left( {{S_1} + {S_2}} \\right)} \\over {2{S_1}{S_2}}}$$ ",
      "$${P \\over Q} = {R \\over {{S_1} + {S_2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "wheatstone-bridge",
    "solution": "$${P \\over Q} = {{R\\left( {{S_1} + {S_2}} \\right)} \\over {{S_1}{S_2}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3vcj8",
    "question": "<p>A wire of length $$10 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ and radius $$\\sqrt{7} \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~m}$$ connected across the right gap of a meter bridge. When a resistance of $$4.5 \\Omega$$ is connected on the left gap by using a resistance box, the balance length is found to be at $$60 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ from the left end. If the resistivity of the wire is $$\\mathrm{R} \\times 10^{-7} \\Omega \\mathrm{m}$$, then value of $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "63",
      "70",
      "66",
      "35"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "current-electricity",
    "topic": "wheatstone-bridge",
    "solution": "66"
  },
  {
    "id": "j0GobDyBXbEQ1R4TLr1qpqahkk8fiiqbl",
    "question": "This question has Statement 1 and Statement 2. Of the four choices given after the statements, choose the one that best describes the two statements.\n<br/><br/> <b>Statement 1 :</b> Davisson - Germer experiment established the wave nature of electrons. <br/><br/><b>Statement 2 :</b> If electrons have wave nature, they can interfere and show diffraction. ",
    "options": [
      "Statement 1 is true, Statement 2 is false",
      "Statement 1 is true, Statement 2 is true, Statement 2 is the correct explanation for Statement 1. ",
      "Statement 1 is true, Statement 2 is true, Statement 2 is not the correct explanation of Statement 1.",
      "Statement 1 is false, Statement 2 is true. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "davisson-and-germer-experiment",
    "solution": "Statement 1 is true, Statement 2 is true, Statement 2 is the correct explanation for Statement 1. "
  },
  {
    "id": "y9UgqES3uXbL76U97R1kmlvx8ti",
    "question": "The speed of electrons in a scanning electron microscope is 1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> ms<sup>-1</sup>. If the protons having the same speed are used instead of electrons, then the resolving power of scanning proton microscope will be changed by a factor of :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {1837}}$$",
      "1837",
      "$${\\sqrt {1837} }$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt {1837} }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "davisson-and-germer-experiment",
    "solution": "1837"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5akxdim",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Davisson-Germer experiment establishes the wave nature of electrons.</p>\n<p>Statement II : If electrons have wave nature, they can interfere and show diffraction.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements choose the correct answer from the option given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "davisson-and-germer-experiment",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpjswzk",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : The beam of electrons show wave nature and exhibit interference and diffraction.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Davisson Germer Experimentally verified the wave nature of electrons.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is not correct but R is correct.",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is Not the correct explanation of A",
      "A is correct but R is not correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "davisson-and-germer-experiment",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "FsFDTRuhDRQdfGrH",
    "question": "Formation of covalent bonds in compounds exhibits ",
    "options": [
      "wave nature of electron ",
      "particle nature of electron ",
      "both wave and particle nature of electron ",
      "none of these "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "wave nature of electron "
  },
  {
    "id": "alES5b54AmPqiO3X",
    "question": "If the kinetic energy of a free electron doubles, it's deBroglie wavelength changes by the factor ",
    "options": [
      "$$2$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$${\\sqrt 2 }$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "mgydk8X4u7rD2Q4z",
    "question": "A particle A of mass m and initial velocity v collides with a particle B of mass m/2 which is at rest. The\ncollision is head on, and elastic. The ratio of the de-Broglie wavelengths $${\\lambda _A}$$ to $${\\lambda _B}$$ after the collision is:",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\lambda _A}} \\over {{\\lambda _B}}} = {1 \\over 3}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\lambda _A}} \\over {{\\lambda _B}}} = 2$$",
      "$${{{\\lambda _A}} \\over {{\\lambda _B}}} = {2 \\over 3}$$",
      "$${{{\\lambda _A}} \\over {{\\lambda _B}}} = {1 \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${{{\\lambda _A}} \\over {{\\lambda _B}}} = 2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "DYdWfFiwVfYSaj1TM9Fxg",
    "question": "Two electrons are moving with non-relativistic speed perpendicular to each other. If corresponding de Broglie wavelength are $${\\lambda _1}$$ and $${\\lambda _2},$$ their de Broglie wavelength in the frame of reference attached to their center of masses :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\lambda _{CM}} = {\\lambda _1} = {\\lambda _2}$$ ",
      "$${\\lambda _{CM}} = {{2{\\lambda _1}{\\lambda _2}} \\over {\\sqrt {\\lambda _1^2 + \\lambda _2^2} }}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {{\\lambda _{CM}}}} = {1 \\over {{\\lambda _1}}} + {1 \\over {{\\lambda _2}}}$$ ",
      "$${\\lambda _{CM}} = \\left( {{{{\\lambda _1} + {\\lambda _2}} \\over 2}} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${\\lambda _{CM}} = {{2{\\lambda _1}{\\lambda _2}} \\over {\\sqrt {\\lambda _1^2 + \\lambda _2^2} }}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "I2FGpkExYmcIqpafLOzzT",
    "question": "If the de Broglie wavelengths associated with a proton and an $$\\alpha $$-particle are equal, then the ratio of velocities of the proton and the $$\\alpha $$-particle will be :",
    "options": [
      "4 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 2",
      "1 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "4 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "D0GFpBeIrXG4xMsU1E3hh",
    "question": "The de-Broglie wavelength ($$\\lambda $$<sub>B</sub>) associated with the electron orbiting in the second excited state of hydrogen atom is related to that in the ground state ($$\\lambda $$<sub>G</sub>) by : ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>B</sub> = 2$$\\lambda $$<sub>G</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>B</sub> = 3$$\\lambda $$<sub>G</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>B</sub> = $$\\lambda $$<sub>G/2</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>B</sub> = $$\\lambda $$<sub>G/3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda $$<sub>B</sub> = 3$$\\lambda $$<sub>G</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "DaDijtRYe9XUHGUzdkg6y",
    "question": "Both the nucleus and the atom of some element arein their respective first excited states. They get de-excted by emitting photons of wavelengths <sup>$$\\lambda $$</sup>N, <sup>$$\\lambda $$</sup>A  respectively. The ratio $${{{}^\\lambda N} \\over {{}^\\lambda A}}$$is closest to : ",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>$$-$$6</sup>",
      "10",
      "10<sup>$$-$$10</sup>",
      "10<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "10<sup>$$-$$6</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "veJ5gtjAQ0lcQMShGoJUf",
    "question": "In an electron microscope, the resolution that can be achieved is of the order of the wavelength of electrons used. To resolve a width of 7.5 × 10<sup>–12</sup> m, the minimum electron energy required is close to -",
    "options": [
      "25 keV",
      "500 keV",
      "100 keV",
      "1 keV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "25 keV"
  },
  {
    "id": "gkvdIXp9RRo0p7DYCik64",
    "question": "If the de Broglie wavelength of an electron is equal to the 10<sup>–3</sup>  times the wavelength of a photon of  frequency 6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup> Hz, then the speed of electron is equal to : (Speed of light = 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>8</sup>  m/s, Planck's constant = 6.63 $$ \\times $$\n10<sup>–34</sup> J.s, Mass of electron = 9.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–31</sup> kg)\n",
    "options": [
      "1.7 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup> m/s",
      "1.45 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup> m/s",
      "1.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup> m/s",
      "1.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup> m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "1.45 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup> m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "OdwULAdXOexjvxOmahFAV",
    "question": "A particle A of mass 'm' and charge 'q' is accelerated by a potential difference of 50 V. Another particle B of mass ' 4 m' and charge 'q' is accelerated by a potential difference of 2500 V. The ratio of de-Broglie wavelengths $${{{\\lambda _A}} \\over {{\\lambda _B}}}$$ is close to :",
    "options": [
      "4.47",
      "10.00",
      "14.14",
      "0.07"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "14.14"
  },
  {
    "id": "EEzB0y2MGQ0q5jvXbodPz",
    "question": "Two particles move at right angle to each other.\nTheir de-Broglie wavelengths are $$\\lambda _1$$ and $$\\lambda _2$$\nrespectively. The particles suffer perfectly\ninelastic collision. The de-Broglie wavelength\n$$\\lambda _2$$ of the final particle, is given by :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda  = {{{\\lambda _1} + {\\lambda _2}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {{\\lambda ^2}}} = {1 \\over {\\lambda _1^2}} + {1 \\over {\\lambda _2^2}}$$",
      "$$\\lambda  = \\sqrt {{\\lambda _1}{\\lambda _2}} $$",
      "$${2 \\over \\lambda } = {1 \\over {{\\lambda _1}}} + {1 \\over {{\\lambda _2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {{\\lambda ^2}}} = {1 \\over {\\lambda _1^2}} + {1 \\over {\\lambda _2^2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xalFQITtlDzcmeosCIMGX",
    "question": "A nucleus A, with a finite de-broglie\nwavelength $$\\lambda $$<sub>A</sub>, undergoes spontaneous fission\ninto two nuclei B and C of equal mass. B flies\nin the same direction as that of A, while C flies\nin the opposite direction with a velocity equal\nto half of that of B. The de-Broglie wavelengths\n$$\\lambda $$<sub>B</sub> and $$\\lambda $$<sub>C</sub> of B and C are respectively :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>A</sub>, 2$$\\lambda $$<sub>A</sub>",
      "2$$\\lambda $$<sub>A</sub>, $$\\lambda $$<sub>A</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>A</sub>, $$\\lambda $$<sub>A</sub>/2",
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>A</sub>/2, $$\\lambda $$<sub>A</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda $$<sub>A</sub>/2, $$\\lambda $$<sub>A</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "asqToXkbxZF251dVWAPp3",
    "question": "A particle 'P' is formed due to a completely\ninelastic collision of particles 'x' and 'y' having\nde-Broglie wavelengths '$$\\lambda $$<sub>x</sub>' and '$$\\lambda $$<sub>y</sub>'\nrespectively. If x and y were moving in opposite\ndirections, then the de-Broglie wavelength of\n'P' is :-",
    "options": [
      "$${\\lambda _x} - {\\lambda _y}$$",
      "$${{{\\lambda _x}{\\lambda _y}} \\over {\\left| {{\\lambda _x} - {\\lambda _y}} \\right|}}$$",
      "$${\\lambda _x} + {\\lambda _y}$$",
      "$${{{\\lambda _x}{\\lambda _y}} \\over {{\\lambda _x} + {\\lambda _y}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${{{\\lambda _x}{\\lambda _y}} \\over {\\left| {{\\lambda _x} - {\\lambda _y}} \\right|}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ei2rUmc6Jy9P32f82P7k9k2k5ld8cvl",
    "question": "An electron of mass m and magnitude of charge\n|e| initially at rest gets accelerated by a constant\nelectric field E. The rate of change of de-Broglie\nwavelength of this electron at time t ignoring\nrelativistic effects is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{ - h} \\over {\\left| e \\right|Et}}$$",
      "$${{ - h} \\over {\\left| e \\right|E\\sqrt t }}$$",
      "$${{ - h} \\over {\\left| e \\right|E{t^2}}}$$",
      "$${{\\left| e \\right|Et} \\over h}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${{ - h} \\over {\\left| e \\right|E{t^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "i9RlreoY3rNewPKMnyjgy2xukg0cq8qq",
    "question": "Assuming the nitrogen molecule is moving with r.m.s. velocity at 400 K, the de-Broglie wavelength\nof nitrogen molecule is close to : \n<br/>(Given : nitrogen molecule weight : 4.64 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–26</sup> kg, <br/>Boltzman\nconstant: 1.38 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–23</sup> J/K, <br/>Planck constant : 6.63 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–34</sup> J.s)",
    "options": [
      "0.44 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$",
      "0.34 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$",
      "0.20 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$",
      "0.24 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "0.24 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "klPxGf59fWvLLQxIwAjgy2xukfrmlo12",
    "question": "An electron, a doubly ionized helium ion (He<sup>++</sup>) and a proton are having the same kinetic energy.\nThe relation between their respective de-Broglie wavelengths $$\\lambda $$<sub>e</sub>, $$\\lambda $$<sub>He<sup>++</sup></sub> and $$\\lambda $$<sub>p</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>e</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>He<sup>++</sup></sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>p</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>e</sub> &lt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>p</sub> &lt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>He<sup>++</sup></sub>",
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>e</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>p</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>He<sup>++</sup></sub>",
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>e</sub> &lt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>He<sup>++</sup></sub> = $$\\lambda $$<sub>p</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda $$<sub>e</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>p</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>He<sup>++</sup></sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "p8X6ew2D2guHJPoMhUjgy2xukexwy4e2",
    "question": "A particle is moving 5 times as fast as an\nelectron. The ratio of the de-Broglie wavelength\nof the particle to that of the electron is 1.878 $$ \\times $$\n10<sup>–4</sup>. The mass of the particle is close to",
    "options": [
      "1.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–28</sup> kg",
      "9.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–31</sup> kg",
      "4.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–27</sup> kg",
      "9.7 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–28</sup> kg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "9.7 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–28</sup> kg"
  },
  {
    "id": "on0C9OUQaeBK1eukKojgy2xukeu4wpq1",
    "question": "Particle A of mass m<sub>A</sub> = $${m \\over 2}$$ moving along the x-axis with velocity v<sub>0</sub> collides elastically with another particle B at rest having mass m<sub>B</sub> = $${m \\over 3}$$. If both particles move along the x-axis after the collision, the change $$\\Delta $$$$\\lambda $$ in de-Broglie wavlength of particle A, in terms of its de-Broglie wavelength ($$\\lambda $$<sub>0</sub>) before collision is :\n",
    "options": [
      "$$\\Delta $$$$\\lambda $$ = $${5 \\over 2}{\\lambda _0}$$",
      "$$\\Delta $$$$\\lambda $$ = $${3 \\over 2}{\\lambda _0}$$",
      "$$\\Delta $$$$\\lambda $$ = 2$$\\lambda $$<sub>0</sub>",
      "$$\\Delta $$$$\\lambda $$ = 4$$\\lambda $$<sub>0</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\Delta $$$$\\lambda $$ = 4$$\\lambda $$<sub>0</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Z5WfFTlP0aFOz9TVJC7k9k2k5i8f500",
    "question": "A particle moving with kinetic energy E has\nde Broglie wavelength $$\\lambda $$. If energy $$\\Delta $$E is added\nto its energy, the wavelength become $$\\lambda $$/2. Value\nof $$\\Delta $$E, is :",
    "options": [
      "E",
      "3E",
      "2E",
      "4E"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "3E"
  },
  {
    "id": "8x9jjOPX0wtoYeiCH27k9k2k5hhjjfy",
    "question": "An electron (mass m) with initial velocity $$\\overrightarrow v  = {v_0}\\widehat i + {v_0}\\widehat j$$ is in an electric field $$\\overrightarrow E  =  - {E_0}\\widehat k$$. If $$\\lambda _0$$ is initial de-Broglie wavelength of electron,\nits de-Broglie wave length at time t is given\nby :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\lambda _0} } \\over {\\sqrt {1 + {{{e^2}{E^2}{t^2}} \\over {{m^2}v_0^2}}} }}$$",
      "$${{{\\lambda _0}\\sqrt 2 } \\over {\\sqrt {1 + {{{e^2}{E^2}{t^2}} \\over {{m^2}v_0^2}}} }}$$",
      "$${{{\\lambda _0} } \\over {\\sqrt {1 + {{{e^2}{E^2}{t^2}} \\over {2{m^2}v_0^2}}} }}$$",
      "$${{{\\lambda _0}} \\over {\\sqrt {2 + {{{e^2}{E^2}{t^2}} \\over {{m^2}v_0^2}}} }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${{{\\lambda _0} } \\over {\\sqrt {1 + {{{e^2}{E^2}{t^2}} \\over {2{m^2}v_0^2}}} }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xSicfEWAfc7KEgJWOm7k9k2k5f4oskk",
    "question": "An electron (of mass m) and a photon have the same energy E in the range of a few eV. The ratio\nof the de-Broglie wavelength associated with the electron and the wavelength of the photon is (c\n= speed of light in vaccuum)",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over c}{\\left( {{{2E} \\over m}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over c}{\\left( {{E \\over {2m}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{E \\over {2m}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$$c{\\left( {2mE} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over c}{\\left( {{E \\over {2m}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ao715fGQj3WhooRFKt1klrnm25m",
    "question": "An X-ray tube is operated at 1.24 million volt. The shortest wavelength of the produced photon will be :",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> nm",
      "10<sup>$$-$$1</sup> nm",
      "10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> nm",
      "10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "bRotoDezyp8SMoF9f21klromxqu",
    "question": "The de-Broglie wavelength of a proton and $$\\alpha$$-particle are equal. The ratio of their velocities is :",
    "options": [
      "4 : 2",
      "4 : 3",
      "4 : 1",
      "1 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "4 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "LNSAHbketV1tPsz13U1klrwzxba",
    "question": "An $$\\alpha$$ particle and a proton are accelerated from rest by a potential difference of 200V. After this, their de Broglie wavelengths are $$\\lambda$$<sub>$$\\alpha$$</sub> and $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> respectively. The ratio $${{{{\\lambda _p}} \\over {{\\lambda _\\alpha }}}}$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "8",
      "2.8",
      "7.8",
      "3.8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "2.8"
  },
  {
    "id": "JomtsgL1OYNuA3CLyC1klt2e3kk",
    "question": "An electron of mass m<sub>e</sub> and a proton of mass m<sub>p</sub> = 1836 m<sub>e</sub> are moving with the same speed. The ratio of their de Broglie wavelength $${{{}^\\lambda electron} \\over {{}^\\lambda proton}}$$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "1836",
      "$${1 \\over {1836}}$$",
      "918"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "1836"
  },
  {
    "id": "bKNd2SFGMhjS5LGYuf1kltj44kb",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labeled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.<br/><br/>Assertion A : An electron microscope can achieve better resolving power than an optical microscope.<br/><br/>Reason R : The de Broglie's wavelength of the electrons emitted from an electron gun is much less than wavelength of visible light.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "A is false but R is true.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is true but R is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ujXZEWsrvDZQdIIKR1kmip1y1j",
    "question": "The de-Broglie wavelength associated with an electron and a proton were calculated by accelerating them through same potential of 100 V. What should nearly be the ratio of their wavelengths? (m<sub>p</sub> = 1.00727u m<sub>e</sub> = 0.00055u)",
    "options": [
      "41.4 : 1",
      "(1860)<sup>2</sup> : 1",
      "1860 : 1",
      "43 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "43 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "LOKAsIDhTSqq5LWhlE1kmj3vaqs",
    "question": "An electron of mass m and a photon have same energy E. The ratio of wavelength of electron to that of photon is : (c being the velocity of light)",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over c}{\\left( {{{2m} \\over E}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over c}{\\left( {{E \\over {2m}}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{E \\over {2m}}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$",
      "$$c{(2mE)^{1/2}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over c}{\\left( {{E \\over {2m}}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "rF1dBUOtxgJUOSj40M1kmkrbjo5",
    "question": "A particle is travelling 4 time as fast as an electron. Assuming the ratio of de-Broglie wavelength of a particle to that of electron is 2 : 1, the mass of the particle is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {16}}$$ times the mass of e<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "8 times the mass of e<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "16 times the mass of e<sup>$$-$$</sup>",
      "$${1 \\over {8}}$$ times the mass of e<sup>$$-$$</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {8}}$$ times the mass of e<sup>$$-$$</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqcfjeb",
    "question": "An electron having de-Broglie wavelength $$\\lambda$$ is incident on a target in a X-ray tube. Cut-off wavelength of emitted X-ray is :",
    "options": [
      "0",
      "$${{2{m^2}{c^2}{\\lambda ^2}} \\over {{h^2}}}$$",
      "$${{2mc{\\lambda ^2}} \\over h}$$",
      "$${{hc} \\over {mc}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${{2mc{\\lambda ^2}} \\over h}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsvip1h",
    "question": "An electron of mass m<sub>e</sub> and a proton of mass m<sub>p</sub> are accelerated through the same potential difference. The ratio of the de-Broglie wavelength associated with the electron to that with the proton is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{m_e}} \\over {{m_p}}}$$",
      "1",
      "$${{{m_p}} \\over {{m_e}}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{m_p}} \\over {{m_e}}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{{m_p}} \\over {{m_e}}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krue0h9q",
    "question": "What should be the order of arrangement of de-Broglie wavelength of electron ($$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub>), an $$\\alpha$$-particle ($$\\lambda$$<sub>a</sub>) and proton ($$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub>) given that all have the same kinetic energy?",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub> = $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> = $$\\lambda$$<sub>$$\\alpha$$</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub> &lt; $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> &lt; $$\\lambda$$<sub>$$\\alpha$$</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda$$<sub>$$\\alpha$$</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub> = $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda$$<sub>$$\\alpha$$</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda$$<sub>$$\\alpha$$</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kruesfih",
    "question": "A particle of mass 4M at rest disintegrates into two particles of mass M and 3M respectively having non zero velocities. The ratio of de-Broglie wavelength of particle of mass M to that of mass 3M will be :",
    "options": [
      "1 : 3",
      "3 : 1",
      "1 : $$\\sqrt 3 $$",
      "1 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "1 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw9v9n6",
    "question": "An electron moving with speed v and a photon moving with speed c, have same D-Broglie wavelength. The ratio of kinetic energy of electron to that of photon is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{3c} \\over v}$$",
      "$${v \\over {3c}}$$",
      "$${v \\over {2c}}$$",
      "$${{2c} \\over v}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${v \\over {2c}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktbn77dl",
    "question": "The de-Broglie wavelength of a particle having kinetic energy E is $$\\lambda$$. How much extra energy must be given to this particle so that the de-Broglie wavelength reduces to 75% of the initial value?",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 9}$$E",
      "$${7 \\over 9}$$E",
      "E",
      "$${16 \\over 9}$$E"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${7 \\over 9}$$E"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth5htn0",
    "question": "A moving proton and electron have the same de-Broglie wavelength. If K and P denote the K.E. and momentum respectively. Then choose the correct option :",
    "options": [
      "K<sub>p</sub> &lt; K<sub>e</sub> and P<sub>p</sub> = P<sub>e</sub>",
      "K<sub>p</sub> = K<sub>e</sub> and P<sub>p</sub> = P<sub>e</sub>",
      "K<sub>p</sub> &lt; K<sub>e</sub> an P<sub>p</sub> &lt; P<sub>e</sub>",
      "K<sub>p</sub> &gt; K<sub>e</sub> and P<sub>p</sub> = P<sub>e</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "K<sub>p</sub> &lt; K<sub>e</sub> and P<sub>p</sub> = P<sub>e</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjo5z23",
    "question": "Consider two separate ideal gases of electrons and protons having same number of particles. The temperature of both the gases are same. The ratio of the uncertainty in determining the position of an electron to that of a proton is proportional to :-",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left( {{{{m_p}} \\over {{m_e}}}} \\right)^{3/2}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{m_e}} \\over {{m_p}}}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{m_p}} \\over {{m_e}}}} $$",
      "$${{{m_p}} \\over {{m_e}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{{m_p}} \\over {{m_e}}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktmn3gnl",
    "question": "The temperature of an ideal gas in 3-dimensions is 300 K. The corresponding de-Broglie wavelength of the electron approximately at 300 K, is :<br/><br/>[m<sub>e</sub> = mass of electron = 9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$31</sup> kg, h = Planck constant = 6.6 $$\\times$$ 6.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js, k<sub>B</sub> = Boltzmann constant = 1.38 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$23</sup> JK<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "6.26 nm",
      "8.46 nm",
      "2.26 nm",
      "3.25 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "6.26 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l569lzub",
    "question": "<p>The de Broglie wavelengths for an electron and a photon are $$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub> and $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> respectively. For the same kinetic energy of electron and photon, which of the following presents the correct relation between the de Broglie wavelengths of two ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${\\lambda _p} \\propto \\lambda _e^2$$",
      "$${\\lambda _p} \\propto {\\lambda _e}$$",
      "$${\\lambda _p} \\propto \\sqrt {{\\lambda _e}} $$",
      "$${\\lambda _p} \\propto \\sqrt {{1 \\over {{\\lambda _e}}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${\\lambda _p} \\propto \\lambda _e^2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57q7z9d",
    "question": "<p>An $$\\alpha$$ particle and a carbon 12 atom has same kinetic energy K. The ratio of their de-Broglie wavelengths $$({\\lambda _\\alpha }:{\\lambda _{C12}})$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1:\\sqrt 3 $$",
      "$$\\sqrt 3 :1$$",
      "$$3:1$$",
      "$$2:\\sqrt 3 $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt 3 :1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58c7ivm",
    "question": "<p>An electron with speed v and a photon with speed c have the same de-Broglie wavelength. If the kinetic energy and momentum of electron are E<sub>e</sub> and p<sub>e</sub> and that of photon are E<sub>ph</sub> and p<sub>ph</sub> respectively. Which of the following is correct?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${{{E_e}} \\over {{E_{ph}}}} = {{2c} \\over v}$$",
      "$${{{E_e}} \\over {{E_{ph}}}} = {v \\over {2c}}$$",
      "$${{{p_e}} \\over {{p_{ph}}}} = {{2c} \\over v}$$",
      "$${{{p_e}} \\over {{p_{ph}}}} = {v \\over {2c}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${{{E_e}} \\over {{E_{ph}}}} = {v \\over {2c}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59pfvk4",
    "question": "<p>A proton, a neutron, an electron and an $$\\alpha$$ particle have same energy. If $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub>, $$\\lambda$$<sub>n</sub>, $$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub> and $$\\lambda$$<sub>a</sub> are the de Broglie's wavelengths of proton, neutron, electron and $$\\alpha$$ particle respectively, then choose the correct relation from the following :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> = $$\\lambda$$<sub>n</sub> > $$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub> > $$\\lambda$$<sub>a</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>a</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>n</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> = $$\\lambda$$<sub>n</sub> > $$\\lambda$$<sub>a</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub> = $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> = $$\\lambda$$<sub>n</sub> = $$\\lambda$$<sub>a</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda$$<sub>a</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>n</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>p</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>e</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f4md7g",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of wavelengths of proton and deuteron accelerated by potential V<sub>p</sub> and V<sub>d</sub> is 1 : $$\\sqrt2$$. Then the ratio of V<sub>p</sub> to V<sub>d</sub> will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "$$\\sqrt2$$ : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "4 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "4 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jihwsz",
    "question": "<p>An electron (mass $$\\mathrm{m}$$) with an initial velocity $$\\vec{v}=v_{0} \\hat{i}\\left(v_{0}&gt;0\\right)$$ is moving in an electric field $$\\vec{E}=-E_{0} \\hat{i}\\left(E_{0}&gt;0\\right)$$ where $$E_{0}$$ is constant. If at $$\\mathrm{t}=0$$ de Broglie wavelength is $$\\lambda_{0}=\\frac{h}{m v_{0}}$$, then its de Broglie wavelength after time t is given by</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda_{0}$$",
      "$$\\lambda_{0}\\left(1+\\frac{e E_{0} t}{m v_{0}}\\right)$$",
      "$$\\lambda_{0} t$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\lambda_{0}}{\\left(1+\\frac{e E_{0} t}{m v_{0}}\\right)}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\lambda_{0}}{\\left(1+\\frac{e E_{0} t}{m v_{0}}\\right)}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6maxo0s",
    "question": "<p>The equation $$\\lambda=\\frac{1.227}{x} \\mathrm{~nm}$$ can be used to find the de-Brogli wavelength of an electron. In this equation $$x$$ stands for :</p>\n<p>Where</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{m}=$$ mass of electron</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{P}=$$ momentum of electron</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{K}=$$ Kinetic energy of electron</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{V}=$$ Accelerating potential in volts for electron</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{mK}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{P}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{K}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{V}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{V}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rh456f",
    "question": "<p>An $$\\alpha$$ particle and a proton are accelerated from rest through the same potential difference. The ratio of linear momenta acquired by above two particles will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt2$$ : 1",
      "2$$\\sqrt2$$ : 1",
      "4$$\\sqrt2$$ : 1",
      "8 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "2$$\\sqrt2$$ : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldoft2cf",
    "question": "<p>A proton moving with one tenth of velocity of light has a certain de Broglie wavelength of $$\\lambda$$. An alpha particle having certain kinetic energy has the same de-Brogle wavelength $$\\lambda$$. The ratio of kinetic energy of proton and that of alpha particle is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 4",
      "2 : 1",
      "4 : 1",
      "1 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "4 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqux55z",
    "question": "An electron accelerated through a potential difference $V_{1}$ has a de-Broglie wavelength of $\\lambda$. When the potential is changed to $V_{2}$, its de-Broglie wavelength increases by $50 \\%$. The value of $\\left(\\frac{V_{1}}{V_{2}}\\right)$ is equal to",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{3}{2}$",
      "4",
      "3",
      "$\\frac{9}{4}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$\\frac{9}{4}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lds9f4ne",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of de-Broglie wavelength of an $$\\alpha$$ particle and a proton accelerated from rest by the same potential is $$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt m}$$, the value of m is -</p>",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "16",
      "8",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "8"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduhmrk0",
    "question": "<p>Electron beam used in an electron microscope, when accelerated by a voltage of 20 kV, has a de-Broglie wavelength of $$\\lambda_0$$. IF the voltage is increased to 40 kV, then the de-Broglie wavelength associated with the electron beam would be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 $$\\lambda_0$$",
      "9 $$\\lambda_0$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\lambda_0}{\\sqrt2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\lambda_0}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\lambda_0}{\\sqrt2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwqrzxu",
    "question": "An $$\\alpha$$-particle, a proton and an electron have the same kinetic energy. Which one of the following is correct in case of their de-Broglie wavelength:",
    "options": [
      "$${\\lambda _\\alpha } > {\\lambda _p} < {\\lambda _e}$$",
      "$${\\lambda _\\alpha } > {\\lambda _p} > {\\lambda _e}$$",
      "$${\\lambda _\\alpha } = {\\lambda _p} = {\\lambda _e}$$",
      "$${\\lambda _\\alpha } < {\\lambda _p} < {\\lambda _e}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$${\\lambda _\\alpha } < {\\lambda _p} < {\\lambda _e}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgny1m5w",
    "question": "The de Broglie wavelength of an electron having kinetic energy $\\mathrm{E}$ is $\\lambda$. If the kinetic energy of electron becomes $\\frac{E}{4}$, then its de-Broglie wavelength will be :",
    "options": [
      "$\\sqrt{2} \\lambda$",
      "$2 \\lambda$",
      "$\\frac{\\lambda}{2}$",
      "$\\frac{\\lambda}{\\sqrt{2}}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$2 \\lambda$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgridy8u",
    "question": "<p>A proton and an $$\\alpha$$-particle are accelerated from rest by $$2 \\mathrm{~V}$$ and $$4 \\mathrm{~V}$$ potentials, respectively. The ratio of their de-Broglie wavelength is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "8 : 1",
      "16 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "4 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswtznp",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of the de-Broglie wavelengths of proton and electron having same Kinetic energy :</p>\n<p>(Assume $$m_{p}=m_{e} \\times 1849$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "1:43",
      "1:62",
      "2:43",
      "1:30"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "1:43"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgxxq9qb",
    "question": "<p>The de Broglie wavelength of a molecule in a gas at room temperature (300 K) is $$\\lambda_1$$. If the temperature of the gas is increased to 600 K, then the de Broglie wavelength of the same gas molecule becomes</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 $$\\lambda_1$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{2}$$$$\\lambda_1$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt2}$$$$\\lambda_1$$",
      "$$\\sqrt2~\\lambda_1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt2}$$$$\\lambda_1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh02bc3h",
    "question": "<p>Proton $$(\\mathrm{P})$$ and electron (e) will have same de-Broglie wavelength when the ratio of their momentum is (assume, $$\\mathrm{m}_{\\mathrm{p}}=1849 \\mathrm{~m}_{\\mathrm{e}}$$ ):</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "1 : 43",
      "1 : 1849",
      "43 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "1 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh24nf6c",
    "question": "<p>The kinetic energy of an electron, $$\\alpha$$-particle and a proton are given as $$4 \\mathrm{~K}, 2 \\mathrm{~K}$$ and $$\\mathrm{K}$$ respectively. The de-Broglie wavelength associated with electron $$(\\lambda \\mathrm{e}), \\alpha$$-particle $$((\\lambda \\alpha)$$ and the proton $$(\\lambda p)$$ are as follows:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda \\alpha<\\lambda p<\\lambda e$$",
      "$$\\lambda \\alpha>\\lambda p>\\lambda e$$",
      "$$\\lambda \\alpha=\\lambda p<\\lambda e$$",
      "$$\\lambda \\alpha=\\lambda p>\\lambda e$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda \\alpha<\\lambda p<\\lambda e$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbl1egu",
    "question": "The de Broglie wavelengths of a proton and an $\\alpha$ particle are $\\lambda$ and $2 \\lambda$ respectively. The ratio of the velocities of proton and $\\alpha$ particle will be :",
    "options": [
      "$8: 1$",
      "$1: 2$",
      "$1: 8$",
      "$4: 1$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$8: 1$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf11a0t",
    "question": "<p>The de-Broglie wavelength of an electron is the same as that of a photon. If velocity of electron is $$25 \\%$$ of the velocity of light, then the ratio of K.E. of electron and K.E. of photon will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{8}{1}$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{8}$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{8}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2umsu",
    "question": "<p>A proton, an electron and an alpha particle have the same energies. Their de-Broglie wavelengths will be compared as :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda_{\\mathrm{p}}>\\lambda_{\\mathrm{e}}>\\lambda_\\alpha$$\n",
      "$$\\lambda_\\alpha<\\lambda_{\\mathrm{p}}<\\lambda_{\\mathrm{e}}$$\n",
      "$$\\lambda_{\\mathrm{e}}>\\lambda_\\alpha>\\lambda_{\\mathrm{p}}$$\n",
      "$$\\lambda_{\\mathrm{p}}<\\lambda_{\\mathrm{e}}<\\lambda_\\alpha$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda_\\alpha<\\lambda_{\\mathrm{p}}<\\lambda_{\\mathrm{e}}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3vefzw",
    "question": "<p>A proton and an electron have the same de Broglie wavelength. If $$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{p}}$$ and $$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{e}}$$ be the kinetic energies of proton and electron respectively, then choose the correct relation :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{K_p>K_e}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{K_p=K_e}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{p}}<\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{e}}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{p}}=\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{e}}{ }^2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{p}}<\\mathrm{K}_{\\mathrm{e}}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gs90p",
    "question": "<p>A proton and an electron are associated with same de-Broglie wavelength. The ratio of their kinetic energies is:</p>\n<p>(Assume h = 6.63 $$\\times 10^{-34} \\mathrm{~J} \\mathrm{~s}, \\mathrm{~m}_{\\mathrm{e}}=9.0 \\times 10^{-31} \\mathrm{~kg}$$ and $$\\mathrm{m}_{\\mathrm{p}}=1836$$ times $$\\mathrm{m}_{\\mathrm{e}}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: \\frac{1}{1836}$$\n",
      "$$1: \\sqrt{1836}$$\n",
      "$$1: 1836$$\n",
      "$$1: \\frac{1}{\\sqrt{1836}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "matter-waves",
    "solution": "$$1: 1836$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ve4Dqcl01VnIEBou",
    "question": "Photon of frequency $$v$$ has a momentum associated with it. If $$c$$ is the velocity of light, the momentum is ",
    "options": [
      "$$hv/c$$ ",
      "$$v/c$$ ",
      "$$h$$ $$v$$ $$c$$ ",
      "$$hv/{c^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "$$hv/c$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "2cqPDULK6vwwWYVp",
    "question": "If a source of power $$4kW$$ produces $${10^{20}}$$ photons/second, the radiation belongs to a part of the spectrum called ",
    "options": [
      "$$X$$ -rays ",
      "ultraviolet rays ",
      "microwaves ",
      "$$\\gamma $$ - rays "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "$$X$$ -rays "
  },
  {
    "id": "cAS8qWFNS1IIclz7QlAnD",
    "question": "A Laser light of wavelength 660 nm is used to weld Retina detachment. If a Laser pulse of width 60 ms and power 0.5 kW is used the approximate number of photons in the pulse are :\n<br/><br/>[Take Planck's constant h $$=$$ 6.62 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js]",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>20</sup> ",
      "10<sup>18</sup>",
      "10<sup>22</sup>",
      "10<sup>19</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "10<sup>20</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "xhjABBvSWgvzpuiAtKafb",
    "question": "In a Frank-Hertz experiment, an electron of energy 5.6 eV passes through mercury vapour and emerges with an energy 0.7 eV. The minimum wavelength of photons emitted by mercury atoms is close to : ",
    "options": [
      "2020 nm",
      "250 nm",
      "1700 nm",
      "220 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "250 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "EIMP9g235QDa5kzPAj3rsa0w2w9jwzmh7cr",
    "question": "A 2 mW laser operates at wavelength of 500 nm. The number of photons that will be emitted per second is :\n[Given Planck's constant h = 6.6 × 10<sup>–34</sup> Js, speed of light c = 3.0 × 10<sup>8</sup>\n m/s]",
    "options": [
      "5 × 10<sup>15</sup>",
      "1.5 × 10<sup>16</sup>",
      "1 × 10<sup>16</sup>",
      "2 × 10<sup>16</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "5 × 10<sup>15</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "8tswxI2jopQMLVFddKjgy2xukf3r3te7",
    "question": "Two sources of light emit X-rays of wavelength 1 nm and visible light of wavelength 500 nm, respectively. Both the sources emit light of the same power 200 W. The ratio of the number density of\nphotons of X-rays to the number density of photons of the visible light of the given wavelengths is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {500}}$$",
      "500",
      "250",
      "$${1 \\over {250}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {500}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jv7KIdATlIqsD0vR9V1klrjq8yv",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : <br/><br/>Statement I : Two photons having equal linear momenta have equal wavelengths.<br/><br/>Statement II : If the wavelength of photon is decreased, then the momentum and energy of a photon will also decrease.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "hetGVoncSv4VpsJYOq1klule2e4",
    "question": "The recoil speed of a hydrogen atom after it emits a photon in going from n = 5 state to n = 1 state will be :",
    "options": [
      "4.34 m/s",
      "2.19 m/s",
      "3.25 m/s",
      "4.17 m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "4.17 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjni7lb",
    "question": "A free electron of 2.6 eV energy collides with a H<sup>+</sup> ion. This results in the formation of a hydrogen atom in the first excited state and a photon is released. Find the frequency of the emitted photon. (h = 6.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js)",
    "options": [
      "1.45 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>16</sup> MHz",
      "0.19 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup> MHz",
      "1.45 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup> MHz",
      "9.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>27</sup> MHz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "1.45 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup> MHz"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w35hlf",
    "question": "<p>A source of monochromatic light liberates 9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>20</sup> photon per second with wavelength 600 nm when operated at 400 W. The number of photons emitted per second with wavelength of 800 nm by the source of monochromatic light operating at same power will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "12 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>20</sup>",
      "6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>20</sup>",
      "9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>20</sup>",
      "24 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>20</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "12 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>20</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gk1twe",
    "question": "<p>A parallel beam of light of wavelength $$900 \\mathrm{~nm}$$ and intensity $$100 \\,\\mathrm{Wm}^{-2}$$ is incident on a surface perpendicular to the beam. The number of photons crossing $$1 \\mathrm{~cm}^{2}$$ area perpendicular to the beam in one second is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3 \\times 10^{16}$$",
      "$$4.5 \\times 10^{16}$$",
      "$$4.5 \\times 10^{17}$$",
      "$$4.5 \\times 10^{20}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "$$4.5 \\times 10^{16}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpmm2fe",
    "question": "<p>If a source of electromagnetic radiation having power $$15 \\mathrm{~kW}$$ produces $$10^{16}$$ photons per second, the radiation belongs to a part of spectrum is.</p>\n<p>(Take Planck constant $$h=6 \\times 10^{-34} \\mathrm{Js}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "Gamma rays",
      "Radio waves",
      "Micro waves",
      "Ultraviolet rays"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "Gamma rays"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr0wjkf",
    "question": "<p>A small object at rest, absorbs a light pulse of power $$20 \\mathrm{~mW}$$ and duration $$300 \\mathrm{~ns}$$. Assuming speed of light as $$3 \\times 10^{8} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$, the momentum of the object becomes equal to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1 \\times 10^{-17} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$0.5 \\times 10^{-17} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$3 \\times 10^{-17} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$2 \\times 10^{-17} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "$$2 \\times 10^{-17} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsamftqb",
    "question": "Monochromatic light of frequency $6 \\times 10^{14} \\mathrm{~Hz}$ is produced by a laser. The power emitted is $2 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~W}$. <br/><br/>How many photons per second on an average, are emitted by the source ?<br/><br/>\n(Given $\\mathrm{h}=6.63 \\times 10^{-34} \\mathrm{Js}$ )",
    "options": [
      "$5 \\times 10^{15}$",
      "$7 \\times 10^{16}$",
      "$6 \\times 10^{15}$",
      "$9 \\times 10^{18}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "$5 \\times 10^{15}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsan4w1v",
    "question": "Conductivity of a photodiode starts changing only if the wavelength of incident light is less than $660 \\mathrm{~nm}$. The band gap of photodiode is found to be $\\left(\\frac{\\mathrm{X}}{8}\\right) \\mathrm{eV}$. The value of $\\mathrm{X}$ is :<br/><br/>\n(Given, $\\mathrm{h}=6.6 \\times 10^{-34} \\mathrm{Js}, \\mathrm{e}=1.6 \\times 10^{-19} \\mathrm{C}$ )",
    "options": [
      "11",
      "13",
      "15",
      "21"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "15"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfm1x4p",
    "question": "<p>Two sources of light emit with a power of $$200 \\mathrm{~W}$$. The ratio of number of photons of visible light emitted by each source having wavelengths $$300 \\mathrm{~nm}$$ and $$500 \\mathrm{~nm}$$ respectively, will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$5: 3$$\n",
      "$$3: 5$$\n",
      "$$1: 5$$\n",
      "$$1: 3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "$$3: 5$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg6tja7",
    "question": "<p>If the total energy transferred to a surface in time $$\\mathrm{t}$$ is $$6.48 \\times 10^5 \\mathrm{~J}$$, then the magnitude of the total momentum delivered to this surface for complete absorption will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2.16 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$\n",
      "$$2.46 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$\n",
      "$$1.58 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$\n",
      "$$4.32 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "$$2.16 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc58e61",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following phenomena does not explain by wave nature of light.</p>\n<p>A. reflection</p>\n<p>B. diffraction</p>\n<p>C. photoelectric effect</p>\n<p>D. interference</p>\n<p>E. polarization</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "C only\n",
      "B, D only\n",
      "A, C only\n",
      "E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "particle-nature-of-light-the-photon",
    "solution": "C only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "Qu7xmY1BPotMhtRV",
    "question": "Sodium and copper have work functions $$2.3$$ $$eV$$ and $$4.5$$ $$eV$$ respectively. Then the ratio of the wavelengths is nearest to ",
    "options": [
      "$$1:2$$ ",
      "$$4:1$$ ",
      "$$2:1$$ ",
      "$$1:4$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$2:1$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "WitG0xTNyFoJBMVH",
    "question": "Two identical photo-cathodes receive light of frequencies $${f_1}$$ and $${f_2}$$. If the velocities of the photo electrons (of mass $$m$$ ) coming out are respectively $${v_1}$$ and $${v_2},$$ then ",
    "options": [
      "$$v_1^2 - v_2^2 = {{2h} \\over m}\\left( {{f_1} - {f_2}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${v_1} + {v_2} = {\\left[ {{{2h} \\over m}\\left( {{f_1} + {f_2}} \\right)} \\right]^{1/2}}$$",
      "$$v_1^2 + v_2^2 = {{2h} \\over m}\\left( {{f_1} + {f_2}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${v_1} - {v_2} = {\\left[ {{{2h} \\over m}\\left( {{f_1} - {f_2}} \\right)} \\right]^{1/2}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$v_1^2 - v_2^2 = {{2h} \\over m}\\left( {{f_1} - {f_2}} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "rPQL3Teyas56lGkW",
    "question": "The work function of  a substance is $$4.0$$ $$eV.$$ The longest wavelength of light that can cause photo-electron emission from this substance is approximately. ",
    "options": [
      "$$310$$ $$nm$$ ",
      "$$400$$ $$nm$$",
      "$$540$$ $$nm$$ ",
      "$$220$$ $$nm$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$310$$ $$nm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "nrbseZ6OuEZem1EX",
    "question": "According to Einstein's photoelectric equation, the plot of the kinetic energy of the emitted photo electrons from a metal $$Vs$$ the frequency, of the incident radiation gives as straight the whose slope ",
    "options": [
      "depends both on the intensity of the radiation and the metal used",
      "depends on the intensity of the radiation ",
      "depends on the nature of the metal used ",
      "is the same for the all metals and independent of the intensity of the radiation "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "is the same for the all metals and independent of the intensity of the radiation "
  },
  {
    "id": "FFDQfsoCPCowNhlI",
    "question": "A photocell is illuminated by a small bright source placed $$1$$ $$m$$ away. When the same source of light is placed $${1 \\over 2}$$ $$m$$ away, the number of electrons emitted by photo-cathode would ",
    "options": [
      "increases by a factor of $$4$$ ",
      "decreases by a factor of $$4$$ ",
      "increases by a factor of $$2$$ ",
      "decreases by a factor of $$2$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "increases by a factor of $$4$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "EPhe4z1UCmTDtBHI",
    "question": "The time taken by a photoelectron to come out after the photon strikes is approximately ",
    "options": [
      "$${10^{ - 4}}\\,s$$ ",
      "$${10^{ - 10}}\\,s$$ ",
      "$${10^{ - 16}}\\,s$$ ",
      "$${10^{ - 1}}\\,s$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$${10^{ - 10}}\\,s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "GXDVcfVoBoEdGtOH",
    "question": "The threshold frequency for a metallic surface corresponds to an energy of $$6.2$$ $$eV$$ and the stopping potential for a radiation incident on this surface is $$5V.$$ The incident radiation lies in ",
    "options": [
      "ultra-violet region ",
      "infra-red region ",
      "visible region ",
      "$$x$$-ray region"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "ultra-violet region "
  },
  {
    "id": "esXlVYLZzlglWc70",
    "question": "The surface of a metal is illuminated with the light of $$400$$ $$nm.$$ The kinetic energy of the ejected photoelectrons was found to be $$1.68$$ $$eV.$$ The work function of the metal is : $$\\left( {hc = 1240eV.nm} \\right)$$ ",
    "options": [
      "$$1.41$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$1.51$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$1.68$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$3.09$$ $$eV$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$1.41$$ $$eV$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ZCDp3u5CQLvArb4N",
    "question": "<b>Statement - $$1$$ :</b> When ultraviolet light  is incident on a  photocell, its stopping potential is $${V_0}$$ and the maximum kinetic energy of the photoelectrons is $${K_{\\max }}$$. When the ultraviolet light is replaced by $$X$$-rays, both $${V_0}$$ and $${K_{\\max }}$$ increase.\n<p><b>Statement - $$2$$ :</b> Photoelectrons are emitted with speeds ranging from zero to a maximum value because of the range  of frequencies present in the incident light. </p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true; Statement - $$2$$  is the correct explanation of Statement - $$1$$ ",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true; Statement - $$2$$  is not the correct explanation of Statement - $$1$$ ",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is is false, Statement - $$2$$ is true ",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is is true, Statement - $$2$$ is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true; Statement - $$2$$  is not the correct explanation of Statement - $$1$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "AS1zkE4MlKRcGlPg",
    "question": "This question has Statement - $$1$$ and Statement - $$2$$. Of the four choices given after the statements, choose the one that best describes the two statements.\n<p><b>Statement - $$1$$ : </b> A metallic surface is irradiated by a monochromatic light of frequency $$v &gt; {v_0}$$ (the threshold frequency). The maximum kinetic energy and the stopping potential are $${K_{\\max }}$$ and $${V_0}$$ respectively. If the frequency incident on the surface is doubled, both the $${K_{\\max }}$$ anmd $${V_0}$$ are also doubled.\n<br/><b>Statement - $$2$$ : </b> The maximum kinetic energy and the stopping potential of photoelectrons emitted from a surface are linearly dependent on the frequency of incident light. </p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is the correct explanation of Statement - $$1$$.",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is not the correct explanation of Statement - $$1$$.",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is false, Statement - $$2$$ is true.",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "Statement - $$1$$ is false, Statement - $$2$$ is true."
  },
  {
    "id": "Xik8Lah1nucIfYoB",
    "question": "Radiation of wavelength $$\\lambda ,$$ is incident on a photocell. The fastest emitted electron has speed $$v.$$ If the wavelength is changed to $${{3\\lambda } \\over 4},$$ the speed of the fastest emitted electron will be:",
    "options": [
      "$$ = v{\\left( {{4 \\over 3}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ ",
      "$$ = v{\\left( {{3 \\over 4}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ ",
      "$$ &gt; v{\\left( {{4 \\over 3}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ ",
      "$$ &lt; v{\\left( {{4 \\over 3}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$ &gt; v{\\left( {{4 \\over 3}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "nKS3T7KHG0Trb0oXXc7Mw",
    "question": "When photons of wavelength $${\\lambda _1}$$ are incident on an isolated sphere, the corresponding stopping potential is found to be V. When photons of wavelength $${\\lambda _2}$$ are used, the corresponding stopping potential was thrice that of the above value. If light of wavelength $${\\lambda _3}$$ is used then find the stopping potential for this case :",
    "options": [
      "$${{hc} \\over e}\\left[ {{1 \\over {{\\lambda _3}}} - {1 \\over {{\\lambda _2}}} - {1 \\over {{\\lambda _1}}}} \\right]$$",
      "$${{hc} \\over e}\\left[ {{1 \\over {{\\lambda _3}}} + {1 \\over {{\\lambda _2}}} - {1 \\over {{\\lambda _1}}}} \\right]$$",
      "$${{hc} \\over e}\\left[ {{1 \\over {{\\lambda _3}}} + {1 \\over {2{\\lambda _2}}} - {3 \\over {2{\\lambda _1}}}} \\right]$$",
      "$${{hc} \\over e}\\left[ {{1 \\over {{\\lambda _3}}} + {1 \\over {2{\\lambda _2}}} - {1 \\over {{\\lambda _1}}}} \\right]$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$${{hc} \\over e}\\left[ {{1 \\over {{\\lambda _3}}} + {1 \\over {2{\\lambda _2}}} - {3 \\over {2{\\lambda _1}}}} \\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "b6r7lKqAd52ksTxDlvZYH",
    "question": "A photoelectric surface is illuminated successively by monochromatic light of wavelengths $$\\lambda $$ and $${\\lambda  \\over 2}.$$ If the maximum kinetic energy of the emitted photoelectrons in the second case is 3 times that in the first case, the work function of the surface is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{hc} \\over {3\\lambda }}$$ ",
      "$${{hc} \\over {2\\lambda }}$$",
      "$${{hc} \\over {\\lambda }}$$",
      "$${3\\,{hc} \\over {\\lambda }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$${{hc} \\over {2\\lambda }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "sdlfBQAkq7QkYgbIpK1YA",
    "question": "The maximum velocity of the photoelectrons emitted from the surface is v when light of frequency n falls on a metal surface. If the incident frequency is increased to 3n, the maximum velocity of the ejected photoelectrons will be :",
    "options": [
      "less than $$\\sqrt 3 $$ v",
      "v",
      "more than $$\\sqrt 3 \\,v$$ ",
      "equal to  $$\\sqrt 3 \\,v$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "more than $$\\sqrt 3 \\,v$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "yfE4GlkMrqBbtt2xt24Au",
    "question": "The electric field of light wave is given as\n$$$\\overrightarrow E  = {10^{ - 3}}\\cos \\left( {{{2\\pi x} \\over {5 \\times {{10}^{ - 7}}}} - 2\\pi  \\times 6 \\times {{10}^{14}}t} \\right)\\mathop x\\limits^ \\wedge  {{\\rm N} \\over C}$$$\n\nThis\nlight falls on a metal plate of work function\n2eV. The stopping potential of the photoelectrons\nis :<br/>\nGiven, E (in eV) =\n12375/$$\\lambda $$(inÅ)",
    "options": [
      "2.48 V",
      "0.48 V",
      "0.72 V",
      "2.0 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "0.48 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "XwoeKLRmjgbzuA46oV18hoxe66ijvzt2m15",
    "question": "In a photoelectric effect experiment the\nthreshold wavelength of the light is 380 nm. If\nthe wavelentgh of incident light is 260 nm, the\nmaximum kinetic energy of emitted electrons\nwill be:<br/>\nGiven E (in eV) = 1237/$$\\lambda $$ (in nm)",
    "options": [
      "4.5 eV",
      "15.1 eV",
      "3.0 eV",
      "1.5 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "1.5 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "rlPSZjNPZ5tiIiyRtIMl8",
    "question": "When a certain photosensitive surface is illuminated with monochromatic light of frequency v, the stopping\npotential for the current is –V<sub>0</sub>/2. When the surface is illuminated by monochromatic light of frequency v/2, the stopping potential is – V<sub>0</sub>. The threshold frequency for photoelectric emission is : ",
    "options": [
      "2$$v$$",
      "$${4 \\over 3}v$$",
      "$${{3v} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{5v} \\over 3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$${{3v} \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "uVxqGPYVVtTEREPxWPrIP",
    "question": "A metal plate of area 1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup> m<sup>2</sup> is illuminated by a radiation of intensity 16 mW/m<sup>2</sup>. The work function of the metal is 5 eV. The energy of the incident photons is 10 eV and only 10% of it produces photo electrons.\nThe number of emitted photoelectrons per second and their maximum energy, respectively, will be ",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>14</sup> and 10 eV",
      "10<sup>12</sup> and 5 eV",
      "10<sup>11</sup> and 5 eV",
      "10<sup>10</sup> and 5 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "10<sup>11</sup> and 5 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "jGjrJ5raJzrdb982WUc10",
    "question": "The magnetic field associated with a light wave is given, at the origin, by B = B<sub>0</sub> [sin(3.14 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>7</sup>)ct + sin(6.28 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>7</sup>)ct]. If this light falls on a silver plate having a work function of 4.7 eV, what will be the maximum kinetic energy of the photo electrons ? \n<br/>(Take c = 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, h = 6.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup>J-s)",
    "options": [
      "6.82 eV",
      "12.5 eV",
      "8.52 eV",
      "7.72 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "7.72 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "7aPbDyHmLKoT8vTkhgQU8",
    "question": "Surface of certain metal is first illuminated with light of wavelength $$\\lambda $$<sub>1</sub> = 350 nm and then, by light of wavelength $$\\lambda $$<sub>2</sub> = 540 nm. It is found that the maximum speed of the photo electrons in the two cases differ by a factor of 2. The work function of the metal (in eV) is close to : \n<br/><br/>(Energy of photon n = $${{1240} \\over {\\lambda (in\\,mm)}}$$eV)",
    "options": [
      "1.8",
      "2.5",
      "5.6",
      "1.4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "1.8"
  },
  {
    "id": "HYoxdPryi2r6KQbvsZIj5",
    "question": "In a photoelectric experiment, the wavelength of the light incident on a metal is changed from 300 nm to 400 nm. The decrease in the stopping potential is close to:  ($${{{hc} \\over e}}$$ = 1240 nm eV)",
    "options": [
      "0.5 V",
      "1.0 V",
      "2.0 V",
      "1.5 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "1.0 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "8mkVsgrBxoOjNALFxOjgy2xukf14jl8g",
    "question": "When the wavelength of radiation falling on a metal is changed from 500 nm to 200 nm, the\nmaximum kinetic energy of the photoelectrons becomes three times larger. The work function of\nthe metal is close to :",
    "options": [
      "1.02 eV",
      "0.81 eV",
      "0.61 eV",
      "0.52 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "0.61 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "2lAOp8CWialPwm69UD7k9k2k5ielbrc",
    "question": "Radiation, with wavelength 6561 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$ falls on a\nmetal surface to produce photoelectrons. The\nelectrons are made to enter a uniform magnetic\nfield of 3 × 10<sup>–4</sup> T. If the radius of the largest\ncircular path followed by the electrons is\n10 mm, the work function of the metal is\nclose to :",
    "options": [
      "1.8eV",
      "0.8eV",
      "1.1eV",
      "1.6eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "1.1eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "yDaeUpXTllB32t3iK67k9k2k5gv3pf7",
    "question": "When photon of energy 4.0 eV strikes the\nsurface of a metal A, the ejected photoelectrons\nhave maximum kinetic energy T<sub>A</sub> eV end\nde-Broglie wavelength $$\\lambda _A$$. The maximum\nkinetic energy of photoelectrons liberated from\nanother metal B by photon of energy 4.50 eV\nis T<sub>B</sub> = (T<sub>A</sub> – 1.5) eV. If the de-Broglie\nwavelength of these photoelectrons $$\\lambda _B$$ = 2$$\\lambda _A$$,\nthen the work function of metal B is :",
    "options": [
      "1.5eV",
      "4eV",
      "2eV",
      "3eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "4eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "DlwRrPTsfuVvPXBTfA1klt3cieu",
    "question": "The stopping potential for electrons emitted from a photosensitive surface illuminated by light of wavelength 491 nm is 0.710 V. When the incident wavelength is changed to a new value, the stopping potential is 1.43 V. The new wavelength is :",
    "options": [
      "400 nm",
      "329 nm",
      "309 nm",
      "382 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "382 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "63J8F1m6HiqR6xSyPO1kmhownx8",
    "question": "The stopping potential in the context of photoelectric effect depends on the following property of incident electromagnetic radiation :",
    "options": [
      "Phase",
      "Frequency",
      "Amnplitude",
      "Intensity"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "Frequency"
  },
  {
    "id": "RvTWNmgapIuHf2mMkm1kmkag4h0",
    "question": "Two identical photocathodes receive the light of frequencies f<sub>1</sub> and f<sub>2</sub> respectively. If the velocities of the photo-electrons coming out are v<sub>1</sub> and v<sub>2</sub> respectively, then",
    "options": [
      "$${v_1} - {v_2} = {\\left[ {{{2h} \\over m}({f_1} - {f_2})} \\right]^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$$v_1^2 + v_2^2 = {{2h} \\over m}[{f_1} + {f_2}]$$",
      "$${v_1} + {v_2} = {\\left[ {{{2h} \\over m}({f_1} + {f_2})} \\right]^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$$v_1^2 - v_2^2 = {{2h} \\over m}[{f_1} - {f_2}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$v_1^2 - v_2^2 = {{2h} \\over m}[{f_1} - {f_2}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "FvRTqiBMxPlxQuxmAz1krpncjiy",
    "question": "The radiation corresponding to 3 $$\\to$$ 2 transition of a hydrogen atom falls on a gold surface to generate photoelectrons. The electrons are passed through a magnetic field of 5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> T. Assume that the radius of the largest circular path followed by these electrons is 7 mm, the work function of the metal is : (Mass of electron = 9.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$31</sup> kg)",
    "options": [
      "1.36 eV",
      "1.88 eV",
      "0.82 eV",
      "0.16 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "0.82 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krwafg06",
    "question": "When radiation of wavelength $$\\lambda$$ is incident on a metallic surface, the stopping potential of ejected photoelectrons is 4.8 V. If the same surface is illuminated by radiation of double the previous wavelength, then the stopping potential becomes 1.6 V. The threshold wavelength of the metal is :",
    "options": [
      "2$$\\lambda$$",
      "4$$\\lambda$$",
      "8$$\\lambda$$",
      "6$$\\lambda$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "4$$\\lambda$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks0jshx1",
    "question": "An electron and proton are separated by a large distance. The electron starts approaching the proton with energy 3 eV. The proton captures the electron and forms a hydrogen atom in second excited state. The resulting photon is incident on a photosensitive metal of threshold wavelength 4000$$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$. What is the maximum kinetic energy of the emitted photoelectron? ",
    "options": [
      "7.61 eV",
      "1.41 eV",
      "3.3 eV",
      "No photoelectron would be emitted"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "1.41 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktac8sij",
    "question": "In a photoelectric experiment ultraviolet light of wavelength 280 nm is used with lithium cathode having work function $$\\phi$$ = 2.5 eV. If the wavelength of incident light is switched to 400 nm, find out the change in the stopping potential. (h = 6.63 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js, c = 3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "1.3 V",
      "1.1 V",
      "1.9 V",
      "0.6 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "1.3 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kte0pcwe",
    "question": "In a photoelectric experiment, increasing the intensity of incident light :",
    "options": [
      "increases the number of photons incident and also increases the K.E. of the ejected electrons",
      "increases the frequency of photons incident and increases the K.E. of the ejected electrons",
      "increases the frequency of photons incident and the K.E. of the ejected electrons remains unchanged",
      "increases the number of photons incident and the K.E. of the ejected electrons remains unchanged"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "increases the number of photons incident and the K.E. of the ejected electrons remains unchanged"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfmeraj",
    "question": "A monochromatic neon lamp with wavelength of 670.5 nm illuminates a photo-sensitive material which has a stopping voltage of 0.48 V. What will be the stopping voltage if the source light is changed with another source of wavelength of 474.6 nm?",
    "options": [
      "0.96 V",
      "1.25 V",
      "0.24 V",
      "1.5 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "1.25 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5474aqk",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R :</p>\n<p>Assertion A : The photoelectric effect does not takes place, if the energy of the incident radiation is less than the work function of a metal.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Kinetic energy of the photoelectrons is zero, if the energy of the incident radiation is equal to the work function of a metal.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is not the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is correct but R is not correct.",
      "A is not correct but R is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct but R is not the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54uuc8l",
    "question": "<p>The electric field at a point associated with a light wave is given by</p>\n<p>E = 200 [sin (6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup>)t + sin (9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>15</sup>)t] Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup></p>\n<p>Given : h = 4.14 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$15</sup> eVs</p>\n<p>If this light falls on a metal surface having a work function of 2.50 eV, the maximum kinetic energy of the photoelectrons will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.90 eV",
      "3.27 eV",
      "3.60 eV",
      "3.42 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "3.42 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55km7fv",
    "question": "<p>Let K<sub>1</sub> and K<sub>2</sub> be the maximum kinetic energies of photo-electrons emitted when two monochromatic beams of wavelength $$\\lambda$$<sub>1</sub> and $$\\lambda$$<sub>2</sub>, respectively are incident on a metallic surface. If $$\\lambda$$<sub>1</sub> = 3$$\\lambda$$<sub>2</sub> then :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${K_1} > {{{K_2}} \\over 3}$$",
      "$${K_1} < {{{K_2}} \\over 3}$$",
      "$${K_1} = {{{K_2}} \\over 3}$$",
      "$${K_2} = {{{K_1}} \\over 3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$${K_1} < {{{K_2}} \\over 3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58i6qtp",
    "question": "<p>A metal surface is illuminated by a radiation of wavelength 4500 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$. The ejected photo-electron enters a constant magnetic field of 2 mT making an angle of 90$$^\\circ$$ with the magnetic field. If it starts revolving in a circular path of radius 2 mm, the work function of the metal is approximately :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.36 eV",
      "1.69 eV",
      "2.78 eV",
      "2.23 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "1.36 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bc7yy3",
    "question": "<p>The light of two different frequencies whose photons have energies 3.8 eV and 1.4 eV respectively, illuminate a metallic surface whose work function is 0.6 eV successively. The ratio of maximum speeds of emitted electrons for the two frequencies respectively will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "4 : 1",
      "1 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dz7o9g",
    "question": "<p>A metal exposed to light of wavelength $$800 \\mathrm{~nm}$$ and and emits photoelectrons with a certain kinetic energy. The maximum kinetic energy of photo-electron doubles when light of wavelength $$500 \\mathrm{~nm}$$ is used. The workfunction of the metal is : (Take hc $$=1230 \\,\\mathrm{eV}-\\mathrm{nm}$$ ).</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.537 eV",
      "2.46 eV",
      "0.615 eV",
      "1.23 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "0.615 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6knp3m1",
    "question": "<p>With reference to the observations in photo-electric effect, identify the correct statements from below :</p>\n<p>(A) The square of maximum velocity of photoelectrons varies linearly with frequency of incident light.</p>\n<p>(B) The value of saturation current increases on moving the source of light away from the metal surface.</p>\n<p>(C) The maximum kinetic energy of photo-electrons decreases on decreasing the power of LED (light emitting diode) source of light.</p>\n<p>(D) The immediate emission of photo-electrons out of metal surface can not be explained by particle nature of light/electromagnetic waves.</p>\n<p>(E) Existence of threshold wavelength can not be explained by wave nature of light/ electromagnetic waves.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) and (B) only",
      "(A) and (E) only",
      "(C) and (E) only",
      "(D) and (E) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "(A) and (E) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nsyeeo",
    "question": "<p>Two streams of photons, possessing energies equal to five and ten times the work function of metal are incident on the metal surface successively. The ratio of maximum velocities of the photoelectron emitted, in the two cases respectively, will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 2",
      "1 : 3",
      "2 : 3",
      "3 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "2 : 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p5cftg",
    "question": "<p>The kinetic energy of emitted electron is E when the light incident on the metal has wavelength $$\\lambda$$. To double the kinetic energy, the incident light must have wavelength:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{hc}}{\\mathrm{E} \\lambda-\\mathrm{hc}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{hc} \\lambda}{\\mathrm{E} \\lambda+\\mathrm{hc}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{h} \\lambda}{\\mathrm{E} \\lambda+\\mathrm{hc}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\text { hc } \\lambda}{\\mathrm{E} \\lambda-\\mathrm{hc}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{hc} \\lambda}{\\mathrm{E} \\lambda+\\mathrm{hc}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnxrtpe",
    "question": "<p>The threshold frequency of a metal is $$f_{0}$$. When the light of frequency $$2 f_{0}$$ is incident on the metal plate, the maximum velocity of photoelectrons is $$v_{1}$$. When the frequency of incident radiation is increased to $$5 \\mathrm{f}_{0}$$, the maximum velocity of photoelectrons emitted is $$v_{2}$$. The ratio of $$v_{1}$$ to $$v_{2}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{v_{1}}{v_{2}}=\\frac{1}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{v_{1}}{v_{2}}=\\frac{1}{16}$$",
      "$$\\frac{v_{1}}{v_{2}}=\\frac{1}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{v_{1}}{v_{2}}=\\frac{1}{8}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{v_{1}}{v_{2}}=\\frac{1}{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo68faz",
    "question": "If the two metals $\\mathrm{A}$ and $\\mathrm{B}$ are exposed to radiation of wavelength $350 \\mathrm{~nm}$. The work functions of metals $\\mathrm{A}$ and $\\mathrm{B}$ are $4.8 \\mathrm{eV}$ and $2.2 \\mathrm{eV}$. Then choose the correct option.",
    "options": [
      "Metal B will not emit photo-electrons",
      "Both metals $\\mathrm{A}$ and $\\mathrm{B}$ will not emit photo-electrons",
      "Metal A will not emit photo-electrons\n",
      "Both metals A and B will emit photo-electrons"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "Metal A will not emit photo-electrons\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldspqit2",
    "question": "<p>The threshold wavelength for photoelectric emission from a material is 5500 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$. Photoelectrons will be emitted, when this material is illuminated with monochromatic radiation from a</p>\n<p>A. 75 W infra-red lamp</p>\n<p>B. 10 W infra-red lamp</p>\n<p>C. 75 W ultra-violet lamp</p>\n<p>D. 10 W ultra-violet lamp</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "C only",
      "A and D only",
      "C and D only",
      "B and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "C and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtzi30b",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Stopping potential in photoelectric effect does not depend on the power of the light source.</p>\n<p>Statement II : For a given metal, the maximum kinetic energy of the photoelectron depends on the wavelength of the incident light.</p>\n<p>In the light of above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyd7qac",
    "question": "<p>From the photoelectric effect experiment, following observations are made. Identify which of these are correct.</p>\n<p>A. The stopping potential depends only on the work function of the metal.</p>\n<p>B. The saturation current increases as the intensity of incident light increases.</p>\n<p>C. The maximum kinetic energy of a photo electron depends on the intensity of the incident light.</p>\n<p>D. Photoelectric effect can be explained using wave theory of light.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B, D only",
      "A, C, D only",
      "B, C only",
      "B only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "B only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp0f0jj",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Out of microwaves, infrared rays and ultraviolet rays, ultraviolet rays are the most effective for the emission of electrons from a metallic surface.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Above the threshold frequency, the maximum kinetic energy of photoelectrons is inversely proportional to the frequency of the incident light.</p>\n<p>In the light of above statements, choose the correct answer form the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq1zt66",
    "question": "<p>The difference between threshold wavelengths for two metal surfaces $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$ having work function $$\\phi_{A}=9 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$ and $$\\phi_{B}=4 \\cdot 5 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$ in $$\\mathrm{nm}$$ is:</p>\n<p>$$\\{$$ Given, hc $$=1242 ~\\mathrm{eV} \\mathrm{nm}\\}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "264",
      "138",
      "540",
      "276"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "138"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguy18zk",
    "question": "<p>A metallic surface is illuminated with radiation of wavelength $$\\lambda$$, the stopping potential is $$V_{0}$$. If the same surface is illuminated with radiation of wavelength $$2 \\lambda$$. the stopping potential becomes $$\\frac{V_{o}}{4}$$. The threshold wavelength for this metallic surface will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3 \\lambda$$",
      "$$4 \\lambda$$",
      "$$\\frac{3}{2} \\lambda$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\lambda}{4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$3 \\lambda$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqc48m",
    "question": "<p>In photo electric effect</p>\n<p>A. The photocurrent is proportional to the intensity of the incident radiation</p>\n<p>B. Maximum Kinetic energy with which photoelectrons are emitted depends on the intensity of incident light.</p>\n<p>C. Max. K.E with which photoelectrons are emitted depends on the frequency of incident light.</p>\n<p>D. The emission of photoelectrons require a minimum threshold intensity of incident radiation.</p>\n<p>E. Max. K.E of the photoelectrons is independent of the frequency of the incident light.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and E only",
      "A and B only",
      "B and C only",
      "A and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "A and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh3027a8",
    "question": "<p>The work functions of Aluminium and Gold are $$4.1 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$ and and $$5.1 ~\\mathrm{eV}$$ respectively. The ratio of the slope of the stopping potential versus frequency plot for Gold to that of Aluminium is</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.5",
      "1.24",
      "1",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscpar9g",
    "question": "<p>The threshold frequency of a metal with work function $$6.63 \\mathrm{~eV}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$16 \\times 10^{15} \\mathrm{~Hz}$$\n",
      "$$16 \\times 10^{12} \\mathrm{~Hz}$$\n",
      "$$1.6 \\times 10^{15} \\mathrm{~Hz}$$\n",
      "$$1.6 \\times 10^{12} \\mathrm{~Hz}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$1.6 \\times 10^{15} \\mathrm{~Hz}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd5j857",
    "question": "<p>In a photoelectric effect experiment a light of frequency 1.5 times the threshold frequency is made to fall on the surface of photosensitive material. Now if the frequency is halved and intensity is doubled, the number of photo electrons emitted will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "doubled\n",
      "halved\n",
      "Zero\n",
      "quadrupled"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "Zero\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse6bk56",
    "question": "<p>When a metal surface is illuminated by light of wavelength $$\\lambda$$, the stopping potential is $$8 \\mathrm{~V}$$. When the same surface is illuminated by light of wavelength $$3 \\lambda$$, stopping potential is $$2 \\mathrm{~V}$$. The threshold wavelength for this surface is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "3$$\\lambda$$",
      "9$$\\lambda$$",
      "5$$\\lambda$$",
      "4.5$$\\lambda$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "9$$\\lambda$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgcxy3n",
    "question": "<p>The work function of a substance is $$3.0 \\mathrm{~eV}$$. The longest wavelength of light that can cause the emission of photoelectrons from this substance is approximately;</p>",
    "options": [
      "215 nm",
      "400 nm",
      "414 nm",
      "200 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "414 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwd2ka",
    "question": "<p>UV light of $$4.13 \\mathrm{~eV}$$ is incident on a photosensitive metal surface having work function $$3.13 \\mathrm{~eV}$$. The maximum kinetic energy of ejected photoelectrons will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "4.13 eV",
      "1 eV",
      "7.26 eV",
      "3.13 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "1 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erh5l",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A: Number of photons increases with increase in frequency of light.</p>\n<p>Reason R: Maximum kinetic energy of emitted electrons increases with the frequency of incident radiation.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is not correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is correct.\n",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is not correct.\n",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$.\n",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is not correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is correct.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s20zs",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following statement is not true about stopping potential $$(\\mathrm{V}_0)$$ ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "It depends upon frequency of the incident light.\n",
      "It is $$1 / \\mathrm{e}$$ times the maximum kinetic energy of electrons emitted.\n",
      "It increases with increase in intensity of the incident light.\n",
      "It depends on the nature of emitter material."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "It increases with increase in intensity of the incident light.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb295g9",
    "question": "<p>When UV light of wavelength $$300 \\mathrm{~nm}$$ is incident on the metal surface having work function $$2.13 \\mathrm{~eV}$$, electron emission takes place. The stopping potential is :</p>\n<p>(Given hc $$=1240 \\mathrm{~eV} \\mathrm{~nm}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 V",
      "2 V",
      "4.1 V",
      "1.5 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "2 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57nyr",
    "question": "<p>In photoelectric experiment energy of $$2.48 \\mathrm{~eV}$$ irradiates a photo sensitive material. The stopping potential was measured to be $$0.5 \\mathrm{~V}$$. Work function of the photo sensitive material is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.98 eV",
      "1.68 eV",
      "2.48 eV",
      "0.5 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "dual-nature-of-radiation",
    "topic": "photoelectric-effect",
    "solution": "1.98 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "vfWyqHhFmRrnwIx4",
    "question": "When the current changes from $$ + 2A$$ to $$-2A$$ in $$0.05$$ second, an $$e.m.f.$$ of $$8$$ $$V$$ is inducted in a coil. The coefficient of self- induction of the coil is ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.2H$$ ",
      "$$0.4H$$ ",
      "$$0.8$$ $$H$$ ",
      "$$0.1$$ $$H$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "$$0.1$$ $$H$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "uKfHsKpQPKa8APcC",
    "question": "Two coils are placed close to each other. The mutual inductance of the pair of coils depends upon",
    "options": [
      "the rates at which currents are changing in the two coils ",
      "relative position and orientation of the two coils ",
      "the currents in the two coils ",
      "the materials of the wires of the coils  "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "relative position and orientation of the two coils "
  },
  {
    "id": "FxlPB9jcTe9N6KcM",
    "question": "A coil of inductance $$300$$ $$mH$$ and resistance $$2\\,\\Omega $$ is connected to a source of voltage $$2$$ $$V$$. The current reaches half of its steady state value in ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.1$$ $$s$$ ",
      "$$0.05$$ $$s$$ ",
      "$$0.3$$ $$s$$ ",
      "$$0.15$$ $$s$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "$$0.1$$ $$s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "yhQHBFLrc6kZBeGI",
    "question": "Which of the following units denotes the dimension $${{M{L^2}} \\over {{Q^2}}}$$, where $$Q$$ denotes the electric charge? ",
    "options": [
      "$$Wb/{m^2}$$ ",
      "Henry $$(H)$$ ",
      "$$H/{m^2}$$",
      "Weber $$(Wb)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "Henry $$(H)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "n9Ju0KjDnGigKZZU",
    "question": "An ideal coil of $$10H$$ is connected in series with a resistance of $$5\\Omega $$ and a battery of $$5V$$. $$2$$ second after the connection is made, the current flowing in ampere in the circuit is ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {1 - {e^{ - 1}}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {1 - e} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$e$$ ",
      "$${{e^{ - 1}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {1 - {e^{ - 1}}} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "xxjSa907za7ZQy9V",
    "question": "Two coaxial solenoids are made by winding thin insulated wire over a pipe of cross-sectional area $$A=$$ $$10\\,\\,c{m^2}$$ and  length $$=20$$ $$cm$$ . If one of the solenoid has $$300$$ turns and the other $$400$$ turns, their mutual inductance is <br/>$$\\left( {{\\mu _0} = 4\\pi  \\times {{10}^{ - 7}}\\,Tm\\,{A^{ - 1}}} \\right)$$  ",
    "options": [
      "$$2.4\\pi  \\times {10^{ - 5}}H$$ ",
      "$$4.8\\pi  \\times {10^{ - 4}}H$$ ",
      "$$4.8\\pi  \\times {10^{ - 5}}H$$ ",
      "$$2.4\\pi  \\times {10^{ - 4}}H$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "$$2.4\\pi  \\times {10^{ - 4}}H$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "irnszdUGj0LIsKov",
    "question": "Two coaxial solenoids of different radius carry current $$I$$ in the same direction. $$\\overrightarrow {{F_1}} $$ be the magnetic force on the inner solenoid due to the outer one and $$\\overrightarrow {{F_2}} $$ be the magnetic force on the outer solenoid due to the inner one. Then : ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow {{F_1}} $$  is radially in wards and $$\\overrightarrow {{F_2}}  = 0$$ ",
      "$$\\overrightarrow {{F_1}} $$  is radially outwards and $$\\overrightarrow {{F_2}}  = 0$$ ",
      "$$\\overrightarrow {{F_1}}  = \\overrightarrow {{F_2}}  = 0$$ ",
      "$$\\overrightarrow {{F_1}} $$ is radially inwards and $$\\overrightarrow {{F_2}} $$ is radially outards "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow {{F_1}}  = \\overrightarrow {{F_2}}  = 0$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "3vZjqnMh8d7OkCEtKaCgm",
    "question": "A small circular loop of wire of radius a is located at the centre of a much larger circular wire loop of radius b. The two loops are in the same plane. The outer loop of radius b carries an alternating current I = I<sub>o</sub> cos ($$\\omega $$t). The emf induced in the smaller inner loop is nearly : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\pi {\\mu _o}{I_o}} \\over 2}.{{{a^2}} \\over b}\\,\\omega \\sin \\left( {\\omega t} \\right)$$",
      "$${{\\pi {\\mu _o}{I_o}} \\over 2}.{{{a^2}} \\over b}\\,\\omega \\cos \\left( {\\omega t} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$\\pi {\\mu _o}{I_o}\\,{{{a^2}} \\over b}\\omega \\sin \\left( {\\omega t} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${{\\pi {\\mu _o}{I_o}\\,{b^2}} \\over a}\\omega \\cos \\left( {\\omega t} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "$${{\\pi {\\mu _o}{I_o}} \\over 2}.{{{a^2}} \\over b}\\,\\omega \\sin \\left( {\\omega t} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "cBSvlyrMPPjhU4YyaaDFY",
    "question": "There are two long co-axial solenoids of same length $$l$$. The inner and outer coils have radii r<sub>1</sub> and r<sub>2</sub> and number of turns per unit length n<sub>1</sub> and n<sub>2</sub>, respectively. The ratio of mutual inductance to the self - inductance of the inner-coil is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{n_2}} \\over {{n_1}}}.{{{r_2}^2} \\over {{r_1}^2}}$$",
      "$${{{n_2}} \\over {{n_1}}}$$",
      "$${{{n_1}} \\over {{n_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{n_2}} \\over {{n_1}}}.{{{r_1}} \\over {{r_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "$${{{n_2}} \\over {{n_1}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "IcSQGRlXSXy4MRyzYODvD",
    "question": "Two coils 'P' and 'Q' are separated by some\ndistance. When a current of 3 A flows through\ncoil 'P', a magnetic flux of 10<sup>–3</sup> Wb passes\nthrough 'Q'. No current is passed through 'Q'.\nWhen no current passes through 'P' and a\ncurrent of 2 A passes through 'Q', the flux\nthrough 'P' is :-",
    "options": [
      "3.67 × 10<sup>–4</sup> Wb",
      "3.67 × 10<sup>–3</sup> Wb",
      "6.67 × 10<sup>–4</sup> Wb",
      "6.67 × 10<sup>–3</sup> Wb"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "6.67 × 10<sup>–4</sup> Wb"
  },
  {
    "id": "G6knEI7jVv54jc1vhHZlm",
    "question": "The total number of turns and cross-section area\nin a solenoid is fixed. However, its length L is varied\nby adjusting the separation between windings. The\ninductance of solenoid will be proportional to :",
    "options": [
      "1/L<sup>2</sup>",
      "1/L",
      "L",
      "L<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "1/L"
  },
  {
    "id": "yCabWsK3vTgWABXLGzecc",
    "question": "A copper wire is wound on a wooden frame, whose shape is that of an equilateral triangle. If the linear\ndimension of each side of the frame is increased by a factor of 3, keeping the number of turns of the coil per\nunit length of the frame the same, then the self inductance of the coil: \n",
    "options": [
      "decreases by a factor of $$9\\sqrt 3 $$",
      "increases by a factor of 27",
      "decreases by a factor of 9",
      "increases by a factor of  3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "increases by a factor of  3"
  },
  {
    "id": "BkNuOWmJDOUd60izfKnnE",
    "question": "The self induced emf of a coil is 25 volts. When the current in it is changed at uniform rate from 10 A to 25 A in 1s, the change in the energy of the inductance is -\n",
    "options": [
      "740 J",
      "637.5 J",
      "540 J",
      "437.5 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "437.5 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "3LTmhImqV9RuPxxjym1kmlw2i3l",
    "question": "The time taken for the magnetic energy to reach 25% of its maximum value, when a solenoid of resistance R, inductance L is connected to a battery, is :",
    "options": [
      "infinite",
      "$${L \\over R}$$ ln10",
      "$${L \\over R}$$ ln2",
      "$${L \\over R}$$ ln5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "$${L \\over R}$$ ln2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktabt77x",
    "question": "An inductor coil stores 64 J of magnetic field energy and dissipates energy at the rate of 640 W when a current of 8A is passed through it. If this coil is joined across an ideal battery, find the time constant of the circuit in seconds :",
    "options": [
      "0.4",
      "0.8",
      "0.125",
      "0.2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "0.2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth3zfh0",
    "question": "A small square loop of side 'a' and one turn is placed inside a larger square loop of side b and one turn (b &gt;&gt; a). The two loops are coplanar with their centres coinciding. If a current I is passed in the square loop of side 'b', then the coefficient of mutual inductance between the two loops is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\mu _0}} \\over {4\\pi }}8\\sqrt 2 {{{a^2}} \\over b}$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}} \\over {4\\pi }}{{8\\sqrt 2 } \\over a}$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}} \\over {4\\pi }}8\\sqrt 2 {{{b^2}} \\over a}$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}} \\over {4\\pi }}{{8\\sqrt 2 } \\over b}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "$${{{\\mu _0}} \\over {4\\pi }}8\\sqrt 2 {{{a^2}} \\over b}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnyv190",
    "question": "$12 \\mathrm{~V}$ battery connected to a coil of resistance $6 \\Omega$ through a switch, drives a constant current in the circuit. The switch is opened in $1 \\mathrm{~ms}$. The emf induced across the coil is $20 \\mathrm{~V}$. The inductance of the coil is :",
    "options": [
      "$5 ~ \\mathrm{mH}$",
      "$8 ~\\mathrm{mH}$",
      "$10~ \\mathrm{mH}$",
      "$12 ~\\mathrm{mH}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "$10~ \\mathrm{mH}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsan61ku",
    "question": "A transformer has an efficiency of $80 \\%$ and works at $10 \\mathrm{~V}$ and $4 \\mathrm{~kW}$. If the secondary voltage is $240 \\mathrm{~V}$, then the current in the secondary coil is :",
    "options": [
      "$1.33 \\mathrm{~A}$",
      "$13.33 \\mathrm{~A}$",
      "$1.59 \\mathrm{~A}$",
      "$15.1 \\mathrm{~A}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "$13.33 \\mathrm{~A}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb295dx",
    "question": "<p>In a coil, the current changes from $$-2 \\mathrm{~A}$$ to $$+2 \\mathrm{~A}$$ in $$0.2 \\mathrm{~s}$$ and induces an emf of $$0.1 \\mathrm{~V}$$. The self inductance of the coil is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 mH",
      "2.5 mH",
      "1 mH",
      "5 mH"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "inductance-(self-and-mutual)",
    "solution": "5 mH"
  },
  {
    "id": "1jpI7M7Egal8X9QL",
    "question": "In a uniform magnetic field of induction $$B$$ a wire in the form of a semicircle of radius $$r$$ rotates about the diameter of the circle with an angular frequency $$\\omega .$$ The axis of rotation is perpendicular to the field. If the total resistance of the circuit is $$R,$$ the mean power generated per period of rotation is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{{\\left( {B\\pi r\\omega } \\right)}^2}} \\over {2R}}$$ ",
      "$${{{{\\left( {B\\pi {r^2}\\omega } \\right)}^2}} \\over {8R}}$$ ",
      "$${{B\\pi {r^2}\\omega } \\over {2R}}$$ ",
      "$${{{{\\left( {B\\pi r{\\omega ^2}} \\right)}^2}} \\over {8R}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "$${{{{\\left( {B\\pi {r^2}\\omega } \\right)}^2}} \\over {8R}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "U0L4kw1ReNaC9PQF",
    "question": "A coil having $$n$$ turns and resistance $$R\\Omega $$ is connected with a galvanometer of resistance $$4R\\Omega .$$ This combination is moved in time $$t$$ seconds from a magnetic field $${W_1}$$ weber to $${W_2}$$ weber. The induced current in the circuit is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\left( {{W_2} - {W_1}} \\right)} \\over {Rnt}}$$ ",
      "$$ - {{n\\left( {{W_2} - {W_1}} \\right)} \\over {5\\,\\,Rt}}$$ ",
      "$$ - {{\\left( {{W_2} - {W_1}} \\right)} \\over {5\\,\\,Rnt}}$$ ",
      "$$ - {{n\\left( {{W_2} - {W_1}} \\right)} \\over {Rt}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "$$ - {{n\\left( {{W_2} - {W_1}} \\right)} \\over {5\\,\\,Rt}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ItdkA2UL44A1iA1b",
    "question": "The flux linked with a coil at any instant $$'t'$$ is given by \n<br/>$$\\phi  = 10{t^2} - 50t + 250$$ \n<br/>The induced $$emf$$ at $$t=3s$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$-190$$ $$V$$ ",
      "$$-10$$ $$V$$ ",
      "$$10$$ $$V$$ ",
      "$$190$$ $$V$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "$$-10$$ $$V$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "t535UqWrP4k8kuJP",
    "question": "A coil is suspended in a uniform magnetic field, with the plane of the coil parallel to the magnetic lines of force. When a current is passed through the coil it starts oscillating; It is very difficult to stop. But if an aluminium plate is placed near to the coil, it stops. This is due to : ",
    "options": [
      "development of air current when the plate is placed ",
      "induction of electrical charge on the plate ",
      "shielding of magnetic lines of force as aluminium is a para-magnetic material.",
      "electromagnetic induction in the aluminium plate giving rise to electromagnetic damping."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "electromagnetic induction in the aluminium plate giving rise to electromagnetic damping."
  },
  {
    "id": "pfF8gbSS873dkLa4",
    "question": "A circular loop of radius $$0.3$$ $$cm$$ lies center of the small loop is on the axis of the bigger loop. The distance between their centers is $$15$$ $$cm.$$ If a current of $$2.0$$ $$A$$ flows through the smaller loop, than the flux linked with bigger loop is ",
    "options": [
      "$$9.1 \\times {10^{ - 11}}\\,$$  weber ",
      "$$6 \\times {10^{ - 11}}\\,$$  weber ",
      "$$3.3 \\times {10^{ - 11}}\\,$$  weber ",
      "$$6.6 \\times {10^{ - 9}}\\,$$  weber "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "$$9.1 \\times {10^{ - 11}}\\,$$  weber "
  },
  {
    "id": "Z5n0lsUsBLikpE7O6cb1T",
    "question": "A conducting metal circular-wire-loop of radius r is placed perpendicular to a\nmagnetic field which varies with time as \n<br/>B = B<sub>0</sub>e$${^{{{ - t} \\over r}}}$$ , where B<sub>0</sub> and $$\\tau $$ are constants, at time t = 0. If the resistance of the loop is R then the heat generated in the loop after a long time (t $$ \\to $$ $$\\infty $$)  is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\pi ^2}{r^4}B_0^4} \\over {2\\tau R}}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\pi ^2}{r^4}B_0^2} \\over {2\\tau R}}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\pi ^2}{r^4}B_0^2R} \\over \\tau }$$ ",
      "$${{{\\pi ^2}{r^4}B_0^2} \\over {\\tau R}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "$${{{\\pi ^2}{r^4}B_0^2} \\over {2\\tau R}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ALgW7DH8UjJowW2rcQ2Rd",
    "question": "At the center of a fixed large circular coil of radius R, a much smaller circular coil of radius r is placed. The two coils are concentric and are in the same plane. The larger coil carries a current I. The smaller coil is set to rotate with a constant angular velocity $$\\omega $$ about an axis along their common diameter. Calculate the emf induced in their smaller coil after a time t of its start of rotation. ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\mu _o}{\\rm I}} \\over {2\\,R}}$$ $$\\omega $$ $$\\pi $$  r<sup>2</sup> sin$$\\omega $$ t",
      "$${{{\\mu _o}{\\rm I}} \\over {4\\,R}}$$ $$\\omega $$ $$\\pi $$  r<sup>2</sup> sin$$\\omega $$ t",
      "$${{{\\mu _o}{\\rm I}} \\over {4\\,R}}$$ $$\\omega $$  r<sup>2</sup> sin$$\\omega $$ t",
      "$${{{\\mu _o}{\\rm I}} \\over {2\\,R}}$$ $$\\omega $$   r<sup>2</sup> sin$$\\omega $$ t"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "$${{{\\mu _o}{\\rm I}} \\over {2\\,R}}$$ $$\\omega $$ $$\\pi $$  r<sup>2</sup> sin$$\\omega $$ t"
  },
  {
    "id": "k2z8MsUISoQwokP0YEwmv",
    "question": "A coil of cross-sectional area A having n turns is placed in a uniform magnetic field B. When it is rotated with an angular velocity $$\\omega ,$$ the maxium e.m.f. induced in the coil will be: ",
    "options": [
      "3 nBA$$\\omega $$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$ nBA$$\\omega $$",
      "nBA$$\\omega $$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$ nBA$$\\omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "nBA$$\\omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Qndw2dUu3JFCJJmegFOuX",
    "question": "A conducting circular loop made of a thin wire, has area 3.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> m<sup>2</sup> and resistance 10 $$\\Omega $$. It is placed perpendicular to a time dependent magnetic field B(t) = (0.4T)sin(50$$\\pi $$t). The field is uniform in space. Then the net charge flowing through the loop during t = 0 s and t = 10 ms is close to : ",
    "options": [
      "0.14 mC",
      "0.7 mC",
      "0.21 mC",
      "0.6 mC"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "0.14 mC"
  },
  {
    "id": "Iu3gwOOiPHUzNwyUk4EQh",
    "question": "A solid metal cube of edge length 2 cm is moving in a positive y-direction at a constant speed of 6 m/s. There is a uniform magnetic field of 0.1 T in the positive z-direction. The potential difference between the two faces of the cube perpendicular to the x-axis, is - ",
    "options": [
      "2mV",
      "12 mV",
      "6 mV",
      "1 mV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "12 mV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ytEXlOBxQUEHU0EXHjgy2xukf3vcegf",
    "question": "A uniform magnetic field B exists in a direction perpendicular to the plane of a square loop made of\na metal wire. The wire has a diameter of 4 mm and a total length of 30 cm. The magnetic field\nchanges with time at a steady rate $${{dB} \\over {dt}}$$ = 0.032 Ts<sup>–1</sup>. The induced current in the loop is close to\n(Resistivity of the metal wire is 1.23 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–8</sup> $$\\Omega $$m)\n",
    "options": [
      "0.53 A",
      "0.43 A",
      "0.34 A",
      "0.61 A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "0.61 A"
  },
  {
    "id": "Fsz4fAbw2kazUASxfQ7k9k2k5f6q34s",
    "question": "A planar loop of wire rotates in a uniform magnetic field. Initially at t = 0, the plane of the loop\nis perpendicular to the magnetic field. If it rotates with a period of 10 s about an axis in its plane\nthen the magnitude of induced emf will be maximum and minimum, respectively at :",
    "options": [
      "2.5 s and 7.5 s",
      "5.0 s and 10.0 s",
      "5.0 s and 7.5 s",
      "2.5 s and 5.0 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "2.5 s and 5.0 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "UY0mQiu9gQoZ1Uy5rm7k9k2k5djjnvg",
    "question": "A long solenoid of radius R carries a time (t) - dependent current <br/>I(t)=I<sub>0</sub>t(1 - t). A ring of radius 2R is placed coaxially near its middle. During the time interval 0 $$ \\le $$ t $$ \\le $$ 1, the induced current (I<sub>R</sub>) and the induced EMF(V<sub>R</sub>) in the ring change as :",
    "options": [
      "Direction of I<sub>R</sub> remains unchanged and V<sub>R</sub> is zero at t = 0.25",
      "Direction of I<sub>R</sub> remains unchanged and V<sub>R</sub> is maximum at t = 0.5",
      "At t = 0.25 direction of I<sub>R</sub> reverses and V<sub>R</sub> is maximum",
      "At t = 0.5 direction of I<sub>R</sub> reverses and V<sub>R</sub> is zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "At t = 0.5 direction of I<sub>R</sub> reverses and V<sub>R</sub> is zero"
  },
  {
    "id": "RjoDgmNZ1AdNATxKiz7k9k2k5dglzs4",
    "question": "Consider a circular coil of wire carrying constant current I, forming a magnetic dipole. The magnetic flux through an infinite plane that contains the circular coil and excluding the circular coil area is given by $$\\phi $$<sub>i</sub>. The magnetic flux through the area of the circular coil area is given by $$\\phi $$<sub>0</sub>. Which of the following option is correct?\n",
    "options": [
      "$$\\phi $$<sub>i</sub> = $$\\phi $$<sub>0</sub>",
      "$$\\phi $$<sub>i</sub> &lt; $$\\phi $$<sub>0</sub>",
      "$$\\phi $$<sub>i</sub> $$&gt;$$ $$\\phi $$<sub>0</sub>",
      "$$\\phi $$<sub>i</sub> = - $$\\phi $$<sub>0</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "$$\\phi $$<sub>i</sub> = - $$\\phi $$<sub>0</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55kaare",
    "question": "<p>A coil is placed in a time varying magnetic field. If the number of turns in the coil were to be halved and the radius of wire doubled, the electrical power dissipated due to the current induced in the coil would be :</p>\n<p>(Assume the coil to be short circuited.)</p>",
    "options": [
      "Halved",
      "Quadrupled",
      "The same",
      "Doubled"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "Doubled"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58buogs",
    "question": "<p>The magnetic flux through a coil perpendicular to its plane is varying according to the relation $$\\phi  = (5{t^3} + 4{t^2} + 2t - 5)$$ Weber. If the resistance of the coil is 5 ohm, then the induced current through the coil at t = 2 s will be,</p>",
    "options": [
      "15.6 A",
      "16.6 A",
      "17.6 A",
      "18.6 A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "15.6 A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f49mkk",
    "question": "<p>The electric current in a circular coil of 2 turns produces a magnetic induction B<sub>1</sub> at its centre. The coil is unwound and in rewound into a circular coil of 5 tuns and the same current produces a magnetic induction B<sub>2</sub> at its centre. The ratio of $${{{B_2}} \\over {{B_1}}}$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${5 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${25 \\over 4}$$",
      "$${5 \\over 4}$$",
      "$${25 \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "$${25 \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnwcxts",
    "question": "<p>A coil is placed in magnetic field such that plane of coil is perpendicular to the direction of magnetic field. The magnetic flux through a coil can be changed :</p>\n<p>A. By changing the magnitude of the magnetic field within the coil.</p>\n<p>B. By changing the area of coil within the magnetic field.</p>\n<p>C. By changing the angle between the direction of magnetic field and the plane of the coil.</p>\n<p>D. By reversing the magnetic field direction abruptly without changing its magnitude.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B and D only",
      "A, B and C only",
      "A and B only",
      "A and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "A, B and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lds9pijm",
    "question": "<p>A square loop of area 25 cm$$^2$$ has a resistance of 10 $$\\Omega$$. The loop is placed in uniform magnetic field of magnitude 40.0 T. The plane of loop is perpendicular to the magnetic field. The work done in pulling the loop out of the magnetic field slowly and uniformly in 1.0 sec, will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{1.0\\times10^{-3}~J}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{5\\times10^{-3}~J}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{2.5\\times10^{-3}~J}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{1.0\\times10^{-4}~J}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{1.0\\times10^{-3}~J}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldydq30q",
    "question": "<p>A conducting circular loop of radius $$\\frac{10}{\\sqrt\\pi}$$ cm is placed perpendicular to a uniform magnetic field of 0.5 T. The magnetic field is decreased to zero in 0.5 s at a steady rate. The induced emf in the circular loop at 0.25 s is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "emf = 10 mV",
      "emf = 5 mV",
      "emf = 100 mV",
      "emf = 1 mV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "emf = 10 mV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgxwolyh",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : If the number of turns in the coil of a moving coil galvanometer is doubled then the current sensitivity becomes double.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Increasing current sensitivity of a moving coil galvanometer by only increasing the number of turns in the coil will also increase its voltage sensitivity in the same ratio</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh248pml",
    "question": "<p>The induced emf can be produced in a coil by</p>\n<p>A. moving the coil with uniform speed inside uniform magnetic field</p>\n<p>B. moving the coil with non uniform speed inside uniform magnetic field</p>\n<p>C. rotating the coil inside the uniform magnetic field</p>\n<p>D. changing the area of the coil inside the uniform magnetic field</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and C only",
      "C and D only",
      "B and D only",
      "B and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "C and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3ir9a",
    "question": "<p>A rectangular loop of length $$2.5 \\mathrm{~m}$$ and width $$2 \\mathrm{~m}$$ is placed at $$60^{\\circ}$$ to a magnetic field of $$4 \\mathrm{~T}$$. The loop is removed from the field in $$10 \\mathrm{~sec}$$. The average emf induced in the loop during this time is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-2 \\mathrm{~V}$$\n",
      "$$+2 \\mathrm{~V}$$\n",
      "$$+1 \\mathrm{~V}$$\n",
      "$$-1 \\mathrm{~V}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "$$+1 \\mathrm{~V}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse6gmkn",
    "question": "<p>A coil is places perpendicular to a magnetic field of $$5000 \\mathrm{~T}$$. When the field is changed to $$3000 \\mathrm{~T}$$ in $$2 \\mathrm{~s}$$, an induced emf of $$22 \\mathrm{~V}$$ is produced in the coil. If the diameter of the coil is $$0.02 \\mathrm{~m}$$, then the number of turns in the coil is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "35",
      "70",
      "7",
      "140"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "70"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1p9jn",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 523px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 70px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 184px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 94px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 175px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\oint \\vec{B} \\cdot \\overrightarrow{d l}=\\mu_o i_c+\\mu_o \\varepsilon_o \\frac{d \\phi_E}{d t}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Gauss' law for electricity</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\oint \\vec{E} \\cdot \\overrightarrow{d l}=\\frac{d \\phi_B}{d t}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Gauss' law for magnetism</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\oint \\vec{E} \\cdot \\overrightarrow{d A}=\\frac{Q}{\\varepsilon_o}$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Faraday law</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\oint \\vec{B} \\cdot \\overrightarrow{d A}=0$$</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ampere - Maxwell law</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p></p></p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV\n",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II\n",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg5x0jc",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 687px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 70px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 245px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 94px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 278px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Gauss's law of magnetostatics</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\oint \\vec{E} \\cdot \\vec{d} a=\\frac{1}{\\varepsilon_0} \\int \\rho d V$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Faraday's law of electro magnetic induction</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\oint \\vec{B} \\cdot \\vec{d} a=0$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ampere's law</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\int \\vec{E} \\cdot \\vec{d} l=\\frac{-d}{d t} \\int \\vec{B} \\cdot \\vec{d} a$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Gauss's law of electrostatics</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\oint \\vec{B} \\cdot \\vec{d} l=\\mu_0 I$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II\n",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-III, D-I\n",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I\n",
      "A-I, B-III, C-IV, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "magnetic-flux,-faraday's-and-lenz's-laws",
    "solution": "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "BNakOfrO39szUS3t",
    "question": "A metal conductor of length $$1$$ $$m$$ rotates vertically about  one of its ends at angular velocity $$5$$ radians per second. If the horizontal component of earth's magnetic field is $$0.2 \\times {10^{ - 4}}T,$$ then the $$e.m.f.$$ developed between the two ends of the conductor is",
    "options": [
      "$$5mV$$ ",
      "$$50\\mu V$$ ",
      "$$5\\mu V$$",
      "$$50mV$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "motional-emf-and-eddy-current",
    "solution": "$$50\\mu V$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "8ZYOzABkujn3sdfm",
    "question": "A boat is moving due east in a region where the earth's magnetic fields is $$5.0 \\times {10^{ - 5}}$$ $$N{A^{ - 1}}\\,{m^{ - 1}}$$ due north and horizontal. The best carries a vertical aerial $$2$$ $$m$$ long. If the speed of the boat is $$1.50\\,m{s^{ - 1}},$$ the magnitude of the induced $$emf$$ in the wire of aerial is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.75$$ $$mV$$ ",
      "$$0.50$$ $$mV$$ ",
      "$$0.15$$ $$mV$$ ",
      "$$1$$ $$mV$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "motional-emf-and-eddy-current",
    "solution": "$$0.15$$ $$mV$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "CnUgW4A7b5n2YqdytnIvN",
    "question": "A 10 m long horizontal wire extends from North East to South West. It is falling with a speed of 5.0 ms<sup>–1</sup>, at right angles to the horizontal component of the earth's magnetic field of 0.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup><sup></sup>  Wb/m<sup>2</sup>. The value of the induced emf in wire is : ",
    "options": [
      "0.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> V",
      "2.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> V",
      "1.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> V",
      "1.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "motional-emf-and-eddy-current",
    "solution": "1.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> V"
  },
  {
    "id": "TOC7q3W8KVUjoKaYLu1kluke710",
    "question": "An aeroplane, with its wings spread 10 m, is flying at a speed of 180 km/h in a horizontal direction. The total intensity of earth's field at that part is 2.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> Wb/m<sup>2</sup> and the angle of dip is 60$$^\\circ$$. The emf induced between the tips of the plane wings will be __________.",
    "options": [
      "88.37 mV",
      "62.50 mV",
      "54.125 mV",
      "108.25 mV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "motional-emf-and-eddy-current",
    "solution": "108.25 mV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58hyygn",
    "question": "<p>A metallic conductor of length 1 m rotates in a vertical plane parallel to east-west direction about one of its end with angular velocity 5 rad s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. If the horizontal component of earth's magnetic field is 0.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> T, then emf induced between the two ends of the conductor is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "5 $$\\mu$$V",
      "50 $$\\mu$$V",
      "5 mV",
      "50 mv"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "motional-emf-and-eddy-current",
    "solution": "50 $$\\mu$$V"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpjqlnt",
    "question": "<p>Spherical insulating ball and a spherical metallic ball of same size and mass are dropped from the same height. Choose the correct statement out of the following</p>\n<p>{Assume negligible air friction}</p>",
    "options": [
      "Metal ball will reach the earth's surface earlier than the insulating ball",
      "Both will reach the earth's surface simultaneously.",
      "Insulating ball will reach the earth's surface earlier than the metal ball",
      "Time taken by them to reach the earth's surface will be independent of the properties of their materials"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "motional-emf-and-eddy-current",
    "solution": "Insulating ball will reach the earth's surface earlier than the metal ball"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtxnbho",
    "question": "<p>A wire of length 1m moving with velocity 8 m/s at right angles to a magnetic field of 2T. The magnitude of induced emf, between the ends of wire will be __________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "20 V",
      "8 V",
      "16 V",
      "12 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "motional-emf-and-eddy-current",
    "solution": "16 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswnzlv",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A: A bar magnet dropped through a metallic cylindrical pipe takes more time to come down compared to a non-magnetic bar with same geometry and mass.</p>\n<p>Reason R: For the magnetic bar, Eddy currents are produced in the metallic pipe which oppose the motion of the magnetic bar.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "motional-emf-and-eddy-current",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyq6f6x",
    "question": "<p>An emf of $$0.08 \\mathrm{~V}$$ is induced in a metal rod of length $$10 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ held normal to a uniform magnetic field of $$0.4 \\mathrm{~T}$$, when moves with a velocity of:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$20 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$",
      "$$3.2 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$",
      "$$0.5 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "motional-emf-and-eddy-current",
    "solution": "$$2 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh00v92a",
    "question": "<p>Certain galvanometers have a fixed core made of non magnetic metallic material. The function of this metallic material is</p>",
    "options": [
      "to bring the coil to rest quickly",
      "to produce large deflecting torque on the coil",
      "to oscillate the coil in magnetic field for longer period of time",
      "to make the magnetic field radial"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-induction",
    "topic": "motional-emf-and-eddy-current",
    "solution": "to bring the coil to rest quickly"
  },
  {
    "id": "xG2EBDunp2W3GzgQ",
    "question": "Electromagnetic waves are transverse in nature is evident by ",
    "options": [
      "polarization ",
      "interference ",
      "reflection ",
      "diffraction "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "polarization "
  },
  {
    "id": "jCRQrB6VurpfAStv",
    "question": "An electromagnetic wave of frequency $$v=3.0$$ $$MHz$$ passes from vacuum into a dielectric medium with permittivity $$ \\in  = 4.0.$$ Then ",
    "options": [
      "wave length is halved and frequency remains unchanged ",
      "wave length is doubled and the frequency becomes half ",
      "wave length is doubled and the frequency remains unchanged  ",
      "wave length and frequency both remain unchanged."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "wave length is halved and frequency remains unchanged "
  },
  {
    "id": "y8OHX2USJUdhvFvW",
    "question": "A radiation of energy $$E$$ falls normally on a perfectly reflecting surface. The momentum transferred to the surface is ",
    "options": [
      "$$Ec$$ ",
      "$$2E/c$$ ",
      "$$E/c$$ ",
      "$$E/{c^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$2E/c$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "K9vgBPLdLg2CsG9j",
    "question": "The $$rms$$ value of the electric field of the light coming from the Sun is $$720$$ $$N/C.$$ The average total energy density of the electromagnetic wave is ",
    "options": [
      "$$4.58 \\times {10^{ - 6}}\\,J/{m^3}$$  ",
      "$$6.37 \\times {10^{ - 9}}\\,J/{m^3}$$ ",
      "$$81.35 \\times {10^{ - 12}}\\,J/{m^3}$$ ",
      "$$3.3 \\times {10^{ - 3}}\\,J/{m^3}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$4.58 \\times {10^{ - 6}}\\,J/{m^3}$$  "
  },
  {
    "id": "0wLwhn6cgC3UkhIR",
    "question": "An electromagnetic wave in vacuum has the electric and magnetic field $$\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to  $$and $$\\mathop B\\limits^ \\to  $$, which are always perpendicular to each other. The direction of polarization is given by $$\\mathop X\\limits^ \\to  $$ and that of wave propagation by $$\\mathop k\\limits^ \\to  $$. Then ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathop X\\limits^ \\to  ||\\mathop B\\limits^ \\to  $$ and $$\\mathop X\\limits^ \\to  ||\\mathop B\\limits^ \\to   \\times \\mathop E\\limits^ \\to  $$ ",
      "$$\\mathop X\\limits^ \\to  ||\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to  $$ and $$\\mathop k\\limits^ \\to  ||\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to   \\times \\mathop B\\limits^ \\to  $$ ",
      "$$\\mathop X\\limits^ \\to  ||\\mathop B\\limits^ \\to  $$ and $$\\mathop k\\limits^ \\to  ||\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to   \\times \\mathop B\\limits^ \\to  $$ ",
      "$$\\mathop X\\limits^ \\to  ||\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to  $$ and $$\\mathop k\\limits^ \\to  ||\\mathop B\\limits^ \\to   \\times \\mathop E\\limits^ \\to  $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\mathop X\\limits^ \\to  ||\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to  $$ and $$\\mathop k\\limits^ \\to  ||\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to   \\times \\mathop B\\limits^ \\to  $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "4c5niHBpA9z8BUuz",
    "question": "The magnetic field in a travelling electromagnetic wave has a peak value of $$20$$ $$n$$$$T$$. The peak value of electric field strength is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$3V/m$$ ",
      "$$6V/m$$ ",
      "$$9V/m$$ ",
      "$$12V/m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$6V/m$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "282LzDMYWQcD2x5P",
    "question": "During the propagation of electromagnetic waves in a medium : ",
    "options": [
      "Electric energy density is double of the magnetic energy density. ",
      "Electric energy density is half of the magnetic energy density. ",
      "Electric energy density is equal to the magnetic energy density.",
      "Both electric and magnetic energy of densities are zero. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "Electric energy density is equal to the magnetic energy density."
  },
  {
    "id": "MdoFpfEwQALFcvucqsvSB",
    "question": "A lamp emits monochromatic green light uniformly in all directions. The lamp is 3% efficient in converting electrical power to electromagnetic waves and consumes 100 W of power. The amplitude of the electric field associated with the electromagnetic radiation at a distance of 5 m from the lamp will be nearly : ",
    "options": [
      "1.34 V/m",
      "2.68 V/m",
      "4.02 V/m",
      "5.36 V/m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "2.68 V/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "nQtB2JGrvzWCy68tx2sRj",
    "question": "An electromagnetic wave of frequency 1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup> hertz is propagating along z - axis.  The amplitude of electric field is 4 V/m. If $$ \\in $$<sub>0</sub> = 8.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$12</sup> C<sup>2</sup>/N-m<sup>2</sup>, then average energy density of electric field will be : ",
    "options": [
      "35.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$10</sup> J/m<sup>3</sup>",
      "35.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$11</sup> J/m<sup>3</sup>",
      "35.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$12</sup> J/m<sup>3</sup>",
      "35.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$13</sup> J/m<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "35.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$12</sup> J/m<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "vduIu2V5MwArzdRKU6sWR",
    "question": "For plane electromagnetic waves propagating in the z direction, which one of the following  combination  gives the correct possible direction for  $$\\overrightarrow E $$ and $$\\overrightarrow B $$ field respectively ? ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {\\widehat i + 2\\widehat j} \\right)\\,\\,$$ and  $$\\left( {2\\widehat i - \\widehat j} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left(-\\, {2\\widehat i - 3\\widehat j} \\right)$$ and $$\\left( {3\\widehat i - 2\\widehat j} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( {2\\widehat i + 3\\widehat j} \\right)$$ and $$\\left( {\\widehat i + 2\\widehat j} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( {3\\widehat i + 4\\widehat j} \\right)$$ and $$\\left( {4\\widehat i - 3\\widehat j} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\left(-\\, {2\\widehat i - 3\\widehat j} \\right)$$ and $$\\left( {3\\widehat i - 2\\widehat j} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Nnvxd2WOqLWVhesKIzedo",
    "question": "An electromagnetic wave travelling in the x-direction has frequency of 23 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup> Hz and electric field amplitude of 27 Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. From the options given below, which one describes the magnetic field for this wave ?",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow B $$ (x, t) = (3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>T) $$\\widehat j$$\n<br><br>sin [ 2$$\\pi $$ (1.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>x $$-$$ 2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup>t)]",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B $$ (x, t) = (9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>T) $$\\widehat k$$\n<br><br>sin [ 2$$\\pi $$ (1.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup>x $$-$$ 2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup>t)]",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B $$ (x, t) = (9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>T) $$\\widehat i$$\n<br><br>sin [ 2$$\\pi $$ (1.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>x $$-$$ 2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup>t)]",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B $$ (x, t) = (9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>T) $$\\widehat j$$\n<br><br>sin [(1.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> x $$-$$ 2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup>t)]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow B $$ (x, t) = (9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>T) $$\\widehat k$$\n<br><br>sin [ 2$$\\pi $$ (1.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup>x $$-$$ 2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup>t)]"
  },
  {
    "id": "E6BKvbsKQ4NY5NWUO6QFe",
    "question": "Consider an electromagnetic wave propagating in vacuum. Choose the correct\nstatement :",
    "options": [
      "For an electromagnetic wave propagating in +x direction the electric field is $$\\vec E = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{E_{yz}}{\\mkern 1mu} \\left( {x,t} \\right)\\left( {\\hat y - \\hat z} \\right)$$  \n<br><br>and the magnetic field is $$\\vec B = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{B_{yz}}{\\mkern 1mu} \\left( {x,t} \\right)\\left( {\\hat y + \\hat z} \\right)$$",
      "For an electromagnetic wave propagating in +x direction the electric field is\n$$\\vec E = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{E_{yz{\\mkern 1mu} }}\\left( {y,z,t} \\right)\\left( {\\hat y + \\hat z} \\right)$$  \n<br><br>and the magnetic field is $$\\vec B = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{B_{yz{\\mkern 1mu} }}\\left( {y,z,t} \\right)\\left( {\\hat y + \\hat z} \\right)$$",
      "For an electromagnetic wave propagating in + y direction the electric field is\n$$\\overrightarrow E  = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{E_{yz{\\mkern 1mu} }}\\left( {x,t} \\right)\\widehat y$$ \n<br>and the magnetic field is $$\\vec B = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{B_{yz{\\mkern 1mu} }}\\left( {x,t} \\right)\\widehat z$$",
      "For an electromagnetic wave propagating in + y direction the electric field is \n$$\\overrightarrow E  = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{E_{yz{\\mkern 1mu} }}\\left( {x,t} \\right)\\widehat z$$ \n<br>and the magnetic field is $$\\overrightarrow B  = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{B_{z{\\mkern 1mu} }}\\left( {x,t} \\right)\\widehat y$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "For an electromagnetic wave propagating in +x direction the electric field is $$\\vec E = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{E_{yz}}{\\mkern 1mu} \\left( {x,t} \\right)\\left( {\\hat y - \\hat z} \\right)$$  \n<br><br>and the magnetic field is $$\\vec B = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}{B_{yz}}{\\mkern 1mu} \\left( {x,t} \\right)\\left( {\\hat y + \\hat z} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "5vHGPLXaXO7wEvKW1xmXB",
    "question": "The electric field component of a monochromatic radiation is given by\n<br/><br/>$$\\overrightarrow E $$ = 2 E<sub>0</sub> $$\\widehat i$$ cos kz cos $$\\omega $$t\n<br/><br/>Its magnetic field $$\\overrightarrow B $$  is then given by : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{2{E_0}} \\over c}$$ $$\\widehat j$$ sin kz cos $$\\omega $$t",
      "$$-$$ $${{2{E_0}} \\over c}$$ $$\\widehat j$$ sin kz sin $$\\omega $$t",
      "$${{2{E_0}} \\over c}$$ $$\\widehat j$$ sin kz sin $$\\omega $$t",
      "$${{2{E_0}} \\over c}$$ $$\\widehat j$$ cos kz cos $$\\omega $$t"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$${{2{E_0}} \\over c}$$ $$\\widehat j$$ sin kz sin $$\\omega $$t"
  },
  {
    "id": "oMiaCnABqPIHciDAaCaFC",
    "question": "Magnetic field in a plane electromagnetic wave is given by\n<br/><br/>$$\\overrightarrow B $$ = B<sub>0</sub> sin (k x + $$\\omega $$t) $$\\widehat j\\,T$$ \n<br/><br/>Expression for corresponding electric field will be :  \n<br/>Where c is speed of light. ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow E $$ = B<sub>0</sub> c sin (k x + $$\\omega $$t) $$\\widehat k$$ V/m",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E $$ = $${{{B_0}} \\over c}$$ sin  (k x + $$\\omega $$t) $$\\widehat k$$ V/m",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E $$ = $$-$$ B<sub>0</sub> c sin (kx +$$\\omega $$t) $$\\widehat k$$ V/m",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E $$ =  B<sub>0</sub> c sin (kx $$-$$$$\\omega $$t) $$\\widehat k$$ V/m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow E $$ = B<sub>0</sub> c sin (k x + $$\\omega $$t) $$\\widehat k$$ V/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "GxtRoslcEoZq4BXsVoB26",
    "question": "A plane polarized monochromatic EM wave is traveling in vacuum along z direction such that at t = t<sub>1</sub> it is found that the electric field is zero at a spatial point z<sub>1</sub>. The next zero that occurs in its neighbourhood is at z<sub>2</sub>. The frequency of the electroagnetic wave is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{3 \\times {{10}^8}} \\over {\\left| {{z_2} - {z_1}} \\right|}}$$",
      "$${{1.5 \\times {{10}^8}} \\over {\\left| {{z_2} - {z_1}} \\right|}}$$",
      "$${{6 \\times {{10}^8}} \\over {\\left| {{z_2} - {z_1}} \\right|}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {{t_1} + {{\\left| {{z_2} - {z_1}} \\right|} \\over {3 \\times {{10}^8}}}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$${{1.5 \\times {{10}^8}} \\over {\\left| {{z_2} - {z_1}} \\right|}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "gZFiWtAr9eIMfS1N",
    "question": "An EM wave from air enters a medium. The electric fields are<br/><br>\n$$\\overrightarrow {{E_1}} $$ = $${E_{01}}\\widehat x\\cos \\left[ {2\\pi v\\left( {{z \\over c} - t} \\right)} \\right]$$  in air and \n<br/><br/>$$\\overrightarrow {{E_2}} $$ = $${E_{02}}\\widehat x\\cos \\left[ {k\\left( {2z - ct} \\right)} \\right]$$  in medium, <br/><br/>where the wave number k and frequency $$\\nu $$ refer to their values\nin air. The medium is non-magnetic. If $${\\varepsilon _{{r_1}}}$$ and $${\\varepsilon _{{r_2}}}$$ refer to relative permittivities of air and medium\nrespectively, which of the following options is correct ? \n</br>",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\varepsilon _{{r_1}}}} \\over {{\\varepsilon _{{r_2}}}}} = 4$$ ",
      "$${{{\\varepsilon _{{r_1}}}} \\over {{\\varepsilon _{{r_2}}}}} = 2$$",
      "$${{{\\varepsilon _{{r_1}}}} \\over {{\\varepsilon _{{r_2}}}}} = {1 \\over 4}$$",
      "$${{{\\varepsilon _{{r_1}}}} \\over {{\\varepsilon _{{r_2}}}}} = {1 \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$${{{\\varepsilon _{{r_1}}}} \\over {{\\varepsilon _{{r_2}}}}} = {1 \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "V3bZ7JTDqq0H2lEDHj3rsa0w2w9jwzjtoa5",
    "question": "Light is incident normally on a completely absorbing surface with an energy flux of 25 W cm<sup>–2</sup>. If the surface\nhas an area of 25 cm<sup>2</sup>, the momentum transferred to the surface in 40 min time duration will be : ",
    "options": [
      "6.3 × 10<sup>–4</sup> Ns",
      "5.0 × 10<sup>–3</sup> Ns",
      "1.4 × 10<sup>–6</sup> Ns",
      "3.5 × 10<sup>–6</sup> Ns"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "5.0 × 10<sup>–3</sup> Ns"
  },
  {
    "id": "amgMUaNdXU3Gg6NY7J3rsa0w2w9jx6qdavc",
    "question": "A plane electromagnetic wave having a frequency v = 23.9 GHz propagates along the positive z-direction in\nfree space. The peak value of the Electric Field is 60 V/m. Which among the following is the acceptable\nmagnetic field component in the electromagnetic wave ?",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow B $$ = 2 × 10<sup>–7</sup>\n sin(1.5 × 10<sup>2</sup>\nx + 0.5 × 10<sup>11</sup>t) $$\\widehat j$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B $$ = 60\n sin(0.5 × 10<sup>3</sup>x + 0.5 × 10<sup>11</sup>t) $$\\widehat k$$\n",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B $$ = 2 × 10<sup>–7</sup>\n sin(0.5 × 10<sup>3</sup>\nz + 1.5 × 10<sup>11</sup>t) $$\\widehat i$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B $$ = 2 × 10<sup>–7</sup>\n sin(0.5 × 10<sup>3</sup>\nz - 1.5 × 10<sup>11</sup>t) $$\\widehat i$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow B $$ = 2 × 10<sup>–7</sup>\n sin(0.5 × 10<sup>3</sup>\nz - 1.5 × 10<sup>11</sup>t) $$\\widehat i$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xqMtPR5EhmDNdUJo613rsa0w2w9jx3o70xv",
    "question": "An electromagnetic wave is represented by the electric field $$\\overrightarrow E  = {E_0}\\widehat n\\sin \\left[ {\\omega t + \\left( {6y - 8z} \\right)} \\right]$$\n. Taking unit\nvectors in x, y and z directions to be $$\\widehat i,\\widehat j,\\widehat k$$\n, the direction of propagation $$\\widehat s$$, is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\widehat s = {{3\\widehat i - 4\\widehat j} \\over 5}$$",
      "$$\\widehat s = {{ - 4\\widehat k + 3\\widehat j} \\over 5}$$",
      "$$\\widehat s = \\left( {{{ - 3\\widehat j + 4\\widehat k} \\over 5}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\widehat s = {{4\\widehat j - 3\\widehat k} \\over 5}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\widehat s = \\left( {{{ - 3\\widehat j + 4\\widehat k} \\over 5}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "puOt4a2DT6bNbLLn7S18hoxe66ijvznkqu6",
    "question": "The electric field of a plane electromagnetic\nwave is given by<br/>\n$$\\overrightarrow E  = {E_0}\\widehat i\\cos (kz)cos(\\omega t)$$ <br/>The corresponding magnetic field $$\\overrightarrow B $$ is then given by",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow B  = {{{E_0}} \\over C}\\widehat j\\sin (kz)\\sin (\\omega t)$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B  = {{{E_0}} \\over C}\\widehat j\\sin (kz)\\cos (\\omega t)$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B  = {{{E_0}} \\over C}\\widehat j\\cos (kz)\\sin (\\omega t)$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B  = {{{E_0}} \\over C}\\widehat k\\sin (kz)\\cos (\\omega t)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow B  = {{{E_0}} \\over C}\\widehat j\\sin (kz)\\sin (\\omega t)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "H7wcIWefcCVwIWMeIqsoL",
    "question": "50 W/m<sup>2</sup> energy density of sunlight is normally\nincident on the surface of a solar panel. Some\npart of incident energy (25%) is reflected from\nthe surface and the rest is absorbed. The force\nexerted on 1m<sup>2</sup> surface area will be close to\n(c = 3 × 108 m/s) :-",
    "options": [
      "20 × 10<sup>–8</sup> N",
      "35 × 10<sup>–8</sup> N",
      "10 × 10–8 N",
      "15 × 10<sup>–8</sup> N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "20 × 10<sup>–8</sup> N"
  },
  {
    "id": "OGDauNWQqHAueUxnYl6MR",
    "question": "The magnetic field of a plane electromagnetic\nwave is given by :<br/>\n$$$\\overline B  = {B_0}\\widehat i\\left[ {\\cos (kz - \\omega t)} \\right] + {B_i}\\widehat j\\cos (kz + \\omega t)$$$\nB<sub>0</sub> = 3 × 10<sup>–5</sup> T and B1 = 2 × 10<sup>–6</sup> T.\n<br/>The rms\nvalue of the force experienced by a stationary\ncharge Q = 10<sup>–4</sup> C at z = 0 is closest to :",
    "options": [
      "0.6 N",
      "0.9 N",
      "3 × 10<sup>–2</sup> N",
      "0.1 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "0.6 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "eKBoT4kkGKQmAuKU4a1MH",
    "question": "The magnetic field of an electromagnetic wave\nis given by :-<br/><br/>\n$$\\mathop B\\limits^ \\to   = 1.6 \\times {10^{ - 6}}\\cos \\left( {2 \\times {{10}^7}z + 6 \\times {{10}^{15}}t} \\right)\\left( {2\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge   + \\mathop j\\limits^ \\wedge  } \\right){{Wb} \\over {{m^2}}}$$<br/><br/>\nThe associated electric field will be :-",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to   = 4.8 \\times {10^2}\\cos \\left( {2 \\times {{10}^7}z - 6 \\times {{10}^{15}}t} \\right)\\left( -2{\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge   + \\mathop {j}\\limits^ \\wedge  } \\right){V \\over m}$$",
      "$$\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to   = 4.8 \\times {10^2}\\cos \\left( {2 \\times {{10}^7}z - 6 \\times {{10}^{15}}t} \\right)\\left( 2{\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge   + \\mathop {j}\\limits^ \\wedge  } \\right){V \\over m}$$",
      "$$\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to   = 4.8 \\times {10^2}\\cos \\left( {2 \\times {{10}^7}z + 6 \\times {{10}^{15}}t} \\right)\\left( {\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge   - \\mathop {2j}\\limits^ \\wedge  } \\right){V \\over m}$$",
      "$$\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to   = 4.8 \\times {10^2}\\cos \\left( {2 \\times {{10}^7}z + 6 \\times {{10}^{15}}t} \\right)\\left( -{\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge   + \\mathop {2j}\\limits^ \\wedge  } \\right){V \\over m}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to   = 4.8 \\times {10^2}\\cos \\left( {2 \\times {{10}^7}z + 6 \\times {{10}^{15}}t} \\right)\\left( {\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge   - \\mathop {2j}\\limits^ \\wedge  } \\right){V \\over m}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "PsPvuNusKi6XOgeKA4XQ2",
    "question": "A plane electromagnetic wave travels in free\nspace along the x-direction. The electric field\ncomponent of the wave at a particular point of\nspace and time is E = 6 V m<sup>–1</sup> along y-direction.\nIts corresponding magnetic field component,\nB would be :",
    "options": [
      "2 × 10<sup>–8</sup> T along y-direction",
      "6 × 10<sup>–8</sup> T along z-direction",
      "2 × 10<sup>–8</sup> T along z-direction",
      "6 × 10<sup>–8</sup> T along x-direction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "2 × 10<sup>–8</sup> T along z-direction"
  },
  {
    "id": "B4h15SmLI1oiMVNjgrcgK",
    "question": "A light wave is incident normally on a glass slab of refractive index 1.5. If 4 % of light gets reflected and the amplitude of the electric field of the incident light is 30 V/m, then the amplitude of the electric field for the wave propagating in the glass medium will be : ",
    "options": [
      "6 V/m",
      "10 V/m",
      "30 V/m",
      "24 V/m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "24 V/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "TjqrGqGQBr1N4wheYCOUn",
    "question": "A 27 mW laser beam has a cross-sectional area of 10 mm<sup>2</sup>. The magnitude of the maximum electric field in this electromagnetic wave is given by :\n<br/>[Given permittivity of space $$ \\in $$<sub>0</sub> = 9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–12</sup> SI units, Speed of light c = 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>8</sup>  m/s]",
    "options": [
      "2 kV/m",
      "1 kV/m",
      "1.4 kV/m",
      "0.7 kV/m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "1.4 kV/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "P0WbmgrjOu7wPyt29yZyJ",
    "question": "An electromagnetic wave of intensity 50 Wm<sup>–2</sup> enters in a medium of refractive index 'n' without any loss. The ratio of the magnitudes of electric, and the ratio of the magnitudes of magnetic fields of the wave before and after entering into the medium are respectively, given by: ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {{1 \\over {\\sqrt n }},{1 \\over {\\sqrt n }}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( {\\sqrt n ,\\sqrt n } \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( {\\sqrt n ,{1 \\over {\\sqrt n }}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( {{1 \\over {\\sqrt n }},\\sqrt n } \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {\\sqrt n ,{1 \\over {\\sqrt n }}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "C2BB46HIaHRpRBwZuExwp",
    "question": "The electric field of a plane polarized electromagnetic wave in free space at time t = 0 is given by an expression $$\\overrightarrow E \\left( {x,y} \\right) = 10\\widehat j\\cos \\left[ {\\left( {6x + 8z} \\right)} \\right].$$ The magnetic field $$\\overrightarrow B $$(x,z, t) is given by $$-$$ (c  is the velocity of light) ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over c}\\left( {6\\hat k + 8\\widehat i} \\right)\\cos \\left[ {\\left( {6x + 8z - 10ct} \\right)} \\right]$$",
      "$${1 \\over c}\\left( {6\\widehat k - 8\\widehat i} \\right)\\cos \\left[ {\\left( {6x + 8z - 10ct} \\right)} \\right]$$",
      "$${1 \\over c}\\left( {6\\hat k + 8\\widehat i} \\right)\\cos \\left[ {\\left( {6x - 8z + 10ct} \\right)} \\right]$$",
      "$${1 \\over c}\\left( {6\\hat k - 8\\widehat i} \\right)\\cos \\left[ {\\left( {6x - 8z + 10ct} \\right)} \\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over c}\\left( {6\\widehat k - 8\\widehat i} \\right)\\cos \\left[ {\\left( {6x + 8z - 10ct} \\right)} \\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1LlGm8iaXGIVASHSRiyob",
    "question": "If the magnetic field of a plane electromagnetic wave is given by (the speed of light = 3 × 10<sup>8</sup> B = 100 × 10<sup>–6</sup>\n sin $$\\left[ {2\\pi  \\times 2 \\times {{10}^{15}}\\left( {t - {x \\over c}} \\right)} \\right]$$ then the maximum electric field associated with it is -\n ",
    "options": [
      "4.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> N/C",
      "4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> N/C",
      "6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> N/C",
      "3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> N/C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> N/C"
  },
  {
    "id": "0Wbpv63JwP2DxfnRkBNk1",
    "question": "The energy associated with electric field is (U<sub>E</sub>) and with magnetic field is (U<sub>B</sub>) for an electromagnetic wave in free space. Then : ",
    "options": [
      "$${U_E} = {{{U_B}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${U_E} &gt; {U_B}$$",
      "$${U_E} &lt; {U_B}$$",
      "$${U_E} = {U_B}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$${U_E} = {U_B}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "WoEjBb6TS1MN0rAZJazT7",
    "question": "A plane electromagnetic wave of frequency 50 MHz travels in free space along the  positive x-direction. At a particular point in space and time, $$\\overrightarrow E  = 6.3\\widehat j\\,V/m.$$ The corresponding magnetic field $$\\overrightarrow {B,} $$ at that point will be :  ",
    "options": [
      "18.9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> $$\\widehat k$$T",
      "2.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> $$\\widehat k$$T",
      "6.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> $$\\widehat k$$T",
      "18.9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>8</sup> $$\\widehat k$$T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "2.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> $$\\widehat k$$T"
  },
  {
    "id": "gJvYizNTcQVvWKiIF9I8P",
    "question": "The mean intensity of radiation on the surface of the Sun is about 10<sup>8</sup>  W/m<sup>2</sup> . The rms value of the corresponding magnetic field is closet to :",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>2</sup> T",
      "10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> T",
      "10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> T",
      "1 T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> T"
  },
  {
    "id": "bP9cEHcrjWMrP7atGljgy2xukfaju4vh",
    "question": "The electric field of a plane electromagnetic wave is given by\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow E  = {E_0}\\left( {\\widehat x + \\widehat y} \\right)\\sin \\left( {kz - \\omega t} \\right)$$\n<br/>Its magnetic field will be given by :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{E_0}} \\over c}\\left( {\\widehat x + \\widehat y} \\right)\\sin \\left( {kz - \\omega t} \\right)$$",
      "$${{{E_0}} \\over c}\\left( {\\widehat x - \\widehat y} \\right)\\sin \\left( {kz - \\omega t} \\right)$$",
      "$${{{E_0}} \\over c}\\left( {\\widehat x - \\widehat y} \\right)\\cos \\left( {kz - \\omega t} \\right)$$",
      "$${{{E_0}} \\over c}\\left( { - \\widehat x + \\widehat y} \\right)\\sin \\left( {kz - \\omega t} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$${{{E_0}} \\over c}\\left( { - \\widehat x + \\widehat y} \\right)\\sin \\left( {kz - \\omega t} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "KtdVH1xq0D0pZMPsVKjgy2xukfxnxzld",
    "question": "For a plane electromagnetic wave, the magnetic field at a point x and time t is\n<br/><br/>$$\\overrightarrow B \\left( {x,t} \\right)$$ = $$\\left[ {1.2 \\times {{10}^{ - 7}}\\sin \\left( {0.5 \\times {{10}^3}x + 1.5 \\times {{10}^{11}}t} \\right)\\widehat k} \\right]$$ T\n<br/><br/>The instantaneous electric field $$\\overrightarrow E $$\n corresponding to $$\\overrightarrow B $$\n is :\n<br/>(speed of light c = 3 × 10<sup>8</sup>\n ms<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow E \\left( {x,t} \\right) = \\left[ {36\\sin \\left( {1 \\times {{10}^3}x + 1.5 \\times {{10}^{11}}t} \\right)\\widehat i} \\right]$$ $${V \\over m}$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E \\left( {x,t} \\right) = \\left[ {36\\sin \\left( {0.5 \\times {{10}^3}x + 1.5 \\times {{10}^{11}}t} \\right)\\widehat k} \\right]{V \\over m}$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E \\left( {x,t} \\right) = \\left[ {36\\sin \\left( {1 \\times {{10}^3}x + 0.5 \\times {{10}^{11}}t} \\right)\\widehat j} \\right]{V \\over m}$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E \\left( {x,t} \\right) = \\left[ { - 36\\sin \\left( {0.5 \\times {{10}^3}x + 1.5 \\times {{10}^{11}}t} \\right)\\widehat j} \\right]{V \\over m}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow E \\left( {x,t} \\right) = \\left[ { - 36\\sin \\left( {0.5 \\times {{10}^3}x + 1.5 \\times {{10}^{11}}t} \\right)\\widehat j} \\right]{V \\over m}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "KZFlhDyck55AuP9tKijgy2xukfewe6if",
    "question": "An electron is constrained to move along\nthe y-axis with a speed of 0.1 c (c is the\nspeed of light) in the presence of\nelectromagnetic wave, whose electric\nfield is\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow E  = 30\\widehat j\\sin \\left( {1.5 \\times {{10}^7}t - 5 \\times {{10}^{ - 2}}x} \\right)$$ V/m.\n<br/>The maximum magnetic force experienced by\nthe electron will be :\n<br/>(given c = 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>–1</sup> and electron charge =\n1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–19</sup> C)",
    "options": [
      "4.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–19</sup> N",
      "2.4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–18</sup> N",
      "3.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–18</sup> N",
      "1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–18</sup> N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "4.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–19</sup> N"
  },
  {
    "id": "B1LCvQE5DtsMKP0cLJjgy2xukf3v4mfs",
    "question": "The electric field of a plane electromagnetic wave propagating along the x direction in vacuum is\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow E  = {E_0}\\widehat j\\cos \\left( {\\omega t - kx} \\right)$$.\n <br/>The magnetic field $$\\overrightarrow B $$\n, at the moment t = 0 is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow B  = {{{E_0}} \\over {\\sqrt {{\\mu _0}{ \\in _0}} }}\\cos \\left( {kx} \\right)\\widehat j$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B  = {{{E_0}} \\over {\\sqrt {{\\mu _0}{ \\in _0}} }}\\cos \\left( {kx} \\right)\\widehat k$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B  = {E_0}\\sqrt {{\\mu _0}{ \\in _0}} \\cos \\left( {kx} \\right)\\widehat k$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow B  = {E_0}\\sqrt {{\\mu _0}{ \\in _0}} \\cos \\left( {kx} \\right)\\widehat j$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow B  = {E_0}\\sqrt {{\\mu _0}{ \\in _0}} \\cos \\left( {kx} \\right)\\widehat k$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "khhPnOKuzztVxQ3cpjjgy2xukf14w4zh",
    "question": "The magnetic field of a plane electromagnetic wave is\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow B  = 3 \\times {10^{ - 8}}\\sin \\left[ {200\\pi \\left( {y + ct} \\right)} \\right]\\widehat i$$ T\n<br/>where c = 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>8</sup>\n ms<sup>–1</sup> is the speed of light.\nThe corresponding electric field is :\n",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow E  =  - {10^{ - 6}}\\sin \\left[ {200\\pi \\left( {y + ct} \\right)} \\right]\\widehat k$$ V/m",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E  =  - 9\\sin \\left[ {200\\pi \\left( {y + ct} \\right)} \\right]\\widehat k$$ V/m",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E  = 9\\sin \\left[ {200\\pi \\left( {y + ct} \\right)} \\right]\\widehat k$$ V/m",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E  = 3 \\times {10^{ - 8}}\\sin \\left[ {200\\pi \\left( {y + ct} \\right)} \\right]\\widehat k$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow E  =  - 9\\sin \\left[ {200\\pi \\left( {y + ct} \\right)} \\right]\\widehat k$$ V/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "eOSqxQ3fk1N3k8MNARjgy2xukeuuwq8h",
    "question": "A plane electromagnetic wave, has <br/>frequency\nof 2.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>10</sup> Hz and its energy density is\n1.02 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–8</sup> J/m<sup>3</sup> in vacuum. The amplitude of\nthe magnetic field of the wave is close\nto\n<br/>( $${1 \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}} = 9 \\times {10^9}{{N{m^2}} \\over {{C^2}}}$$ and speed of light<br/> =\n3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "190 nT",
      "150 nT",
      "160 nT",
      "180 nT"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "160 nT"
  },
  {
    "id": "HyCaeOcNWIDUKna9s97k9k2k5l1tg9x",
    "question": "A plane electromagnetic wave is propagating\nalong the direction\n$${{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$\n, with its polarization\nalong the direction $$\\widehat k$$ . The correct form of the\nmagnetic field of the wave would be (here B<sub>0</sub>\nis an appropriate constant) :",
    "options": [
      "$${B_0}{{\\widehat i - \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}\\cos \\left( {\\omega t - k{{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}} \\right)$$",
      "$${B_0}{{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}\\cos \\left( {\\omega t - k{{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}} \\right)$$",
      "$${B_0}{{\\widehat j - \\widehat i} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}\\cos \\left( {\\omega t + k{{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}} \\right)$$",
      "$${B_0}\\widehat k\\cos \\left( {\\omega t - k{{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$${B_0}{{\\widehat i - \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}\\cos \\left( {\\omega t - k{{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "a1MqrQXt4uNz66BZM27k9k2k5i7uvtf",
    "question": "The electric fields of two plane electromagnetic\nplane waves in vacuum are given by\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow {{E_1}}  = {E_0}\\widehat j\\cos \\left( {\\omega t - kx} \\right)$$\nand\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow {{E_2}}  = {E_0}\\widehat k\\cos \\left( {\\omega t - ky} \\right)$$\n<br/>At t = 0, a particle of charge q is at origin with\n<br/>a velocity $$\\overrightarrow v  = 0.8c\\widehat j$$ (c is the speed of light in\nvacuum). The instantaneous force experienced\nby the particle is :",
    "options": [
      "$${E_0}q\\left( {0.8\\widehat i - \\widehat j + 0.4\\widehat k} \\right)$$",
      "$${E_0}q\\left( { - 0.8\\widehat i + \\widehat j + \\widehat k} \\right)$$",
      "$${E_0}q\\left( {0.8\\widehat i + \\widehat j + 0.2\\widehat k} \\right)$$",
      "$${E_0}q\\left( {0.4\\widehat i - 3\\widehat j + 0.8\\widehat k} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$${E_0}q\\left( {0.8\\widehat i + \\widehat j + 0.2\\widehat k} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lK7D0NhsPKaMPgSnrh7k9k2k5hgokbk",
    "question": "A plane electromagnetic wave of frequency\n25 GHz is propagating in vacuum along the\nz-direction. At a particular point in space and\ntime, the magnetic field is given by $$\\overrightarrow B  = 5 \\times {10^{ - 8}}\\widehat jT$$. The corresponding electric field $$\\overrightarrow E $$ is (speed of light c = 3 × 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "15 $$\\widehat i$$V / m",
      "-15 $$\\widehat i$$V / m",
      "1.66 × 10<sup>–16</sup> $$\\widehat i$$V / m",
      "-1.66 × 10<sup>–16</sup> $$\\widehat i$$V / m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "15 $$\\widehat i$$V / m"
  },
  {
    "id": "EbHIkuASeOhQAXqWBI7k9k2k5f970fh",
    "question": "The electric field of a plane electromagnetic wave is given by\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow E  = {E_0}{{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}\\cos \\left( {kz + \\omega t} \\right)$$\n<br/><br/>At t = 0, a positively charged particle is at the point (x, y, z) = $$\\left( {0,0,{\\pi  \\over k}} \\right)$$.\n<br/> If its instantaneous velocity at\n(t = 0) is $${v_0}\\widehat k$$\n, the force acting on it due to the wave is :",
    "options": [
      "parallel to $$\\widehat k$$",
      "parallel to $${{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "antiparallel to $${{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "antiparallel to $${{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lBP1uqrgpsW4RQjldT7k9k2k5dqw8pe",
    "question": "If the magnetic field in a plane electromagnetic wave is given by\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow B $$ = 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-8</sup> sin(1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup>x + 48 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>10</sup>t)$$\\widehat j$$ T, then what will be expression for electric field ?\n",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow E $$ = (9sin(1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup>x + 48 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>10</sup>t)$$\\widehat k$$ V/m)",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E $$ = (60sin(1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup>x + 48 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>10</sup>t)$$\\widehat k$$ V/m)",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E $$ = (3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-8</sup> sin(1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup>x + 48 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>10</sup>t)$$\\widehat i$$ V/m)",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E $$ = (3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-8</sup> sin(1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup>x + 48 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>10</sup>t)$$\\widehat j$$ V/m)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow E $$ = (9sin(1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup>x + 48 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>10</sup>t)$$\\widehat k$$ V/m)"
  },
  {
    "id": "2fu620cxEZwIT2qKGqjgy2xukexrl14m",
    "question": "In a plane electromagnetic wave, the directions\nof electric field and magnetic field are\nrepresented by $$\\widehat k$$ and $$2\\widehat i - 2\\widehat j$$, respectively.\nWhat is the unit vector along direction of\npropagation of the wave?",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}\\left( {\\widehat i + 2\\widehat j} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}\\left( {2\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}\\left( {\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}\\left( {\\widehat j + \\widehat k} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}\\left( {\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "oq6jfusfmyOTHVVEz31kmhol9dz",
    "question": "A plane electromagnetic wave of frequency 500 MHz is travelling in vacuum along y-direction. At a particular point in space and time, <br/>$$\\overrightarrow B $$ = 8.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> $$\\widehat z$$T. The value of electric field at this point is :<br/><br/>(speed of light = 3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)<br/><br/>$$\\widehat x$$, $$\\widehat y$$, $$\\widehat z$$ are unit vectors along x, y and z directions.",
    "options": [
      "2.6 $$\\widehat x$$ V/m",
      "$$-$$24 $$\\widehat x$$ V/m",
      "24 $$\\widehat x$$ V/m",
      "$$-$$2.6 $$\\widehat y$$ V/m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$-$$24 $$\\widehat x$$ V/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "INnagC7ldNSMlgnAfP1kmhovr2p",
    "question": "For an electromagnetic wave travelling in free space, the relation between average energy densities due to electric (U<sub>e</sub>) and magnetic (U<sub>m</sub>) fields is :",
    "options": [
      "U<sub>e</sub> = U<sub>m</sub>",
      "U<sub>e</sub> $$\\ne$$ U<sub>m</sub>",
      "U<sub>e</sub> &lt; U<sub>m</sub>",
      "U<sub>e</sub> &gt; U<sub>m</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "U<sub>e</sub> = U<sub>m</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "O3jI5IHglvDMs9OL6h1kmkqzygi",
    "question": "A plane electromagnetic wave of frequency 100 MHz is travelling in vacuum along the x-direction. At a particular point in space and time, $$\\overrightarrow B  = 2.0 \\times {10^{ - 8}}\\widehat kT$$. (where, $$\\widehat k$$ is unit vector along z-direction) What is $$\\overrightarrow E $$ at this point?",
    "options": [
      "0.6 $$\\widehat j$$ V/m",
      "6.0 $$\\widehat k$$ V/m",
      "6.0 $$\\widehat j$$ V/m",
      "0.6 $$\\widehat k$$ V/m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "6.0 $$\\widehat j$$ V/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "7wGYP8oBZmpaPHqp421kmlvdfre",
    "question": "A plane electromagnetic wave propagating along y-direction can have the following pair of electric field $$\\left( {\\overrightarrow E } \\right)$$ and magnetic field $$\\left( {\\overrightarrow B } \\right)$$ components.",
    "options": [
      "E<sub>x</sub>, B<sub>z</sub> or E<sub>z</sub>, B<sub>x</sub>",
      "E<sub>x</sub>, B<sub>y</sub> or E<sub>y</sub>, B<sub>x</sub>",
      "E<sub>y</sub>, B<sub>y</sub> or E<sub>z</sub>, B<sub>z</sub>",
      "E<sub>y</sub>, B<sub>x</sub> or E<sub>x</sub>, B<sub>y</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "E<sub>x</sub>, B<sub>z</sub> or E<sub>z</sub>, B<sub>x</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqb8ril",
    "question": "In an electromagnetic wave the electric field vector and magnetic field vector are given as $$\\overrightarrow E  = {E_0}\\widehat i$$ and $$\\overrightarrow B  = {B_0}\\widehat k$$ respectively. The direction of propagation of electromagnetic wave is along :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {\\widehat k} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\widehat j$$",
      "$$\\left( { - \\widehat k} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( { - \\widehat j} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\left( { - \\widehat j} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsucbx4",
    "question": "Intensity of sunlight is observed as 0.092 Wm<sup>$$-$$2</sup> at a point in free space. What will be the peak value of magnetic field at the point?<br/><br/>($${\\varepsilon _0} = 8.85 \\times {10^{ - 12}}{C^2}{N^{ - 1}}{m^{ - 2}}$$)",
    "options": [
      "2.77 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> T",
      "1.96 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> T",
      "8.31 T",
      "5.88 T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "2.77 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> T"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kruly8xw",
    "question": "A linearly polarized electromagnetic wave in vacuum is <br/><br/>$$E = 3.1\\cos \\left[ {(1.8)z - (5.4 \\times {{10}^6})t} \\right]\\widehat iN/C$$<br/><br/>is incident normally on a perfectly reflecting wall at z = a. Choose the correct option",
    "options": [
      "The wavelength is 5.4 m",
      "The frequency of electromagnetic wave is 54 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup> Hz.",
      "The transmitted wave will be $$3.1\\cos \\left[ {(1.8)z - (5.4 \\times {{10}^6})t} \\right]\\widehat iN/C$$",
      "The reflected wave will be $$3.1\\cos \\left[ {(1.8)z + (5.4 \\times {{10}^6})t} \\right]\\widehat iN/C$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "The reflected wave will be $$3.1\\cos \\left[ {(1.8)z + (5.4 \\times {{10}^6})t} \\right]\\widehat iN/C$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krytb7sk",
    "question": "The relative permittivity of distilled water is 81. The velocity of light in it will be :<br/><br/>(Given $$\\mu$$<sub>r</sub> = 1)",
    "options": [
      "4.33 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> m/s",
      "2.33 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> m/s",
      "3.33 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> m/s",
      "5.33 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "3.33 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktbnruai",
    "question": "A light beam is described by $$E = 800\\sin \\omega \\left( {t - {x \\over c}} \\right)$$. An electron is allowed to move normal to the propagation of light beam with a speed of 3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. What is the maximum magnetic force exerted on the electron?",
    "options": [
      "1.28 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$18</sup> N",
      "1.28 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$21</sup> N",
      "12.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$17</sup> N",
      "12.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$18</sup> N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "12.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$18</sup> N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kte6j88r",
    "question": "Electric field in a plane electromagnetic wave is given by E = 50 sin(500x $$-$$ 10 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup> t) V/m The velocity of electromagnetic wave in this medium is :<br/><br/>(Given C = speed of light in vacuum)",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$C",
      "C",
      "$${2 \\over 3}$$C",
      "$${C \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over 3}$$C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjp2itf",
    "question": "The magnetic field vector of an electromagnetic wave is given by $$B = {B_0}{{\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}\\cos (kz - \\omega t)$$; where $$\\widehat i,\\widehat j$$ represents unit vector along x and y-axis respectively. At t = 0s, two electric charges q<sub>1</sub> of 4$$\\pi$$ coulomb and q<sub>2</sub> of 2$$\\pi$$ coulomb located at $$\\left( {0,0,{\\pi  \\over k}} \\right)$$ and $$\\left( {0,0,{{3\\pi } \\over k}} \\right)$$, respectively, have the same velocity of 0.5 c $$\\widehat i$$, (where c is the velocity of light). The ratio of the force acting on charge q<sub>1</sub> to q<sub>2</sub> is :-",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\sqrt 2 :1$$",
      "$$1:\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "2 : 1",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 :1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktmpsv5d",
    "question": "Electric field of plane electromagnetic wave propagating through a non-magnetic medium is given by <br/><br>E = 20cos(2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup> t $$-$$ 200x) V/m. The dielectric constant of the medium is equal to : (Take $$\\mu$$<sub>r</sub> = 1)</br>",
    "options": [
      "9",
      "2",
      "$${1 \\over 3}$$",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "9"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55kidqb",
    "question": "<p>An EM wave propagating in x-direction has a wavelength of 8 mm. The electric field vibrating y-direction has maximum magnitude of 60 Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. Choose the correct equations for electric and magnetic fields if the EM wave is propagating in vacuum :</p>",
    "options": [
      "<p>$${E_y} = 60\\sin \\left[ {{\\pi  \\over 4} \\times {{10}^3}(x - 3 \\times {{10}^8}t)} \\right]\\widehat j\\,\\,V{m^{ - 1}}$$</p>\n<p>$${B_z} = 2\\sin \\left[ {{\\pi  \\over 4} \\times {{10}^3}(x - 3 \\times {{10}^8}t)} \\right]\\widehat k\\,\\,T$$</p>",
      "<p>$${E_y} = 60\\sin \\left[ {{\\pi  \\over 4} \\times {{10}^3}(x - 3 \\times {{10}^8}t)} \\right]\\widehat j\\,\\,V{m^{ - 1}}$$</p>\n<p>$${B_z} = 2 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\sin \\left[ {{\\pi  \\over 4} \\times {{10}^3}(x - 3 \\times {{10}^8}t)} \\right]\\widehat k\\,\\,T$$</p>",
      "<p>$${E_y} = 2 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\sin \\left[ {{\\pi  \\over 4} \\times {{10}^3}(x - 3 \\times {{10}^8}t)} \\right]\\widehat j\\,\\,V{m^{ - 1}}$$</p>\n<p>$${B_z} = 60\\sin \\left[ {{\\pi  \\over 4} \\times {{10}^3}(x - 3 \\times {{10}^8}t)} \\right]\\widehat k\\,\\,T$$</p>",
      "<p>$${E_y} = 2 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\sin \\left[ {{\\pi  \\over 4} \\times {{10}^4}(x - 4 \\times {{10}^8}t)} \\right]\\widehat j\\,\\,V{m^{ - 1}}$$</p>\n<p>$${B_z} = 60\\sin \\left[ {{\\pi  \\over 4} \\times {{10}^4}(x - 4 \\times {{10}^8}t)} \\right]\\widehat k\\,\\,T$$</p>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "<p>$${E_y} = 60\\sin \\left[ {{\\pi  \\over 4} \\times {{10}^3}(x - 3 \\times {{10}^8}t)} \\right]\\widehat j\\,\\,V{m^{ - 1}}$$</p>\n<p>$${B_z} = 2 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\sin \\left[ {{\\pi  \\over 4} \\times {{10}^3}(x - 3 \\times {{10}^8}t)} \\right]\\widehat k\\,\\,T$$</p>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l569d42t",
    "question": "<p>A radar sends an electromagnetic signal of electric field (E<sub>0</sub>) = 2.25 V/m and magnetic field (B<sub>0</sub>) = 1.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> T which strikes a target on line of sight at a distance of 3 km in a medium. After that, a part of signal (echo) reflects back towards the radar with same velocity and by same path. If the signal was transmitted at time t = 0 from radar, then after how much time echo will reach to the radar?</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> s",
      "4.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> s",
      "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> s",
      "8.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "4.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56v7nwq",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : A time varying electric field is a source of changing magnetic field and vice-versa. Thus a disturbance in electric or magnetic field creates EM waves.</p>\n<p>Statement II : In a material medium, the EM wave travels with speed $$v = {1 \\over {\\sqrt {{\\mu _0}{ \\in _0}} }}$$. In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58c31uc",
    "question": "<p>If Electric field intensity of a uniform plane electromagnetic wave is given as $$E =  - 301.6\\sin (kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_x} + 452.4\\sin (kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_y}{V \\over m}$$. Then magnetic intensity 'H' of this wave in Am<sup>$$-$$1</sup> will be :</p>\n<p>[Given : Speed of light in vacuum $$c = 3 \\times {10^8}$$ ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, Permeability of vacuum $${\\mu _0} = 4\\pi  \\times {10^{ - 7}}$$ NA<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$ + 0.8\\sin (kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_y} + 0.8\\sin (kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_x}$$",
      "$$ + 1.0 \\times {10^{ - 6}}\\sin (kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_y} + 1.5 \\times {10^{ - 6}}(kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_x}$$",
      "$$ - 0.8\\sin (kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_y} - 1.2\\sin (kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_x}$$",
      "$$ - 1.0 \\times {10^{ - 6}}\\sin (kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_y} - 1.5 \\times {10^{ - 6}}\\sin (kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_x}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$ - 0.8\\sin (kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_y} - 1.2\\sin (kz - \\omega t){\\widehat a_x}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58c4m2t",
    "question": "<p>In free space, an electromagnetic wave of 3 GHz frequency strikes over the edge of an object of size $${\\lambda  \\over {100}}$$, where $$\\lambda$$ is the wavelength of the wave in free space. The phenomenon, which happens there will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Reflection",
      "Refraction",
      "Diffraction",
      "Scattering"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "Scattering"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59p8cqw",
    "question": "<p>The electromagnetic waves travel in a medium at a speed of 2.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> m/s. The relative permeability of the medium is 1.0. The relative permittivity of the medium will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.25",
      "4.25",
      "6.25",
      "8.25"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "2.25"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5akrd1g",
    "question": "<p>The electric field in an electromagnetic wave is given by E = 56.5 sin $$\\omega$$(t $$-$$ x/c) NC<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. Find the intensity of the wave if it is propagating along x-axis in the free space.</p>\n<p>(Given : $$\\varepsilon $$<sub>0</sub> = 8.85 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$12</sup>C<sup>2</sup>N<sup>$$-$$1</sup>m<sup>$$-$$2</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "5.65 Wm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "4.24 Wm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "1.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> Wm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "56.5 Wm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "4.24 Wm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bc6h11",
    "question": "<p>An electric bulb is rated as 200 W. What will be the peak magnetic field at 4 m distance produced by the radiations coming from this bulb? Consider this bulb as a point source with 3.5% efficiency.</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.19 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>T",
      "1.71 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>T",
      "0.84 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>T",
      "3.36 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "1.71 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>T"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c3zqv4",
    "question": "<p>A plane electromagnetic wave travels in a medium of relative permeability 1.61 and relative permittivity 6.44. If magnitude of magnetic intensity is 4.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> Am<sup>$$-$$1</sup> at a point, what will be the approximate magnitude of electric field intensity at that point?</p>\n<p>(Given : Permeability of free space $$\\mu$$<sub>0</sub> = 4$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> NA<sup>$$-$$2</sup>, speed of light in vacuum c = 3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "16.96 Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "2.25 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "8.48 Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "6.75 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>6</sup> Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "8.48 Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w2wlzw",
    "question": "<p>An expression for oscillating electric field in a plane electromagnetic wave is given as E<sub>z</sub> = 300 sin(5$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup>x $$-$$ 3$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>11</sup>t) Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup></p>\n<p>Then, the value of magnetic field amplitude will be :</p>\n<p>(Given : speed of light in Vacuum c = 3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> T",
      "5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> T",
      "18 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup> T",
      "21 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup> T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> T"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dywbms",
    "question": "<p>The rms value of conduction current in a parallel plate capacitor is $$6.9 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{A}$$. The capacity of this capacitor, if it is connected to $$230 \\mathrm{~V}$$ ac supply with an angular frequency of $$600 \\,\\mathrm{rad} / \\mathrm{s}$$, will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "5 pF",
      "50 pF",
      "100 pF",
      "200 pF"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "50 pF"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f4smf8",
    "question": "<p>Light wave travelling in air along x-direction is given by $${E_y} = 540\\sin \\pi  \\times {10^4}(x - ct)\\,V{m^{ - 1}}$$. Then, the peak value of magnetic field of wave will be (Given c = 3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "18 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> T",
      "54 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> T",
      "54 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> T",
      "18 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "18 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> T"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gk7gfd",
    "question": "<p>The magnetic field of a plane electromagnetic wave is given by :</p>\n<p>$$\n\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}=2 \\times 10^{-8} \\sin \\left(0.5 \\times 10^{3} x+1.5 \\times 10^{11} \\mathrm{t}\\right) \\,\\hat{j} \\mathrm{~T}$$.</p>\n<p>The amplitude of the electric field would be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$6\\, \\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$ along $$x$$-axis",
      "$$3\\, \\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$ along $$z$$-axis",
      "$$6\\, \\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$ along $$z$$-axis",
      "$$2 \\times 10^{-8} \\,\\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$ along $$z$$-axis"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$6\\, \\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$ along $$z$$-axis"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i0kafr",
    "question": "<p>The oscillating magnetic field in a plane electromagnetic wave is given by <br/><br/>$$B_{y}=5 \\times 10^{-6} \\sin 1000 \\pi\\left(5 x-4 \\times 10^{8} t\\right) T$$. The amplitude of electric field will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$15 \\times 10^{2} \\,\\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$",
      "$$5 \\times 10^{-6} \\,\\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$",
      "$$16 \\times 10^{12} \\,\\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$",
      "$$4 \\times 10^{2} \\,\\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$4 \\times 10^{2} \\,\\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i1kxdj",
    "question": "<p>A velocity selector consists of electric field $$\\vec{E}=E \\,\\hat{k}$$ and magnetic field $$\\vec{B}=B \\,\\hat{j}$$ with $$B=12 \\,m T$$. The value of $$E$$ required for an electron of energy $$728 \\,\\mathrm{e} V$$ moving along the positive $$x$$-axis to pass undeflected is :</p>\n<p>(Given, mass of electron $$=9.1 \\times 10^{-31} \\mathrm{~kg}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$192 \\,\\mathrm{kVm}^{-1}$$",
      "$$192 \\,\\mathrm{mVm}^{-1}$$",
      "$$9600 \\,\\mathrm{kVm}^{-1}$$",
      "$$16 \\,\\mathrm{kVm}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$192 \\,\\mathrm{kVm}^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jibjjv",
    "question": "<p>A beam of light travelling along $$X$$-axis is described by the electric field $$E_{y}=900 \\sin \\omega(\\mathrm{t}-x / c)$$. The ratio of electric force to magnetic force on a charge $$\\mathrm{q}$$ moving along $$Y$$-axis with a speed of $$3 \\times 10^{7} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ will be :</p>\n<p>(Given speed of light $$=3 \\times 10^{8} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "1 : 10",
      "10 : 1",
      "1 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "10 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6knllmm",
    "question": "<p>Identify the correct statements from the following descriptions of various properties of electromagnetic waves.</p>\n<p>(A) In a plane electromagnetic wave electric field and magnetic field must be perpendicular to each other and direction of propagation of wave should be along electric field or magnetic field.</p>\n<p>(B) The energy in electromagnetic wave is divided equally between electric and magnetic fields.</p>\n<p>(C) Both electric field and magnetic field are parallel to each other and perpendicular to the direction of propagation of wave.</p>\n<p>(D) The electric field, magnetic field and direction of propagation of wave must be perpendicular to each other.</p>\n<p>(E) The ratio of amplitude of magnetic field to the amplitude of electric field is equal to speed of light.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(D) only",
      "(B) and (D) only",
      "(B), (C) and (E) only",
      "(A), (B) and (E) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "(B) and (D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nsuzar",
    "question": "<p>Sun light falls normally on a surface of area $$36 \\mathrm{~cm}^{2}$$ and exerts an average force of $$7.2 \\times 10^{-9} \\mathrm{~N}$$ within a time period of 20 minutes. Considering a case of complete absorption, the energy flux of incident light is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$25.92 \\times 10^{2} \\mathrm{~W} / \\mathrm{cm}^{2}$$",
      "$$8.64 \\times 10^{-6} \\mathrm{~W} / \\mathrm{cm}^{2}$$",
      "$$6.0 \\mathrm{~W} / \\mathrm{cm}^{2}$$",
      "$$0.06\\mathrm{~W} / \\mathrm{cm}^{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$0.06\\mathrm{~W} / \\mathrm{cm}^{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnw4zqr",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of average electric energy density and total average energy density of electromagnetic wave is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "3",
      "2",
      "$$\\frac{1}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqvfxpf",
    "question": "A point source of $100 \\mathrm{~W}$ emits light with $5 \\%$ efficiency. At a distance of $5 \\mathrm{~m}$ from the source, the intensity produced by the electric field component is:",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{1}{40 \\pi} \\frac{W}{m^2}$",
      "$\\frac{1}{10 \\pi} \\frac{W}{m^2}$",
      "$\\frac{1}{20 \\pi} \\frac{W}{m^2}$",
      "$\\frac{1}{2 \\pi} \\frac{W}{m^2}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$\\frac{1}{40 \\pi} \\frac{W}{m^2}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsa8zxf",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Electromagnetic waves are not deflected by electric and magnetic field.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The amplitude of electric field and the magnetic field in electromagnetic waves are related to each other as $${E_0} = \\sqrt {{{{\\mu _0}} \\over {{\\varepsilon _0}}}} {B_0}$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true and Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "Statement I is true and Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldspc6fa",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following are true?</p>\n<p>A. Speed of light in vacuum is dependent on the direction of propagation.</p>\n<p>B. Speed of light in a medium is independent of the wavelength of light.</p>\n<p>C. The speed of light is independent of the motion of the source.</p>\n<p>D. The speed of light in a medium is independent of intensity.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "B and D only",
      "B and C only",
      "A and C only",
      "C and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "C and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtxzrmx",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 669px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Gauss's Law in Electrostatics</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\oint {\\overrightarrow E \\,.\\,d\\overrightarrow l  =  - {{d{\\phi _B}} \\over {dt}}} $$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Faraday's Law</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\oint {\\overrightarrow B \\,.\\,d\\overrightarrow A  = 0} $$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Gauss's Law in Magnetism</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\oint {\\overrightarrow B \\,.\\,d\\overrightarrow l  = {\\mu _0}{i_c} + {\\mu _0}{ \\in _0}{{d{\\phi _E}} \\over {dt}}} $$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ampere-Maxwell Law</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\oint {\\overrightarrow E \\,.\\,d\\overrightarrow s  = {q \\over {{ \\in _0}}}} $$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduhw3w4",
    "question": "<p>An electromagnetic wave is transporting energy in the negative $$z$$ direction. At a certain point and certain time the direction of electric field of the wave is along positive $$y$$ direction. What will be the direction of the magnetic field of the wave at that point and instant?</p>",
    "options": [
      "Negative direction of $$y$$",
      "Positive direction of $$z$$",
      "Positive direction of $$x$$",
      "Negative direction $$x$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "Positive direction of $$x$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwr9mnf",
    "question": "<p>The electric field and magnetic field components of an electromagnetic wave going through vacuum is described by</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{{E_x} = {E_o}\\sin (kz - \\omega t)}$$</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{{B_y} = {B_o}\\sin (kz - \\omega t)}$$</p>\n<p>Then the correct relation between E$$_0$$ and B$$_0$$ is given by</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{{E_o}{B_o} = \\omega k}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{{E_0} = k{B_0}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{k{E_0} = \\omega {B_0}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{\\omega {E_0} = k{B_0}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{k{E_0} = \\omega {B_0}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyelb09",
    "question": "<p>In $$\\overrightarrow E $$ and $$\\overrightarrow K $$ represent electric field and propagation vectors of the EM waves in vacuum, then magnetic field vector is given by :</p>\n<p>($$\\omega$$ - angular frequency) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over \\omega }\\left( {\\overline K  \\times \\overline E } \\right)$$",
      "$$\\overline K  \\times \\overline E $$",
      "$$\\omega \\left( {\\overline K  \\times \\overline E } \\right)$$",
      "$$\\omega \\left( {\\overline E  \\times \\overline K } \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over \\omega }\\left( {\\overline K  \\times \\overline E } \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgozyf20",
    "question": "<p>In an electromagnetic wave, at an instant and at particular position, the electric field is along the negative $$z$$-axis and magnetic field is along the positive $$x$$-axis. Then the direction of propagation of electromagnetic wave is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "at $$45^{\\circ}$$ angle from positive y-axis",
      " positive $$y$$-axis",
      "negative $$\\mathrm{y}$$-axis",
      "positive z-axis"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "negative $$\\mathrm{y}$$-axis"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq2j714",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following Maxwell's equation is valid for time varying conditions but not valid for static conditions :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\oint \\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{E}} \\cdot \\overrightarrow{d l}=0$$",
      "$$\\oint \\vec{B} \\cdot \\overrightarrow{d l}=\\mu_{0} I$$",
      "$$\\oint \\vec{E} \\cdot \\overrightarrow{d l}=-\\frac{\\partial \\phi_{B}}{\\partial t}$$",
      "$$\\oint \\vec{D} \\cdot \\overrightarrow{d A}=Q$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\oint \\vec{E} \\cdot \\overrightarrow{d l}=-\\frac{\\partial \\phi_{B}}{\\partial t}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswh6t1",
    "question": "<p>A plane electromagnetic wave of frequency $$20 ~\\mathrm{MHz}$$ propagates in free space along $$\\mathrm{x}$$-direction. At a particular space and time, $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{E}}=6.6 \\hat{j} \\mathrm{~V} / \\mathrm{m}$$. What is $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}$$ at this point?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-2.2 \\times 10^{-8} \\hat{i} T$$",
      "$$2.2 \\times 10^{-8} \\hat{i} T$$",
      "$$2.2 \\times 10^{-8} \\hat{k} T$$",
      "$$-2.2 \\times 10^{-8} \\hat{k} T$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$2.2 \\times 10^{-8} \\hat{k} T$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguxxzet",
    "question": "<p>The electric field in an electromagnetic wave is given as</p>\n<p>$$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{E}}=20 \\sin \\omega\\left(\\mathrm{t}-\\frac{x}{\\mathrm{c}}\\right) \\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{j}} \\mathrm{NC}^{-1}$$</p>\n<p>where $$\\omega$$ and $$c$$ are angular frequency and velocity of electromagnetic wave respectively. The energy contained in a volume of $$5 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~m}^{3}$$ will be</p>\n<p>(Given $$\\varepsilon_{0}=8.85 \\times 10^{-12} \\mathrm{C}^{2} / \\mathrm{Nm}^{2}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "<p>$$17 \\cdot 7 \\times 10^{-13} \\mathrm{~J}$$</p>",
      "$$28 \\cdot 5 \\times 10^{-13} \\mathrm{~J}$$",
      "$$8 \\cdot 85 \\times 10^{-13} \\mathrm{~J}$$",
      "$$88 \\cdot 5 \\times 10^{-13} \\mathrm{~J}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$8 \\cdot 85 \\times 10^{-13} \\mathrm{~J}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvrnazv",
    "question": "<p>The amplitude of magnetic field in an electromagnetic wave propagating along y-axis is $$6.0 \\times 10^{-7} \\mathrm{~T}$$. The maximum value of electric field in the electromagnetic wave is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$6.0 \\times 10^{-7} ~\\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$",
      "$$5 \\times 10^{14} ~\\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$",
      "$$180 ~\\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$",
      "$$2 \\times 10^{15} ~\\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$180 ~\\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgxwty7j",
    "question": "<p>The energy of an electromagnetic wave contained in a small volume oscillates with</p>",
    "options": [
      "double the frequency of the wave",
      "the frequency of the wave",
      "half the frequency of the wave",
      "zero frequency"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "double the frequency of the wave"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh25dl4z",
    "question": "<p>For the plane electromagnetic wave given by $$E=E_{0} \\sin (\\omega t-k x)$$ and $$B=B_{0} \\sin (\\omega t-k x)$$, the ratio of average electric energy density to average magnetic energy density is</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "4",
      "2",
      "1/2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh2zrxuq",
    "question": "<p>The energy density associated with electric field $$\\vec{E}$$ and magnetic field $$\\vec{B}$$ of an electromagnetic wave in free space is given by $$\\left(\\epsilon_{0}-\\right.$$ permittivity of free space, $$\\mu_{0}-$$ permeability of free space)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$U_{E}=\\frac{\\epsilon_{0} E^{2}}{2}, U_{B}=\\frac{B^{2}}{2 \\mu_{0}}$$",
      "$$U_{E}=\\frac{E^{2}}{2 \\epsilon_{0}}, U_{B}=\\frac{\\mu_{0} B^{2}}{2}$$",
      "$$U_{E}=\\frac{\\epsilon_{0} E^{2}}{2}, U_{B}=\\frac{\\mu_{0} B^{2}}{2}$$",
      "$$U_{E}=\\frac{E^{2}}{2 \\epsilon_{0}}, U_{B}=\\frac{B^{2}}{2 \\mu_{0}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$U_{E}=\\frac{\\epsilon_{0} E^{2}}{2}, U_{B}=\\frac{B^{2}}{2 \\mu_{0}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsan1vgp",
    "question": "If frequency of electromagnetic wave is $60 \\mathrm{~MHz}$ and it travels in air along $z$ direction then the corresponding electric and magnetic field vectors will be mutually perpendicular to each other and the wavelength of the wave (in $\\mathrm{m}$ ) is :",
    "options": [
      "2.5",
      "5",
      "10",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "5"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3rg5e",
    "question": "<p>A plane electromagnetic wave propagating in $$\\mathrm{x}$$-direction is described by</p>\n<p>$$E_y=\\left(200 \\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}\\right) \\sin \\left[1.5 \\times 10^7 t-0.05 x\\right] \\text {; }$$</p>\n<p>The intensity of the wave is :</p>\n<p>(Use $$\\epsilon_0=8.85 \\times 10^{-12} \\mathrm{C}^2 \\mathrm{~N}^{-1} \\mathrm{~m}^{-2}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$35.4 \\mathrm{~Wm}^{-2}$$\n",
      "$$53.1 \\mathrm{~Wm}^{-2}$$\n",
      "$$26.6 \\mathrm{~Wm}^{-2}$$\n",
      "$$106.2 \\mathrm{~Wm}^{-2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$53.1 \\mathrm{~Wm}^{-2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscpkphx",
    "question": "<p>An object is placed in a medium of refractive index 3 . An electromagnetic wave of intensity $$6 \\times 10^8 \\mathrm{~W} / \\mathrm{m}^2$$ falls normally on the object and it is absorbed completely. The radiation pressure on the object would be (speed of light in free space $$=3 \\times 10^8 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ ) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$6 \\mathrm{~Nm}^{-2}$$\n",
      "$$36 \\mathrm{~Nm}^{-2}$$\n",
      "$$18 \\mathrm{~Nm}^{-2}$$\n",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~Nm}^{-2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$6 \\mathrm{~Nm}^{-2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd5dntd",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I: Electromagnetic waves carry energy as they travel through space and this energy is equally shared by the electric and magnetic fields.</p>\n<p>Statement II: When electromagnetic waves strike a surface, a pressure is exerted on the surface.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct.\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.\n",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse6nvzl",
    "question": "<p>In a plane EM wave, the electric field oscillates sinusoidally at a frequency of $$5 \\times 10^{10} \\mathrm{~Hz}$$ and an amplitude of $$50 \\mathrm{~Vm}^{-1}$$. The total average energy density of the electromagnetic field of the wave is : [Use $$\\varepsilon_0=8.85 \\times 10^{-12} \\mathrm{C}^2 / \\mathrm{Nm}^2$$ ]</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4.425 \\times 10^{-8} \\mathrm{Jm}^{-3}$$\n",
      "$$2.212 \\times 10^{-10} \\mathrm{Jm}^{-3}$$\n",
      "$$2.212 \\times 10^{-8} \\mathrm{Jm}^{-3}$$\n",
      "$$1.106 \\times 10^{-8} \\mathrm{Jm}^{-3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$1.106 \\times 10^{-8} \\mathrm{Jm}^{-3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsflup2v",
    "question": "<p>A plane electromagnetic wave of frequency $$35 \\mathrm{~MHz}$$ travels in free space along the $$X$$-direction. At a particular point (in space and time) $$\\vec{E}=9.6 \\hat{j} \\mathrm{~V} / \\mathrm{m}$$. The value of magnetic field at this point is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$9.6 \\hat{j} T$$\n",
      "$$3.2 \\times 10^{-8} \\hat{i} T$$\n",
      "$$9.6 \\times 10^{-8} \\hat{k} T$$\n",
      "$$3.2 \\times 10^{-8} \\hat{k} T$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$3.2 \\times 10^{-8} \\hat{k} T$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgdfsz5",
    "question": "<p>The electric field of an electromagnetic wave in free space is represented as $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{E}}=\\mathrm{E}_0 \\cos (\\omega \\mathrm{t}-\\mathrm{kz}) \\hat{i}$$. The corresponding magnetic induction vector will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}=\\mathrm{E}_0 \\mathrm{C} \\cos (\\omega \\mathrm{t}+\\mathrm{k} z) \\hat{j}$$\n",
      "$$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}=\\frac{\\mathrm{E}_0}{\\mathrm{C}} \\cos (\\omega \\mathrm{t}-\\mathrm{kz}) \\hat{j}$$\n",
      "$$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}=\\mathrm{E}_0 \\mathrm{C} \\cos (\\omega \\mathrm{t}-\\mathrm{k} z) \\hat{j}$$\n",
      "$$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}=\\frac{\\mathrm{E}_0}{\\mathrm{C}} \\cos (\\omega \\mathrm{t}+\\mathrm{kz}) \\hat{j}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}=\\frac{\\mathrm{E}_0}{\\mathrm{C}} \\cos (\\omega \\mathrm{t}-\\mathrm{kz}) \\hat{j}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxweb5k",
    "question": "<p>The magnetic field in a plane electromagnetic wave is $$\\mathrm{B}_{\\mathrm{y}}=\\left(3.5 \\times 10^{-7}\\right) \\sin \\left(1.5 \\times 10^3 x+0.5 \\times 10^{11} t\\right) \\mathrm{T}$$. The corresponding electric field will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$E_z=105 \\sin \\left(1.5 \\times 10^3 x+0.5 \\times 10^{11} t\\right) \\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$E_y=10.5 \\sin \\left(1.5 \\times 10^3 x+0.5 \\times 10^{11} t\\right) \\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$E_y=1.17 \\sin \\left(1.5 \\times 10^3 x+0.5 \\times 10^{11} t\\right) \\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$E_z=1.17 \\sin \\left(1.5 \\times 10^3 x+0.5 \\times 10^{11} t\\right) \\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$E_z=105 \\sin \\left(1.5 \\times 10^3 x+0.5 \\times 10^{11} t\\right) \\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luy9clsu",
    "question": "<p>A plane EM wave is propagating along $$x$$ direction. It has a wavelength of $$4 \\mathrm{~mm}$$. If electric field is in $$y$$ direction with the maximum magnitude of $$60 \\mathrm{~Vm}^{-1}$$, the equation for magnetic field is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{B}_z=2 \\times 10^{-7} \\sin \\left[\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\left(x-3 \\times 10^8 \\mathrm{t}\\right)\\right] \\hat{\\mathrm{k}} \\mathrm{T}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{B}_z=2 \\times 10^{-7} \\sin \\left[\\frac{\\pi}{2} \\times 10^3\\left(x-3 \\times 10^8 \\mathrm{t}\\right)\\right] \\hat{\\mathrm{k}} \\mathrm{T}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{B}_z=60 \\sin \\left[\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\left(x-3 \\times 10^8 \\mathrm{t}\\right)\\right] \\hat{\\mathrm{k}} \\mathrm{T}$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{B}_x=60 \\sin \\left[\\frac{\\pi}{2}\\left(x-3 \\times 10^8 \\mathrm{t}\\right)\\right] \\hat{\\mathrm{i}} \\mathrm{T}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{B}_z=2 \\times 10^{-7} \\sin \\left[\\frac{\\pi}{2} \\times 10^3\\left(x-3 \\times 10^8 \\mathrm{t}\\right)\\right] \\hat{\\mathrm{k}} \\mathrm{T}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxsz4",
    "question": "<p>The electric field in an electromagnetic wave is given by $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{E}}=\\hat{i} 40 \\cos \\omega(\\mathrm{t}-z / \\mathrm{c}) \\mathrm{NC}^{-1}$$. The magnetic field induction of this wave is (in SI unit) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}=\\hat{j} \\frac{40}{\\mathrm{c}} \\cos \\omega(\\mathrm{t}-z / \\mathrm{c})$$\n",
      "$$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}=\\hat{i} \\frac{40}{\\mathrm{c}} \\cos \\omega(\\mathrm{t}-z / \\mathrm{c})$$\n",
      "$$\\vec{B}=\\hat{j} 40 \\cos \\omega(t-z / c)$$\n",
      "$$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}=\\hat{k} \\frac{40}{\\mathrm{c}} \\cos \\omega(\\mathrm{t}-z / \\mathrm{c})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}=\\hat{j} \\frac{40}{\\mathrm{c}} \\cos \\omega(\\mathrm{t}-z / \\mathrm{c})$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gsw9i",
    "question": "<p>Average force exerted on a non-reflecting surface at normal incidence is $$2.4 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~N}$$. If $$360 \\mathrm{~W} / \\mathrm{cm}^2$$ is the light energy flux during span of 1 hour 30 minutes, Then the area of the surface is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$20 \\mathrm{~m}^2$$\n",
      "$$0.2 \\mathrm{~m}^2$$\n",
      "$$0.1 \\mathrm{~m}^2$$\n",
      "$$0.02 \\mathrm{~m}^2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "$$0.02 \\mathrm{~m}^2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29elu",
    "question": "<p>In the given electromagnetic wave $$\\mathrm{E}_{\\mathrm{y}}=600 \\sin (\\omega t-\\mathrm{kx}) \\mathrm{Vm}^{-1}$$, intensity of the associated light beam is (in $$\\mathrm{W} / \\mathrm{m}^2$$ : (Given $$\\epsilon_0=9 \\times 10^{-12} \\mathrm{C}^2 \\mathrm{~N}^{-1} \\mathrm{~m}^{-2}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "486",
      "729",
      "243",
      "972"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "486"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57nqe",
    "question": "<p>Electromagnetic waves travel in a medium with speed of $$1.5 \\times 10^8 \\mathrm{~m} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$. The relative permeability of the medium is 2.0. The relative permittivity will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "1",
      "2",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "displacement-current-and-properties-of-em-waves",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "9TyLi4Ad66ficdgT",
    "question": "Which of the following are not electromagnetic waves? ",
    "options": [
      "cosmic rays ",
      "gamma rays ",
      "$$\\beta $$-rays ",
      "$$X$$-rays "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\beta $$-rays "
  },
  {
    "id": "H1N8OkCJzvninLLpHWFlJ",
    "question": "Match the <b>List - I</b> (Phenomenon associated with electromagnetic radiation) with <b>List - II</b> (Part of electromagnetic spectrum) and select the correct code from the choices given the lists  : \n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-13k7{font-size:20px;text-align:left}\n.tg .tg-p7ly{font-weight:bold;font-size:20px;text-align:center}\n.tg .tg-fbrz{font-weight:bold;font-size:20px;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-60hs{font-size:20px;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-p7ly\" colspan=\"2\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-p7ly\" colspan=\"2\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Doublet of sodium</td>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Visible radiation</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Wavelength<br/>corresponding to<br/>temperature associated<br/>with the isotropic<br/>radiation filling all space</td>\n<td class=\"tg-p7ly\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">Microwave</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-fbrz\">(III</td>\n<td class=\"tg-60hs\">Wavelength emitted by<br/>atomic hydrogen in<br/>interstellar space</td>\n<td class=\"tg-fbrz\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-60hs\">Short radiowave</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-fbrz\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-60hs\">Wavelength of radiation<br/>arising from two close<br/>energy levels in hydrogen</td>\n<td class=\"tg-fbrz\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-60hs\">X - rays</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "(I)-(A),&nbsp;(II)-(B),&nbsp;(III)-(B),&nbsp;(IV)-(C)",
      "(I)-(A),&nbsp;(II)-(B),&nbsp;(III)-(C),&nbsp;(IV)-(C)",
      "(I)-(D),&nbsp;(II)-(C),&nbsp;(III)-(A),&nbsp;(IV)-(B)",
      "(I)-(B),&nbsp;(II)-(A),&nbsp;(III)-(D),&nbsp;(IV)-(A)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "(I)-(A),&nbsp;(II)-(B),&nbsp;(III)-(C),&nbsp;(IV)-(C)"
  },
  {
    "id": "k7ytCLWB74M9WShStuaww",
    "question": "If microwaves, X rays, infracted, gamma rays, ultra-violet, radio waves and visible parts of the electromagnetic spectrum by M, X, I,  G, U, R and V, the following is the arrangement in ascending order of wavelength : ",
    "options": [
      "R, M, I, V, U, X &nbsp;and&nbsp; G",
      "M, R, V, X, U, G &nbsp;and&nbsp; I",
      "G, X, U, V, I, M &nbsp;and&nbsp; R",
      "I, M, R,  U, V, X &nbsp;and&nbsp; G"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "G, X, U, V, I, M &nbsp;and&nbsp; R"
  },
  {
    "id": "WAwUW3jVZsfVH4PGnJHx0",
    "question": "Microwave oven acts on the principle of :",
    "options": [
      "transferring electrons from lower to higher energy levels in water molecule",
      "giving rotational energy to water molecules ",
      "giving vibrational energy to water molecules",
      "giving translational energy to water molecules "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "giving vibrational energy to water molecules"
  },
  {
    "id": "6w6lQuuDWsYO91LpgAp50",
    "question": "Arrange the following electromagnetic\nradiations per quantum in the order of\nincreasing energy :\n<br/><br/>A : Blue light           B : Yellow light\n<br/><br/>C : X-ray                 D : Radiowave.\n",
    "options": [
      "C, A, B, D",
      "B, A, D, C",
      "D, B, A, C",
      "A, B, D, C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "D, B, A, C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1FaB6PXo2jufHbi6fPjgy2xukf6dxkff",
    "question": "Choose the correct option relating wave lengths of different parts of electromagnetic wave spectrum:",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>radio waves</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>micro waves</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>visible</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>x-rays</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>visible</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>x-rays</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>radio waves</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>micro waves</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>visible</sub> &lt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>micro waves</sub> &lt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>radio waves</sub> &lt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>x-rays</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda $$<sub>x-rays</sub>\n &lt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>micro waves</sub> &lt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>radio waves</sub> &lt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>visible</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda $$<sub>radio waves</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>micro waves</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>visible</sub> &gt; $$\\lambda $$<sub>x-rays</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "j4bezf75HbErwCQpP8jgy2xukfl2kjj2",
    "question": "The correct match between the entries in\ncolumn I and column II are :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\"><b>I</b></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\"><b>II</b></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\"><b>Radiation</b></td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\"><b>Wavelength</b>\n</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(a) Microwave </td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(i) 100 m</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(b) Gamma rays</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(ii) 10<sup>–15</sup> m</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(c) A.M. radio waves</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(iii) 10<sup>–10</sup> m\n</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(d) X-rays </td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(iv) 10<sup>–3</sup> m</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(ii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "(a)-(iv), (b)-(ii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "MyDXxdIgrukOhwRk5V1klroi84o",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Source of microwave frequency</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Radioactive decay of nucleus</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Source of infrared frequency</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Magnetron</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Source of Gamma Rays</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Inner shell electrons</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Source of X-rays</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Vibration of atoms and molecules</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td></td>\n<td></td>\n<td>(v)</td>\n<td>LASER</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td></td>\n<td></td>\n<td>(vi)</td>\n<td>RC circuit</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(vi), (b)-(v), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(vi), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(vi), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(v)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57q65ka",
    "question": "<p>Match List-I with List-II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-1wig{font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 472px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 44px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 143px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 42px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 243px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-1wig\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(a)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Ultraviolet rays</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(i)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Study crystal structure</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(b)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Microwaves</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(ii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Greenhouse effect</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(c)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Infrared rays</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(iii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Sterilizing surgical instrument</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(d)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">X-rays</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(iv)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Radar system</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(iii), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58i2ej5",
    "question": "<p>Which is the correct ascending order of wavelengths?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>visible</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>X-ray</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>gamma-ray</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>microwave</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>gamma-ray</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>X-ray</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>visible</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>microwave</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>X-ray</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>gamma-ray</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>visible</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>microwave</sub>",
      "$$\\lambda$$<sub>microwave</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>visible</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>gamma-ray</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>X-ray</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda$$<sub>gamma-ray</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>X-ray</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>visible</sub> < $$\\lambda$$<sub>microwave</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p5a0dm",
    "question": "<p>Match List - I with List - II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-fymr{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 494px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 53px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 143px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 40px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 258px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-fymr\">List - I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-fymr\">List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(a)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">UV rays</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(i)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Diagnostic tool in medicine</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(b)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">X-rays</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(ii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Water purification</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(c)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Microwave</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(iii)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Communication, Radar</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(d)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Infrared wave</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(iv)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Improving visibility in foggy days</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(iii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(ii), (d)-(iv)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iii), (d)-(iv)"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo6iorp",
    "question": "Match List <b>I</b> with List <b>II</b><br/><br/>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\" colspan=\"2\"> LIST I </th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\" colspan=\"2\"> LIST II </th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Microwaves</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Physiotherapy</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">UV rays</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Treatment of cancer</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Infra-red light</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Lasik eye surgery</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">X-ray</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Aircraft navigation</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below:",
    "options": [
      "A - IV, B - III, C - I, D - II",
      "A - II, B - IV, C - III, D - I",
      "A - III, B - II, C - I, D - IV",
      "A - IV, B - I, C - II, D - III"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "A - IV, B - III, C - I, D - II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldog4ddy",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 581px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 223px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 263px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Microwaves</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Radio active decay of the nucleus</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Gamma rays</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Rapid acceleration and deceleration of electron in aerials</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Radio waves</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Inner shell electrons</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">X-rays</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Klystron valve</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-III, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnys79e",
    "question": "Match <b>List I</b> with <b>List II</b> of Electromagnetic waves with corresponding wavelength range :<br/><br/>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A) Microwave</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I) $400 \\mathrm{~nm}$ to $1 \\mathrm{~nm}$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B) Ultraviolet</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II) $1 \\mathrm{~nm}$ to $10^{-3} \\mathrm{~nm}$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C) X-Ray</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III) $1 \\mathrm{~mm}$ to $700 \\mathrm{~nm}$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D) Infra-red</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV) $0.1 \\mathrm{~m}$ to $1 \\mathrm{~mm}$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below:",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(IV), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(III), (D) -(II)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(II), (C)-(I), (D)-(III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrhh4x2",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A : EM waves used for optical communication have longer wavelengths than that of microwave, employed in Radar technology.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Infrared EM waves are more energetic than microwaves, (used in Radar)</p>\n<p>In the light of given statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ are true but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathrm{A}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is false",
      "Both $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathrm{r}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathrm{A}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erjny",
    "question": "<p>Arrange the following in the ascending order of wavelength:</p>\n<p>A. Gamma rays $$\\left(\\lambda_1\\right)$$</p>\n<p>B. $$x$$ - rays $$\\left(\\lambda_2\\right)$$</p>\n<p>C. Infrared waves $$\\left(\\lambda_3\\right)$$</p>\n<p>D. Microwaves $$\\left(\\lambda_4\\right)$$</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda_1<\\lambda_2<\\lambda_3<\\lambda_4$$\n",
      "$$\\lambda_2<\\lambda_1<\\lambda_4<\\lambda_3$$\n",
      "$$\\lambda_4<\\lambda_3<\\lambda_2<\\lambda_1$$\n",
      "$$\\lambda_4<\\lambda_3<\\lambda_1<\\lambda_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda_1<\\lambda_2<\\lambda_3<\\lambda_4$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s20u5",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 703px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/>EM-Wave</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/>Wavelength Range</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Infra-red</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$&lt;10^{-3}$$ nm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Ultraviolet</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">400 nm to 1 nm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">X-rays</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">1 mm to 700 nm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Gamma rays</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">1 nm to $$10^{-3}$$ nm</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(III), (C)-(II), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(II), (C)-(IV), (D)-(I)\n",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)\n",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electromagnetic-waves",
    "topic": "em-spectrum",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(II), (C)-(IV), (D)-(I)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "U683HfsRt4UJObxWdwxO0",
    "question": "The truth table given in fig. represents :\n<br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-13k7{font-size:20px;text-align:left}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-13k7\">A</th>\n<th class=\"tg-13k7\">B</th>\n<th class=\"tg-13k7\">Y</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">0</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">0</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">0</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">0</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">1</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">1</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">1</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">0</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">1</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">1</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">1</td>\n<td class=\"tg-13k7\">1</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>",
    "options": [
      "AND - Gate",
      "OR - Gate",
      "NAND - Gate",
      "NOR - Gate"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "digital-circuits",
    "solution": "OR - Gate"
  },
  {
    "id": "2Ll365INyRjoiOpD",
    "question": "At absolute zero, Si acts as ",
    "options": [
      "non-metal  ",
      "metal ",
      "insulator ",
      "none of these "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "insulator "
  },
  {
    "id": "CwzupXnlzhxjZIQe",
    "question": "By increasing the temperature, the specific resistance of a conductor and a semiconductor ",
    "options": [
      "increases for both ",
      "decreases for both ",
      "increases, decreases ",
      "decreases, increases "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "increases, decreases "
  },
  {
    "id": "mujjQqukBDM6jkKE",
    "question": "The energy band gap is maximum in ",
    "options": [
      "metals ",
      "superconductors ",
      "insulator ",
      "semiconductor "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "insulator "
  },
  {
    "id": "gL9KCiEII2AT3bmM",
    "question": "A strip of copper and another of germanium are cooled from room temperature to $$80K.$$ The resistance of ",
    "options": [
      "each of these decreases ",
      "copper strip increases and that of germanium decreases ",
      "copper strip decreases and that of germanium increases ",
      "each of these increases "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "copper strip decreases and that of germanium increases "
  },
  {
    "id": "SaKNBNutig9WrHj1",
    "question": "The difference in the variation of resistance with temperature in a metal and a semiconductor arises essentially due to the difference in the ",
    "options": [
      "crystal structure ",
      "variation of the number of charge carries with temperature ",
      "type of bonding ",
      "variation of scattering mechanism with temperature "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "variation of the number of charge carries with temperature "
  },
  {
    "id": "OVn1bK0PsFzGZVzY",
    "question": "In the middle of the depletion layer of a reverse- biased $$p$$-$$n$$ junction, the ",
    "options": [
      "electric field is zero ",
      "potential is maximum ",
      "electric field is maximum ",
      "potential is zero "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "electric field is zero "
  },
  {
    "id": "OE5KoPFX8MX81RjU",
    "question": "A piece of copper and another of germanium are cooled  from room temperature to $$77K,$$ the resistance of ",
    "options": [
      "copper increases and germanium decreases ",
      "each of them decreases ",
      "each of them increases ",
      "copper decreases and germanium increases "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "copper decreases and germanium increases "
  },
  {
    "id": "U6tsWDrJ7NVU2Xkl",
    "question": "The manifestation of band structure in solids is due to ",
    "options": [
      "Bohr's correspondence principle ",
      "Pauli's exclusion principle ",
      "Heisenberg's uncertainty principle ",
      "Boltzmann's law"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "Pauli's exclusion principle "
  },
  {
    "id": "faDTBUTygXo4dUD2",
    "question": "When $$p$$-$$n$$ junction diode is forward biased then ",
    "options": [
      "both the depletion region and barrier height are reduced ",
      "the depletion region is widened and barrier height is reduced ",
      "the depletion region is reduced and barrier height is increased ",
      "both the depletion region and barrier height are increased "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "both the depletion region and barrier height are reduced "
  },
  {
    "id": "beX7J8ryENkdcOln",
    "question": "The electrical conductivity of a semiconductor increases when electromagnetic radiation of wavelength shorter than $$2480$$ $$nm$$ is incident on it. The band gap in $$(eV)$$ for the semiconductor is ",
    "options": [
      "$$2.5$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$1.1$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$0.7$$ $$eV$$ ",
      "$$0.5$$ $$eV$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "$$0.5$$ $$eV$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "C3FYWZMsAxsD6Oos",
    "question": "In a full wave rectifier circuit operating from $$50$$ $$Hz$$ mains frequency, the fundamental frequency in the ripple would be ",
    "options": [
      "$$25$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$50$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$70.7$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$100$$ $$Hz$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "$$100$$ $$Hz$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "9PHB1DWhe3WP0H5p",
    "question": "If the ratio of the concentration of electrons to that of holes in a semiconductor is $${7 \\over 5}$$ and the ratio of currents is $${7 \\over 4},$$ then what is the ratio of their drift velocities? ",
    "options": [
      "$${5 \\over 8}$$ ",
      "$${4 \\over 5}$$",
      "$${5 \\over 4}$$",
      "$${4 \\over 7}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "$${5 \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Uyg4SJDH1WaEMxG9",
    "question": "A solid which is not transparent to visible light and whose conductivity increases with temperature is formed by ",
    "options": [
      "Ionic bonding ",
      "Covalent bonding",
      "Vander Waals bonding ",
      "Metallic bonding "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "Covalent bonding"
  },
  {
    "id": "7ZH7XpyPcDiA0CDv",
    "question": "Carbon, silicon and germanium have four valence electrons each. At room temperature which one of the following statements is most appropriate ? ",
    "options": [
      "The number of free electrons for conduction is significant only in $$Si$$ and $$Ge$$ but small in $$C.$$ ",
      "The number of free conduction electrons is significant in $$C$$ but small in $$Si$$ and $$Ge.$$ ",
      "The number of free conduction electrons is negligibly small in all the three.",
      "The number of free electrons for conduction is significant in all the three "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "The number of free electrons for conduction is significant only in $$Si$$ and $$Ge$$ but small in $$C.$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "cBnPK2H3eTAvPlhE",
    "question": "The current voltage relation of diode is given by $${\\rm I} = \\left( {{e^{100V/T}} - 1} \\right)mA,$$ where the applied voltage $$V$$ is in volts and the temperature $$T$$ is in degree kelvin. If a student makes an error measuring $$ \\pm 0.01\\,V$$ while measuring the current of $$5$$ $$mA$$ at $$300$$ $$K,$$ what will be the error in the value of current on $$mA$$? ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.2$$ $$mA$$ ",
      "$$0.02$$ $$mA$$ ",
      "$$0.5$$ $$mA$$ ",
      "$$0.05$$ $$mA$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "$$0.2$$ $$mA$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "oGXPLiJTFE13Dh5Q",
    "question": "A red $$LED$$ emits light at $$0.1$$ watt uniformly around it. The amplitude of the electric field of the light at a distance of $$1$$ $$m$$ from the diode is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$5.48$$ $$V/m$$ ",
      "$$7.75$$ $$V/m$$ ",
      "$$1.73$$ $$V/m$$ ",
      "$$2.45$$ $$V/m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "$$2.45$$ $$V/m$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "DnVE0kH55DnBWvQS",
    "question": "The temperature dependence of resistance of $$Cu$$ and undoped $$Si$$ in the temperature range $$300-400$$ $$K,$$ is best described by : ",
    "options": [
      "Linear increases for $$Cu,$$ exponential decrease of $$Si.$$ ",
      "Linear decrease for $$Cu,$$ linear decrease for $$Si$$",
      "Linear increase for $$Cu,$$ linear increase for $$Si.$$ ",
      "Linear increase for $$Cu,$$ exponential increase for $$Si$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "Linear increases for $$Cu,$$ exponential decrease of $$Si.$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "qAf99m7xYkpvG8WFPuzVl",
    "question": "An experiment is performed to determine the <i>I</i> - V characteristics of a Zener diode, which has a protective resistance of R = 100 $$\\Omega $$, and a maximum power of dissipation rating of 1 W. The minimum voltage range of the DC source in the circuit is :",
    "options": [
      "0 $$-$$ 5 V ",
      "0 $$-$$ 8 V ",
      "0 $$-$$ 12 V ",
      "0 $$-$$ 24 V "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "0 $$-$$ 24 V "
  },
  {
    "id": "BLQak8nJn2ejQEGlyaQXO",
    "question": "What is the conductivity of a semiconductor sale having electron concentration of  $$5 \\times {10^{18}}\\,\\,{m^{ - 3}},$$ hole concentration of $$5 \\times {10^{19}}\\,\\,{m^{ - 3}},$$ electron mobility of 2.0 m<sup>2</sup> V<sup>$$-$$1</sup> s<sup>-1</sup> and hole mobility of 0.01 m<sup>2</sup>  V<sup>$$-$$1</sup> s<sup>$$-$$1</sup> ? \n<br/><br/>(Take charge of electronas 1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup> $$-$$19</sup> c)",
    "options": [
      "1.68 ($$\\Omega $$-m)<sup>$$-$$1</sup> ",
      "1.83 ($$\\Omega $$-m)<sup>$$-$$1</sup> ",
      "0.59 ($$\\Omega $$-m)<sup>$$-$$1</sup> ",
      "1.20 ($$\\Omega $$-m)<sup>$$-$$1</sup> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "1.68 ($$\\Omega $$-m)<sup>$$-$$1</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "slYhwAHR6GTNecnIcrAMQ",
    "question": "Mobility of electrons in a semiconductor is defined as the ratio of their drift velocity to the applied electric field. If, for an n-type semiconductor, the density of electrons is 10<sup>19</sup> m<sup>$$-$$3</sup> and their mobility is 1.6 m<sup>2</sup>/(V.s) then the resistivity of the semiconductor (since it is an n-type semiconductor contribution of holes is ignored) is close to : ",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\,\\Omega $$m",
      "4$$\\,\\Omega $$m",
      "0.4 $$\\,\\Omega $$m",
      "0.2 $$\\,\\Omega $$m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "0.4 $$\\,\\Omega $$m"
  },
  {
    "id": "ICqUWbAOPejxd9Jby2jgy2xukff4sbr7",
    "question": "With increasing biasing voltage of a photodiode,\nthe photocurrent magnitude :",
    "options": [
      "Increases initially and after attaining\ncertain value, it decreases",
      "Increases linearly",
      "Increases initially and saturates finally",
      "Remains constant"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "Increases initially and saturates finally"
  },
  {
    "id": "cEUo9DA9LRQQXXQhIajgy2xukf3u0vk4",
    "question": "Which of the following will NOT be observed when a multimeter (operating in resistance measuring\nmode) probes connected across a component, are just reversed?",
    "options": [
      "Multimeter shows NO deflection in both cases i.e. before and after reversing the probes if the\nchosen component is metal wire.",
      "Multimeter shows a deflection, accompanied by a splash of light out of connected component in one direction and NO deflection on reversing the probes if the chosen component is LED.",
      "Multimeter shows an equal deflection in both cases i.e. before and after reversing the probes if\nthe chosen component is resistor.",
      "Multimeter shows NO deflection in both cases i.e. before and after reversing the probes if the\nchosen component is capacitor."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "Multimeter shows NO deflection in both cases i.e. before and after reversing the probes if the\nchosen component is capacitor."
  },
  {
    "id": "LnRZ1avI0pLVSq6I8Njgy2xukf3r7m2l",
    "question": "If a semiconductor photodiode can detect a photon with a maximum wavelength of 400 nm, then\nits band gap energy is :\n<br/><br/>Planck’s constant h = 6.63 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–34</sup> J.s. Speed of light c = 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>8</sup>\n m/s",
    "options": [
      "1.5 eV",
      "2.0 eV",
      "3.1 eV",
      "1.1 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "3.1 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "PMQIGV1VZ0s4XAiblrjgy2xukf22zwt6",
    "question": "When a diode is forward biased, it has a\nvoltage drop of 0.5 V. The safe limit of current\nthrough the diode is 10 mA. If a battery of emf\n1.5 V is used in the circuit, the value of\nminimum resistance to be connected in series\nwith the diode so that the current does not\nexceed the safe limit is",
    "options": [
      "50 $$\\Omega $$",
      "200 $$\\Omega $$",
      "300 $$\\Omega $$",
      "100 $$\\Omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "100 $$\\Omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "i95WpdvObIwTI19uj01klrolqw3",
    "question": "Zener breakdown occurs in a p $$-$$ n junction having p and n both :",
    "options": [
      "heavily doped and have wide depletion layer.",
      "lightly doped and have narrow depletion layer.",
      "heavily doped and have narrow depletion layer.",
      "lightly doped and have wide depletion layer."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "heavily doped and have narrow depletion layer."
  },
  {
    "id": "UiU9YbKf6soIzmQNQv1klt37dvv",
    "question": "For extrinsic semiconductors; when doping level is increased;",
    "options": [
      "Fermi-level of both p-type and n-type semiconductors will go upward for T &gt; T<sub>F</sub>K and downward for T &lt; T<sub>F</sub>K, where T<sub>F</sub> is Fermi temperature.",
      "Fermi-level of p-type semiconductor will go upward and Fermi-level of n-type semiconductors will go downward",
      "Fermi-level of p and n-type semiconductors will not be affected.",
      "Fermi-level of p-type semiconductors will go downward and Fermi-level of n-type semiconductor will go upward."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "Fermi-level of p-type semiconductors will go downward and Fermi-level of n-type semiconductor will go upward."
  },
  {
    "id": "u8ujECKdBMbuaHpCXw1klthilgm",
    "question": "LED is constructed from Ga-As-P semiconducting material. The energy gap of this LED is 1.9 eV. Calculate the wavelength of light emitted and its colour.<br/><br/>[h = 6.63 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$34</sup> Js and c = 3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "654 nm and orange colour",
      "654 nm and red colour",
      "1046 nm and red colour",
      "1046 nm and blue colour"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "654 nm and red colour"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krswlx8f",
    "question": "Consider a situation in which reserve biased current of a particular P-N junction increases when it is exposed to a light of wavelength $$\\le$$ 621 nm. During this process, enhancement in carrier concentration takes place due to generation of hole-electron pairs. The value of band gap is nearly.",
    "options": [
      "1 eV",
      "4 eV",
      "0.5 eV",
      "2 eV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "2 eV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktafk570",
    "question": "Statement I : By doping silicon semiconductor with pentavalent material, the electrons density increases.<br/><br/>Statement II : The n-type semiconductor has net negative charge.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement - I is true but Statement - II is false.",
      "Statement - I is false but Statement - II is true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "Statement - I is true but Statement - II is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjpylhf",
    "question": "Statement - I :<br/><br/>To get a steady dc output from the pulsating voltage received from a full wave rectifier we can connect a capacitor across the output parallel to the load R<sub>L</sub>.<br/><br/>Statement - II :<br/><br/>To get a steady dc output from the pulsating voltage received from a full wave rectifier we can connect an inductor in series with R<sub>L</sub>.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l569qy6b",
    "question": "<p>For using a multimeter to identify diode from electrical components, choose the correct statement out of the following about the diode :</p>",
    "options": [
      "It is two terminal device which conducts current in both directions.",
      "It is two terminal device which conducts current in one direction only.",
      "It does not conduct current gives an initial deflection which decays to zero.",
      "It is three terminal device which conducts current in one direction only between central terminal and either of the remaining two terminals"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "It is two terminal device which conducts current in one direction only."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5al0nmq",
    "question": "<p>The photodiode is used to detect the optical signals. These diodes are preferably operated in reverse biased mode because :</p>",
    "options": [
      "fractional change in majority carriers produce higher forward bias current",
      "fractional change in majority carriers produce higher reverse bias current",
      "fractional change in minority carriers produce higher forward bias current",
      "fractional change in minority carriers produce higher reverse bias current"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "fractional change in minority carriers produce higher reverse bias current"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnwyq76",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct statement about Zener diode :</p>",
    "options": [
      "It works as a voltage regulator in reverse bias and behaves like simple pn junction diode in forward bias. ",
      "It works as a voltage regulator in both forward and reverse bias.",
      "It works as a voltage regulator only in forward bias.",
      "It works as a voltage regulator in forward bias and behaves like simple pn junction diode in reverse bias."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "It works as a voltage regulator in reverse bias and behaves like simple pn junction diode in forward bias. "
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldof5th4",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II:</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 581px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 223px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 263px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Intrinsic semiconductor</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Fermi-level near the valence bond</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">n-type semiconductor</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Fermi-level in the middle of valence and conduction band.</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">p-type semiconductor</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Fermi-level near the conduction band</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Metals</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Fermi-level inside the conduction band</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-I, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpjvejn",
    "question": "<p>The effect of increase in temperature on the number of electrons in conduction band ($$\\mathrm{n_e}$$) and resistance of a semiconductor will be as:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{n}_{\\mathrm{e}}$$ decreases, resistance increases",
      "Both $$\\mathrm{n}_{\\mathrm{e}}$$ and resistance increase",
      "$$\\mathrm{n}_{\\mathrm{e}}$$ increases, resistance decreases",
      "Both $$\\mathrm{n}_{\\mathrm{e}}$$ and resistance decrease"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{n}_{\\mathrm{e}}$$ increases, resistance decreases"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldspis14",
    "question": "<p>Which one of the following statement is <b>not</b> correct in the case of light emitting diodes?</p>\n<p>A. It is a heavily doped p-n junction.</p>\n<p>B. It emits light only when it is forward biased.</p>\n<p>C. It emits light only when it is reverse biased.</p>\n<p> D. The energy of the light emitted is equal to or slightly less than the energy gap of the semiconductor used.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A",
      "B",
      "C and D",
      "C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtz0elt",
    "question": "<p>Statement I : When a Si sample is doped with Boron, it becomes P type and when doped by Arsenic it becomes N-type semi conductor such that P-type has excess holes and N-type has excess electrons.</p>\n<p>Statement II : When such P-type and N-type semi-conductors, are fused to make a junction, a current will automatically flow which can be detected with an externally connected ameter.</p>\n<p>In the light of above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but statement II is correct",
      "Both Statement I and statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldugzwp4",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Photodiodes are used in forward bias usually for measuring the light intensity.</p>\n<p>Reason R : For a p-n junction diode, at applied voltage V the current in the forward bias is more than the current in the reverse bias for $$\\mathrm{|{V_z}| &gt;  \\pm v \\ge |{v_0}|}$$ where $$\\mathrm{v_0}$$ is the threshold voltage and $$\\mathrm{V_z}$$ is the breakdown voltage.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is false but R is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "A is false but R is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldycd6au",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Photodiodes are preferably operated in reverse bias condition for light intensity measurement.</p>\n<p>Reason R : The current in the forward bias is more than the current in the reverse bias for a $$p-n$$ junction diode.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "A is true but R is false",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh2zx3wy",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A: Diffusion current in a p-n junction is greater than the drift current in magnitude if the junction is forward biased.</p>\n<p>Reason R: Diffusion current in a p-n junction is from the $$\\mathrm{n}$$-side to the p-side if the junction is forward biased.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "A is correct but R is not correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "luy9cm5p",
    "question": "<p>A light emitting diode (LED) is fabricated using GaAs semiconducting material whose band gap is $$1.42 \\mathrm{~eV}$$. The wavelength of light emitted from the LED is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1243 nm",
      "875 nm",
      "650 nm",
      "1400 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "875 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb295bj",
    "question": "<p>The acceptor level of a p-type semiconductor is $$6 \\mathrm{~eV}$$. The maximum wavelength of light which can create a hole would be : Given $$\\mathrm{hc}=1242 \\mathrm{~eV} \\mathrm{~nm}$$.</p>",
    "options": [
      "407 nm",
      "103.5 nm",
      "414 nm",
      "207 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "semiconductor-and-p-n-junction-diode",
    "solution": "207 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "FtygbvHxfeTjC9NT",
    "question": "The part of a transistor which is most heavily doped to produce large number of majority carriers is ",
    "options": [
      "emmiter ",
      "base ",
      "collector ",
      "can be any of the above three"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "emmiter "
  },
  {
    "id": "CrEmDgRD1fKHwy9r",
    "question": "When $$npn$$ transistor is used as an amplifer",
    "options": [
      "electrons move from collector to base ",
      "holes move from emitter to base ",
      "electrons move from base to collector",
      "holes move from base to emitter "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "electrons move from base to collector"
  },
  {
    "id": "J6ku1wdJ6dkpqQif",
    "question": "For a transistor amplifier in common emitter configuration for load impedance of $$1k\\,\\Omega $$ $$\\left( {{h_{fe}} = 50} \\right.$$ and $$\\left. {{h_{oe}} = 25} \\right)$$ the current gain is ",
    "options": [
      "$$-24.8$$ ",
      "$$-15.7$$ ",
      "$$-5.2$$ ",
      "$$-48.78$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "$$-48.78$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "aMu07cyNltPV7qiw",
    "question": "In a common base amplifier, the phase difference between the input signal voltage and output voltage is ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\pi $$ ",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 4}$$ ",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 2}$$",
      "$$0$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "$$0$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "fUATvH2PU7Xyf6TQ",
    "question": "In a common base mode of a transistor, the collector current is $$5.488$$ $$mA$$ for an emitter current of $$5.60mA.$$ The value of the base current amplification factor $$\\left( \\beta  \\right)$$ will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$49$$ ",
      "$$50$$ ",
      "$$51$$ ",
      "$$48$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "$$49$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "XP82ezFnHkVCrrU7",
    "question": "A working transistor with its three legs marked $$P,Q$$ and $$R$$ is tested using a multi-meter. No conduction is found between $$P$$ and $$Q$$. By connecting the common (negative) terminal of the multi-meter to $$R$$ and the other (positive) terminal to $$P$$ or $$Q,$$ some resistance is seen on the multi-meter. Which of the following is true for the transistor? ",
    "options": [
      "It is an $$npn$$ transistor with $$R$$ as base ",
      "It is an $$pnp$$ transistor with $$R$$ as collector",
      "It is an $$pnp$$ transistor with $$R$$ as emitter ",
      "It is an $$npn$$ transistor with $$R$$ as collector "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "It is an $$npn$$ transistor with $$R$$ as base "
  },
  {
    "id": "fQDmutxXysYJKfIab5qRt",
    "question": "The ratio (R) of output resistance r<sub>0</sub>, and the input resistance ri in measurements of input and output characteristics of a transistor is typically in the range:",
    "options": [
      "R ~ 10<sup>2</sup> $$-$$ 10<sup>3</sup>",
      "R ~ 1 $$-$$ 10",
      "R ~ 0.1  $$-$$  0.01",
      "R ~ 0.1 $$-$$ 1.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "R ~ 1 $$-$$ 10"
  },
  {
    "id": "TeNbRRJF9fQUAoRi7Qiue",
    "question": "An unknown transistor needs to be identified as a <i>npn</i> or <i>pnp</i> type. A multimeter, with + ve and − ve terminals, is used to measure resistance between different terminals of transistor. If terminal 2 is the base of the transistor then which of the following is correct for a pnp transistor ?",
    "options": [
      "+ ve termial 1,  $$-$$ve terminal 2, resistance high",
      "+ ve termial 2,  $$-$$ve terminal 1, resistance high",
      "+ ve termial 3,  $$-$$ve terminal 2, resistance high",
      "+ ve termial 2,  $$-$$ve terminal 3, resistance low"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "+ ve termial 1,  $$-$$ve terminal 2, resistance high"
  },
  {
    "id": "59pAEl5h118hJxwNw8EhE",
    "question": "The current gain of a common emitter amplifier is 69. If the emitter current is 7.0 mA, collector current is :",
    "options": [
      "9.6 mA",
      "6.9 mA",
      "0.69 mA",
      "69 mA"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "6.9 mA"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ixwa3JfkZDmUX1IN",
    "question": "In a common emitter amplifier circuit using an n-p-n transistor, the phase difference between the input and\nthe output voltages will be: ",
    "options": [
      "180°",
      "45°",
      "90°",
      "135°"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "180°"
  },
  {
    "id": "REjfwmDqhbUcNDwTpsaeH",
    "question": "In a common emitter configuration with suitable bias, it is given that $${R_L}$$  is the load resistance and $${R_{BE}}$$ is small signal dynamic resistance (input side). Then, voltage gain, current gain and power gain are given, respectively, by : \n<br/><br/>$$\\beta $$ is curret gain, $${{\\rm I}_B},{{\\rm I}_C}$$  and $${{\\rm I}_E}$$ are respectively base, collector and emitter currents. ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\beta {{{R_L}} \\over {{R_{BE}}}},{{\\Delta {{\\rm I}_C}} \\over {\\Delta {{\\rm I}_B}}},{\\beta ^2}{{{R_L}} \\over {{R_{BE}}}}$$",
      "$$\\beta {{{R_L}} \\over {{R_{BE}}}},{{\\Delta {{\\rm I}_E}} \\over {\\Delta {{\\rm I}_B}}},{\\beta ^2}{{{R_L}} \\over {{R_{BE}}}}$$",
      "$${\\beta ^2}{{{R_L}} \\over {{R_{BE}}}},{{\\Delta {{\\rm I}_C}} \\over {\\Delta {{\\rm I}_E}}},{\\beta ^2}{{{R_L}} \\over {{R_{BE}}}}$$",
      "$${\\beta ^2}{{{R_L}} \\over {{R_{BE}}}},{{\\Delta {{\\rm I}_C}} \\over {\\Delta {{\\rm I}_B}}},\\beta {{{R_L}} \\over {{R_{BE}}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "$$\\beta {{{R_L}} \\over {{R_{BE}}}},{{\\Delta {{\\rm I}_C}} \\over {\\Delta {{\\rm I}_B}}},{\\beta ^2}{{{R_L}} \\over {{R_{BE}}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "uFS8QCqEbkcvqyadMjiw0",
    "question": "An NPN transistor is used in common emitter\nconfiguration as an amplifier with 1 k$$\\Omega $$ load\nresistance. Signal voltage of 10 mV is applied\nacross the base-emitter. This produces a 3 mA\nchange in the collector current and 15μA\nchange in the base current of the amplifier. The\ninput resistance and voltage gain are :",
    "options": [
      "0.67 kW, 200",
      "0.33 kW, 1.5",
      "0.67 kW, 300",
      "0.33 kW, 300"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "0.67 kW, 300"
  },
  {
    "id": "0tv7BChyS4MV1jSnIU18hoxe66ijvzthxg5",
    "question": "An n-p-n transistor operates as a common emitter\namplifier, with a power gain of 60 dB. The input\ncircuit resistance is 100$$\\Omega $$ and the output load\nresistance is 10 k$$\\Omega $$. The common emitter\ncurrent gain $$\\beta $$ is :",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>4</sup>",
      "10<sup>2</sup>",
      "6 × 10<sup>2</sup>",
      "60"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "10<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "ANrqAECBtZtOo0iEqb1klriaa5g",
    "question": "If an emitter current is changed by 4 mA, the collector current changes by 3.5 mA. The value of $$\\beta$$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "0.875",
      "0.5",
      "3.5",
      "7"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "7"
  },
  {
    "id": "rzMuuflWsgCHPNprHb1klro6ukk",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : PN junction diodes can be used to function as transistor, simply by connecting two diodes, back to back, which acts as the base terminal.<br/><br/>Statement II : In the study of transistor, the amplification factor $$\\beta$$ indicates ratio of the collector current to the base current.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "TnkF92Rj7LmOKjOFC91kmlvjnhq",
    "question": "The correct relation between $$\\alpha$$ (ratio of collector current to emitter current) and $$\\beta$$ (ratio of collector current to base current) of a transistor is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\beta  = {\\alpha  \\over {1 + \\alpha }}$$",
      "$$\\alpha  = {\\beta  \\over {1 - \\alpha }}$$",
      "$$\\alpha  = {\\beta  \\over {1 + \\beta }}$$",
      "$$\\beta  = {1 \\over {1 - \\alpha }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha  = {\\beta  \\over {1 + \\beta }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kte0iahh",
    "question": "For a transistor in CE mode to be used as an amplifier, it must be operated in :",
    "options": [
      "Both cut-off and Saturation",
      "Saturation region only",
      "Cut-off region only",
      "The active region only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "The active region only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfjgsk1",
    "question": "For a transistor $$\\alpha$$ and $$\\beta$$ are given as $$\\alpha  = {{{I_C}} \\over {{I_E}}}$$ and $$\\beta  = {{{I_C}} \\over {{I_B}}}$$. Then the correct relation between $$\\alpha$$ and $$\\beta$$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\alpha  = {{1 - \\beta } \\over \\beta }$$",
      "$$\\beta  = {\\alpha  \\over {1 - \\alpha }}$$",
      "$$\\alpha \\beta  = 1$$",
      "$$\\alpha  = {\\beta  \\over {1 - \\beta }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "$$\\beta  = {\\alpha  \\over {1 - \\alpha }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l569tqsw",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : n-p-n transistor permits more current than a p-n-p transistor.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Electrons have greater mobility as a charge carrier.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true, and R is correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true, and R is correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56vh7gs",
    "question": "<p>For a transistor to act as a switch, it must be operated in</p>",
    "options": [
      "Active region.",
      "Saturation state only.",
      "Cut-off state only.",
      "Saturation and cut-off state."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "Saturation and cut-off state."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58i9qj5",
    "question": "<p>The positive feedback is required by an amplifier to act an oscillator. The feedback here means :</p>",
    "options": [
      "External input is necessary to sustain ac signal in output.",
      "A portion of the output power is returned back to the input.",
      "Feedback can be achieved by LR network.",
      "The base-collector junction must be forward biased."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "A portion of the output power is returned back to the input."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6knu8my",
    "question": "<p>For a constant collector-emitter voltage of $$8 \\mathrm{~V}$$, the collector current of a transistor reached to the value of $$6 \\mathrm{~mA}$$ from $$4 \\mathrm{~mA}$$, whereas base current changed from $$20 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{A}$$ to $$25 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{A}$$ value. If transistor is in active state, small signal current gain (current amplification factor) will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "240",
      "400",
      "0.0025",
      "200"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "400"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo7ah2h",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p><b>Statement I:</b> In a typical transistor, all three regions emitter, base and collector have same doping level.</p>\n<p><b>Statement II:</b> In a transistor, collector is the thickest and base is the thinnest segment.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "<b>Statement I</b> is correct but <b>Statement II</b> is incorrect",
      "Both <b>Statement I</b> and <b>Statement II</b> are incorrect",
      "<b>Statement I</b> is incorrect but <b>Statement II</b> is correct",
      "Both <b>Statement I</b> and <b>Statement II</b> are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "<b>Statement I</b> is incorrect but <b>Statement II</b> is correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrhigtk",
    "question": "<p>In an n-p-n common emitter (CE) transistor the collector current changes from 5 $$\\mathrm{mA}$$ to $$16 \\mathrm{~mA}$$ for the change in base current from $$100~ \\mu \\mathrm{A}$$ and $$200 ~\\mu \\mathrm{A}$$, respectively. The current gain of transistor is __________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "210",
      "0.9",
      "9",
      "110"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electronic-devices",
    "topic": "transistors",
    "solution": "110"
  },
  {
    "id": "qGInw3Vashui8HWL",
    "question": "If a charge $$q$$ is placed at the center of the line joining two equal charges $$Q$$ such that the system is in equilibrium then the value of $$q$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$Q/2$$ ",
      "$$ - Q/2$$",
      "$$Q/4$$",
      "$$ - Q/4$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$ - Q/4$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Rg6gNzp3AuTngWVw",
    "question": "A charge $$Q$$ is placed at each of the opposite corners of a square. A charge $$q$$ is placed at each of the  other two corners. If the net electrical force on $$Q$$ is zero, then $$Q/q$$ equals: ",
    "options": [
      "$$-1$$ ",
      "$$1$$ ",
      "$$ - {1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "$$ - 2\\sqrt 2 $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$ - 2\\sqrt 2 $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "E0XOnkex58yFOnaZ",
    "question": "Two identical charged spheres are suspended by strings of equal lengths. The strings make an angle of $${30^ \\circ }$$ with each other. When suspended in a liquid of density $$0.8g$$ $$c{m^{ - 3}},$$ the angle remains the same. If density of the material of the sphere is $$1.6$$ $$g$$ $$c{m^{ - 3}},$$ the dielectric constant of the liquid is ",
    "options": [
      "$$4$$ ",
      "$$3$$ ",
      "$$2$$ ",
      "$$1$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "bKD8xxG45AJ1mvuz",
    "question": "Two identical charged spheres suspended from a common point by two massless strings of length $$l$$ are initially a distance $$d\\left( {d &lt;  &lt; 1} \\right)$$ apart because of their mutual repulsion. The charge begins to leak from both the spheres at a constant rate. As a result charges approach each other with a velocity $$v$$. Then as a function of distance $$x$$ between them,  ",
    "options": [
      "$$v\\, \\propto \\,{x^{ - 1}}$$ ",
      "$$y\\, \\propto \\,{x^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}}}$$ ",
      "$$v\\, \\propto \\,x$$ ",
      "$$v\\, \\propto \\,{x^{ - {\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$v\\, \\propto \\,{x^{ - {\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "vpssfco95NSf7bXl",
    "question": "Two charges, each equals to $$q,$$ are kept at $$x=-a$$ and $$x=a$$ on the $$x$$-axis. A particle of mass $$m$$ and charge $${q_0} = {q \\over 2}$$ is placed at the origin. If charge  $${q_0}$$ is given a small displacement $$\\left( {y &lt;  &lt; a} \\right)$$ along the $$y$$-axis, the net force acting on the particle is proportional to ",
    "options": [
      "$$y$$ ",
      "$$-y$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over y}$$ ",
      "$$-{1 \\over y}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$y$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "x2HRDKMJNMxZ26viLZ3tC",
    "question": "Two identical conducting spheres A and B,  carry equal charge. They are separated by a distance much larger than their diameters,  and the force between theis F.  A third identical conducting sphere, C,  is uncharged. Sphere C is first touhed to A, then to B, and then removed. As a result, the force between A and B would be equal to : ",
    "options": [
      "F ",
      "$${{3F} \\over 4}$$",
      "$${{3F} \\over 8}$$",
      "$${{F} \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$${{3F} \\over 8}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "YzMGHibXCab3V7OiuWoPv",
    "question": "Three charges + Q, q, + Q are placed respectively, at distance, 0, d/2 and d from the origin, on the  x-axis. If the net force experienced by + Q, placed at x = 0, is zero, then value of q is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$ $${Q \\over 4}$$",
      "+ $${Q \\over 2}$$",
      "+ $${Q \\over 4}$$",
      "$$-$$ $${Q \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$-$$ $${Q \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "MJMMWzwvnhKd8AxTg4ca3",
    "question": "Charge is distributed within a sphere of radius R with a volume charge density $$\\rho \\left( r \\right) = {A \\over {{r^2}}}{e^{ - {{2r} \\over s}}},$$ where A and a are constants. If Q is the total charge of this charge distribution, the radius R is : ",
    "options": [
      "a log $$\\left( {1 - {Q \\over {2\\pi aA}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${a \\over 2}$$ log $$\\left( {{1 \\over {1 - {Q \\over {2\\pi aA}}}}} \\right)$$",
      "a log $$\\left( {{1 \\over {1 - {Q \\over {2\\pi aA}}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${a \\over 2}$$ log $$\\left( {1 - {Q \\over {2\\pi aA}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$${a \\over 2}$$ log $$\\left( {{1 \\over {1 - {Q \\over {2\\pi aA}}}}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "5CoiRmXf0hfxGO46OR1klrob7jk",
    "question": "Two electrons each are fixed at a distance '2d'. A third charge proton placed at the midpoint is displaced slightly by a distance x (x &lt;&lt; d) perpendicular to the line joining the two fixed charges. Proton will execute simple harmonic motion having angular frequency : (m = mass of charged particle)",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left( {{{2{q^2}} \\over {\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}m{d^3}}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{{q^2}} \\over {2\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}m{d^3}}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{2\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}m{d^3}} \\over {{q^2}}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}m{d^3}} \\over {2{q^2}}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$${\\left( {{{{q^2}} \\over {2\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}m{d^3}}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "d8784Me2wwop8j8cEV1krplv220",
    "question": "A certain charge Q is divided into two parts q and (Q $$-$$ q). How should the charges Q and q be divided so that q and (Q $$-$$ q) placed at a certain distance apart experience maximum electrostatic repulsion?",
    "options": [
      "Q = 2q",
      "Q = 4q",
      "Q = 3q",
      "Q = $${q \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "Q = 2q"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kryxm0fy",
    "question": "Two identical tennis balls each having mass 'm' and charge 'q' are suspended from a fixed point by threads of length 'l'. What is the equilibrium separation when each thread makes a small angle '$$\\theta$$' with the vertical?",
    "options": [
      "$$x = {\\left( {{{{q^2}l} \\over {2\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}mg}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$$x = {\\left( {{{{q^2}l} \\over {2\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}mg}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 3}}}$$",
      "$$x = {\\left( {{{{q^2}{l^2}} \\over {2\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}{m^2}g}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 3}}}$$",
      "$$x = {\\left( {{{{q^2}{l^2}} \\over {2\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}{m^2}{g^2}}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 3}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$x = {\\left( {{{{q^2}l} \\over {2\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}mg}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 3}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54um9cc",
    "question": "<p>Two point charges Q each are placed at a distance d apart. A third point charge q is placed at a distance x from mid-point on the perpendicular bisector. The value of x at which charge q will experience the maximum Coulomb's force is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "x = d",
      "$$x = {d \\over 2}$$",
      "$$x = {d \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$$x = {d \\over {2\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$x = {d \\over {2\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbjszf",
    "question": "<p>Two identical charged particles each having a  mass 10 g and charge 2.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup>C are placed on a horizontal table with a separation of L between them such that they stay in limited equilibrium. If the coefficient of friction between each particle and the table is 0.25, find the value of L. [Use g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]</p>",
    "options": [
      "12 cm",
      "10 cm",
      "8 cm",
      "5 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "12 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bc4qew",
    "question": "<p>A long cylindrical volume contains a uniformly distributed charge of density $$\\rho$$. The radius of cylindrical volume is R. A charge particle (q) revolves around the cylinder in a circular path. The kinetic energy of the particle is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\rho q{R^2}} \\over {4{\\varepsilon _0}}}$$",
      "$${{\\rho q{R^2}} \\over {2{\\varepsilon _0}}}$$",
      "$${{q\\rho } \\over {4{\\varepsilon _0}{R^2}}}$$",
      "$${{4{\\varepsilon _0}{R^2}} \\over {q\\rho }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$${{\\rho q{R^2}} \\over {4{\\varepsilon _0}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jhp4z4",
    "question": "<p>Two identical positive charges $$Q$$ each are fixed at a distance of '2a' apart from each other. Another point charge $$q_{0}$$ with mass 'm' is placed at midpoint between two fixed charges. For a small displacement along the line joining the fixed charges, the charge $$\\mathrm{q}_{0}$$ executes $$\\mathrm{SHM}$$. The time period of oscillation of charge $$\\mathrm{q}_{0}$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{4 \\pi^{3} \\varepsilon_{0} m a^{3}}{q_{0} Q}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{q_{0} Q}{4 \\pi^{3} \\varepsilon_{0} m a^{3}}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{2 \\pi^{2} \\varepsilon_{0} m a^{3}}{q_{0} Q}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{8 \\pi^{3} \\varepsilon_{0} m a^{3}}{q_{0} Q}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{4 \\pi^{3} \\varepsilon_{0} m a^{3}}{q_{0} Q}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kn49lt",
    "question": "<p>A charge of $$4 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$ is to be divided into two. The distance between the two divided charges is constant. The magnitude of the divided charges so that the force between them is maximum, will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$ and $$3 \\,\\mu\\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$2 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$ and $$2\\, \\mu \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "0 and $$4\\, \\mu\\, \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$1.5 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$ and $$2.5\\, \\mu \\mathrm{C}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$2 \\,\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$ and $$2\\, \\mu \\mathrm{C}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rgcvvx",
    "question": "<p>Two identical metallic spheres $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$ when placed at certain distance in air repel each other with a force of $$\\mathrm{F}$$. Another identical uncharged sphere $$\\mathrm{C}$$ is first placed in contact with $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and then in contact with $$\\mathrm{B}$$ and finally placed at midpoint between spheres A and B. The force experienced by sphere C will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "3F/2",
      "3F/4",
      "F",
      "2F"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "3F/4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr1gyae",
    "question": "<p>Two isolated metallic solid spheres of radii $$\\mathrm{R}$$ and $$2 \\mathrm{R}$$ are charged such that both have same charge density $$\\sigma$$. The spheres are then connected by a thin conducting wire. If the new charge density of the bigger sphere is $$\\sigma^{\\prime}$$. The ratio $$\\frac{\\sigma^{\\prime}}{\\sigma}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{5}{3}$$",
      "$$\\frac{5}{6}$$",
      "$$\\frac{9}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{4}{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{5}{6}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldydmrgz",
    "question": "<p>If two charges q$$_1$$ and q$$_2$$ are separated with distance 'd' and placed in a medium of dielectric constant K. What will be the equivalent distance between charges in air for the same electrostatic force?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$d\\sqrt k$$",
      "$$1\\,.\\,5d\\sqrt k$$",
      "$$k\\sqrt d$$",
      "$$2d\\sqrt k$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$d\\sqrt k$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp0afk4",
    "question": "<p>A $$10 ~\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$ charge is divided into two parts and placed at $$1 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ distance so that the repulsive force between them is maximum. The charges of the two parts are:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$9 ~\\mu\\mathrm{C}, 1 ~\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$5 ~\\mu\\mathrm{C}, 5 ~\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$8 ~\\mu\\mathrm{C}, 2 ~\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$7 ~\\mu\\mathrm{C}, 3 ~\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$5 ~\\mu\\mathrm{C}, 5 ~\\mu \\mathrm{C}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd7l922",
    "question": "<p>Force between two point charges $$q_1$$ and $$q_2$$ placed in vacuum at '$$r$$' cm apart is $$F$$. Force between them when placed in a medium having dielectric constant $$K=5$$ at '$$r / 5$$' $$\\mathrm{cm}$$ apart will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$5 F$$\n",
      "$$25 F$$\n",
      "$$F / 5$$\n",
      "$$F / 25$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$5 F$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5grvxd",
    "question": "<p>Two charged conducting spheres of radii $$a$$ and $$b$$ are connected to each other by a conducting wire. The ratio of charges of the two spheres respectively is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$a b$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{b}{a}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{a}{b}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{a b}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{a}{b}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3kbz",
    "question": "<p>In hydrogen like system the ratio of coulombian force and gravitational force between an electron and a proton is in the order of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>19</sup>",
      "10<sup>39</sup>",
      "10<sup>29</sup>",
      "10<sup>36</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "10<sup>39</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s23t6",
    "question": "<p>The vehicles carrying inflammable fluids usually have metallic chains touching the ground:</p>",
    "options": [
      "To protect tyres from catching dirt from ground\n",
      "It is a custom\n",
      "To alert other vehicles\n",
      "To conduct excess charge due to air friction to ground and prevent sparking"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "To conduct excess charge due to air friction to ground and prevent sparking"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29ebb",
    "question": "<p>Two identical conducting spheres P and S with charge Q on each, repel each other with a force $$16 \\mathrm{~N}$$. A third identical uncharged conducting sphere $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is successively brought in contact with the two spheres. The new force of repulsion between $$\\mathrm{P}$$ and $$\\mathrm{S}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 N",
      "6 N",
      "12 N",
      "4 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-charges-and-coulomb's-law",
    "solution": "6 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "OFRdGv9vf0OAf0OA",
    "question": "An electric dipole is placed at an angle of $${30^ \\circ }$$ to a non-uniform electric field. The dipole will experience ",
    "options": [
      "a translation force only in the direction of the field ",
      "a translation force only in a direction normal to the direction of the field ",
      "a torque as well as a translational force",
      "a torque only "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "a torque as well as a translational force"
  },
  {
    "id": "Fo1ZOjOFhYHueuPb",
    "question": "An electric dipole has a fixed dipole moment $$\\overrightarrow p $$, which makes angle $$\\theta$$ with respect to x-axis. When\nsubjected to an electric field  $$\\mathop {{E_1}}\\limits^ \\to   = E\\widehat i$$ , it experiences a torque $$\\overrightarrow {{T_1}}  = \\tau \\widehat k$$ . When subjected to another electric\nfield $$\\mathop {{E_2}}\\limits^ \\to   = \\sqrt 3 {E_1}\\widehat j$$  it experiences a torque $$\\mathop {{T_2}}\\limits^ \\to   = \\mathop { - {T_1}}\\limits^ \\to  $$ . The angle $$\\theta$$ is: ",
    "options": [
      "90<sup>o</sup>",
      "45<sup>o</sup>",
      "30<sup>o</sup>",
      "60<sup>o</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "60<sup>o</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "xrVhiRfWRwCdqiWVtFmi3",
    "question": "An electric field of 1000 V/m is applied to an electric dipole at angle of 45<sup>o</sup>. The value of electric dipole moment is 10<sup>–29</sup> C.m. What is the potential energy of the electric dipole? ",
    "options": [
      "- 7 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–27</sup> J",
      "$$-$$ 9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–20</sup> J",
      "$$-$$ 10 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–29</sup> J",
      "$$-$$ 20 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–18</sup> J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "- 7 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–27</sup> J"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ucp9nRTjEoC3IHY8Fo3rsa0w2w9jx3mppe4",
    "question": "A point dipole $$\\overrightarrow p  =  - {p_0}\\widehat x$$\nis kept at the origin. The potential and electric field due to this dipole on the\ny-axis at a distance d are, respectively: (Take V= 0 at infinity)",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\left| {\\overrightarrow p } \\right|} \\over {4\\pi { \\in _0}{d^2}}},{{ - \\overrightarrow p } \\over {4\\pi { \\in _0}{d^3}}}$$",
      "$$0,{{\\overrightarrow p } \\over {4\\pi { \\in _0}{d^3}}}$$",
      "$${{\\left| {\\overrightarrow p } \\right|} \\over {4\\pi { \\in _0}{d^2}}},{{\\overrightarrow p } \\over {4\\pi { \\in _0}{d^3}}}$$",
      "$$0,{{ - \\overrightarrow p } \\over {4\\pi { \\in _0}{d^3}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "$$0,{{ - \\overrightarrow p } \\over {4\\pi { \\in _0}{d^3}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "HVoH4xklgH9aXRqiaG7k9k2k5imsmyi",
    "question": "An electric dipole of moment\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow p  = \\left( { - \\widehat i - 3\\widehat j + 2\\widehat k} \\right) \\times {10^{ - 29}} $$ C.m is <br/>at the origin\n(0, 0, 0). The electric field due to this dipole at\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow r  =  + \\widehat i + 3\\widehat j + 5\\widehat k$$ (note that $$\\overrightarrow r .\\overrightarrow p  = 0$$ ) is parallel to :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( { + \\widehat i + 3\\widehat j - 2\\widehat k} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( { + \\widehat i - 3\\widehat j - 2\\widehat k} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( { - \\widehat i + 3\\widehat j - 2\\widehat k} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( { - \\widehat i - 3\\widehat j + 2\\widehat k} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "$$\\left( { + \\widehat i + 3\\widehat j - 2\\widehat k} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "U61buzOgQTZ10HCEVejgy2xukg0hgwyh",
    "question": "Two identical electric point dipoles have dipole moments $${\\overrightarrow p _1} = p\\widehat i$$ and $${\\overrightarrow p _2} =  - p\\widehat i$$ and are held on the x\naxis at distance '$$a$$' from each other. When released, they move along the x-axis with the direction\nof their dipole moments remaining unchanged. If the mass of each dipole is 'm', their speed when\nthey are infinitely far apart is :",
    "options": [
      "$${p \\over a}\\sqrt {{3 \\over {2\\pi { \\in _0}ma}}} $$",
      "$${p \\over a}\\sqrt {{1 \\over {\\pi { \\in _0}ma}}} $$",
      "$${p \\over a}\\sqrt {{1 \\over {2\\pi { \\in _0}ma}}} $$",
      "$${p \\over a}\\sqrt {{2 \\over {\\pi { \\in _0}ma}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "$${p \\over a}\\sqrt {{1 \\over {2\\pi { \\in _0}ma}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "4YUwG2C3IiqkuiCYhp1klula5r4",
    "question": "Given below are two statements: <br/><br/>Statement I : An electric dipole is placed at the center of a hollow sphere. The flux of the electric field through the sphere is zero but the electric field is not zero anywhere in the sphere.<br/><br/>Statement II : If R is the radius of a solid metallic sphere and Q be the total charge on it. The electric field at any point on the spherical surface of radius r (&lt; R) is zero but the electric flux passing through this closed spherical surface of radius r is not zero..<br><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</br>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsumx7v",
    "question": "An electric dipole is placed on x-axis in proximity to a line charge of linear charge density 3.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> C/m. Line charge is placed on z-axis and positive and negative charge of dipole is at a distance of 10 mm and 12 mm from the origin respectively. If total force of 4N is exerted on the dipole, find out the amount of positive or negative charge of the dipole.",
    "options": [
      "0.485 mC",
      "815.1 nC",
      "8.8 $$\\mu$$C",
      "4.44 $$\\mu$$C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "4.44 $$\\mu$$C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58bt72a",
    "question": "<p>Given below two statements : One is labelled as Assertion (A) and other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : Non-polar materials do not have any permanent dipole moment.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : When a non-polar material is placed in an electric field, the centre of the positive charge distribution of it's individual atom or molecule coincides with the centre of the negative charge distribution.</p>\n<p>In the light of above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is not the correct explanation of (A).",
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct.",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq26pdf",
    "question": "<p>Two charges each of magnitude $$0.01 ~\\mathrm{C}$$ and separated by a distance of $$0.4 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ constitute an electric dipole. If the dipole is placed in an uniform electric field '$$\\vec{E}$$' of 10 dyne/C making $$30^{\\circ}$$ angle with $$\\vec{E}$$, the magnitude of torque acting on dipole is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4 \\cdot 0 \\times 10^{-10} ~\\mathrm{Nm}$$",
      "$$1.5 \\times 10^{-9} ~\\mathrm{Nm}$$",
      "$$1.0 \\times 10^{-8} ~\\mathrm{Nm}$$",
      "$$2.0 \\times 10^{-10} ~\\mathrm{Nm}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "$$2.0 \\times 10^{-10} ~\\mathrm{Nm}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrigha1",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : If an electric dipole of dipole moment $$30 \\times 10^{-5} ~\\mathrm{C} ~\\mathrm{m}$$ is enclosed by a closed surface, the net flux coming out of the surface will be zero.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Electric dipole consists of two equal and opposite charges.</p>\n<p>In the light of above, statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh30lxvl",
    "question": "<p>A dipole comprises of two charged particles of identical magnitude $$q$$ and opposite in nature. The mass 'm' of the positive charged particle is half of the mass of the negative charged particle. The two charges are separated by a distance '$$l$$'. If the dipole is placed in a uniform electric field '$$\\bar{E}$$'; in such a way that dipole axis makes a very small angle with the electric field, '$$\\bar{E}$$'. The angular frequency of the oscillations of the dipole when released is given by:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{3 q E}{2 m l}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{4 q E}{m l}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{8 q E}{3 m l}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{8 q E}{m l}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{3 q E}{2 m l}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgd3mbl",
    "question": "<p>The electrostatic potential due to an electric dipole at a distance '$$r$$' varies as :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{r^3}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{r}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{r^2}$$",
      "r"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-dipole",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{r^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "bctkNeUNDUliE7hJ",
    "question": "Four charges equal to -$$Q$$ are placed at the four corners of a square and  a charge $$q$$ is at its center. If the system is in equilibrium the value of $$q$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$ - {Q \\over 2}\\left( {1 + 2\\sqrt 2 } \\right)$$ ",
      "$${Q \\over 4}\\left( {1 + 2\\sqrt 2 } \\right)$$ ",
      "$$ - {Q \\over 4}\\left( {1 + 2\\sqrt 2 } \\right)$$ ",
      "$${Q \\over 2}\\left( {1 + 2\\sqrt 2 } \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$${Q \\over 4}\\left( {1 + 2\\sqrt 2 } \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "9MTD6o50mPdNBFq7",
    "question": "A charged oil drop is suspended in a uniform field of $$3 \\times {10^4}$$ $$v/m$$  so that it neither falls nor rises. The charge on the drop will be (Take the mass of the charge $$ = 9.9 \\times {10^{ - 15}}\\,\\,kg$$ and $$g = 10\\,m/{s^2}$$) ",
    "options": [
      "$$1.6 \\times {10^{ - 18}}\\,C$$ ",
      "$$3.2 \\times {10^{ - 18}}\\,C$$",
      "$$3.3 \\times {10^{ - 18}}\\,C$$",
      "$$4.8 \\times {10^{ - 18}}\\,C$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$$3.3 \\times {10^{ - 18}}\\,C$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "wyelwCFEQvhxLkqf",
    "question": "Two point charges $$+8q$$ and $$-2q$$ are located at $$x=0$$ and $$x=L$$ respectively. The location of a point on the $$x$$ axis at which the net electric field due to these two point charges is zero is ",
    "options": [
      "$${L \\over 4}$$ ",
      "$$2$$ $$L$$ ",
      "$$4$$ $$L$$ ",
      "$$8$$ $$L$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$$2$$ $$L$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "cVELXW3tKHjNNqmz",
    "question": "Let $$P\\left( r \\right) = {Q \\over {\\pi {R^4}}}r$$ be the change density distribution for a solid sphere of radius $$R$$ and total charge $$Q$$. For a point $$'p'$$ inside the sphere at distance $${r_1}$$ from the center of the sphere, the magnitude of electric field is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${Q \\over {4\\pi \\,{ \\in _0}\\,r_1^2}}$$ ",
      "$${{Qr_1^2} \\over {4\\pi \\,{ \\in _0}\\,{R^4}}}$$",
      "$${{Qr_1^2} \\over {3\\pi \\,{ \\in _0}\\,{R^4}}}$$ ",
      "$$0$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$${{Qr_1^2} \\over {4\\pi \\,{ \\in _0}\\,{R^4}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "djZbC84NYDv3VYt2",
    "question": "Let there be a spherically symmetric charge distribution with charge density varying as $$\\rho \\left( r \\right) = {\\rho _0}\\left( {{5 \\over 4} - {r \\over R}} \\right)$$ upto $$r=R,$$ and $$\\rho \\left( r \\right) = 0$$ for $$r&gt;R,$$ where $$r$$ is the distance from the erigin. The electric field at a distance $$r\\left( {r &lt; R} \\right)$$ from the origin is given by ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\rho _0}r} \\over {4{\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {{5 \\over 3} - {r  \\over R}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${{4\\pi {\\rho _0}r} \\over {3{\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {{5 \\over 3} - {r  \\over R}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${{4{\\rho _0}r} \\over {4{\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {{5 \\over 4} - {r  \\over R}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${{{\\rho _0}r} \\over {3{\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {{5 \\over 4} - {r  \\over R}} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$${{{\\rho _0}r} \\over {4{\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {{5 \\over 3} - {r  \\over R}} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "71eHfG7eCnrZx688BsgXY",
    "question": "A body of mass $$M$$ and charge $$q$$ is connected to spring of spring constant $$k.$$  It is oscillating along $$x$$-direction about its equilibrium position, taken to be at $$x=0,$$ with an amplitude $$A$$. An electric field $$E$$ is applied along the $$x$$-direction. Which of the following statements is <b>correct</b> ?",
    "options": [
      "The new equilibrium position is at a distance $${{qE} \\over {2k}}$$ from $$x=0.$$",
      "The total energy of the system is $${1 \\over 2}m{\\omega ^2}{A^2} + {1 \\over 2}{{{q^2}{E^2}} \\over k}.$$",
      "The total energy of the system is $${1 \\over 2}m{\\omega ^2}{A^2} - {1 \\over 2}{{{q^2}{E^2}} \\over k}.$$",
      "The new equilibrium position is at a distance $${{2qE} \\over k}$$ from $$x=0.$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "The total energy of the system is $${1 \\over 2}m{\\omega ^2}{A^2} + {1 \\over 2}{{{q^2}{E^2}} \\over k}.$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "hgkqbGjnZ0JRMHv42SsFg",
    "question": "A solid ball of radius R has a charge density  $$\\rho $$ \n<br/>given by $$\\rho $$ = $$\\rho $$<sub>o</sub> (1 $$-$$ $${\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle r$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle R$}}$$) for 0 $$ \\le $$ r $$ \\le $$ R. The electric field outside the ball is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\rho _o}{R^3}} \\over {{ \\in _o}{r^2}}}$$",
      "$${{{\\rho _o}{R^3}} \\over {12{ \\in _o}{r^2}}}$$",
      "$${{4{\\rho _o}{R^3}} \\over {3{ \\in _o}{r^2}}}$$ ",
      "$${{3{\\rho _o}{R^3}} \\over {4{ \\in _o}{r^2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$${{{\\rho _o}{R^3}} \\over {12{ \\in _o}{r^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "gGLz6Fg1XP41Br3Q75bBG",
    "question": "For a uniformly charged ring of radius R, the electric field on its axis has the largest magnitude  at a distance h from its center. Then value of h is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${R \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}$$",
      "$${R \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "R",
      "R$$\\sqrt 2 $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$${R \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "YY3uk84puRG86EYnTW7te",
    "question": "Four point charges –q, +q, +q and –q are placed\non y-axis at y = –2d, y = –d, y = +d and\ny = +2d, respectively. The magnitude of the\nelectric field E at a point on the x-axis at\nx = D, with D &gt;&gt; d, will behave as :-",
    "options": [
      "$$E \\propto {1 \\over D^3}$$",
      "$$E \\propto {1 \\over D}$$",
      "$$E \\propto {1 \\over D^4}$$",
      "$$E \\propto {1 \\over D^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$$E \\propto {1 \\over D^4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "wNC36OiOLMkUBQZmugDD1",
    "question": "The bob of a simple pendulum has mass 2g and\na charge of 5.0 μC. It is at rest in a uniform\nhorizontal electric field of intensity 2000 V/m.\nAt equilibrium, the angle that the pendulum\nmakes with the vertical is : (take g = 10 m/s<sup>2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "tan<sup>–1</sup>(5.0)",
      "tan<sup>–1</sup>(2.0)",
      "tan<sup>–1</sup>(0.5)",
      "tan<sup>–1</sup>(0.2)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "tan<sup>–1</sup>(0.5)"
  },
  {
    "id": "T2vPSW3gpzKTHuv3NhINP",
    "question": "Two point charges q<sub>1</sub>$$\\left( {\\sqrt {10} \\mu C} \\right)$$ and q<sub>2</sub>($$-$$ 25 $$\\mu $$C) are placed on the x-axis at x = 1 m and x = 4 m respectively. The electric field (in V/m) at a point y = 3 m on y-axis is, \n<br/>[take $${1 \\over {4\\pi { \\in _0}}}$$ = 9 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>9</sup> Nm<sup>2</sup>C<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {63\\widehat i - 27\\widehat j} \\right) \\times {10^2}$$",
      "$$\\left( { - 63\\widehat i + 27\\widehat j} \\right) \\times {10^2}$$",
      "$$\\left( {81\\widehat i - 81\\widehat j} \\right) \\times {10^2}$$",
      "$$\\left( { - 81\\widehat i + 81\\widehat j} \\right) \\times {10^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {63\\widehat i - 27\\widehat j} \\right) \\times {10^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "C3dUrFug6o6GxPz33Njgy2xukg0h4wya",
    "question": "Consider the force F on a charge 'q' due to a uniformly charged spherical shell of radius R carrying\ncharge Q distributed uniformly over it. Which one of the following statements is true for F, if 'q' is\nplaced at distance r from the centre of the shell?",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}{{qQ} \\over {{R^2}}} &gt; F &gt; 0$$ for r &lt; R",
      "$$F = {1 \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}{{qQ} \\over {{r^2}}}$$ for r &gt; R",
      "$$F = {1 \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}{{qQ} \\over {{r^2}}}$$ for all r",
      "$$F = {1 \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}{{qQ} \\over {{R^2}}}$$ for r &lt; R"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$$F = {1 \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}{{qQ} \\over {{r^2}}}$$ for r &gt; R"
  },
  {
    "id": "CKw9imxNSehN3xJr8Tjgy2xukfakhzkn",
    "question": "A particle of charge q and mass m is subjected to an electric field<br/> E = E<sub>0</sub>\n (1 – $$a$$x<sup>2</sup>) in the x-direction,\nwhere $$a$$ and E<sub>0</sub>\n are constants. Initially the particle was at rest at x = 0. Other than the initial\nposition the kinetic energy of the particle becomes zero when the distance of the particle from the\norigin is :",
    "options": [
      "$$a$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{2 \\over a}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over a}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{1 \\over a}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over a}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "PXJT3Cd9SpbBiSSPFp1kmipehcv",
    "question": "Find out the surface charge density at the intersection of point x = 3 m plane and x-axis, in the region of uniform line charge of 8 nC/m lying along the z-axis in free space.",
    "options": [
      "0.424 nC m<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "4.0 nC m<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "47.88 C/m",
      "0.07 nC m<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "0.424 nC m<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "RZQXGYTlncPboo7V2Z1kmkqrr6k",
    "question": "An oil drop of radius 2 mm with a density 3g cm<sup>$$-$$3</sup> is held stationary under a constant electric field 3.55 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> V m<sup>$$-$$1</sup> in the Millikan's oil drop experiment. What is the number of excess electrons that the oil drop will possess? (consider g = 9.81 m/s<sup>2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "48.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>11</sup>",
      "1.73 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup>",
      "17.3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup>",
      "1.73 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>12</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "1.73 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktdy8xq6",
    "question": "A uniformly charged disc of radius R having surface charge density $$\\sigma$$ is placed in the xy plane with its center at the origin. Find the electric field intensity along the z-axis at a distance Z from origin :-",
    "options": [
      "$$E = {\\sigma  \\over {2{\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {1 - {Z \\over {{{({Z^2} + {R^2})}^{1/2}}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$$E = {\\sigma  \\over {2{\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {1 + {Z \\over {{{({Z^2} + {R^2})}^{1/2}}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$$E = {{2{\\varepsilon _0}} \\over \\sigma }\\left( {{1 \\over {{{({Z^2} + {R^2})}^{1/2}}}} + Z} \\right)$$",
      "$$E = {\\sigma  \\over {2{\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {{1 \\over {({Z^2} + {R^2})}} + {1 \\over {{Z^2}}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$$E = {\\sigma  \\over {2{\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {1 - {Z \\over {{{({Z^2} + {R^2})}^{1/2}}}}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l547q70t",
    "question": "<p>A positive charge particle of 100 mg is thrown in opposite direction to a uniform electric field of strength 1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> NC<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. If the charge on the particle is 40 $$\\mu$$C and the initial velocity is 200 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, how much distance it will travel before coming to the rest momentarily :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 m",
      "5 m",
      "10 m",
      "0.5 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "0.5 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55k3s6k",
    "question": "<p>Two point charges A and B of magnitude +8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> C and $$-$$8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> C respectively are placed at a distance d apart. The electric field at the middle point O between the charges is 6.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup> NC<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. The distance 'd' between the point charges A and B is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.0 m",
      "3.0 m",
      "1.0 m",
      "4.0 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "3.0 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5696143",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : A point charge is brought in an electric field. The value of electric field at a point near to the charge may increase if the charge is positive.</p>\n<p>Statement II : An electric dipole is placed in a non-uniform electric field. The net electric force on the dipole will not be zero.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c30ewz",
    "question": "<p>A vertical electric field of magnitude 4.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> N/C just prevents a water droplet of a mass 0.1 g from falling. The value of charge on the droplet will be :</p>\n<p>(Given : g = 9.8 m/s<sup>2</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$9</sup> C",
      "2.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$9</sup> C",
      "3.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$9</sup> C",
      "0.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$9</sup> C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "2.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$9</sup> C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i0h93e",
    "question": "<p>Two uniformly charged spherical conductors $$A$$ and $$B$$ of radii $$5 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ and $$10 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ are separated by a distance of $$2 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. If the spheres are connected by a conducting wire, then in equilibrium condition, the ratio of the magnitudes of the electric fields at the surface of the sphere $$A$$ and $$B$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 2",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 1",
      "1 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr1dwex",
    "question": "<p>Electric field in a certain region is given by $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{E}}=\\left(\\frac{\\mathrm{A}}{x^{2}} \\hat{i}+\\frac{\\mathrm{B}}{y^{3}} \\hat{j}\\right) \\text {. The } \\mathrm{SI} \\text { unit of } \\mathrm{A} \\text { and } \\mathrm{B}$$ are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{Nm}^{2} \\mathrm{C} ; \\mathrm{Nm}^{3} \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Nm}^{3} \\mathrm{C}^{-1} ; \\mathrm{Nm}^{2} \\mathrm{C}^{-1}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Nm}^{3} \\mathrm{C} ; \\mathrm{Nm}^{2} \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{Nm}^{2} \\mathrm{C}^{-1} ; \\mathrm{Nm}^{3} \\mathrm{C}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{Nm}^{2} \\mathrm{C}^{-1} ; \\mathrm{Nm}^{3} \\mathrm{C}^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsb78kq",
    "question": "<p>A point charge $$2\\times10^{-2}~\\mathrm{C}$$ is moved from P to S in a uniform electric field of $$30~\\mathrm{NC^{-1}}$$ directed along positive x-axis. If coordinates of P and S are (1, 2, 0) m and (0, 0, 0) m respectively, the work done by electric field will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "600 mJ",
      "$$-1200$$ mJ",
      "1200 mJ",
      "$$-600$$ mJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$$-600$$ mJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtyr0m1",
    "question": "<p>A point charge of 10 $$\\mu$$C is placed at the origin. At what location on the X-axis should a point charge of 40 $$\\mu$$C be placed so that the net electric field is zero at $$x=2$$cm on the X-axis?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$x=6$$ cm",
      "$$x=8$$ cm",
      "$$x=4$$ cm",
      "$$x=-4$$ cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$$x=6$$ cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnxxzq9",
    "question": "The electric field due to a short electric dipole at a large distance $(r)$ from center of dipole on the equatorial plane varies with distance as :",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{1}{r^{2}}$",
      "$\\frac{1}{r}$",
      "$r$",
      "$\\frac{1}{r^{3}}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$\\frac{1}{r^{3}}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvraetn",
    "question": "<p>In a metallic conductor, under the effect of applied electric field, the free electrons of the conductor</p>",
    "options": [
      "move in the straight line paths in the same direction",
      "move with the uniform velocity throughout from lower potential to higher potential",
      "drift from higher potential to lower potential.",
      "move in the curved paths from lower potential to higher potential"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "move in the curved paths from lower potential to higher potential"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscpi6ha",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : Work done by electric field on moving a positive charge on an equipotential surface is always zero.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Electric lines of forces are always perpendicular to equipotential surfaces.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)\n",
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct\n",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)\n",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse6341e",
    "question": "<p>Two charges $$q$$ and $$3 q$$ are separated by a distance '$$r$$' in air. At a distance $$x$$ from charge $$q$$, the resultant electric field is zero. The value of $$x$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{r}{3(1+\\sqrt{3})}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{(1+\\sqrt{3})}{r}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{r}{(1+\\sqrt{3})}$$\n",
      "$$r(1+\\sqrt{3})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-field-and-electric-field-intensity",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{r}{(1+\\sqrt{3})}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "XpDfytTYoWuHJQ5U",
    "question": "If the electric flux entering and leaving an enclosed surface respectively is $${\\phi _1}$$ and $${\\phi _2},$$ the electric charge inside the surface will be",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {{\\phi _2} - {\\phi _1}} \\right){\\varepsilon _0}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {{\\phi _2} + {\\phi _1}} \\right)/{\\varepsilon _0}$$",
      "$$\\left( {{\\phi _1} - {\\phi _2}} \\right)/{\\varepsilon _0}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {{\\phi _1} + {\\phi _2}} \\right){\\varepsilon _0}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-flux-and-gauss-law",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {{\\phi _2} - {\\phi _1}} \\right){\\varepsilon _0}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "6Hwvdp5RDX0cmfILeQ3rsa0w2w9jx6nl04q",
    "question": "Let a total charge 2Q be distributed in a sphere of radius R, with the charge density given by $$\\rho $$(r) = kr, where\nr is the distance from the centre. Two charges A and B, of –Q each, are placed on diametrically opposite\npoints, at equal distance, $$a$$ from the centre. If A and B do not experience any force, then :",
    "options": [
      "$$a = {8^{ - 1/4}}R$$",
      "$$a = {2^{ - 1/4}}R$$",
      "$$a = {{3R} \\over {{2^{1/4}}}}$$",
      "$$a = {R \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-flux-and-gauss-law",
    "solution": "$$a = {8^{ - 1/4}}R$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "knDqptSHqalU3FrMub7k9k2k5gw0kba",
    "question": "In finding the electric field using Gauss Law\nthe formula $$\\left| {\\overrightarrow E } \\right| = {{{q_{enc}}} \\over {{\\varepsilon _0}\\left| A \\right|}}$$ is applicable. In the\nformula $${{\\varepsilon _0}}$$ is permittivity of free space, A is the\narea of Gaussian surface and q<sub>enc</sub> is charge\nenclosed by the Gaussian surface. The equation\ncan be used in which of the following situation?",
    "options": [
      "Only when $$\\left| {\\overrightarrow E } \\right|$$ = constant on the surface.",
      "For any choice of Gaussian surface.",
      "Only when the Gaussian surface is an\nequipotential surface.",
      "Only when the Gaussian surface is an\nequipotential surface and $$\\left| {\\overrightarrow E } \\right|$$ is constant on\nthe surface."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-flux-and-gauss-law",
    "solution": "Only when the Gaussian surface is an\nequipotential surface and $$\\left| {\\overrightarrow E } \\right|$$ is constant on\nthe surface."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjpcd4j",
    "question": "Choose the incorrect statement :<br/><br/>(1) The electric lines of force entering into a Gaussian surface provide negative flux.<br/><br/>(2) A charge 'q' is placed at the centre of a cube. The flux through all the faces will be the same.<br/><br/>(3) In a uniform electric field net flux through a closed Gaussian surface containing no net charge, is zero.<br/><br/>(4) When electric field is parallel to a Gaussian surface, it provides a finite non-zero flux.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below",
    "options": [
      "(3) and (4) only",
      "(2) and (4) only",
      "(4) only",
      "(1) and (3) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-flux-and-gauss-law",
    "solution": "(4) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldso44r5",
    "question": "<p>In a cuboid of dimension $$2 \\mathrm{~L} \\times 2 \\mathrm{~L} \\times \\mathrm{L}$$, a charge $$q$$ is placed at the center of the surface '$$\\mathrm{S}$$' having area of $$4 \\mathrm{~L}^{2}$$. The flux through the opposite surface to '$$\\mathrm{S}$$' is given by</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{q}{2 \\epsilon_{0}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{q}{3 \\epsilon_{0}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{q}{12 \\epsilon_{0}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{q}{6 \\in_{0}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-flux-and-gauss-law",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{q}{6 \\in_{0}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1c6hx",
    "question": "<p>Two charges of $$5 Q$$ and $$-2 Q$$ are situated at the points $$(3 a, 0)$$ and $$(-5 a, 0)$$ respectively. The electric flux through a sphere of radius '$$4 a$$' having center at origin is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{2 Q}{\\varepsilon_0}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{7 Q}{\\varepsilon_0}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{3 Q}{\\varepsilon_0}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{5 Q}{\\varepsilon_0}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-flux-and-gauss-law",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{5 Q}{\\varepsilon_0}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsflpssv",
    "question": "<p>An electric field is given by $$(6 \\hat{i}+5 \\hat{j}+3 \\hat{k}) \\mathrm{N} / \\mathrm{C}$$. The electric flux through a surface area $$30 \\hat{i} \\mathrm{~m}^2$$ lying in YZ-plane (in SI unit) is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "60",
      "90",
      "180",
      "150"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-flux-and-gauss-law",
    "solution": "180"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg6ka1a",
    "question": "<p>A particle of charge '$$-q$$' and mass '$$m$$' moves in a circle of radius '$$r$$' around an infinitely long line charge of linear charge density '$$+\\lambda$$'. Then time period will be given as :</p>\n<p>(Consider $$k$$ as Coulomb's constant)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$T^2=\\frac{4 \\pi^2 m}{2 k \\lambda q} r^3$$\n",
      "$$T=\\frac{1}{2 \\pi r} \\sqrt{\\frac{m}{2 k \\lambda q}}$$\n",
      "$$T=\\frac{1}{2 \\pi} \\sqrt{\\frac{2 k \\lambda q}{m}}$$",
      "$$T=2 \\pi r \\sqrt{\\frac{m}{2 k \\lambda q}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-flux-and-gauss-law",
    "solution": "$$T=2 \\pi r \\sqrt{\\frac{m}{2 k \\lambda q}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erzcz",
    "question": "<p>A charge $$q$$ is placed at the center of one of the surface of a cube. The flux linked with the cube is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{q}{2 \\epsilon_0}$$\n",
      "Zero\n",
      "$$\\frac{q}{4 \\epsilon_0}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{q}{8 \\epsilon_0}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-flux-and-gauss-law",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{q}{2 \\epsilon_0}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc58e7h",
    "question": "<p>$$\\sigma$$ is the uniform surface charge density of a thin spherical shell of radius R. The electric field at any point on the surface of the spherical shell is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sigma / \\epsilon_o R$$\n",
      "$$\\sigma / \\in_o$$\n",
      "$$\\sigma / 2 \\epsilon_o$$\n",
      "$$\\sigma / 4 \\epsilon_o$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-flux-and-gauss-law",
    "solution": "$$\\sigma / \\in_o$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "NxSGjUMbmBOLafyg",
    "question": "On moving a charge of $$20$$ coulomb by $$2$$ $$cm,$$ $$2$$ $$J$$ of work is done, then the potential differences between the points is ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.1$$ $$V$$ ",
      "$$8$$ $$V$$",
      "$$2V$$ ",
      "$$0.5$$ $$V.$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$$0.1$$ $$V$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "NiJWQTXa5drcMmG6",
    "question": "A thin spherical conducting shell of radius $$R$$ has a charge $$q.$$ Another charge $$Q$$ is placed at the center of the shell. The electrostatic potential at a point $$P$$ a distance $${R \\over 2}$$ from the center of the shell is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{2Q} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$ ",
      "$${{2Q} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}} - {{2q} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$ ",
      "$${{2Q} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}} + {q \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$ ",
      "$${{\\left( {q + Q} \\right)2} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$${{2Q} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}} + {q \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Qz2u4D8L4DkJrTXG",
    "question": "Two spherical conductors $$B$$ and $$C$$ having equal radii and carrying equal charges on them repel each other with a force $$F$$ when kept apart at some distance. A third spherical conductor having same radius as that $$B$$ but uncharged is brought in contact with $$B,$$ then brought in correct with $$C$$ and finally removed away from both. The new force of repulsion between $$B$$ and $$C$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$F/8$$ ",
      "$$3$$ $$F/4$$ ",
      "$$F/4$$ ",
      "$$3$$ $$F/8$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$$3$$ $$F/8$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "hcRGNXDoV85s0ZmC",
    "question": "A charge particle $$'q'$$ is shot towards another charged particle $$'Q'$$ which is fixed, with a speed $$'v'$$. It approaches $$'Q'$$ upto a closest distance $$r$$ and then returns. If $$q$$ were given a speed of $$'2v'$$ the closest distances of approaches would be ",
    "options": [
      "$$r/2$$ ",
      "$$2r$$ ",
      "$$r$$ ",
      "$$r/4$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$$r/4$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Lz3Xvu7apCfZSZ8N",
    "question": "Two thin wire rings each having a radius $$R$$ are placed at a distance $$d$$ apart with their axes coinciding. The charges on the two rings are $$+q$$ and $$-q.$$ The potential difference between the centres of the two rings is  ",
    "options": [
      "$${q \\over {2\\pi \\,{ \\in _0}}}\\left[ {{1 \\over R} - {1 \\over {\\sqrt {{R^2} + {d^2}} }}} \\right]$$ ",
      "$${{qR} \\over {4\\pi \\,{ \\in _0}\\,{d^2}}}$$ ",
      "$${q \\over {4\\pi \\,{ \\in _0}}}\\left[ {{1 \\over R} - {1 \\over {\\sqrt {{R^2} + {d^2}} }}} \\right]$$ ",
      "zero "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$${q \\over {2\\pi \\,{ \\in _0}}}\\left[ {{1 \\over R} - {1 \\over {\\sqrt {{R^2} + {d^2}} }}} \\right]$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "B6JVgIOFDvXPdmnc",
    "question": "Two spherical conductors $$A$$ and $$B$$ of radii $$1$$ $$mm$$ and $$2$$ $$mm$$ are separated by a distance of $$5$$ $$cm$$ and are uniformly charged. If the spheres are connected by a conducting wire then in equilibrium condition, the ratio of the magnitude of the electric fields at the surfaces of spheres $$A$$ and $$B$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$4:1$$ ",
      "$$1:2$$ ",
      "$$2:1$$ ",
      "$$1:4$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$$2:1$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "d7qzd6QNbjrg9qc7",
    "question": "An electric charge $${10^{ - 3}}\\,\\,\\mu \\,C$$ is placed at the origin $$(0,0)$$ of $$X-Y$$ co-ordinate system. Two points $$A$$ and $$B$$ are situated at $$\\left( {\\sqrt 2 ,\\sqrt 2 } \\right)$$  and $$\\left( {2,0} \\right)$$ respectively. The potential difference between the points $$A$$ and $$B$$ will be",
    "options": [
      "$$4.5$$ volts ",
      "$$9$$ volts",
      "zero ",
      "$$2$$ volts"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "zero "
  },
  {
    "id": "EdWWTR8JpqiUdKu9",
    "question": "The potential at a point $$x$$ (measured in $$\\mu \\,m$$) due to some charges situated on the $$x$$-axis is given by $$V\\left( x \\right) = 20/\\left( {{x^2} - 4} \\right)$$ volt\n<br/>The electric field $$E$$ at $$x = 4\\,\\mu \\,m$$ is given by ",
    "options": [
      "$$(10/9)$$ volt / $$\\mu $$ $$m$$ and in the $$ + ve$$ $$x$$ direction",
      "$$\\left( {5/3} \\right)$$ volt/ $$\\mu $$ $$m$$ and in the $$-ve$$ $$x$$ direction",
      "$$\\left( {5/3} \\right)$$ volt/$$\\mu $$ $$m$$ and in the $$+ve$$ $$x$$ direction ",
      "$$\\left( {10/9} \\right)$$ volt/ $$\\mu \\,m$$ and in the $$-ve$$ $$x$$ direction "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$$(10/9)$$ volt / $$\\mu $$ $$m$$ and in the $$ + ve$$ $$x$$ direction"
  },
  {
    "id": "FVnf38AvrFMmUWi6",
    "question": "(This question contains Statement-1 and Statement-2. Of the four choices given after the statements, choose the one that best describes the two statements.)\n<p><b>Statement-1 :</b> For a charged particle moving from point $$P$$ to point $$Q$$, the net work done by an electrostatic field on the particle is independent of the path connecting point $$P$$ to point $$Q.$$\n<br/><b>Statement-2 :</b> The net work done by a conservative force on an object moving along a closed loop is zero.</p> ",
    "options": [
      "Statement-1 is true, Statement-2 is true; Statement-2 is the correct explanation of Statement-1.",
      "Statement-1 is true, Statement-2 is true; Statement-2 is not  the correct explanation of Statement-1.",
      "Statement- 1 is false, Statement- 2 is true.",
      "Statement- 1 true, Statement- 2 is false "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "Statement-1 is true, Statement-2 is true; Statement-2 is the correct explanation of Statement-1."
  },
  {
    "id": "ecJstlq5xeQtS07S",
    "question": "Two points $$P$$ and $$Q$$ are maintained at the potentials of $$10$$ $$V$$ and $$-4$$ $$V$$, respectively. The work done in moving $$100$$ electrons from $$P$$ to $$Q$$ is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$9.60 \\times {10^{ - 17}}J$$ ",
      "$$ - 2.24 \\times {10^{ - 16}}J$$ ",
      "$$ 2.24 \\times {10^{ - 16}}J$$ ",
      "$$- 9.60 \\times {10^{ - 17}}J$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$$ 2.24 \\times {10^{ - 16}}J$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "rgP80zkYdRStk8mK",
    "question": "The electrostatic potential inside a charged spherical ball is given by $$\\phi  = a{r^2} + b$$ where $$r$$ is the distance from the center and $$a,b$$ are constants. Then the charge density inside the ball is: ",
    "options": [
      "$$ - 6a{\\varepsilon _0}r$$ ",
      "$$ - 24\\pi a{\\varepsilon _0}$$ ",
      "$$ - 6a{\\varepsilon _0}$$ ",
      "$$ - 24\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}r$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$$ - 6a{\\varepsilon _0}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "kZvRddnHfhUblAZ0",
    "question": "This question has statement- $$1$$ and statement- $$2.$$ Of the four choices given after the statements, choose the one that best describe the two statements.\n<br/>An insulating solid sphere of radius $$R$$ has a uniformly positive charge density $$\\rho $$. As a result of this uniform charge distribution there is a finite value of electric potential at the center of the sphere, at the surface of the sphere and also at a point out side the sphere. The electric potential at infinite is zero. \n<p><b>Statement- $$1:$$</b> When a charge $$q$$ is take from the centre of the surface of the sphere its potential energy changes by $${{q\\rho } \\over {3{\\varepsilon _0}}}$$ \n<br/><b>Statement- $$2:$$</b> The electric field at a distance $$r\\left( {r &lt; R} \\right)$$ from the center of the sphere is $${{\\rho r} \\over {3{\\varepsilon _0}}}.$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement- $$1$$ is true,  Statement- $$2$$ is true; Statement- $$2$$  is not the correct explanation of Statement- $$1$$.",
      "Statement $$1$$ is true, Statement $$2$$ is false.",
      "Statement $$1$$ is false,  Statement $$2$$ is true.",
      "Statement- $$1$$ is true,  Statement- $$2$$ is true; Statement- $$2$$  is the correct explanation of Statement- $$1$$."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "Statement $$1$$ is false,  Statement $$2$$ is true."
  },
  {
    "id": "mYHueforZ9AVvImQ",
    "question": "Assume that an electric field $$\\overrightarrow E  = 30{x^2}\\widehat i$$ exists in space. Then the potential difference $${V_A} - {V_O},$$ where $${V_O}$$ is the potential at the origin and $${V_A}$$ the potential at $$x=2$$ $$m$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$$120$$ $$J/C$$ ",
      "$$-120$$ $$J/C$$ ",
      "$$-80$$ $$J/C$$ ",
      "$$80$$ $$J/C$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$$-80$$ $$J/C$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "opIW6M7POd09qeaiYQ0tm",
    "question": "The potential (in volts) of a charge distribution is given by.\n<br/><br/>V(z) = 30 $$-$$ 5x<sup>2</sup> for $$\\left| z \\right|$$ $$ \\le $$ 1 m.\n<br/>V(z) = 35 $$-$$ 10 $$\\left| z \\right|$$ for $$\\left| z \\right|$$ $$ \\ge $$1 m.\n<br/><br/>V(z)  does not depend on x and y. If this potential is generated by a constant charge per unit volume $${\\rho _0}$$ (in units of $${\\varepsilon _0}$$) which is spread over a certain region, then choose the correct statement.",
    "options": [
      "$${\\rho _0}$$ = 10 $${\\varepsilon _0}$$ for $$\\left| z \\right|$$ $$ \\le $$ 1 m  and $${\\rho _0} = 0$$ elsewhere",
      "$${\\rho _0}$$ = 20 $${\\varepsilon _0}$$ in the entire region",
      "$${\\rho _0}$$ = 40 $${\\varepsilon _0}$$ in the entire region",
      "$${\\rho _0}$$ = 20 $${\\varepsilon _0}$$ for $$\\left| z \\right|$$ $$ \\le $$ 1 m  and $${\\rho _0} = 0$$ elsewhere"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$${\\rho _0}$$ = 10 $${\\varepsilon _0}$$ for $$\\left| z \\right|$$ $$ \\le $$ 1 m  and $${\\rho _0} = 0$$ elsewhere"
  },
  {
    "id": "h9gwfwlBDbNi9CdftROh6",
    "question": "Within a spherical charge distribution of charge density $$\\rho $$(r), N equipotential surfaces of potential V<sub>0</sub>, V<sub>0</sub> + $$\\Delta $$V, V<sub>0</sub> + 2$$\\Delta $$V, .......... V<sub>0</sub> + N$$\\Delta $$V ($$\\Delta $$ V &gt; 0), are drawn and have increasing radii r<sub>0</sub>, r<sub>1</sub>, r<sub>2</sub>,..........r<sub>N</sub>, respectively. If the difference in the radii of the surfaces is constant for all values of V<sub>0</sub> and $$\\Delta $$V then :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\rho $$ (r) $$\\alpha $$ r",
      "$$\\rho $$ (r) = constant ",
      "$$\\rho $$ (r)  $$\\alpha $$ $${1 \\over r}$$ ",
      "$$\\rho $$ (r) $$\\alpha $$ $${1 \\over {{r^2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$$\\rho $$ (r)  $$\\alpha $$ $${1 \\over r}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "l6jUFDtMAVkdGSNRSqSIe",
    "question": "There is a uniform electrostatic field in a region. The potential at various points on a small sphere centred at $$P,$$ in the region, is found to vary between the limits 589.0 V to 589.8 V. What is the potential at a point on the sphere whose radius vector makes an angle of 60<sup>o</sup> with the direction of the field ?",
    "options": [
      "589.5 V",
      "589.2 V",
      "589.4 V",
      "589.6 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "589.4 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "C7lmZNbUrOJKrRhh",
    "question": "Three concentric metal shells A, B and C of respective radii a, b and c (a &lt; b &lt; c) have surface charge\ndensities $$ + \\sigma $$, $$ - \\sigma $$ and $$ + \\sigma $$ respectively. The potential of shell B is :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\sigma  \\over { \\in {}_0}}\\left[ {{{{b^2} - {c^2}} \\over c} + a} \\right]$$ ",
      "$${\\sigma  \\over { \\in {}_0}}\\left[ {{{{a^2} - {b^2}} \\over a} + c} \\right]$$ ",
      "$${\\sigma  \\over { \\in {}_0}}\\left[ {{{{a^2} - {b^2}} \\over b} + c} \\right]$$ ",
      "$${\\sigma  \\over { \\in {}_0}}\\left[ {{{{b^2} - {c^2}} \\over b} + a} \\right]$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$${\\sigma  \\over { \\in {}_0}}\\left[ {{{{a^2} - {b^2}} \\over b} + c} \\right]$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "mKDPC385uLb9zFngSX3rsa0w2w9jwzam63i",
    "question": "In free space, a particle A of charge 1$$\\mu $$C is held fixed at a point P. Another particle B of the same charge and\nmass 4$$\\mu $$g is kept at a distance of 1 mm from P. If B is released, then its velocity at a distance of 9 mm from P\nis :\n$$\\left[ {Take\\,{1 \\over {4\\pi { \\in _0}}} = 9 \\times {{10}^9}N{m^2}{C^{ - 2}}} \\right]$$",
    "options": [
      "1.0 m/s",
      "6.32 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> m/s",
      "2.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup> m/s",
      "1.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>2</sup> m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "6.32 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "fnIEQ5g7U6KMm3aMwx18hoxe66ijvztor5i",
    "question": "A uniformly charged ring of radius 3a and total\ncharge q is placed in xy-plane centred at origin.\nA point charge q is moving towards the ring\nalong the z-axis and has speed u at z = 4a. The\nminimum value of u such that it crosses the\norigin is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{2 \\over m}} {\\left( {{2 \\over {15}}{{{q^2}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}a}}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{2 \\over m}} {\\left( {{1 \\over {15}}{{{q^2}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}a}}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{2 \\over m}} {\\left( {{1 \\over {5}}{{{q^2}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}a}}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{2 \\over m}} {\\left( {{4 \\over {15}}{{{q^2}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}a}}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{2 \\over m}} {\\left( {{2 \\over {15}}{{{q^2}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}a}}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "wNKzzwUhAdNCElKmWNkcP",
    "question": "The electric field in a region is given by\n$$\\mathop E\\limits^ \\to   = \\left( {Ax + B} \\right)\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge  $$\n, where E is in NC<sup>–1</sup> and x is in\nmetres. The values of constants are\nA = 20 SI unit and B = 10 SI unit. If the potential\nat x = 1 is V<sub>1</sub> and that at x = –5 is V<sub>2</sub>, then\nV<sub>1</sub> – V<sub>2</sub> is :-",
    "options": [
      "–520 V",
      "180 V",
      "–48 V",
      "320 V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "180 V"
  },
  {
    "id": "uKkiguKXPfwVaPq2QqXeS",
    "question": "A solid conducting sphere, having a charge Q,\nis surrounded by an uncharged conducting\nhollow spherical shell. Let the potential\ndifference between the surface of the solid\nsphere and that of the outer surface of the\nhollow shell be V. If the shell is now given a\ncharge of –4 Q, the new potential difference\nbetween the same two surfaces is :",
    "options": [
      "V",
      "2V",
      "–2V",
      "4V"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "V"
  },
  {
    "id": "fz4z1Wuv1kZ7N8Az0K5vY",
    "question": "A charge Q is distributed over three concentric spherical shells of radii a, b, c (a &lt; b &lt; c) such that their surface charge densities are equal to one another. The total potential at a point at distance r from their common centre, where r &lt; a, would be -",
    "options": [
      "$${{Q\\left( {{a^2} + {b^2} + {c^2}} \\right)} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}\\left( {{a^3} + {b^3} + {c^3}} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${Q \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}\\left( {a + b + c} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${Q \\over {12\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}{{ab + bc + ca} \\over {abc}}$$",
      "$${{Q\\left( {a + b + c} \\right)} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}\\left( {{a^2} + {b^2} + {c^2}} \\right)}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$${{Q\\left( {a + b + c} \\right)} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}\\left( {{a^2} + {b^2} + {c^2}} \\right)}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "0HFsqj2ahMdBtYDEggqus",
    "question": "Four equal point charges Q each are placed in the xy plane at (0, 2), (4, 2), (4, –2) and (0, –2). The work required to put a fifth charge Q at the origin of the coordinate system will be -",
    "options": [
      "$${{{Q_2}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}$$",
      "$${{{Q^2}} \\over {2\\sqrt 2 \\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}$$",
      "$${{{Q_2}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {1 + {1 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}} \\right)$$",
      "$${{{Q_2}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {1 + {1 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$${{{Q_2}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left( {1 + {1 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "CtiTHPYMYOy2vYkMTe7k9k2k5hhof2i",
    "question": "Consider two charged metallic spheres S<sub>1</sub> and\nS<sub>2</sub> of radii R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub>, respectively. The electric\nfields E<sub>1</sub> (on S<sub>1</sub>) and E<sub>2</sub> (on S<sub>2</sub>) on their surfaces\nare such that E<sub>1</sub>/E<sub>2</sub> = R<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>. Then the ratio\nV<sub>1</sub> (on S<sub>1</sub>) / V<sub>2</sub> (on S<sub>2</sub>) of the electrostatic\npotentials on each sphere is :",
    "options": [
      "(R<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>)<sup>2</sup>",
      "(R<sub>2</sub>/R<sub>1</sub>)",
      "(R<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>)<sup>3</sup>",
      "R<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "(R<sub>1</sub>/R<sub>2</sub>)<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Lxf5pRnSBvfie61Wjbjgy2xukf24x8ce",
    "question": "Two isolated conducting spheres S<sub>1</sub> and S<sub>2</sub> of\nradius $${2 \\over 3}R$$ and $${1 \\over 3}R$$ have 12 $$\\mu $$C and –3 $$\\mu $$C\ncharges, respectively, and are at a large\ndistance from each other. They are now\nconnected by a conducting wire. A long time\nafter this is done the charges on S<sub>1</sub> and S<sub>2</sub> are\nrespectively :",
    "options": [
      "4.5 $$\\mu $$C on both",
      "+4.5 $$\\mu $$C and –4.5 $$\\mu $$C",
      "6 $$\\mu $$C and 3 $$\\mu $$C",
      "3 $$\\mu $$C and 6 $$\\mu $$C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "6 $$\\mu $$C and 3 $$\\mu $$C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1KHLCaZUjsFMDcrPLOjgy2xukf3uxetk",
    "question": "Concentric metallic hollow spheres of radii R and 4R hold charges Q<sub>1</sub>\n and Q<sub>2</sub>\n respectively. Given that\nsurface charge densities of the concentric spheres are equal, the potential difference V(R) – V(4R) is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{3{Q_2}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$",
      "$${{3{Q_1}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$",
      "$${{3{Q_1}} \\over {16\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$",
      "$${{{Q_2}} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$${{3{Q_1}} \\over {16\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "KkfjLO3WF7JAsho77Djgy2xukfl25hbl",
    "question": "Ten charges are placed on the circumference\nof a circle of radius R with constant angular\nseparation between successive charges.\nAlternate charges 1, 3, 5, 7, 9 have charge (+q)\neach, while 2, 4, 6, 8, 10 have charge (–q) each.\nThe potential V and the electric field E at the\ncentre of the circle are respectively.\n<br/>(Take V = 0 at infinity)",
    "options": [
      "V = 0; E = 0",
      "$$V = {{10q} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$; $$E = {{10q} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}{R^2}}}$$",
      "$$V = {{10q} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}R}}$$; E = 0",
      "V = 0; $$E = {{10q} \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}{R^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "V = 0; E = 0"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktbnxlg7",
    "question": "The two thin coaxial rings, each of radius 'a' and having charges +Q and $$-$$Q respectively are separated by a distance of 's'. The potential difference between the centres of the two rings is :",
    "options": [
      "$${Q \\over {2\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left[ {{1 \\over a} + {1 \\over {\\sqrt {{s^2} + {a^2}} }}} \\right]$$",
      "$${Q \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left[ {{1 \\over a} + {1 \\over {\\sqrt {{s^2} + {a^2}} }}} \\right]$$",
      "$${Q \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left[ {{1 \\over a} - {1 \\over {\\sqrt {{s^2} + {a^2}} }}} \\right]$$",
      "$${Q \\over {2\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left[ {{1 \\over a} - {1 \\over {\\sqrt {{s^2} + {a^2}} }}} \\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$${Q \\over {2\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}\\left[ {{1 \\over a} - {1 \\over {\\sqrt {{s^2} + {a^2}} }}} \\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54vg1ub",
    "question": "<p>If the electric potential at any point (x, y, z) m in space is given by V = 3x<sup>2</sup> volt. The electric field at the point (1, 0, 3) m will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, directed along positive x-axis.",
      "3 Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, directed along negative x-axis. ",
      "6 Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, directed along positive x-axis.",
      "6 Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, directed along negative x-axis."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "6 Vm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, directed along negative x-axis."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58hs7g0",
    "question": "<p>Sixty four conducting drops each of radius 0.02 m and each carrying a charge of 5 $$\\mu$$C are combined to form a bigger drop. The ratio of surface density of bigger drop to the smaller drop will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 4",
      "4 : 1",
      "1 : 8",
      "8 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "4 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p4ymxs",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements.</p>\n<p>Statement I : Electric potential is constant within and at the surface of each conductor.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Electric field just outside a charged conductor is perpendicular to the surface of the conductor at every point.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo6p32l",
    "question": "Considering a group of positive charges, which of the following statements is correct ?",
    "options": [
      "Net potential of the system cannot be zero at a point but net electric field can be zero at that point",
      "Net potential of the system at a point can be zero but net electric field can't be zero at that point.",
      "Both the net potential and the net electric field cannot be zero at a point.",
      "Both the net potential and the net field can be zero at a point."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "Net potential of the system cannot be zero at a point but net electric field can be zero at that point"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqr0ia",
    "question": "<p>Electric potential at a point '$$\\mathrm{P}$$' due to a point charge of $$5 \\times 10^{-9} \\mathrm{C}$$ is $$50 \\mathrm{~V}$$. The distance of '$$\\mathrm{P}$$' from the point charge is:</p>\n<p>(Assume, $$\\frac{1}{4 \\pi \\varepsilon_{0}}=9 \\times 10^{+9} ~\\mathrm{Nm}^{2} \\mathrm{C}^{-2}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.9 cm",
      "90 cm",
      "3 cm",
      "9 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "90 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3ly23",
    "question": "<p>An electric charge $$10^{-6} \\mu \\mathrm{C}$$ is placed at origin $$(0,0)$$ $$\\mathrm{m}$$ of $$\\mathrm{X}-\\mathrm{Y}$$ co-ordinate system. Two points $$\\mathrm{P}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Q}$$ are situated at $$(\\sqrt{3}, \\sqrt{3}) \\mathrm{m}$$ and $$(\\sqrt{6}, 0) \\mathrm{m}$$ respectively. The potential difference between the points $\\mathrm{P}$ and $\\mathrm{Q}$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{3} \\mathrm{~V}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{6} \\mathrm{~V}$$\n",
      "$$0 \\mathrm{~V}$$\n",
      "$$3 \\mathrm{~V}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "electrostatics",
    "topic": "electric-potential-energy-and-electric-potential",
    "solution": "$$0 \\mathrm{~V}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "UMRnnU7VkmcC2Kof",
    "question": "A plano convex lens of refractive index $$1.5$$ and radius of curvature $$30$$ $$cm$$. Is silvered at the curved surface. Now this lens has been used to form the image of an object. At what distance from this lens an object be placed in order to have a real image of size of the object ",
    "options": [
      "$$60$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$30$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$20$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$80$$ $$cm$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$$20$$ $$cm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "8MTviplPuzKIkeMH",
    "question": "A thin glass (refractive index $$1.5$$) lens has optical power of $$-5$$ $$D$$ in air. Its optical power in a liquid medium with refractive index $$1.6$$ will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$-1$$ $$D$$ ",
      "$$1$$ $$D$$ ",
      "$$-25$$ $$D$$ ",
      "$$25$$ $$D$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$$1$$ $$D$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "N93RksJ30NYA8ysz",
    "question": "Two lenses of power $$-15$$ $$D$$ and $$+5$$ $$D$$ are in contact with each other. The focal length of the combination is ",
    "options": [
      "$$ + 10\\,cm$$ ",
      "$$ - 20\\,cm$$",
      "$$ - 10\\,cm$$",
      "$$ + 20\\,cm$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$$ - 10\\,cm$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jNhKtkSIRYIy9woC",
    "question": "In an optics experiment, with the position of the object fixed, a student varies the position of a convex lens and for each position, the screen is adjusted to get a clear image of the object. A graph between the object distance $$u$$ and the image distance $$v,$$ from the lens, is plotted using the same scale for the two axes. A straight line passing through the origin and making an angle of $${45^ \\circ }$$  with the $$x$$-axis meets the experimental curve at $$P.$$ The coordinates of $$P$$ will be : ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {{f \\over 2},{f \\over 2}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {f,f} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {4f,4f} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {2f,2f} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {2f,2f} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "h6o7Ed95gvDtiKy2",
    "question": "An object $$2.4$$ $$m$$ in front of a lens forms a sharp image on a film $$12$$ $$cm$$ behind the lens.  A glass plate $$1$$ $$cm$$ thick, of refractive index $$1.50$$ is interposed between lens and film with its plane faces parallel to film. At what distance (from lens) should object shifted to be in sharp focus of film? ",
    "options": [
      "$$7.2$$ $$m$$ ",
      "$$24$$ $$m$$ ",
      "$$3.2$$ $$m$$ ",
      "$$5.6$$ $$m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$$5.6$$ $$m$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "QBKQfus1LKHDHtNk",
    "question": "Diameter of a plano-convex lens is $$6$$ $$cm$$ and thickness at the center is $$3mm$$. If speed of light in material of lens is $$2 \\times {10^8}\\,m/s,$$ the focal length of the lens is ",
    "options": [
      "$$15$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$20$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$30$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$10$$ $$cm$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$$30$$ $$cm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "xNIG8WpORNYinWn2",
    "question": "A thin convex lens made from crown glass $$\\left( {\\mu  = {3 \\over 2}} \\right)$$ has focal length $$f$$. When it is measured in two different liquids having refractive indices $${4 \\over 3}$$ and $${5 \\over 3},$$  it has the focal lengths $${f_1}$$ and $${f_2}$$ respectively. The correct relation between the focal lengths is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${f_1} = {f_2} &lt; f$$ ",
      "$${f_1} &gt; f$$ and $${f_2}$$ becomes negative ",
      "$${f_2} &gt; f$$ and $${f_1}$$ becomes negative ",
      "$${f_1}\\,$$ and$${f_2}\\,$$ both become negative "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$${f_1} &gt; f$$ and $${f_2}$$ becomes negative "
  },
  {
    "id": "oG9JGEP1uiDq1rmVm22Ym",
    "question": "To find the focal length of a convex mirror, a student records the following data :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg th{font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-weight:normal;padding:10px 5px;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;overflow:hidden;word-break:normal;border-color:black;}\n.tg .tg-wrg0{font-size:22px;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-wv9z{font-size:22px;text-align:center}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<tbody><tr>\n<th class=\"tg-wv9z\">Object<br/>Pin</th>\n<th class=\"tg-wv9z\">Convex<br/>Lens</th>\n<th class=\"tg-wv9z\">Convex<br/>Mirror</th>\n<th class=\"tg-wrg0\">Image<br/>Pin</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">22.2 cm</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">32.2 cm</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wv9z\">45.8 cm</td>\n<td class=\"tg-wrg0\">71.2 cm</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody></table>\n<br/><br/>The focal length of the convex lens is f<sub>1</sub> and that of mirror is f<sub>2</sub>. Then taking index correction to be negligibly small, f<sub>1</sub> and f<sub>2</sub> are close to :",
    "options": [
      "f<sub>1</sub> = 12.7 cm&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; f<sub>2</sub> = 7.8 cm",
      "f<sub>1</sub> = 7.8 cm&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; f<sub>2</sub> = 12.7 cm",
      "f<sub>1</sub> = 7.8 cm&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; f<sub>2</sub> = 25.4 cm",
      "f<sub>1</sub> = 15.6 cm&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; f<sub>2</sub> = 25.4 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "f<sub>1</sub> = 7.8 cm&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; f<sub>2</sub> = 12.7 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "mmI4TdE5otk9XYLM7MAu9",
    "question": "In an experiment a convex lens of focal length 15 cm is placed coaxially on an optical bench in front of a convex mirror at a distance of 5 cm from it. It is found that an object and its image coincide, if the object is placed at a distance of 20 cm from the lens. The focal length of the convex mirror is :  ",
    "options": [
      "27.5 cm",
      "20.0 cm",
      "25.0 cm",
      "30.5 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "27.5 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "CgPelWEWGd8PskdE",
    "question": "A diverging lens with magnitude of focal length 25 cm is placed at a distance of 15cm from a converging\nlens of magnitude of focal length 20cm. A beam of parallel light falls on the diverging lens. The final\nimage formed is:",
    "options": [
      "real and at a distance of 6 cm from the convergent lens.",
      "real and at a distance of 40 cm from convergent lens.",
      "virtual and at a distance of 40 cm from convergent lens.",
      "real and at a distance of 40 cm from the divergent lens."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "real and at a distance of 40 cm from convergent lens."
  },
  {
    "id": "Scp4CmUbhUqB5akfep1eU",
    "question": "A convergent doublet of separated lenses, corrected for spherical aberration, has resultant focal length of 10 cm. The separation between the two lenses is $$2$$ cm. The focal lengths of the component lenses are : ",
    "options": [
      "10 cm, 12 cm",
      "12 cm, 14 cm",
      "16 cm, 18 cm",
      "18 cm, 20cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "18 cm, 20cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "HANDsjkXe5buQmS0JoLKe",
    "question": "A plano-convex lens (focal length f<sub>2</sub>, refractive index $$\\mu $$<sub>2</sub>, radius of curvature R) fits exactly into a plano-concave lens (focal length f<sub>1</sub>, refractive index $$\\mu $$<sub>1</sub>, radius of curvature R). Their plane surfaces are parallel to each other. Then, the focal length of the combination will be : \n",
    "options": [
      "f<sub>1</sub><sub></sub> + f<sub>2</sub>",
      "f<sub>1</sub> $$-$$ f<sub>2</sub>",
      "$${R \\over {{\\mu _2} - {\\mu _1}}}$$",
      "$${{2{f_1}{f_2}} \\over {{f_1} + {f_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$${R \\over {{\\mu _2} - {\\mu _1}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "IEKDHT0eM8TDV5qSHppje",
    "question": "A convex lens of focal length 20 cm produces\nimages of the same magnification 2 when an\nobject is kept at two distances x<sub>1</sub> and x<sub>2</sub>\n(x<sub>1</sub> &gt; x<sub>2</sub>) from the lens. The ratio of x<sub>1</sub> and x<sub>2</sub>\nis :-",
    "options": [
      "3 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "5 : 3",
      "4 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "3 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "vMmFWJZKzLPyuBsfdGl8U",
    "question": "A convex lens (of focal length 20 cm) and a\nconcave mirror, having their principal axes\nalong the same lines, are kept 80 cm apart from\neach other. The concave mirror is to the right\nof the convex lens. When an object is kept at\na distance of 30 cm to the left of the convex\nlens, its image remains at the same position\neven if the concave mirror is removed. The\nmaximum distance of the object for which this\nconcave mirror, by itself would produce a\nvirtual image would be :-",
    "options": [
      "25 cm",
      "10 cm",
      "20 cm",
      "30 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "10 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "Zly3XvQjqaA02vIrdIVd6",
    "question": "An upright object is placed at a distance of\n40 cm in front of a convergent lens of focal\nlength 20 cm. A convergent mirror of focal\nlength 10 cm is placed at a distance of 60 cm\non the other side of the lens. The position and\nsize of the final image will be :",
    "options": [
      "20 cm from the convergent mirror, same\nsize as the object",
      "40 cm from the convergent mirror, same\nsize as the object",
      "40 cm from the convergent lens, same\nsize as the object",
      "20 cm from the convergent mirror, twice the\nsize of the object"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "40 cm from the convergent lens, same\nsize as the object"
  },
  {
    "id": "8jQFrC0IaBqVJdr5sZUfe",
    "question": "An object is at a distance of 20 m from a convex lens of focal length 0.3 m. The lens forms an image of the object. If the object moves away from the lens at a speed of 5 m/s, the speed and direction of the image will be : ",
    "options": [
      "1.16 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> m/s towards the lens ",
      "2.26 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> m/s away from the lens",
      "3.22 × 10<sup>–3</sup> m/s towards the lens",
      "0.92 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> m/s away from the lens"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "1.16 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> m/s towards the lens "
  },
  {
    "id": "6iYzcxw1Hm8enZIFG2NDI",
    "question": "The eye can be regarded as a single refracting surface. The radius of curvature of this surface is equal to that of cornea (7.8 mm). This surface separateds two media of refractive indices 1 and 1.34. Calculate the distance from the refracting surface at which a parallel beam of light will come to focus -",
    "options": [
      "2 cm",
      "3.1 cm",
      "4.0 cm",
      "1 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "3.1 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1m5Hv1CkT3Dq6cfxAglmD",
    "question": "A plano convex lens of refractive index $$\\mu $$<sub>1</sub> and focal length ƒ<sub>1</sub> is kept in contact with another plano concave lens of refractive index $$\\mu $$<sub>2</sub> and focal length ƒ<sub>2</sub>. If the radius of curvature of their spherical faces is R each and ƒ<sub>1</sub> = 2ƒ<sub>2</sub>, then $$\\mu $$<sub>1</sub> and $$\\mu $$<sub>2</sub> are related as -",
    "options": [
      "$$3{\\mu _2} - 2{\\mu _1}$$ = 1",
      "$${\\mu _1} + {\\mu _2}$$ = 3",
      "$$2{\\mu _1} - {\\mu _2}$$ = 1",
      "$$2{\\mu _2} - {\\mu _1}$$ = 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$$2{\\mu _1} - {\\mu _2}$$ = 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "7p8e61TpaHO7YAaYwjSBZ",
    "question": "A convex lens is put 10 cm from a light source and it makes a sharp image on a screen, kept 10 cm from the lens. Now a glass block (refractive index 1.5) of 1.5 cm thickness is placed in contact with the  light source. To get the sharp image again, the screen is shifted by a distance d. Then d is : ",
    "options": [
      "1.1 cm away from the lens",
      "0",
      "0.55 cm towards the lens",
      "0.55 cm away from the lens"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "0.55 cm away from the lens"
  },
  {
    "id": "5SpfAsKpCKEQJp72q77k9k2k5f7jlte",
    "question": "A thin lens made of glass (refractive index = 1.5) of focal length f = 16 cm is immersed in a liquid\nof refractive index 1.42. If its focal length in liquid is f<sub>1</sub>\n, then the ratio $${{{f_1}} \\over f}$$ is closest to the\ninteger :",
    "options": [
      "17",
      "1",
      "9",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "9"
  },
  {
    "id": "vdsCyt6mGC6NsYipzQjgy2xukfrowb2o",
    "question": "A point like object is placed at a distance of 1 m in front of a convex lens of focal length 0.5 m. A\nplane mirror is placed at a distance of 2 m behind the lens. The position and nature of the final\nimage formed by the system is :",
    "options": [
      "2.6 m from the mirror, real",
      "1 m from the mirror, real",
      "2.6 m from the mirror, virtual",
      "1 m from the mirror, virtual"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "2.6 m from the mirror, real"
  },
  {
    "id": "6M9U3zpBj2SyZvh6RHjgy2xukg09z0ui",
    "question": "A double convex lens has power P and same radii of curvature R of both the surfaces. The radius of\ncurvature of a surface of a plano-convex lens made of the same material with power 1.5 P is :",
    "options": [
      "$${R \\over 3}$$",
      "$${{3R} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${R \\over 2}$$",
      "2R"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$${R \\over 3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "sk6OHjgasMT1o2GEQW1kmiogq4k",
    "question": "The refractive index of a converging lens is 1.4. What will be the focal length of this lens if it is placed in a medium of same refractive index? Assume the radii of curvature of the faces of lens are R<sub>1</sub> and R<sub>2</sub> respectively.",
    "options": [
      "Zero",
      "Infinite",
      "1",
      "$${{{R_1}{R_2}} \\over {{R_1} - {R_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "Infinite"
  },
  {
    "id": "UXW2043csIElKMbMBx1kmj21n72",
    "question": "The thickness at the centre of a plane convex lens is 3 mm and the diameter is 6 cm. If the speed of light in the material of the lens is 2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. The focal length of the lens is ____________.",
    "options": [
      "0.30 cm",
      "30 cm",
      "15 cm",
      "1.5 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "30 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth17ivn",
    "question": "An object is placed at the focus of concave lens having focal length f. What is the magnification and distance of the image from the optical centre of the lens?",
    "options": [
      "1, $$\\infty$$",
      "Very high, $$\\infty$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$, $${f \\over 2}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}$$, $${f \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}$$, $${f \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f4ohfa",
    "question": "<p>For an object placed at a distance 2.4 m from a lens, a sharp focused image is observed on a screen placed at a distance 12 cm from the lens. A glass plate of refractive index 1.5 and thickness 1 cm is introduced between lens and screen such that the glass plate plane faces parallel to the screen. By what distance should the object be shifted so that a sharp focused image is observed again on the screen?</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.8 m",
      "3.2 m",
      "1.2 m",
      "5.6 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "3.2 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nsxeio",
    "question": "<p>The power of a lens (biconvex) is $$1.25 \\mathrm{~m}^{-1}$$ in particular medium. Refractive index of the lens is 1.5 and radii of curvature are $$20 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ and $$40 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ respectively. The refractive index of surrounding medium:</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.0",
      "$$\\frac{9}{7}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{4}{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{9}{7}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr2gyi9",
    "question": "<p>A person has been using spectacles of power $$-1.0$$ dioptre for distant vision and a separate reading glass of power $$2.0$$ dioptres. What is the least distance of distinct vision for this person :</p>",
    "options": [
      "50 cm",
      "40 cm",
      "30 cm",
      "10 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "50 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh2zt8kr",
    "question": "<p>A 2 meter long scale with least count of $$0.2 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ is used to measure the locations of objects on an optical bench. While measuring the focal length of a convex lens, the object pin and the convex lens are placed at $$80 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ mark and $$1 \\mathrm{~m}$$ mark, respectively. The image of the object pin on the other side of lens coincides with image pin that is kept at $$180 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ mark. The $$\\%$$ error in the estimation of focal length is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.70",
      "0.51",
      "1.02",
      "0.85"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "1.70"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3ndoy",
    "question": "<p>A convex lens of focal length $$40 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ forms an image of an extended source of light on a photoelectric cell. A current I is produced. The lens is replaced by another convex lens having the same diameter but focal length $$20 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. The photoelectric current now is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{\\frac{I}{2}}$$",
      "4 I",
      "2 I",
      "I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "I"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1dkee",
    "question": "<p>A biconvex lens of refractive index 1.5 has a focal length of $$20 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ in air. Its focal length when immersed in a liquid of refractive index 1.6 will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$16 cm",
      "+16 cm",
      "+160 cm",
      "$$-$$160 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$$-$$160 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "luyitaa6",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : When an object is placed at the centre of curvature of a concave lens, image is formed at the centre of curvature of the lens on the other side.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : Concave lens always forms a virtual and erect image.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxked",
    "question": "<p>An effective power of a combination of 5 identical convex lenses which are kept in contact along the principal axis is $$25 \\mathrm{D}$$. Focal length of each of the convex lens is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "50 cm",
      "20 cm",
      "25 cm",
      "500 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "20 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxm1t",
    "question": "<p>In an experiment to measure focal length ($$f$$) of convex lens, the least counts of the measuring scales for the position of object (u) and for the position of image (v) are $$\\Delta u$$ and $$\\Delta v$$, respectively. The error in the measurement of the focal length of the convex lens will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2 f\\left[\\frac{\\Delta \\mathrm{u}}{\\mathrm{u}}+\\frac{\\Delta \\mathrm{v}}{\\mathrm{v}}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$f\\left[\\frac{\\Delta \\mathrm{u}}{\\mathrm{u}}+\\frac{\\Delta \\mathrm{v}}{\\mathrm{v}}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$f^2\\left[\\frac{\\Delta \\mathrm{u}}{\\mathrm{u}^2}+\\frac{\\Delta \\mathrm{v}}{\\mathrm{v}^2}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\Delta \\mathrm{u}}{\\mathrm{u}}+\\frac{\\Delta \\mathrm{v}}{\\mathrm{v}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "$$f^2\\left[\\frac{\\Delta \\mathrm{u}}{\\mathrm{u}^2}+\\frac{\\Delta \\mathrm{v}}{\\mathrm{v}^2}\\right]$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29ea0",
    "question": "<p>For the thin convex lens, the radii of curvature are at $$15 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ and $$30 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ respectively. The focal length the lens is $$20 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. The refractive index of the material is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.2",
      "1.5",
      "1.4",
      "1.8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "lenses",
    "solution": "1.5"
  },
  {
    "id": "PxrdrrjHeoGbS4Jy",
    "question": "Wavelength of light used in an  optical instrument are $${\\lambda _1} = 4000\\mathop A\\limits^ \\circ  $$ and $${\\lambda _2} = 5000\\mathop A\\limits^ \\circ  ,$$  then ratio of their respective resolving powers (corresponding  to $${\\lambda _1}$$ and $${\\lambda _2}$$ ) is :",
    "options": [
      "$$16:25$$ ",
      "$$9:1$$ ",
      "$$4:5$$ ",
      "$$5:4$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "$$5:4$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "iowVHNs05L4o3jck",
    "question": "An astronomical telescope has a large aperture to ",
    "options": [
      "reduce spherical aberration ",
      "have high resolution ",
      "increase span of observation ",
      "have low dispersion"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "have high resolution "
  },
  {
    "id": "cQ7FUUH6v54llMkK",
    "question": "The image formed by an objective of a compound microscope is ",
    "options": [
      "virtual and diminished ",
      "real an diminished   ",
      "real and enlarged ",
      "virtual and enlarged  "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "real and enlarged "
  },
  {
    "id": "Ds91CkLT5O3mFF64",
    "question": "An observer looks at a distant tree of height $$10$$ $$m$$ with a telescope of magnifying power of $$20.$$ To the observer the tree appears: ",
    "options": [
      "$$20$$ times taller ",
      "$$20$$ times nearer ",
      "$$10$$ times taller ",
      "$$10$$ times nearer "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "$$20$$ times nearer "
  },
  {
    "id": "1U6jmr9CHqlu0sKIEb7k9k2k5dm1hr8",
    "question": "If we need a magnification of 375 from a compound microscope of tube length 150 mm and an objective of focal length 5 mm, the focal length of the eye-piece, should be close to :",
    "options": [
      "22 mm",
      "12 mm",
      "33 mm",
      "2 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "22 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "PtF1LjGZkgsXloqgMu7k9k2k5gw7a65",
    "question": "The magnifying power of a telescope with tube\n60 cm is 5. What is the focal length of its eye\npiece ?",
    "options": [
      "40 cm",
      "10 cm",
      "30 cm",
      "20 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "10 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "xVzYerlkhALt4nKGN77k9k2k5ienu4q",
    "question": "The aperture diameter of a telescope is 5m. The\nseparation between the moon and the earth is\n4 × 10<sup>5</sup> km. With light of wavelength of\n5500 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$, the minimum separation between\nobjects on the surface of moon, so that they are\njust resolved, is close to :",
    "options": [
      "20 m",
      "200 m",
      "600 m",
      "60 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "60 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "gkL0G4pOagR6hfNTXt1klulw37j",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labeled as Assertion A and the other is labeled as Reason R.<br/><br/>Assertion A : For a simple microscope, the angular size of the object equals the angular size of the image.<br/><br/>Reason R : Magnification is achieved as the small object can be kept much closer to the eye than 25 cm and hence it subtends a large angle.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "XA3LKdpyvhS3qJ4dep1kmkrjyhc",
    "question": "Your friend is having eye sight problem. She is not able to see clearly a distant uniform window mesh and it appears to her as non-uniform and distorted. The doctor diagnosed the problem as :",
    "options": [
      "Astigmatism",
      "Myopia with Astigmatism",
      "Presbyopia with Astigmatism",
      "Myopia and Hypermetropia"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "Myopia with Astigmatism"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l569j7k0",
    "question": "<p>The aperture of the objective is 24.4 cm. The resolving power of this telescope, if a light of wavelength 2440 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$ is used to see th object will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "8.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>6</sup>",
      "10.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup>",
      "8.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>",
      "1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "8.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jie6bw",
    "question": "<p>A microscope was initially placed in air (refractive index 1). It is then immersed in oil (refractive index 2). For a light whose wavelength in air is $$\\lambda$$, calculate the change of microscope's resolving power due to oil and choose the correct option.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Resolving power will be $$\\frac{1}{4}$$ in the oil than it was in the air.",
      "Resolving power will be twice in the oil than it was in the air.",
      "Resolving power will be four times in the oil than it was in the air.",
      "Resolving power will be $$\\frac{1}{2}$$ in the oil than it was in the air."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "Resolving power will be twice in the oil than it was in the air."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6mativv",
    "question": "<p>In normal adujstment, for a refracting telescope, the distance between objective and eye piece is $$30 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. The focal length of the objective, when the angular magnification of the telescope is 2 , will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "20 cm",
      "30 cm",
      "10 cm",
      "15 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "20 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsa5twm",
    "question": "<p>A scientist is observing a bacteria through a compound microscope. For better analysis and to improve its resolving power he should. (Select the best option)</p>",
    "options": [
      "Decrease the focal length of the eye piece.",
      "Increase the wave length of the light",
      "Increase the refractive index of the medium between the object and objective lens",
      "Decrease the diameter of the objective lens"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "Increase the refractive index of the medium between the object and objective lens"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh00tbxb",
    "question": "<p>In a reflecting telescope, a secondary mirror is used to:</p>",
    "options": [
      "make chromatic aberration zero",
      "remove spherical aberration",
      "reduce the problem of mechanical support",
      "move the eyepiece outside the telescopic tube"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "move the eyepiece outside the telescopic tube"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc38c3k",
    "question": "<p>Identify the physical quantity that cannot be measured using spherometer :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Radius of curvature of concave surface\n",
      "Specific rotation of liquids\n",
      "Thickness of thin plates\n",
      "Radius of curvature of convex surface\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "optical-instruments",
    "solution": "Specific rotation of liquids\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "4i0m2CL34d4CxsWa",
    "question": "If two mirrors are kept at $${60^ \\circ }$$ to each other, then the number of images formed by them is ",
    "options": [
      "$$5$$ ",
      "$$6$$ ",
      "$$7$$ ",
      "$$8$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "$$5$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "LKUoc372hiY6EZIb",
    "question": "To get three images of a single object, one should have two plane mirrors at an angle of ",
    "options": [
      "$${60^ \\circ }$$ ",
      "$${90^ \\circ }$$",
      "$${120^ \\circ }$$",
      "$${30^ \\circ }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "$${90^ \\circ }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "PJKzdsiV6Xy5Eyi0",
    "question": "A car is fitted with a convex side-view mirror of focal length $$20$$ $$cm$$. A second car $$2.8m$$ behind the first car is overtaking the first car at a relative speed of $$15$$ $$m/s$$. The speed of the image of the second car as seen in the mirror of the first one is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {15}}\\,m/s$$ ",
      "$$10\\,m/s$$ ",
      "$$15\\,m/s$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {10}}\\,m/s$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {15}}\\,m/s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "KUdHNKvbxVETGrks1LdhS",
    "question": "Two plane mirrors are inclined to each other such that a ray of light incident on the first mirror (M<sub>1</sub>) and parallel to the second mirror (M<sub>2</sub>) is finally reflected from the second mirror (M<sub>2</sub>) parallel to the first mirror (M<sub>1</sub>). The angle between the two mirrors will be : ",
    "options": [
      "45<sup>o</sup>",
      "60<sup>o</sup>",
      "75<sup>o</sup>",
      "90<sup>o</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "60<sup>o</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "9QuDakUlkW8GXU2KsNZli",
    "question": "A concave mirror for face viewing has focal\nlength of 0.4 m. The distance at which you hold\nthe mirror from your face in order to see your\nimage upright with a magnification of 5 is :",
    "options": [
      "0.24 m",
      "0.32 m",
      "1.60 m",
      "0.16 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "0.32 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "8AEi8nmNnDCK1Q9GAa1klrhk0r2",
    "question": "The focal length f is related to the radius of curvature r of the spherical convex mirror by :",
    "options": [
      "f = r",
      "f = $$-$$ r",
      "f = +$${{1 \\over 2}}$$ r",
      "f = $$-$$$${{1 \\over 2}}$$ r"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "f = +$${{1 \\over 2}}$$ r"
  },
  {
    "id": "Cqju81PF0bDbuTN4aK1klthl4b3",
    "question": "A short straight object of height 100 cm lies before the central axis of a spherical mirror whose focal length has absolute value | f | = 40 cm. The image of object produced by the mirror is of height 25 cm and has the same orientation of the object. One may conclude from the information :",
    "options": [
      "Image is real, same side of convex mirror.",
      "Image is virtual, opposite side of convex mirror.",
      "Image is virtual, opposite side of concave mirror.",
      "Image is real, same side of concave mirror."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "Image is virtual, opposite side of convex mirror."
  },
  {
    "id": "lLdDTLTDsxu0Nc7QbW1klulicnz",
    "question": "The incident ray, reflected ray and the outward drawn normal are denoted by the unit vectors $$\\overrightarrow a $$, $$\\overrightarrow b $$ and $$\\overrightarrow c $$ respectively. Then choose the correct relation for these vectors.",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow b $$ = $$\\overrightarrow a $$ + 2$$\\overrightarrow c $$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow b $$ = $$\\overrightarrow a $$ $$-$$ 2 ($$\\overrightarrow a $$ . $$\\overrightarrow c $$)$$\\overrightarrow c $$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow b $$ = 2$$\\overrightarrow a $$ + $$\\overrightarrow c $$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow b $$ = $$\\overrightarrow a $$ $$-$$ $$\\overrightarrow c $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow b $$ = $$\\overrightarrow a $$ $$-$$ 2 ($$\\overrightarrow a $$ . $$\\overrightarrow c $$)$$\\overrightarrow c $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kta8r120",
    "question": "Car B overtakes another car A at a relative speed of 40 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. How fast will the image of car B appear to move in the mirror of focal length 10 cm fitted in car A, when the car B is 1.9 m away from the car A?",
    "options": [
      "4 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "0.2 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "40 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "0.1 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "0.1 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktdz3bkj",
    "question": "An object is placed beyond the centre of curvature C of the given concave mirror. If the distance of the object is d<sub>1</sub> from C and the distance of the image formed is d<sub>2</sub> from C, the radius of curvature of this mirror is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2{d_1}{d_2}} \\over {{d_1} - {d_2}}}$$",
      "$${{2{d_1}{d_2}} \\over {{d_1} + {d_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{d_1}{d_2}} \\over {{d_1} + {d_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{d_1}{d_2}} \\over {{d_1} - {d_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "$${{2{d_1}{d_2}} \\over {{d_1} - {d_2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnx5spy",
    "question": "<p>Two objects A and B are placed at 15 cm and 25 cm from the pole in front of a concave mirror having radius of curvature 40 cm. The distance between images formed by the mirror is _______________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "60 cm",
      "40 cm",
      "160 cm",
      "100 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "160 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtxe5ew",
    "question": "<p>The light rays from an object have been reflected towards an observer from a standard flat mirror, the image observed by the observer are :-</p>\n<p>A. Real</p>\n<p>B. Erect</p>\n<p>C. Smaller in size then object</p>\n<p>D. Laterally inverted</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "B and D only",
      "A, C, and D only",
      "A and D only",
      "B and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "B and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswr535",
    "question": "<p>When one light ray is reflected from a plane mirror with $$30^{\\circ}$$ angle of reflection, the angle of deviation of the ray after reflection is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$140^{\\circ}$$",
      "$$130^{\\circ}$$",
      "$$120^{\\circ}$$",
      "$$110^{\\circ}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "$$120^{\\circ}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyeva3m",
    "question": "<p>An object is placed at a distance of 12 cm in front of a plane mirror. The virtual and erect image is formed by the mirror. Now the mirror is moved by 4 cm towards the stationary object. The distance by which the position of image would be shifted, will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 cm towards mirror",
      "2 cm towards mirror",
      "8 cm away from mirror",
      "8 cm towards mirror"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "8 cm towards mirror"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf12puz",
    "question": "<p>A convex mirror of radius of curvature $$30 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ forms an image that is half the size of the object. The object distance is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$45 cm",
      "$$-$$15 cm",
      "45 cm",
      "15 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "$$-$$15 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsflt02d",
    "question": "<p>If the distance between object and its two times magnified virtual image produced by a curved mirror is $$15 \\mathrm{~cm}$$, the focal length of the mirror must be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-10$$ cm",
      "$$-12$$ cm",
      "15 cm",
      "10/3 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "reflection-of-light",
    "solution": "$$-10$$ cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "A8p8zu1JxHYskZrA",
    "question": "Which of the following is used in optical fibres? ",
    "options": [
      "total internal reflection ",
      "scattering ",
      "diffracttion",
      "refraction "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "total internal reflection "
  },
  {
    "id": "pzFBfp35IyZlQIsH",
    "question": "A fish looking up through the water sees the outside world contained in a circular horizon. If the refractive index of water is $${4 \\over 3}$$ and the fish is $$12$$ $$cm$$ below the surface, the radius of this circle in $$cm$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{36} \\over {\\sqrt 7 }}$$ ",
      "$${36\\sqrt 7 }$$ ",
      "$${4\\sqrt 5 }$$",
      "$${36\\sqrt 5 }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$${{36} \\over {\\sqrt 7 }}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "xXtUOzMFWNL9kHRX",
    "question": "The refractive index of a glass is $$1.520$$ for red light and $$1.525$$ for blue light. Let $${D_1}$$ and $${D_2}$$ be angles of minimum deviation for red and blue light respectively in a prism of this glass. Then, ",
    "options": [
      "$${D_1} &lt; {D_2}$$ ",
      "$${D_1} = {D_2}$$ ",
      "$${D_1}$$ can be less than or greater than $${D_2}$$ depending upon the angle of prism",
      "$${D_1} &gt; {D_2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$${D_1} &lt; {D_2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "f24ncbwOBEaRtFtN",
    "question": "An initially parallel cylindrical beam travels in a medium of refractive index $$\\mu \\left( I \\right) = {\\mu _0} + {\\mu _2}\\,I,$$ where $${\\mu _0}$$ and $${\\mu _2}$$ are positive constants and $$I$$ is the intensity of the light beam. The intensity of the beam is decreasing with increasing radius.\n<p>The speed of light in the medium is </p> ",
    "options": [
      "minimum on the axis of the beam ",
      "the same everywhere in the beam ",
      "directly proportional to the intensity $$I$$ ",
      "maximum on the axis of the beam  "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "minimum on the axis of the beam "
  },
  {
    "id": "SyKBYYXIU01IaDI2",
    "question": "An initially parallel cylindrical beam travels in a medium of refractive index $$\\mu \\left( I \\right) = {\\mu _0} + {\\mu _2}\\,I,$$ where $${\\mu _0}$$ and $${\\mu _2}$$ are positive constants and $$I$$ is the intensity of the light beam. The intensity of the beam is decreasing with increasing radius.\n<p>As the beam enters the medium, it will</p>",
    "options": [
      "diverge ",
      "converge ",
      "diverge near the axis and converge near the periphery ",
      "travel as a cylindrical beam "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "converge "
  },
  {
    "id": "o4baCtIPx5ST7CTO",
    "question": "Let $$x$$-$$z$$ plane be the boundary between two transparent media. Medium $$1$$ in $$z \\ge 0$$ has a refractive index of $$\\sqrt 2 $$ and medium $$2$$ with   $$z &lt; 0$$ has a refractive index of $$\\sqrt 3 .$$ A ray of light in medium $$1$$ given by the vector $$\\overrightarrow A  = 6\\sqrt 3 \\widehat i + 8\\sqrt 3 \\widehat j - 10\\widehat k$$ is incident on the plane of separation. The angle of refraction in medium $$2$$ is: ",
    "options": [
      "$${45^ \\circ }$$ ",
      "$${60^ \\circ }$$",
      "$${75^ \\circ }$$",
      "$${30^ \\circ }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$${45^ \\circ }$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "srWimqDukx0JqubM",
    "question": "A green light is incident from the water to the air - water interface at the critical angle $$\\left( \\theta  \\right)$$. Select the correct statement. ",
    "options": [
      "The entire spectrum of visible light will come out of the water at an angle of $${90^ \\circ }$$  to the normal. ",
      "The spectrum of visible light whose frequency is less than that of green light will come out to the air medium. ",
      "The spectrum of visible light whose frequency is more than that of green light will come out to the air medium.  ",
      "The entire spectrum of visible light will come out of the water at various angles to the normal. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "The spectrum of visible light whose frequency is less than that of green light will come out to the air medium. "
  },
  {
    "id": "UxSgOI6kOexcAJNd",
    "question": "In an experiment for determination of refractive index of glass of a prism by $$i - \\delta ,$$ plot it was found thata ray incident at angle $${35^ \\circ }$$, suffers a deviation of $${40^ \\circ }$$ and that it emerges at angle $${79^ \\circ }.$$ In that case which of the following is closest to the maximum possible value of the refractive index? ",
    "options": [
      "$$1.7$$ ",
      "$$1.8$$ ",
      "$$1.5$$ ",
      "$$1.6$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$1.5$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "J2twtaEF5XBq0vojzUch7",
    "question": "To determine refractive index of glass slab using a travelling microscope, minimum number of readings required are :",
    "options": [
      "Two ",
      "Three ",
      "Four ",
      "Five "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "Three "
  },
  {
    "id": "qqfeaDwzdvRSZVAJXpJNG",
    "question": "Let the refractive index of a denser medium with respect to a rarer medium be n<sub>12</sub> and its critical angle be θ<sub>C</sub> . At an angle of incidence A when light is travelling from\ndenser medium to rarer medium, a part of the light is reflected and the rest is refracted and the angle between reflected and refracted rays is 90<sup>o</sup>. Angle A is given by :\n",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {{{\\cos }^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sin {\\theta _C}} \\right)}}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {{{\\tan }^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sin {\\theta _C}} \\right)}}$$ ",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\,\\left( {\\sin {\\theta _C}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\,\\left( {\\sin {\\theta _C}} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\,\\left( {\\sin {\\theta _C}} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "DrMPgNxapSLlruIX94VCT",
    "question": "A ray of light is incident at an angle of 60<sup>o</sup> on one face of a prism of angle 30<sup>o</sup>. The  emergent ray of light makes an angle of 30<sup>o</sup> with incident ray.  The angle made by the emergent ray with second face of prism will be : ",
    "options": [
      "0<sup>o</sup> ",
      "90<sup>o</sup> ",
      "45<sup>o</sup> ",
      "30<sup>o</sup> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "90<sup>o</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "a5KLqpQNDBy4zmbdBSx0i",
    "question": "A monochromatic light is incident at a certain angle on an equilateral triangular prism and suffers minimum deviation. If the refractive index of the material of the prism is $$\\sqrt 3 $$, then the angle of incidence is:",
    "options": [
      "60<sup>o</sup>",
      "45<sup>o</sup>",
      "90<sup>o</sup>",
      "30<sup>o</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "60<sup>o</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "bM05YrOJdKAL6xPLU57k9k2k5gxtbv8",
    "question": "The critical angle of a medium for a specific wavelength, if the medium has relative permittivity 3 and relative permeability $${4 \\over 3}$$ for this wavelength, will be :",
    "options": [
      "45°",
      "15°",
      "30°",
      "60°"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "30°"
  },
  {
    "id": "OqaVI8B9VVOnl9Kc1w7k9k2k5l66eku",
    "question": "There is a small source of light at some depth\nbelow the surface of water (refractive\nindex = $${4 \\over 3}$$) in a tank of large cross sectional\nsurface area. Neglecting any reflection from the\nbottom and absorption by water, percentage of\nlight that emerges out of surface is (nearly) :\n<br/>[Use the fact that surface area of a spherical cap\nof height h and radius of curvature r is 2$$\\pi $$rh]:",
    "options": [
      "17%",
      "34%",
      "50%",
      "21%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "17%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1qG4bizr0hC8qJNzlG7k9k2k5iecjk8",
    "question": "A vessel of depth 2h is half filled with a liquid\nof refractive index $$2\\sqrt 2 $$ and the upper half with\nanother liquid of refractive index $$\\sqrt 2 $$ . The\nliquids are immiscible. The apparent depth of\nthe inner surface of the bottom of vessel\nwill be :",
    "options": [
      "$${h \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$${h \\over {3\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 4}h\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$${h \\over {2\\left( {\\sqrt 2  + 1} \\right)}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 4}h\\sqrt 2 $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "mYKRDVwa4iHPiZJ1aq1kmiozx5v",
    "question": "Red light differs from blue light as they have :",
    "options": [
      "Different frequencies and same wavelengths",
      "Different frequencies and different wavelengths",
      "Same frequencies and different wavelengths",
      "Same frequencies and same wavelengths"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "Different frequencies and different wavelengths"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kruk66qm",
    "question": "A ray of laser of a wavelength 630 nm is incident at an angle of 30$$^\\circ$$ at the diamond-air interface. It is going from diamond to air. The refractive index of diamond is 2.42 and that of air is 1. Choose the correct option.",
    "options": [
      "angle of refraction is 24.41$$^\\circ$$",
      "angle of refraction is 30$$^\\circ$$",
      "refraction is not possible",
      "angle of refraction is 53.4$$^\\circ$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "refraction is not possible"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw6rahd",
    "question": "A prism of refractive index $$\\mu$$ and angle of prism A is placed in the position of minimum angle of deviation. If minimum angle of deviation is also A, then in terms of refractive index",
    "options": [
      "$$2{\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{\\mu  \\over 2}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{\\mu  \\over 2}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sqrt {{{\\mu  - 1} \\over 2}} } \\right)$$",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{\\mu  \\over 2}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$2{\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{\\mu  \\over 2}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktmon3i5",
    "question": "A glass tumbler having inner depth of 17.5 cm is kept on a table. A student starts pouring water ($$\\mu$$ = 4/3) into it while looking at the surface of water from the above. When he feels that the tumbler is half filled, he stops pouring water. Up to what height, the tumbler is actually filled?",
    "options": [
      "11.7 cm",
      "10 cm",
      "7.5 cm",
      "8.75 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "10 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54uqp0p",
    "question": "<p>The speed of light in media 'A' and 'B' are $$2.0 \\times {10^{10}}$$ cm/s and $$1.5 \\times {10^{10}}$$ cm/s respectively. A ray of light enters from the medium B to A at an incident angle '$$\\theta$$'. If the ray suffers total internal reflection, then</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\theta  = {\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{3 \\over 4}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\theta  > {\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{2 \\over 3}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\theta  < {\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{3 \\over 4}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\theta  > {\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{3 \\over 4}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$\\theta  > {\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{3 \\over 4}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l569fw07",
    "question": "<p>The refracting angle of a prism is A and refractive index of the material of the prism is cot (A/2). Then the angle of minimum deviation will be -</p>",
    "options": [
      "180 $$-$$ 2A",
      "90 $$-$$ A",
      "180 + 2A",
      "180 $$-$$ 3A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "180 $$-$$ 2A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57qelb6",
    "question": "<p>Consider a light ray travelling in air is incident into a medium of refractive index $$\\sqrt{2n}$$. The incident angle is twice that of refracting angle. Then, the angle of incidence will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sqrt n } \\right)$$",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sqrt {{n \\over 2}} } \\right)$$",
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sqrt {2n} } \\right)$$",
      "$$2{\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sqrt {{n \\over 2}} } \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$2{\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sqrt {{n \\over 2}} } \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5akuvgf",
    "question": "<p>A light wave travelling linearly in a medium of dielectric constant  4, incidents on the horizontal interface separating medium with air. The angle of incidence for which the total intensity of incident wave will be reflected back into the same medium will be :</p>\n<p>(Given : relative permeability of medium $$\\mu$$<sub>r</sub> = 1)</p>",
    "options": [
      "10$$^\\circ$$",
      "20$$^\\circ$$",
      "30$$^\\circ$$",
      "60$$^\\circ$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "60$$^\\circ$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5al36bh",
    "question": "<p>The difference of speed of light in the two media A and B (v<sub>A</sub> $$-$$ v<sub>B</sub>) is 2.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> m/s. If the refractive index of medium B is 1.47, then the ratio of refractive index of medium B to medium A is : (Given : speed of light in vacuum c = 3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.303",
      "1.318",
      "1.13",
      "0.12"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "1.13"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dyxoaa",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following statement is correct?</p>",
    "options": [
      "In primary rainbow, observer sees red colour on the top and violet on the bottom",
      "In primary rainbow, observer sees violet colour on the top and red on the bottom",
      "In primary rainbow, light wave suffers total internal reflection twice before coming out of water drops.",
      "Primary rainbow is less bright than secondary rainbow."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "In primary rainbow, observer sees red colour on the top and violet on the bottom"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dz4gfe",
    "question": "<p>Time taken by light to travel in two different materials $$A$$ and $$B$$ of refractive indices $$\\mu_{A}$$ and $$\\mu_{B}$$ of same thickness is $$t_{1}$$ and $$t_{2}$$ respectively. If $$t_{2}-t_{1}=5 \\times 10^{-10}$$ s and the ratio of $$\\mu_{A}$$ to $$\\mu_{B}$$ is $$1: 2$$. Then, the thickness of material, in meter is: (Given $$v_{\\mathrm{A}}$$ and $$v_{\\mathrm{B}}$$ are velocities of light in $$A$$ and $$B$$ materials respectively.)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$5 \\times 10^{-10} \\,v_{\\mathrm{A}}\\, \\mathrm{m}$$",
      "$$5 \\times 10^{-10} \\mathrm{~m}$$",
      "$$1.5 \\times 10^{-10} \\mathrm{~m}$$",
      "$$5 \\times 10^{-10} \\,v_{\\mathrm{B}} \\,\\mathrm{m}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$5 \\times 10^{-10} \\,v_{\\mathrm{A}}\\, \\mathrm{m}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i0nlu8",
    "question": "<p>Light travels in two media $$M_{1}$$ and $$M_{2}$$ with speeds $$1.5 \\times 10^{8} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ and $$2.0 \\times 10^{8} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ respectively. The critical angle between them is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{7}}\\right)$$",
      "$$\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{2}{3}\\right)$$",
      "$$\\cos ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{3}{4}\\right)$$",
      "$$\\sin ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{2}{3}\\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{3}{\\sqrt{7}}\\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rhtqcn",
    "question": "<p>Light enters from air into a given medium at an angle of $$45^{\\circ}$$ with interface of the air-medium surface. After refraction, the light ray is deviated through an angle of \n$$15^{\\circ}$$ from its original direction. The refractive index of the medium is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.732",
      "1.333",
      "1.414",
      "2.732"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "1.414"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo6yp89",
    "question": "A microscope is focused on an object at the bottom of a bucket. If liquid with refractive index $\\frac{5}{3}$\n\nis poured inside the bucket, then the microscope has to be raised by $30 \\mathrm{~cm}$ to focus the object again.\n\nThe height of the liquid in the bucket is :",
    "options": [
      "$50 \\mathrm{~cm}$",
      "$18 \\mathrm{~cm}$",
      "$75 \\mathrm{~cm}$",
      "$12 \\mathrm{~cm}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$75 \\mathrm{~cm}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqv98p7",
    "question": "<p>A thin prism $P_1$ with an angle $6^{\\circ}$ and made of glass of refractive index $1.54$ is combined with another prism $P_2$ made from glass of refractive index $1.72$ to produce dispersion without average deviation. The angle of prism $P_2$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$4.5^{\\circ}$",
      "$7.8^{\\circ}$",
      "$1.3^{\\circ}$",
      "$6^{\\circ}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$4.5^{\\circ}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwr3l59",
    "question": "<p>When a beam of white light is allowed to pass through convex lens parallel to principal axis, the different colours of light converge at different point on the principle axis after refraction. This is called :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Spherical aberration",
      "Scattering",
      "Polarisation",
      "Chromatic aberration"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "Chromatic aberration"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq1p0sp",
    "question": "<p>A vessel of depth '$$d$$' is half filled with oil of refractive index $$n_{1}$$ and the other half is filled with water of refractive index $$n_{2}$$. The apparent depth of this vessel when viewed from above will be-</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{2 d\\left(n_{1}+n_{2}\\right)}{n_{1} n_{2}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{d\\left(n_{1}+n_{2}\\right)}{2 n_{1} n_{2}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{d n_{1} n_{2}}{2\\left(n_{1}+n_{2}\\right)}$$",
      "$$\\frac{d n_{1} n_{2}}{\\left(n_{1}+n_{2}\\right)}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{d\\left(n_{1}+n_{2}\\right)}{2 n_{1} n_{2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrhs6f8",
    "question": "<p>An ice cube has a bubble inside. When viewed from one side the apparent distance of the bubble is $$12 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. When viewed from the opposite side, the apparent distance of the bubble is observed as $$4 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. If the side of the ice cube is $$24 \\mathrm{~cm}$$, the refractive index of the ice cube is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{4}{3}$$",
      "$$\\frac{2}{3}$$",
      "$$\\frac{6}{5}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgux7q96",
    "question": "<p>The critical angle for a denser-rarer interface is $$45^{\\circ}$$. The speed of light in rarer medium is $$3 \\times 10^{8} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. The speed of light in the denser medium is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2 .12 \\times 10^{8} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$5 \\times 10^{7} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{2} \\times 10^{8} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$3.12 \\times 10^{7} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$2 .12 \\times 10^{8} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh24ps5y",
    "question": "<p>A monochromatic light wave with wavelength $$\\lambda_{1}$$ and frequency $$v_{1}$$ in air enters another medium. If the angle of incidence and angle of refraction at the interface are $$45^{\\circ}$$ and $$30^{\\circ}$$ respectively, then the wavelength $$\\lambda_{2}$$ and frequency $$v_{2}$$ of the refracted wave are:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\lambda_{2}=\\lambda_{1}, v_{2}=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} v_{1}$$",
      "$$\\lambda_{2}=\\lambda_{1}, v_{2}=\\sqrt{2} v_{1}$$",
      "$$\\lambda_{2}=\\sqrt{2} \\lambda_{1}, v_{2}=v_{1}$$",
      "$$\\lambda_{2}=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\lambda_{1}, v_{2}=v_{1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$\\lambda_{2}=\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} \\lambda_{1}, v_{2}=v_{1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh2zozli",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A: The phase difference of two light waves change if they travel through different media having same thickness, but different indices of refraction.</p>\n<p>Reason R: The wavelengths of waves are different in different media.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc2wpgx",
    "question": "<p>If the refractive index of the material of a prism is $$\\cot \\left(\\frac{A}{2}\\right)$$, where $$A$$ is the angle of prism then the angle of minimum deviation will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\pi-2 \\mathrm{~A}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{2}-2 \\mathrm{~A}$$\n",
      "$$\\pi-\\mathrm{A}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\mathrm{A}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$\\pi-2 \\mathrm{~A}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse6cweq",
    "question": "<p>The refractive index of a prism with apex angle $$A$$ is $$\\cot A / 2$$. The angle of minimum deviation is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\delta_m=180^{\\circ}-3 \\mathrm{~A}$$\n",
      "$$\\delta_m=180^{\\circ}-4 A$$\n",
      "$$\\delta_m=180^{\\circ}-2 A$$\n",
      "$$\\delta_m=180^{\\circ}-A$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$\\delta_m=180^{\\circ}-2 A$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gswap",
    "question": "<p>Critical angle of incidence for a pair of optical media is $$45^{\\circ}$$. The refractive indices of first and second media are in the ratio:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: 2$$\n",
      "$$1: \\sqrt{2}$$\n",
      "$$2: 1$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{2}: 1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "geometrical-optics",
    "topic": "refraction,-tir-and-prism",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{2}: 1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "NwEGmO4A7wagMLmX",
    "question": "The change in the value of $$g$$ at a height $$h$$ above the surface of the earth is the same as at a depth $$d$$ below the surface of earth. When both $$d$$ and $$h$$ are much smaller than the radius of earth, then which one of the following is correct? ",
    "options": [
      "$$d = {{3h} \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$$d = {h \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$$d = h$$ ",
      "$$d = 2\\,h$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$$d = 2\\,h$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "u489dvI5VYscDU0X",
    "question": "If $${g_E}$$ and $${g_M}$$ are the accelerations due to gravity on the surfaces of the earth and the moon respectively and if  Millikan's oil drop experiment could be performed on the two surfaces, one will find the ratio \n<br/>$${{electro\\,\\,ch\\arg e\\,\\,on\\,\\,the\\,\\,moon} \\over {electronic\\,\\,ch\\arg e\\,\\,on\\,\\,the\\,\\,earth}}\\,\\,to\\,be$$ ",
    "options": [
      "$${g_M}/{g_E}$$ ",
      "$$1$$  ",
      "$$0$$ ",
      "$${g_E}/{g_M}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$$1$$  "
  },
  {
    "id": "DJA6gakv8s78Q6bP",
    "question": "The height at which the acceleration due to gravity becomes $${g \\over 9}$$ (where $$g=$$ the acceleration due to gravity on the surface of the earth) in terms of $$R,$$ the radius of the earth, is: ",
    "options": [
      "$${R \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "$$R/2$$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 \\,\\,R$$ ",
      "$$2\\,R$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$$2\\,R$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "cHKCIlto0NLtWaegyU28r",
    "question": "If the Earth has no rotational motion, the weight of a person on the equator is W. Determine the speed with which the earth would have to rotate about its axis so that the person at the equator will weigh $${3 \\over 4}$$  W. Radius of the Earth is 6400 km and g=10 m/s<sup>2</sup>.",
    "options": [
      "1.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>−3</sup>  rad/s ",
      "0.83 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>−3</sup>  rad/s ",
      "0.63 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>−3</sup>  rad/s ",
      "0.28 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>−3</sup>  rad/s "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "0.63 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>−3</sup>  rad/s "
  },
  {
    "id": "OSuATH4nBcRDsemOQm5yS",
    "question": "Suppose that the angular velocity of rotation of earth is increased. Then, as a consequence : ",
    "options": [
      "Weight of the object, everywhere on the earth, will increase. ",
      "Weight of the object, everywhere on the earth, will decrease. ",
      "There will be no change in weight anywhere on the earth.",
      "Except at poles, weight of the object on the earth will decrease."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "Except at poles, weight of the object on the earth will decrease."
  },
  {
    "id": "HLuqiuPqmYocjJR4xL18hoxe66ijvztpv00",
    "question": "The value of acceleration due to gravity at\nEarth's surface is 9.8 ms<sup>–2</sup>. The altitude above\nits surface at which the acceleration due to\ngravity decreases to 4.9 ms<sup>–2</sup>, is close to :\n(Radius of earth = 6.4 × 10<sup>6</sup> m)",
    "options": [
      "1.6 × 10<sup>6</sup> m",
      "9.0 × 10<sup>6</sup> m",
      "6.4 × 10<sup>6</sup> m",
      "2.6 × 10<sup>6</sup> m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "2.6 × 10<sup>6</sup> m"
  },
  {
    "id": "EwYQGoScQ3F4Q9ebqu7k9k2k5fb2gev",
    "question": "A box weight 196 N on a spring balance at the north pole. Its weight recorded on the same\nbalance if it is shifted to the equator is close to (Take g = 10 ms<sup>–2</sup> at the north pole and the radius\nof the earth = 6400 km) :",
    "options": [
      "194.32 N",
      "195.66 N",
      "195.32 N",
      "194.66 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "195.32 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "v73vAqbrjACDGVn0Xijgy2xukexxbbjs",
    "question": "The height ‘h’ at which the weight of a body will\nbe the same as that at the same depth ‘h’ from\nthe surface of the earth is (Radius of the earth\nis R and effect of the rotation of the earth is\nneglected)",
    "options": [
      "$${R \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt 5 R - R} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt 3 R - R} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt 5 } \\over 2}R - R$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$${{\\sqrt 5 R - R} \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "tVvLTC6iX4v2OZy4rjjgy2xukf3qy45t",
    "question": "The mass density of a planet of radius R varies with the distance r from its centre as\n<br/>$$\\rho $$(r) = $${\\rho _0}\\left( {1 - {{{r^2}} \\over {{R^2}}}} \\right)$$.\n<br/>Then the gravitational field is maximum at :",
    "options": [
      "$$r = {1 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}R$$",
      "r = R",
      "$$r = \\sqrt {{3 \\over 4}} R$$",
      "$$r = \\sqrt {{5 \\over 9}} R$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$$r = \\sqrt {{5 \\over 9}} R$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "JZM1W6Nb01kbMNm2T7jgy2xukf6hcdq6",
    "question": "On the x-axis and at a distance x from the origin, the gravitational field due a mass distribution is\ngiven by $${{Ax} \\over {{{\\left( {{x^2} + {a^2}} \\right)}^{3/2}}}}$$ in the x-direction. The magnitude of gravitational potential on the x-axis at a\ndistance x, taking its value to be zero at infinity, is:",
    "options": [
      "$${A{{\\left( {{x^2} + {a^2}} \\right)}^{3/2}}}$$",
      "$${A{{\\left( {{x^2} + {a^2}} \\right)}^{1/2}}}$$",
      "$${A \\over {{{\\left( {{x^2} + {a^2}} \\right)}^{1/2}}}}$$",
      "$${A \\over {{{\\left( {{x^2} + {a^2}} \\right)}^{3/2}}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$${A \\over {{{\\left( {{x^2} + {a^2}} \\right)}^{1/2}}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "uieo9M9hxL3WUNSGk1jgy2xukfg7aaur",
    "question": "The value of the acceleration due to gravity is\ng<sub>1</sub> at a height h = $${R \\over 2}$$ (R = radius of the earth) from the surface of the earth. It is again equal\nto g<sub>1</sub> at a depth d below the surface of the\nearth. The ratio $$\\left( {{d \\over R}} \\right)$$ equals :",
    "options": [
      "$${5 \\over 9}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 9}$$",
      "$${7 \\over 9}$$",
      "$${4 \\over 9}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$${5 \\over 9}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "LIfiREm7HD14hnjG9cjgy2xukfl43bnp",
    "question": "The acceleration due to gravity on the earth’s\nsurface at the poles is g and angular velocity of\nthe earth about the axis passing through the\npole is $$\\omega $$. An object is weighed at the equator\nand at a height h above the poles by using a\nspring balance. If the weights are found to be\nsame, then h is (h &lt;&lt; R, where R is the radius\nof the earth)\n",
    "options": [
      "$${{{R^2}{\\omega ^2}} \\over {2g}}$$",
      "$${{{R^2}{\\omega ^2}} \\over g}$$",
      "$${{{R^2}{\\omega ^2}} \\over {8g}}$$",
      "$${{{R^2}{\\omega ^2}} \\over {4g}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$${{{R^2}{\\omega ^2}} \\over {2g}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "DTg56QR7gdFJEwDrmI1klrnrxks",
    "question": "A body weights 49N on a spring balance at the north pole. What will be its weight recorded on the same weighing machine, if it is shifted to the equator?<br/><br/>[Use $$g = {{GM} \\over {{R^2}}}$$ = 9.8 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup> and radius of earth, R = 6400 km.]",
    "options": [
      "49 N",
      "49.83 N",
      "48.83 N",
      "49.17 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "48.83 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "UKrdZK6HTkDJS4Z1Kz1kmlvfe2f",
    "question": "If the angular velocity of earth's spin is increased such that the bodies at the equator start floating, the duration of the day would be approximately : [Take g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>, the radius of earth, R = 6400 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> m, Take $$\\pi$$ = 3.14]",
    "options": [
      "84 minutes",
      "1200 minutes",
      "60 minutes",
      "does not change"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "84 minutes"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw97dzk",
    "question": "Consider a planet in some solar system which has a mass double the mass of earth and density equal to the average density of earth. If the weight of an object on earth is W, the weight of the same object on that planet will be :",
    "options": [
      "2W",
      "W",
      "$${2^{{1 \\over 3}}}$$W",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 $$W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$${2^{{1 \\over 3}}}$$W"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjq4l8a",
    "question": "If R<sub>E</sub> be the radius of Earth, then the ratio between the acceleration due to gravity at a depth 'r' below and a height 'r' above the earth surface is : (Given : r &lt; R<sub>E</sub>)",
    "options": [
      "$$1 - {r \\over {{R_E}}} - {{{r^2}} \\over {R_E^2}} - {{{r^3}} \\over {R_E^3}}$$",
      "$$1 + {r \\over {{R_E}}} + {{{r^2}} \\over {R_E^2}} + {{{r^3}} \\over {R_E^3}}$$",
      "$$1 + {r \\over {{R_E}}} - {{{r^2}} \\over {R_E^2}} + {{{r^3}} \\over {R_E^3}}$$",
      "$$1 + {r \\over {{R_E}}} - {{{r^2}} \\over {R_E^2}} - {{{r^3}} \\over {R_E^3}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$$1 + {r \\over {{R_E}}} - {{{r^2}} \\over {R_E^2}} - {{{r^3}} \\over {R_E^3}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57ptkmv",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The law of gravitation holds good for any pair of bodies in the universe.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The weight of any person becomes zero when the person is at the centre of the earth.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58hk8w7",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : If we move from poles to equator, the direction of acceleration due to gravity of earth always points towards the center of earth without any variation in its magnitude.</p>\n<p>Reason R : At equator, the direction of acceleration due to the gravity is towards the center of earth.</p>\n<p>In the light of above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "A is false but R is true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5ak9ev3",
    "question": "<p>The height of any point P above the surface of earth is equal to diameter of earth. The value of acceleration due to gravity at point P will be : (Given g = acceleration due to gravity at the surface of earth).</p>",
    "options": [
      "g/2",
      "g/4",
      "g/3",
      "g/9"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "g/9"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c3sj2c",
    "question": "<p>The approximate height from the surface of earth at which the weight of the body becomes $${1 \\over 3}$$ of its weight on the surface of earth is :</p>\n<p>[Radius of earth R = 6400 km and $$\\sqrt 3 $$ = 1.732]</p>",
    "options": [
      "3840 km",
      "4685 km",
      "2133 km",
      "4267 km"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "4685 km"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w1w33h",
    "question": "<p>The radii of two planets A and B are in the ratio 2 : 3. Their densities are 3$$\\rho$$ and 5$$\\rho$$ respectively. The ratio of their acceleration due to gravity is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "9 : 4",
      "9 : 8",
      "9 : 10",
      "2 : 5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "2 : 5"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f509ec",
    "question": "<p>The length of a seconds pendulum at a height h = 2R from earth surface will be:</p>\n<p>(Given R = Radius of earth and acceleration due to gravity at the surface of earth, g = $$\\pi$$<sup>2</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${2 \\over 9}$$ m",
      "$${4 \\over 9}$$ m",
      "$${8 \\over 9}$$ m",
      "$${1 \\over 9}$$ m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 9}$$ m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f55tlh",
    "question": "<p>An object is taken to a height above the surface of earth at a distance $${5 \\over 4}$$ R from the centre of the earth. Where radius of earth, R = 6400 km. The percentage decrease in the weight of the object will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "36%",
      "50%",
      "64%",
      "25%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "36%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gmz34p",
    "question": "<p>The percentage decrease in the weight of a rocket, when taken to a height of $$32 \\mathrm{~km}$$ above the surface of earth will, be :</p>\n<p>$$($$ Radius of earth $$=6400 \\mathrm{~km})$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "1%",
      "3%",
      "4%",
      "0.5%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "1%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6m9tn6b",
    "question": "<p>If the radius of earth shrinks by $$2 \\%$$ while its mass remains same. The acceleration due to gravity on the earth's surface will approximately :</p>",
    "options": [
      "decrease by $$2 \\%$$",
      "decrease by $$4 \\%$$",
      "increase by $$2 \\%$$",
      "increase by $$4 \\%$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "increase by $$4 \\%$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnx7uwh",
    "question": "<p>For a body projected at an angle with the horizontal from the ground, choose the correct statement.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Gravitational potential energy is maximum at the highest point.",
      "The vertical component of momentum is maximum at the highest point.",
      "The horizontal component of velocity is zero at the highest point.",
      "The Kinetic Energy (K.E.) is zero at the highest point of projectile motion."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "Gravitational potential energy is maximum at the highest point."
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo6n798",
    "question": "A body weight $\\mathrm{W}$, is projected vertically upwards from earth's surface to reach a height above the earth which is equal to nine times the radius of earth. The weight of the body at that height will be :",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{W}{91}$",
      "$\\frac{\\mathrm{W}}{3}$",
      "$\\frac{\\mathrm{W}}{100}$",
      "$\\frac{\\mathrm{W}}{9}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$\\frac{\\mathrm{W}}{100}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldofuwj7",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I: Acceleration due to gravity is different at different places on the surface of earth.</p>\n<p>Statement II: Acceleration due to gravity increases as we go down below the earth's surface.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpkdljv",
    "question": "<p>At a certain depth \"d \" below surface of earth, value of acceleration due to gravity becomes four times that of its value at a height $$\\mathrm{3 R}$$ above earth surface. Where $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is Radius of earth (Take $$\\mathrm{R}=6400 \\mathrm{~km}$$ ). The depth $$\\mathrm{d}$$ is equal to</p>",
    "options": [
      "5260 km",
      "2560 km",
      "640 km",
      "4800 km"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "4800 km"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduhejk2",
    "question": "<p>Assume that the earth is a solid sphere of uniform density and a tunnel is dug along its diameter throughout the earth. It is found that when a particle is released in this tunnel, it executes a simple harmonic motion. The mass of the particle is 100 g. The time period of the motion of the particle will be (approximately)</p>\n<p>(Take g = 10 m s$$^{-2}$$ , radius of earth = 6400 km)</p>",
    "options": [
      "12 hours",
      "1 hour 24 minutes",
      "24 hours",
      "1 hour 40 minutes"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "1 hour 24 minutes"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwqz3lt",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : A pendulum clock when taken to Mount Everest becomes fast.</p>\n<p>Reason R : The value of g (acceleration due to gravity) is less at Mount Everest than its value on the surface of earth.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is not correct but R is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "A is not correct but R is correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwrlc96",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Acceleration due to earth's gravity decreases as you go 'up' or 'down' from earth's surface.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Acceleration due to earth's gravity is same at a height 'h' and depth 'd' from earth's surface, if h = d.</p>\n<p>In the light of above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorect",
      "Both Statement I and II are correct",
      "Statement I is incorrect but statement II is correct",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorect"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyd2c7x",
    "question": "<p>The weight of a body at the surface of earth is 18 N. The weight of the body at an altitude of 3200 km above the earth's surface is (given, radius of earth $$\\mathrm{R_e=6400~km}$$) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "9.8 N",
      "4.9 N",
      "19.6 N",
      "8 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "8 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgozwopt",
    "question": "<p>Two planets A and B of radii $$\\mathrm{R}$$ and 1.5 R have densities $$\\rho$$ and $$\\rho / 2$$ respectively. The ratio of acceleration due to gravity at the surface of $$\\mathrm{B}$$ to $$\\mathrm{A}$$ is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 : 1",
      "2 : 3",
      "4 : 3",
      "3 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "3 : 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguxhmvl",
    "question": "<p>The radii of two planets 'A' and 'B' are 'R' and '4R' and their densities are $$\\rho$$ and $$\\rho / 3$$ respectively. The ratio of acceleration due to gravity at their surfaces $$\\left(g_{A}: g_{B}\\right)$$ will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 : 16",
      "4 : 3",
      "1 : 16",
      "3 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "3 : 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvrxzo1",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Rotation of the earth shows effect on the value of acceleration due to gravity (g)</p>\n<p>Statement II : The effect of rotation of the earth on the value of 'g' at the equator is minimum and that at the pole is maximum.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyfbw5p",
    "question": "<p>Assuming the earth to be a sphere of uniform mass density, the weight of a body at a depth $$d=\\frac{R}{2}$$ from the surface of earth, if its weight on the surface of earth is 200 N, will be:</p>\n<p>(Given R = radius of earth)</p>",
    "options": [
      "100 N",
      "400 N",
      "300 N",
      "500 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "100 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqka47",
    "question": "<p>The acceleration due to gravity at height $$h$$ above the earth if $$h &lt;&lt; \\mathrm{R}$$ (Radius of earth) is given by</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$g^{\\prime}=g\\left(1-\\frac{2 h}{R}\\right)$$",
      "$$g^{\\prime}=g\\left(1-\\frac{2 h^{2}}{R^{2}}\\right)$$",
      "$$g^{\\prime}=g\\left(1-\\frac{h^{2}}{2 R^{2}}\\right)$$",
      "$$g^{\\prime}=g\\left(1-\\frac{h}{2 R}\\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$$g^{\\prime}=g\\left(1-\\frac{2 h}{R}\\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh02a7gd",
    "question": "<p>The weight of a body on the earth is $$400 \\mathrm{~N}$$. Then weight of the body when taken to a depth half of the radius of the earth will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "300 N",
      "200 N",
      "100 N",
      "Zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "200 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh30sxby",
    "question": "<p>The weight of a body on the surface of the earth is $$100 \\mathrm{~N}$$. The gravitational force on it when taken at a height, from the surface of earth, equal to one-fourth the radius of the earth is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "50 N",
      "64 N",
      "25 N",
      "100 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "64 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbkkgb5",
    "question": "If $\\mathrm{R}$ is the radius of the earth and the acceleration due to gravity on the surface of earth is $g=\\pi^2 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$, then the length of the second's pendulum at a height $\\mathrm{h}=2 R$ from the surface of earth will be, :",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{1}{9} \\mathrm{~m}$",
      "$\\frac{8}{9} \\mathrm{~m}$",
      "$\\frac{2}{9} \\mathrm{~m}$",
      "$\\frac{4}{9} \\mathrm{~m}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$\\frac{1}{9} \\mathrm{~m}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc33oqz",
    "question": "<p>The acceleration due to gravity on the surface of earth is $$\\mathrm{g}$$. If the diameter of earth reduces to half of its original value and mass remains constant, then acceleration due to gravity on the surface of earth would be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "g/4",
      "2g",
      "g/2",
      "4g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "4g"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1734z",
    "question": "<p>At what distance above and below the surface of the earth a body will have same weight. (take radius of earth as $$R$$.)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{3} R-R}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{R}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{5} R-R}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{5} R-R$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{5} R-R}{2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erys9",
    "question": "<p>A $$90 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ body placed at $$2 \\mathrm{R}$$ distance from surface of earth experiences gravitational pull of :</p>\n<p>($$\\mathrm{R}=$$ Radius of earth, $$\\mathrm{g}=10 \\mathrm{~m} \\mathrm{~s}^{-2}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "300 N",
      "225 N",
      "100 N",
      "120 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "100 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29ej7",
    "question": "<p>Assuming the earth to be a sphere of uniform mass density, a body weighed $$300 \\mathrm{~N}$$ on the surface of earth. How much it would weigh at R/4 depth under surface of earth ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "75 N",
      "375 N",
      "300 N",
      "225 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "acceleration-due-to-gravity-and-its-variation",
    "solution": "225 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "FDLqTQutEYbfE6Rf",
    "question": "The escape velocity of a body depends upon mass as ",
    "options": [
      "$${m^0}$$ ",
      "$${m^1}$$ ",
      "$${m^2}$$ ",
      "$${m^3}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$${m^0}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "w3I1CXletGh0mbjL",
    "question": "The kinetic energy needed to project a body of mass $$m$$ from the earth surface (radius $$R$$) to infinity is ",
    "options": [
      "$$mgR/2$$ ",
      "$$2mgR$$ ",
      "$$mgR$$ ",
      "$$mgR/4$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$mgR$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ZgE0IquZtHg5OwIe",
    "question": "The escape velocity for a body projected vertically upwards from the surface of earth is $$11$$ $$km/s.$$ If the body is projected at an angle of $${45^ \\circ }$$  with the vertical, the escape velocity will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$11\\sqrt 2 \\,\\,km/s$$ ",
      "$$22$$ $$km/s$$ ",
      "$$11$$ $$km/s$$ ",
      "$${{11} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}km/s$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$11$$ $$km/s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "xEphVcFhVVV7FQnG",
    "question": "Suppose the gravitational force varies inversely as the n<sup>th</sup> power of distance. Then the time period of a planet in circular orbit of radius $$R$$ around the sun will be proportional to ",
    "options": [
      "$${R^n}$$ ",
      "$${R^{\\left( {{{n - 1} \\over 2}} \\right)}}$$ ",
      "$${R^{\\left( {{{n + 1} \\over 2}} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${R^{\\left( {{{n - 2} \\over 2}} \\right)}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$${R^{\\left( {{{n + 1} \\over 2}} \\right)}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "RjMWoBxj4sK6AiG6",
    "question": "A planet in a distant solar system is $$10$$ times more massive than the earth and its radius is $$10$$ times smaller. Given that the escape velocity from the earth is $$11\\,\\,km\\,{s^{ - 1}},$$  the escape velocity from the surface of the planet would be ",
    "options": [
      "$$1.1\\,\\,km\\,{s^{ - 1}}$$ ",
      "$$100\\,\\,km\\,{s^{ - 1}}$$ ",
      "$$110\\,\\,km\\,{s^{ - 1}}$$ ",
      "$$0.11\\,\\,km\\,{s^{ - 1}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$110\\,\\,km\\,{s^{ - 1}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "HRdYbt32HlVxvYeW",
    "question": "The mass of a spaceship is $$1000$$ $$kg.$$ It is to be launched from the earth's surface out into free space. The value of $$g$$ and $$R$$ (radius of earth ) are $$10\\,m/{s^2}$$ and $$6400$$ $$km$$ respectively. The required energy for this work will be:",
    "options": [
      "$$6.4 \\times {10^{11}}\\,$$ Joules",
      "$$6.4 \\times {10^8}\\,$$ Joules ",
      "$$6.4 \\times {10^9}\\,$$ Joules ",
      "$$6.4 \\times {10^{10}}\\,$$ Joules"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$6.4 \\times {10^{10}}\\,$$ Joules"
  },
  {
    "id": "6Ot3CDBrI7pZoxru",
    "question": "What is the minimum energy required to launch a satellite of mass $$m$$ from the surface of a planet of mass $$M$$ and radius $$R$$ in a circular orbit at an altitude of $$2R$$? ",
    "options": [
      "$${{5GmM} \\over {6R}}$$ ",
      "$${{2GmM} \\over {3R}}$$ ",
      "$${{GmM} \\over {2R}}$$ ",
      "$${{GmM} \\over {3R}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$${{5GmM} \\over {6R}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Dy8gMv06swuzNAoE",
    "question": "A satellite is revolving in a circular orbit at a height $$'h'$$ from the earth's surface (radius of  earth $$R;h &lt;  &lt; R$$). The minimum increase in its orbital velocity required, so that the satellite could escape from the earth's gravitational field, is close to : (Neglect the effect of atmosphere.) ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{2 g R}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{g R}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{g R / 2}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{g R}(\\sqrt{2}-1)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{g R}(\\sqrt{2}-1)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "nHZUU19s7VE7hQMCgSDac",
    "question": "A test particle is moving in a circular orbit in\nthe gravitational field produced by a mass\ndensity $$\\rho (r) = {K \\over {{r^2}}}$$  . Identify the correct relation\nbetween the radius R of the particle's orbit and\nits period T",
    "options": [
      "T<sup>2</sup>/R<sup>3</sup> is a constant",
      "TR is a constant",
      "T/R<sup>2</sup> is a constant",
      "T/R is a constant"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "T/R is a constant"
  },
  {
    "id": "i78V2HeDkRD8DPxXHN4Cx",
    "question": "A rocket has to be launched from earth in such\na way that it never returns. If E is the minimum\nenergy delivered by the rocket launcher, what\nshould be the minimum energy that the\nlauncher should have if the same rocket is to\nbe launched from the surface of the moon ?\nAssume that the density of the earth and the\nmoon are equal and that the earth's volume is\n64 times the volume of the moon :-",
    "options": [
      "E/32",
      "E/16",
      "E/4",
      "E/64"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "E/16"
  },
  {
    "id": "TnF55Ef2X7TMdSZf9id5Q",
    "question": "Two satellites, A and B, have masses m and 2m respectively. A is in a circular orbit of radius R, and B is in a circular orbit of radius 2R around the earth. The ratio of their kinetic energies, T<sub>A</sub>/T<sub>B</sub>, is ;\n",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "$${{1 \\over 2}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{1 \\over 2}} $$",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "ryG1T8AvwxBtSwbdbFL25",
    "question": "A satellite of mass M is in a circular orbit of radius R about the centre of the earth. A meteorite of the same mass, falling towards the earth, collides with the satellite completely inelastically. The speeds of the satellite and the meteorite are the same, just before the collision. The subsequent motion of the combined body will be : ",
    "options": [
      "in the same circular orbit of radius R",
      "such that it escapes to infinity",
      "in a circular orbit of a different radius ",
      "in an elliptical orbit"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "in an elliptical orbit"
  },
  {
    "id": "JElfsLqhtqVj9cMxPNpU8",
    "question": "Two stars of masses 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>31</sup> kg each, and at distance 2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>11</sup> m rotate in a plane about their common centre of mass O. A meteorite passes through O moving perpendicular to the star’s rotation plane. In order to escape from the gravitational field of this double star, the minimum speed that meteorite should have at O is - (Take Gravitational constant; G = 6.67 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–11</sup> Nm<sup>2</sup> kg<sup>–2</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "2.4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> m/s",
      "1.4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup> m/s",
      "3.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> m/s",
      "2.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup> m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "2.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup> m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "G15zlAfrVxIHPFMW1E6DQ",
    "question": "A satellite is moving with a constant speed v in circular orbit around the earth. An object of mass ‘m’ is ejected from the satellite such that it just escapes from the gravitational pull of the earth. At the time of ejection, the kinetic energy of the object is -\n",
    "options": [
      "mv<sup>2</sup>",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$ mv<sup>2</sup>",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$ mv<sup>2</sup>",
      "2 mv<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "mv<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "joGNcYCzUBeyp3MYtJaGG",
    "question": "The energy required to take a satellite to a height 'h' above Earth surface (radius of Earth = 6.4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup> km) is E<sub>1</sub> and kinetic energy required for the satellite to be in a circular orbit at this height is E<sub>2</sub>. The value of h for which E<sub>1</sub> and E<sub>2</sub> are equal, is ",
    "options": [
      "1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup> km",
      "3.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup> km",
      "6.4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup> km",
      "1.28 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> km"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "3.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup> km"
  },
  {
    "id": "zgvITvPSQFNCof3MzzwaR",
    "question": "A satellite is revolving in a circular orbit at a height h form the earth surface, such that h &lt; &lt; R where R is the earth. Assuming that the effect of earth's atmosphere can be neglected the minimum increase in the speed required so that the satellite could escape from the gravitational field of earth is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {gR} \\left( {\\sqrt 2  - 1} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {2gR} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {gR} $$",
      "$${{\\sqrt {gR} } \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {gR} \\left( {\\sqrt 2  - 1} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jMy0gsVS8L9Ul6e15Zjgy2xukf16efbg",
    "question": "A satellite is moving in a low nearly circular orbit around the earth. Its radius is roughly equal to\nthat of the earth’s radius R<sub>e</sub>\n. By firing rockets attached to it, its speed is instantaneously increased\nin the direction of its motion so that it become $$\\sqrt {{3 \\over 2}} $$\n times larger. Due to this the farthest distance\nfrom the centre of the earth that the satellite reaches is R. Value of R is :",
    "options": [
      "2R<sub>e</sub>",
      "3R<sub>e</sub>",
      "4R<sub>e</sub>",
      "2.5R<sub>e</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "3R<sub>e</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "VHcy9CkWpZG6nMnj4Ajgy2xukfak8dx2",
    "question": "A body is moving in a low circular orbit about a planet of mass M and radius R. The radius of the\norbit can be taken to be R itself. Then the ratio of the speed of this body in the orbit to the escape\nvelocity from the planet is:\n",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "1",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1o6C7Qu4KDyhQmZQQ6jgy2xukev1eaty",
    "question": "The mass density of a spherical galaxy varies\nas\n$${K \\over r}$$ over a large distance ‘r’ from its centre.\nIn that region, a small star is in a circular orbit\nof radius R. Then the period of revolution, T\ndepends on R as :",
    "options": [
      "T<sup>2</sup> $$ \\propto $$ R",
      "T<sup>2</sup> $$ \\propto $$ R<sup>3</sup>",
      "T $$ \\propto $$ R",
      "T<sup>2</sup> $$ \\propto $$ $${1 \\over {{R^3}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "T<sup>2</sup> $$ \\propto $$ R"
  },
  {
    "id": "97LU0e1lqmdn5gpKEK7k9k2k5lc1lci",
    "question": "Planet A has mass M and radius R. Planet B has\nhalf the mass and half the radius of Planet A.\nIf the escape velocities from the Planets A and\nB are v<sub>A</sub> and v<sub>B</sub>, respectively, then $${{{v_A}} \\over {{v_B}}} = {n \\over 4}$$.\nThe value of n is :",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "2",
      "4",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "xmTRopIk2GtOx1TuFB7k9k2k5dlt5p2",
    "question": "A satellite of mass m is launched vertically upwards with an initial speed u from the surface of the earth. After it reaches height R (R = radius of the earth), it ejects a rocket\nof mass $${m \\over {10}}$$\nso that subsequently the\nsatellite moves in a circular orbit. The kinetic energy of the rocket is (G is the gravitational constant; M is the mass of the earth) :\n",
    "options": [
      "$${{3m} \\over 8}{\\left( {u + \\sqrt {{{5GM} \\over {6R}}} } \\right)^2}$$",
      "$${m \\over {20}}\\left( {{u^2} + {{113} \\over {100}}{{GM} \\over R}} \\right)$$",
      "$$5m\\left( {{u^2} - {{119} \\over {100}}{{GM} \\over R}} \\right)$$",
      "$${m \\over {20}}{\\left( {u - \\sqrt {{{2GM} \\over {3R}}} } \\right)^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$5m\\left( {{u^2} - {{119} \\over {100}}{{GM} \\over R}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "g68HbDE7a392OSDPNS1klrhqm80",
    "question": "Consider two satellites S<sub>1</sub> and S<sub>2</sub> with periods of revolution 1 hr. and 8 hr. respectively revolving around a planet in circular orbits. The ratio of angular velocity of satellite S<sub>1</sub> to the angular velocity of satellite S<sub>2</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "1 : 4",
      "8 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "8 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "srbuItQplQGedf4awm1klrypxi3",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.<br/><br/>Assertion A : The escape velocities of planet A and B are same. But A and B are of unequal mass.<br/><br/>Reason R : The product of their mass and radius must be same. M<sub>1</sub>R<sub>1</sub> = M<sub>2</sub>R<sub>2</sub><br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "A is not correct but R is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "A is correct but R is not correct"
  },
  {
    "id": "56WBuMrdtHRvDxZhIW1kmkbsz5z",
    "question": "A geostationary satellite is orbiting around an arbitrary planet 'P' at a height of 11R above the surface of 'P', R being the radius of 'P'. The time period of another satellite in hours at a height of 2R from the surface of 'P' is _________. 'P' has the time period of 24 hours.",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "5",
      "$$6\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$${6 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqauf83",
    "question": "A satellite is launched into a circular orbit of radius R around earth, while a second satellite is launched into a circular orbit of radius 1.02 R. The percentage difference in the time periods of the two satellites is : ",
    "options": [
      "1.5",
      "2.0",
      "0.7",
      "3.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "3.0"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks198ixv",
    "question": "The planet Mars has two moons, if one of them has a period 7 hours, 30 minutes and an orbital radius of 9.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> km. Find the mass of Mars.<br/><br/>$$\\left\\{ {Given\\,{{4{\\pi ^2}} \\over G} = 6 \\times {{10}^{11}}{N^{ - 1}}{m^{ - 2}}k{g^2}} \\right\\}$$",
    "options": [
      "5.96 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>19</sup> kg",
      "3.25 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>21</sup> kg",
      "7.02 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>25</sup> kg",
      "6.00 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>23</sup> kg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "6.00 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>23</sup> kg"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth3u9z1",
    "question": "The masses and radii of the earth and moon are (M<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>1</sub>) and (M<sub>2</sub>, R<sub>2</sub>) respectively. Their centres are at a distance 'r' apart. Find the minimum escape velocity for a particle of mass 'm' to be projected from the middle of these two masses :",
    "options": [
      "$$V = {1 \\over 2}\\sqrt {{{4G({M_1} + {M_2})} \\over r}} $$",
      "$$V = \\sqrt {{{4G({M_1} + {M_2})} \\over r}} $$",
      "$$V = {1 \\over 2}\\sqrt {{{2G({M_1} + {M_2})} \\over r}} $$",
      "$$V = {{\\sqrt {2G} ({M_1} + {M_2})} \\over r}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$V = \\sqrt {{{4G({M_1} + {M_2})} \\over r}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l547jjt6",
    "question": "<p>The escape velocity of a body on a planet 'A' is 12 kms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. The escape velocity of the body on another planet 'B', whose density is four times and radius is half of the planet 'A', is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "12 kms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "24 kms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "36 kms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "6 kms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "12 kms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i0smpt",
    "question": "<p>A body is projected vertically upwards from the surface of earth with a velocity equal to one third of escape velocity. The maximum height attained by the body will be :</p>\n<p>(Take radius of earth $$=6400 \\mathrm{~km}$$ and $$\\mathrm{g}=10 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "800 km",
      "1600 km",
      "2133 km",
      "4800 km"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "800 km"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jh7ku0",
    "question": "<p>Two satellites $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$, having masses in the ratio $$4: 3$$, are revolving in circular orbits of radii $$3 \\mathrm{r}$$ and $$4 \\mathrm{r}$$ respectively around the earth. The ratio of total mechanical energy of $$\\mathrm{A}$$ to $$\\mathrm{B}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "9 : 16",
      "16 : 9",
      "1 : 1",
      "4 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "16 : 9"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kmozat",
    "question": "<p>A body of mass $$\\mathrm{m}$$ is projected with velocity $$\\lambda \\,v_{\\mathrm{e}}$$ in vertically upward direction from the surface of the earth into space. It is given that $$v_{\\mathrm{e}}$$ is escape velocity and $$\\lambda&lt;1$$. If air resistance is considered to be negligible, then the maximum height from the centre of earth, to which the body can go, will be :</p>\n<p>(R : radius of earth)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{R}}{1+\\lambda^{2}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{R}{1-\\lambda^{2}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{R}{1-\\lambda}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\lambda^{2} \\mathrm{R}}{1-\\lambda^{2}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{R}{1-\\lambda^{2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnw3vyn",
    "question": "<p>The escape velocities of two planets $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$ are in the ratio $$1: 2$$. If the ratio of their radii respectively is $$1: 3$$, then the ratio of acceleration due to gravity of planet A to the acceleration of gravity of planet B will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{4}{3}$$",
      "$$\\frac{2}{3}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{3}{4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldoff4pr",
    "question": "<p>If earth has a mass nine times and radius twice to that of a planet P. Then $$\\frac{v_{e}}{3} \\sqrt{x} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ will be the minimum velocity required by a rocket to pull out of gravitational force of $$\\mathrm{P}$$, where $$v_{e}$$ is escape velocity on earth. The value of $$x$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "3",
      "2",
      "18"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgoyfzdm",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : For a planet, if the ratio of mass of the planet to its radius increases, the escape velocity from the planet also increases.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Escape velocity is independent of the radius of the planet.</p>\n<p>In the light of above statements, choose the most appropriate answer form the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct",
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but statement II is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq1c0ah",
    "question": "<p>A planet having mass $$9 \\mathrm{Me}$$ and radius $$4 \\mathrm{R}_{\\mathrm{e}}$$, where $$\\mathrm{Me}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Re}$$ are mass and radius of earth respectively, has escape velocity in $$\\mathrm{km} / \\mathrm{s}$$ given by:</p>\n<p>(Given escape velocity on earth $$\\mathrm{V}_{\\mathrm{e}}=11.2 \\times 10^{3} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "33.6",
      "11.2",
      "16.8",
      "67.2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "16.8"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrhjnmi",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of escape velocity of a planet to the escape velocity of earth will be:-</p>\n<p>Given: Mass of the planet is 16 times mass of earth and radius of the planet is 4 times the radius of earth.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: 4$$",
      "$$1: \\sqrt{2}$$",
      "$$4: 1$$",
      "$$2: 1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$2: 1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrhl0d6",
    "question": "<p>Two satellites $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$ move round the earth in the same orbit. The mass of $$\\mathrm{A}$$ is twice the mass of $$\\mathrm{B}$$. The quantity which is same for the two satellites will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "Potential energy",
      " Kinetic energy",
      "Total energy",
      "Speed"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "Speed"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsx75tb",
    "question": "<p>A space ship of mass $$2 \\times 10^{4} \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is launched into a circular orbit close to the earth surface. The additional velocity to be imparted to the space ship in the orbit to overcome the gravitational pull will be (if $$g=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$ and radius of earth $$=6400 \\mathrm{~km}$$ ):</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$7.9(\\sqrt{2}-1) \\mathrm{km} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$11.2(\\sqrt{2}-1) \\mathrm{km} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$7.4(\\sqrt{2}-1) \\mathrm{km} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$8(\\sqrt{2}-1) \\mathrm{km} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$8(\\sqrt{2}-1) \\mathrm{km} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvrp2gw",
    "question": "<p>The time period of a satellite, revolving above earth's surface at a height equal to $$\\mathrm{R}$$ will be</p>\n<p>(Given $$g=\\pi^{2} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}, \\mathrm{R}=$$ radius of earth)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{32 R}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{4 \\mathrm{R}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{8 R}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{2 R}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{32 R}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyewnv9",
    "question": "<p>Two satellites of masses m and 3m revolve around the earth in circular orbits of radii r &amp; 3r respectively. The ratio of orbital speeds of the satellites respectively is</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 : 1",
      "$$\\sqrt3$$ : 1",
      "1 : 1",
      "9 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt3$$ : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqs0ch",
    "question": "<p>The orbital angular momentum of a satellite is L, when it is revolving in a circular orbit at height h from earth surface. If the distance of satellite from the earth centre is increased by eight times to its initial value, then the new angular momentum will be -</p>",
    "options": [
      "9L",
      "8L",
      "4L",
      "3L"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "3L"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh00x86h",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I: If $$\\mathrm{E}$$ be the total energy of a satellite moving around the earth, then its potential energy will be $$\\frac{E}{2}$$.</p>\n<p>Statement II: The kinetic energy of a satellite revolving in an orbit is equal to the half the magnitude of total energy $$\\mathrm{E}$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh24ku0k",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Earth has atmosphere whereas moon doesn't have any atmosphere.</p>\n<p>Reason R : The escape velocity on moon is very small as compared to that on earth.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is true",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh30uw1f",
    "question": "<p>Choose the incorrect statement from the following:</p>",
    "options": [
      "The linear speed of a planet revolving around the sun remains constant.",
      "When a body falls towards earth, the displacement of earth towards the body is negligible.",
      "The speed of satellite in a given circular orbit remains constant.",
      "For a planet revolving around the sun in an elliptical orbit, the total energy of the planet remains constant."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "The linear speed of a planet revolving around the sun remains constant."
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscp51wv",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : The angular speed of the moon in its orbit about the earth is more than the angular speed of the earth in its orbit about the sun.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : The moon takes less time to move around the earth than the time taken by the earth to move around the sun.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is correct but (R) is not correct",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is not correct but (R) is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd83bit",
    "question": "<p>The mass of the moon is $$\\frac{1}{144}$$ times the mass of a planet and its diameter is $$\\frac{1}{16}$$ times the diameter of a planet. If the escape velocity on the planet is $$v$$, the escape velocity on the moon will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{v}}{4}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{v}}{6}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{V}}{12}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{v}}{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{v}}{3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg6odx4",
    "question": "<p>Escape velocity of a body from earth is $$11.2 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{s}$$. If the radius of a planet be onethird the radius of earth and mass be one-sixth that of earth, the escape velocity from the planet is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "7.9 km/s",
      "8.4 km/s",
      "4.2 km/s",
      "11.2 km/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "7.9 km/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxweb2z",
    "question": "<p>A satellite of $$10^3 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ mass is revolving in circular orbit of radius $$2 R$$. If $$\\frac{10^4 R}{6} \\mathrm{~J}$$ energy is supplied to the satellite, it would revolve in a new circular orbit of radius</p>\n<p>(use $$g=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2, R=$$ radius of earth)</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 R",
      "6 R",
      "2.5 R",
      "3 R"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "6 R"
  },
  {
    "id": "luz2u3w3",
    "question": "<p>An astronaut takes a ball of mass $$m$$ from earth to space. He throws the ball into a circular orbit about earth at an altitude of $$318.5 \\mathrm{~km}$$. From earth's surface to the orbit, the change in total mechanical energy of the ball is $$x \\frac{\\mathrm{GM}_{\\mathrm{e}} \\mathrm{m}}{21 \\mathrm{R}_{\\mathrm{e}}}$$. The value of $$x$$ is (take $$\\mathrm{R}_{\\mathrm{e}}=6370 \\mathrm{~km})$$ :</p>",
    "options": [
      "12",
      "11",
      "9",
      "10"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "11"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2er9jv",
    "question": "<p>Correct formula for height of a satellite from earths surface is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left(\\frac{T^2 R^2 g}{4 \\pi^2}\\right)^{1 / 3}-R$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{T^2 R^2 g}{4 \\pi}\\right)^{1 / 2}-R$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{T^2 R^2 g}{4 \\pi^2}\\right)^{-1 / 3}+R$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{T^2 R^2}{4 \\pi^2 g}\\right)^{1 / 3}-R$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$\\left(\\frac{T^2 R^2 g}{4 \\pi^2}\\right)^{1 / 3}-R$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s213g",
    "question": "<p>A satellite revolving around a planet in stationary orbit has time period 6 hours. The mass of planet is one-fourth the mass of earth. The radius orbit of planet is :</p>\n<p>(Given $$=$$ Radius of geo-stationary orbit for earth is $$4.2 \\times 10^4 \\mathrm{~km}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1.68 \\times 10^5 \\mathrm{~km}$$\n",
      "$$1.4 \\times 10^4 \\mathrm{~km}$$\n",
      "$$8.4 \\times 10^4 \\mathrm{~km}$$\n",
      "$$1.05 \\times 10^4 \\mathrm{~km}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "escape-speed-and-motion-of-satellites",
    "solution": "$$1.05 \\times 10^4 \\mathrm{~km}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "BRlFiH6S5JAIOpYZ",
    "question": "Energy required to move a body of mass $$m$$ from an orbit of radius $$2R$$ to $$3R$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{GMm} \\over {12{R^2}}}$$",
      "$${{GMm} \\over {3{R^2}}}$$",
      "$${{GMm} \\over {8R}}$$ ",
      "$${{GMm} \\over {6R}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$${{GMm} \\over {6R}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "3doGoWyeohUWtqgf",
    "question": "If $$g$$ is the acceleration due to gravity on the earth's surface, the gain in the potential energy of an object of mass $$m$$ raised from the surface of the earth to a height equal to the radius $$R$$ of the earth is ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 4}mgR$$  ",
      "$$2mgR$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}mgR$$ ",
      "$$mgR$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}mgR$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "rNwgmKFOSSQgCzZV",
    "question": "A particle of mass $$10$$ $$g$$ is kept on the surface of a uniform sphere of mass $$100$$ $$kg$$ and radius $$10$$ $$cm.$$ Find the work to be done against the gravitational force between them to take the particle far away from the sphere (you may take $$G$$ $$ = 6.67 \\times {10^{ - 11}}\\,\\,N{m^2}/k{g^2}$$) ",
    "options": [
      "$$3.33 \\times {10^{ - 10}}\\,J$$ ",
      "$$13.34 \\times {10^{ - 10}}\\,J$$ ",
      "$$6.67 \\times {10^{ - 10}}\\,J$$ ",
      "$$6.67 \\times {10^{ - 9}}\\,J$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$$6.67 \\times {10^{ - 10}}\\,J$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "PHJa0snc3xgjrE0U",
    "question": "Two bodies of masses $$m$$ and $$4$$ $$m$$ are placed at a distance $$r.$$ The gravitational potential at a point on the line joining them where the gravitational field is zero is: ",
    "options": [
      "$$ - {{4Gm} \\over r}$$ ",
      "$$ - {{6Gm} \\over r}$$ ",
      "$$ - {{9Gm} \\over r}$$ ",
      "zero "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$$ - {{9Gm} \\over r}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "NLt4siTZCUeim2398ojgy2xukg0hqiet",
    "question": "Two planets have masses M and 16 M and their radii are $$a$$ and 2$$a$$, respectively. The separation\nbetween the centres of the planets is 10$$a$$. A body of mass m is fired from the surface of the larger\nplanet towards the smaller planet along the line joining their centres. For the body to be able to\nreach at the surface of smaller planet, the minimum firing speed needed is :",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\sqrt {{{GM} \\over a}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{G{M^2}} \\over {ma}}} $$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}\\sqrt {{{5GM} \\over a}} $$",
      "$$4\\sqrt {{{GM} \\over a}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 2}\\sqrt {{{5GM} \\over a}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsuid2y",
    "question": "A body is projected vertically upwards from the surface of earth with a velocity sufficient enough to carry it to infinity. The time taken by it to reach height h is ___________ s.",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{{2{R_e}} \\over g}} \\left[ {{{\\left( {1 + {h \\over {{R_e}}}} \\right)}^{{3 \\over 2}}} - 1} \\right]$$",
      "$${1 \\over 3}\\sqrt {{{{R_e}} \\over {2g}}} \\left[ {{{\\left( {1 + {h \\over {{R_e}}}} \\right)}^{{3 \\over 2}}} - 1} \\right]$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{R_e}} \\over {2g}}} \\left[ {{{\\left( {1 + {h \\over {{R_e}}}} \\right)}^{{3 \\over 2}}} - 1} \\right]$$",
      "$${1 \\over 3}\\sqrt {{{2{R_e}} \\over g}} \\left[ {{{\\left( {1 + {h \\over {{R_e}}}} \\right)}^{{3 \\over 2}}} - 1} \\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 3}\\sqrt {{{2{R_e}} \\over g}} \\left[ {{{\\left( {1 + {h \\over {{R_e}}}} \\right)}^{{3 \\over 2}}} - 1} \\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kta8w9bm",
    "question": "Inside a uniform spherical shell :<br/><br/>(1) the gravitational field is zero<br/><br/>(2) the gravitational potential is zero<br/><br/>(3) the gravitational field is same everywhere<br/><br/>(4) the gravitational potential is same everywhere<br/><br/>(5) all of the above<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(1), (3) and (4) only",
      "(5) only",
      "(1), (2) and (3) only",
      "(2), (3) and (4) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "(1), (3) and (4) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfm4sii",
    "question": "A mass of 50 kg is placed at the centre of a uniform spherical shell of mass 100 kg and radius 50 m. If the gravitational potential at a point, 25 m from the centre is V kg/m. The value of V is :",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$60 G",
      "+2 G",
      "$$-$$20 G",
      "$$-$$4 G"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$$-$$4 G"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55juo36",
    "question": "<p>Water falls from a 40 m high dam at the rate of 9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup> kg per hour. Fifty percentage of gravitational potential energy can be converted into electrical energy. Using this hydroelectric energy number of 100 W lamps, that can be lit, is :</p>\n<p>(Take g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "25",
      "50",
      "100",
      "18"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "50"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rh9ui9",
    "question": "<p>An object of mass $$1 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is taken to a height from the surface of earth which is equal to three times the radius of earth. The gain in potential energy of the object will be [If, $$\\mathrm{g}=10 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$ and radius of earth $$=6400 \\mathrm{~km}$$ ]</p>",
    "options": [
      "48 MJ",
      "24 MJ",
      "36 MJ",
      "12 MJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "48 MJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldquud7t",
    "question": "An object is allowed to fall from a height $R$ above the earth, where $R$ is the radius of earth. Its velocity when it strikes the earth's surface, ignoring air resistance, will be",
    "options": [
      "$\\sqrt{\\frac{g R}{2}}$",
      "$\\sqrt{g R}$",
      "$\\sqrt{2 g R}$",
      "$2 \\sqrt{g R}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$\\sqrt{g R}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr2al1l",
    "question": "<p>If the gravitational field in the space is given as $$\\left(-\\frac{K}{r^{2}}\\right)$$. Taking the reference point to be at $$\\mathrm{r}=2 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ \nwith gravitational potential $$\\mathrm{V}=10 \\mathrm{~J} / \\mathrm{kg}$$. Find the gravitational potential at $$\\mathrm{r}=3 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ in SI unit (Given, that $$\\mathrm{K}=6 \\mathrm{~Jcm} / \\mathrm{kg}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "9",
      "11",
      "10",
      "12"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "11"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtzcnjc",
    "question": "<p>A body of mass is taken from earth surface to the height h equal to twice the radius of earth (R$$_e$$), the increase in potential energy will be :</p>\n<p>(g  = acceleration due to gravity on the surface of Earth)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{2}mgR_e$$",
      "$$3~mgR_e$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{3}mgR_e$$",
      "$$\\frac{2}{3}mgR_e$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{2}{3}mgR_e$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnybh2l",
    "question": "A body is released from a height equal to the radius $(\\mathrm{R})$ of the earth. The velocity of the body when it strikes the surface of the earth will be\n<br/><br/>\n(Given $g=$ acceleration due to gravity on the earth.)",
    "options": [
      "$\\sqrt{\\frac{g R}{2}}$",
      "$\\sqrt{4 g R}$",
      "$\\sqrt{2 g R}$",
      "$\\sqrt{g R}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$\\sqrt{g R}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsxaxnl",
    "question": "<p>If $$\\mathrm{V}$$ is the gravitational potential due to sphere of uniform density on it's surface, then it's value at the center of sphere will be:-</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{3 \\mathrm{~V}}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{V}}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{4}{3} \\mathrm{~V}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{V}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{3 \\mathrm{~V}}{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgx6elh",
    "question": "<p>The gravitational potential at a point above the surface of earth is $$-5.12 \\times 10^7 \\mathrm{~J} / \\mathrm{kg}$$ and the acceleration due to gravity at that point is $$6.4 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$$. Assume that the mean radius of earth to be $$6400 \\mathrm{~km}$$. The height of this point above the earth's surface is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1600 km",
      "1200 km",
      "540 km",
      "1000 km"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "1600 km"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v4o5n",
    "question": "<p>If $$\\mathrm{G}$$ be the gravitational constant and $$\\mathrm{u}$$ be the energy density then which of the following quantity have the dimensions as that of the $$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{uG}}$$ :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Gravitational potential\n",
      "pressure gradient per unit mass\n",
      "Energy per unit mass\n",
      "Force per unit mass"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "Force per unit mass"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3v9l",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 703px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Kinetic energy of planet</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>-\\mathrm{GMm} / \\mathrm{a}<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Gravitation Potential energy of sun-planet system</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\mathrm{GMm} / 2 \\mathrm{a}<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Total mechanical energy of planet</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\frac{\\mathrm{Gm}}{\\mathrm{r}}<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Escape energy at the surface of planet for unit mass object</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>-\\mathrm{GMm} / 2 \\mathrm{a}<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>(Where $$\\mathrm{a}=$$ radius of planet orbit, $$\\mathrm{r}=$$ radius of planet, $$\\mathrm{M}=$$ mass of Sun, $$\\mathrm{m}=$$ mass of planet)</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(III)\n",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(II), (C)-(III), (D)-(IV)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(IV), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "(A)-(II), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(III)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57pmu",
    "question": "<p>To project a body of mass $$m$$ from earth's surface to infinity, the required kinetic energy is (assume, the radius of earth is $$R_E, g=$$ acceleration due to gravity on the surface of earth):</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1 / 2 m g R_E$$\n",
      "$$4 m g R_E$$\n",
      "$$m g R_E$$\n",
      "$$2 m g R_E$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "gravitational-potential-and-gravitational-potential-energy",
    "solution": "$$m g R_E$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "6qCaJGywpVm4aQ1h",
    "question": "If suddenly the gravitational force of attraction between Earth and a satellite revolving around it becomes zero,  then the satellite will ",
    "options": [
      "continue to move in its orbit with same velocity",
      "move tangentially to the original orbit with the same velocity",
      "become stationary in its orbit",
      "move towards the earth"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "move tangentially to the original orbit with the same velocity"
  },
  {
    "id": "KtUWn2cwiqkCwKsv",
    "question": "The time period of satellite of earth is $$5$$ hours. If the separation between the earth and the satellite is increased to $$4$$ times the previous value, the new time period will become ",
    "options": [
      "$$10$$ hours ",
      "$$80$$ hours ",
      "$$40$$ hours ",
      "$$20$$ hours "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$40$$ hours "
  },
  {
    "id": "R4pcXzy0527zrAzT",
    "question": "Two spherical bodies of mass $$M$$ and $$5M$$ &amp; radii $$R$$ &amp; $$2R$$ respectively are released in free space with initial separation between their centers equal to $$12R$$. If they attract each other due to gravitational force only, then the distance covered by the smaller body just before collision is ",
    "options": [
      "$$2.5$$ $$R$$ ",
      "$$4.5$$ $$R$$  ",
      "$$7.5$$ $$R$$  ",
      "$$1.5$$ $$R$$  "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$7.5$$ $$R$$  "
  },
  {
    "id": "ZcBvISXpJculBaNl",
    "question": "The time period of an earth satellite in circular orbit is independent of ",
    "options": [
      "both the mass and radius of the orbit",
      "radius of its orbit ",
      "the mass of the satellite ",
      "neither the mass of the satellite nor the radius of its orbit "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "the mass of the satellite "
  },
  {
    "id": "fKNFrQLaoB5ALOA8",
    "question": "A satellite of mass $$m$$ revolves around the earth of radius $$R$$ at a height $$x$$ from its surface. If $$g$$ is the acceleration due to gravity on the surface of the earth, the orbital speed of the satellite is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{g{R^2}} \\over {R + x}}$$ ",
      "$${{gR} \\over {R - x}}$$ ",
      "$${gx}$$ ",
      "$${\\left( {{{g{R^2}} \\over {R + x}}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$${\\left( {{{g{R^2}} \\over {R + x}}} \\right)^{1/2}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "HX17M0EaT8QqzrLp",
    "question": "Average density of the earth ",
    "options": [
      "is a complex function of $$g$$ ",
      "does not depend on $$g$$ ",
      "is inversely proportional to $$g$$ ",
      "is directly proportional to $$g$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "is directly proportional to $$g$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "4CQFSMKw1f0zwJ0A",
    "question": "This question contains Statement - $$1$$ and Statement - $$2$$. of the four choices given after the statements, choose the one that best describes the two statements.\n<br/><br/><b>Statement - $$1$$:</b>\n<br/><br/>For a mass $$M$$ kept at the center of a cube of side $$'a'$$, the flux of gravitational field passing through its sides $$4\\,\\pi \\,GM.$$ \n<br/><br/><b>Statement - 2:</b>\n<br/><br/>If the direction of a field due to a point source is radial and its dependence on the distance $$'r'$$ from the source is given as $${1 \\over {{r^2}}},$$ its flux through a closed surface depends only on the strength of the source enclosed by the surface and not on the size or shape of the surface. ",
    "options": [
      "Statement - $$1$$ is false, Statement - $$2$$ is true",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true; Statement - $$2$$ is a correct explanation for Statement - $$1$$",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true; Statement - $$2$$ is not a correct explanation for Statement - $$1$$",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true; Statement - $$2$$ is a correct explanation for Statement - $$1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ahlnTnaPo4XNBFY8",
    "question": "Four particles, each of mass $$M$$ and equidistant from each other, move along a circle of radius $$R$$ under the action of their mutual gravitational attraction. The speed of each particle is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{{GM} \\over R}} $$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt {2\\sqrt 2 {{GM} \\over R}} $$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{GM} \\over R}\\left( {1 + 2\\sqrt 2 } \\right)} $$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}\\sqrt {{{GM} \\over R}\\left( {1 + 2\\sqrt 2 } \\right)} $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}\\sqrt {{{GM} \\over R}\\left( {1 + 2\\sqrt 2 } \\right)} $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "eyOAI1M2PavCgFN5",
    "question": "A particle is moving with a uniform speed in a circular orbit of radius R in a central force inversely\nproportional to the n<sup>th</sup> power of R. If the period of rotation of the particle is T, then :",
    "options": [
      "T $$ \\propto $$ R<sup>n/2</sup> ",
      "T $$ \\propto $$ R<sup>3/2</sup> for any n ",
      "T $$ \\propto $$ R<sup>n/2 +1</sup>",
      "T $$ \\propto $$ R<sup>(n+1)/2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "T $$ \\propto $$ R<sup>(n+1)/2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "ny8ocbFf8QMDPlOwFsttQ",
    "question": "A body of mass m is moving in a circular orbit of radius R about a planet of mass M. At some instant, it splits into two equal masses. The first mass moves in a circular orbit of radius $${R \\over 2},$$ and the other mass, in a circular orbit of radius $${3R \\over 2}$$. The difference between the final and initial total energies is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$ - {{GMm} \\over {2R}}$$ ",
      "$$ + {{GMm} \\over {6R}}$$",
      "$${{GMm} \\over {2R}}$$",
      "$$ - {{GMm} \\over {6R}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$ - {{GMm} \\over {6R}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "QIkfT9oveO52Y6u2byKfH",
    "question": "Take the mean distance of the moon and the sun from the earth to be $$0.4 \\times {10^6}$$ km and $$150 \\times {10^6}$$ km respectively. Their masses are $$8 \\times {10^{22}}$$ kg and $$2 \\times {10^{30}}$$ kg respectively. The radius of the earth is $$6400$$ km. Let $$\\Delta {F_1}$$ be the difference in the forces exerted by the moon at the nearest and farthest points on the earth and $$\\Delta {F_2}$$ be the difference in the force exerted by the sun at the nearest and farthest points on the earth. Then, the number closest to $${{\\Delta {F_1}} \\over {\\Delta {F_2}}}$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$$2$$",
      "$${10^{ - 2}}$$",
      "$$0.6$$",
      "$$6$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "aXBMAIzVxhLTr7gzAc3rsa0w2w9jx7j2kaz",
    "question": "The ratio of the weights of a body on the Earth’s surface to that on the surface of a planets is 9 : 4. The mass\nof the planet is\n$${1 \\over 9}$$\nth of that of the Earth. If 'R' is the radius of the Earth, what is the radius of the planet ?\n(Take the planets to have the same mass density)",
    "options": [
      "$${R \\over 9}$$",
      "$${R \\over 2}$$",
      "$${R \\over 3}$$",
      "$${R \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$${R \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "IjovubYYBDXwSEvtJk3rsa0w2w9jwzj35e6",
    "question": "A spaceship orbits around a planet at a height of 20 km from its surface. Assuming that only gravitational\nfield of the planet acts on the spaceship, what will be the number of complete revolutions made by the\nspaceship in 24 hours around the planet?\n<br/><br/>[Given ; Mass of planet = 8 × 10<sup>22</sup> kg, Radius of planet = 2 × 10<sup>6</sup>\n m, Gravitational constant\nG = 6.67 × 10<sup>–11</sup> Nm<sup>2</sup>\n/kg<sup>2</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "13",
      "9",
      "17",
      "11"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "11"
  },
  {
    "id": "BLvNqZnVNi2UZOuJmedUr",
    "question": "A solid sphere of mass 'M' and radius 'a' is\nsurrounded by a uniform concentric spherical\nshell of thickness 2a and mass 2M. The\ngravitational field at distance '3a' from the\ncentre will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{GM} \\over {3{a^2}}}$$",
      "$${{2GM} \\over {9{a^2}}}$$",
      "$${{GM} \\over {9{a^2}}}$$",
      "$${{2GM} \\over {3{a^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$${{GM} \\over {3{a^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "fymKG3IhXIFlVqb7wfnK1",
    "question": "A straight rod of length L extends from x = a to x = L + a. The gravitational force it exerts on a point mass 'm' at x = 0, if the mass per unit length of the rod is A + Bx<sup>2</sup> , is given by : \n",
    "options": [
      "$$Gm\\left[ {A\\left( {{1 \\over a} - {1 \\over {a + L}}} \\right) - BL} \\right]$$",
      "$$Gm\\left[ {A\\left( {{1 \\over a} - {1 \\over {a + L}}} \\right) + BL} \\right]$$",
      "$$Gm\\left[ {A\\left( {{1 \\over {a + L}} - {1 \\over a}} \\right) + BL} \\right]$$",
      "$$Gm\\left[ {A\\left( {{1 \\over {a + L}} - {1 \\over a}} \\right) - BL} \\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$Gm\\left[ {A\\left( {{1 \\over a} - {1 \\over {a + L}}} \\right) + BL} \\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "mYzxw4TiukOxKfgLep7k9k2k5i769zr",
    "question": "A body A of mass m is moving in a circular orbit\nof radius R about a planet. Another body B of\nmass\n$${m \\over 2}$$\ncollides with A with a velocity which is half $$\\left( {{{\\overrightarrow v } \\over 2}} \\right)$$ the instantaneous velocity$${\\overrightarrow v }$$\nof A.\nThe collision is completely inelastic. Then, the\ncombined body :",
    "options": [
      "starts moving in an elliptical orbit around\nthe planet.",
      "Falls vertically downwards towards the\nplanet",
      "Escapes from the Planet's Gravitational field.",
      "continues to move in a circular orbit"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "starts moving in an elliptical orbit around\nthe planet."
  },
  {
    "id": "4I8WG8eRN0d7ejkTUzjgy2xukfrnbi36",
    "question": "A satellite is in an elliptical orbit around a planet P. It is observed that the velocity of the satellite\nwhen it is farthest from the planet is 6 times less than that when it is closest to the planet. The\nratio of distances between the satellite and the planet at closest and farthest points is:",
    "options": [
      "1 : 2",
      "1 : 3",
      "1 : 6",
      "3 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "1 : 6"
  },
  {
    "id": "ikQPxx5wpz4uPOxaba1klrholsa",
    "question": "Four identical particles of equal masses 1 kg made to move along the circumference of a circle of radius 1 m under the action of their own mutual gravitational attraction. The speed of each particle will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{G \\over 2}(1 + 2\\sqrt 2 )} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{G \\over 2}(2\\sqrt 2  - 1)} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {G(1 + 2\\sqrt 2 )} $$",
      "$${1\\over2}\\sqrt {G(1 + 2\\sqrt 2 )} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$${1\\over2}\\sqrt {G(1 + 2\\sqrt 2 )} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "7JnEoGPaIoBFxShumE1klri98sn",
    "question": "Two stars of masses m and 2m at a distance d rotate about their common centre of mass in free space. The period of revolution is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\sqrt {{{{d^3}} \\over {3Gm}}} $$",
      "$$2\\pi \\sqrt {{{3Gm} \\over {{d^3}}}} $$",
      "$${1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\sqrt {{{3Gm} \\over {{d^3}}}} $$",
      "$$2\\pi \\sqrt {{{{d^3}} \\over {3Gm}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$2\\pi \\sqrt {{{{d^3}} \\over {3Gm}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "gsljhrfY7zIYTCsx3S1kltj103i",
    "question": "A planet revolving in elliptical orbit has :<br/><br/>A. a constant velocity of revolution.<br/><br/>B. has the least velocity when it is nearest to the sun.<br/><br/>C. its areal velocity is directly proportional to its velocity.<br/><br/>D. areal velocity is inversely proportional to its velocity.<br/><br/>E. to follow a trajectory such that the areal velocity is constant.<br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "D only",
      "E only",
      "C only",
      "A only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "E only"
  },
  {
    "id": "uB8v7xxObniWZRhlP31kmhonmay",
    "question": "The maximum and minimum distances of a comet from the Sun are 1.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>12</sup> m and 8.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup> m respectively. If the speed of the comet at the nearest point is 6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, the speed at the farthest point is :",
    "options": [
      "3.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> m/s",
      "6.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> m/s",
      "1.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> m/s",
      "4.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "3.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "doA9Yy306JJCrcWKTC1kmkrmejs",
    "question": "The time period of a satellite in a circular orbit of radius R is T. The period of another satellite in a circular orbit of radius 9R is :",
    "options": [
      "9 T",
      "27 T",
      "12 T",
      "3 T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "27 T"
  },
  {
    "id": "7SlPrQN46cTFTLyekk1kmlvpws3",
    "question": "The angular momentum of a planet of mass M moving around the sun in an elliptical orbit is $${\\overrightarrow L }$$. The magnitude of the areal velocity of the planet is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2L} \\over M}$$",
      "$${{L} \\over 2M}$$",
      "$${{L} \\over M}$$",
      "$${{4L} \\over M}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$${{L} \\over 2M}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqd0iy8",
    "question": "Consider a binary star system of star A and star B with masses m<sub>A</sub> and m<sub>B</sub> revolving in a circular orbit of radii r<sub>A</sub> an r<sub>B</sub>, respectively. If T<sub>A</sub> and T<sub>B</sub> are the time period of star A and star B, respectively,<br/><br/>Then :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{T_A}} \\over {{T_B}}} = {\\left( {{{{r_A}} \\over {{r_B}}}} \\right)^{{3 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${T_A} = {T_B}$$",
      "$${T_A} &gt; {T_B}$$ (if $${m_A} &gt; {m_B}$$)",
      "$${T_A} &gt; {T_B}$$ (if $${r_A} &gt; {r_B}$$)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$${T_A} = {T_B}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krumgywu",
    "question": "The minimum and maximum distances of a planet revolving around the sun are x<sub>1</sub> and x<sub>2</sub>. If the minimum speed of the planet on its trajectory is v<sub>0</sub> then its maximum speed will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{v_0}x_1^2} \\over {x_2^2}}$$",
      "$${{{v_0}x_2^2} \\over {x_1^2}}$$",
      "$${{{v_0}x_1^{}} \\over {x_2^{}}}$$",
      "$${{{v_0}x_2^{}} \\over {x_1^{}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$${{{v_0}x_2^{}} \\over {x_1^{}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks18gqcx",
    "question": "Two identical particles of mass 1 kg each go round a circle of radius R, under the action of their mutual gravitational attraction. The angular speed of each particle is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{G \\over {2{R^3}}}} $$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}\\sqrt {{G \\over {{R^3}}}} $$",
      "$${1 \\over {2R}}\\sqrt {{1 \\over G}} $$",
      "$${{2G} \\over {{R^3}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}\\sqrt {{G \\over {{R^3}}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54v1rrr",
    "question": "<p>The time period of a satellite revolving around earth in a given orbit is 7 hours. If the radius of orbit is increased to three times its previous value, then approximate new time period of the satellite will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "40 hours",
      "36 hours",
      "30 hours",
      "25 hours"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "36 hours"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55jw5xz",
    "question": "<p>Two objects of equal masses placed at certain distance from each other attracts each other with a force of F. If one-third mass of one object is transferred to the other object, then the new force will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${2 \\over 9}$$ F",
      "$${16 \\over 9}$$ F",
      "$${8 \\over 9}$$ F",
      "F"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$${8 \\over 9}$$ F"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l568yvnp",
    "question": "<p>Two planets A and B of equal mass are having their period of revolutions T<sub>A</sub> and T<sub>B</sub> such that T<sub>A</sub> = 2T<sub>B</sub>. These planets are revolving in the circular orbits of radii r<sub>A</sub> and r<sub>B</sub> respectively. Which out of the following would be the correct relationship of their orbits?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2r_A^2 = r_B^3$$",
      "$$r_A^3 = 2r_B^3$$",
      "$$r_A^3 = 4r_B^3$$",
      "$$T_A^2 - T_B^2 = {{{\\pi ^2}} \\over {GM}}\\left( {r_B^3 - 4r_A^3} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$r_A^3 = 4r_B^3$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56ued56",
    "question": "<p>The distance of the Sun from earth is 1.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>11</sup> m and its angular diameter is (2000) s when observed from the earth. The diameter of the Sun will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.45 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup> m",
      "1.45 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup> m",
      "1.45 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup> m",
      "0.14 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup> m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "1.45 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup> m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbgmzz",
    "question": "<p>The distance between Sun and Earth is R. The duration of year if the distance between Sun and Earth becomes 3R will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt 3 $$ years",
      "3 years",
      "9 years",
      "3$$\\sqrt 3 $$ years"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "3$$\\sqrt 3 $$ years"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dy2uti",
    "question": "<p>Three identical particles $$\\mathrm{A}, \\mathrm{B}$$ and $$\\mathrm{C}$$ of mass $$100 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ each are placed in a straight line with $$\\mathrm{AB}=\\mathrm{BC}=13 \\mathrm{~m}$$. The gravitational force on a fourth particle $$\\mathrm{P}$$ of the same mass is $$\\mathrm{F}$$, when placed at a distance $$13 \\mathrm{~m}$$ from the particle $$\\mathrm{B}$$ on the perpendicular bisector of the line $$\\mathrm{AC}$$. The value of $$\\mathrm{F}$$ will be approximately :</p>",
    "options": [
      "21 G",
      "100 G",
      "59 G",
      "42 G"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "100 G"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsamjxf",
    "question": "<p>The time period of a satellite of earth is 24 hours. If the separation between the earth and the satellite is decreased to one fourth of the previous value, then its new time period will become.</p>",
    "options": [
      "12 hours",
      "3 hours",
      "6 hours",
      "4 hours"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "3 hours"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsnu25e",
    "question": "<p>Two particles of equal mass '$$m$$' move in a circle of radius '$$r$$' under the action of their mutual gravitational attraction. The speed of each particle will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{G m}{4 r}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{G m}{2 r}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{G m}{r}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{4 G m}{r}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{G m}{4 r}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtyi5sp",
    "question": "<p>Every planet revolves around the sun in an elliptical orbit :-</p>\n<p>A. The force acting on a planet is inversely proportional to square of distance from sun.</p>\n<p>B. Force acting on planet is inversely proportional to product of the masses of the planet and the sun.</p>\n<p>C. The Centripetal force acting on the planet is directed away from the sun.</p>\n<p>D. The square of time period of revolution of planet around sun is directly proportional to cube of semi-major axis of elliptical orbit.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "C and D only",
      "B and C only",
      "A and D only",
      "A and C only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "A and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwrgknp",
    "question": "<p>If the distance of the earth from Sun is 1.5 $$\\times$$ 10$$^6$$ km. Then the distance of an imaginary planet from Sun, if its period of revolution is 2.83 years is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$6\\times10^6$$ km",
      "$$3\\times10^7$$ km",
      "$$6\\times10^7$$ km",
      "$$3\\times10^6$$ km"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$3\\times10^6$$ km"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgny675b",
    "question": "Two identical particles each of mass ' $m$ ' go round a circle of radius $a$ under the action of their mutual gravitational attraction. The angular speed of each particle will be :",
    "options": [
      "$\\sqrt{\\frac{G m}{2 a^{3}}}$",
      "$\\sqrt{\\frac{G m}{a^{3}}}$\n",
      "$\\sqrt{\\frac{G m}{8 a^{3}}}$",
      "$\\sqrt{\\frac{G m}{4 a^{3}}}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$\\sqrt{\\frac{G m}{4 a^{3}}}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh252xti",
    "question": "<p>A planet has double the mass of the earth. Its average density is equal to that of the earth. An object weighing $$\\mathrm{W}$$ on earth will weigh on that planet:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2^{2 / 3} \\mathrm{~W}$$",
      "W",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~W}$$",
      "$$2^{1 / 3} \\mathrm{~W}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$2^{1 / 3} \\mathrm{~W}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsamy2vh",
    "question": "A light planet is revolving around a massive star in a circular orbit of radius $\\mathrm{R}$ with a period of revolution T. If the force of attraction between planet and star is proportional to $\\mathrm{R}^{-3 / 2}$ then choose the correct option :",
    "options": [
      "$\\mathrm{T}^2 \\propto \\mathrm{R}^{7 / 2}$",
      "$\\mathrm{T}^2 \\propto \\mathrm{R}^3$",
      "$\\mathrm{T}^2 \\propto \\mathrm{R}^{5 / 2}$",
      "$\\mathrm{T}^2 \\propto \\mathrm{R}^{3 / 2}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$\\mathrm{T}^2 \\propto \\mathrm{R}^{5 / 2}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse61sz2",
    "question": "<p>Four identical particles of mass $$m$$ are kept at the four corners of a square. If the gravitational force exerted on one of the masses by the other masses is $$\\left(\\frac{2 \\sqrt{2}+1}{32}\\right) \\frac{\\mathrm{Gm}^2}{L^2}$$, the length of the sides of the square is</p>",
    "options": [
      "4L",
      "3L",
      "2L",
      "$$\\frac{L}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "4L"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsflq7rh",
    "question": "<p>A planet takes 200 days to complete one revolution around the Sun. If the distance of the planet from Sun is reduced to one fourth of the original distance, how many days will it take to complete one revolution :</p>",
    "options": [
      "20",
      "50",
      "100",
      "25"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "25"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxkbr",
    "question": "<p>A metal wire of uniform mass density having length $$L$$ and mass $$M$$ is bent to form a semicircular arc and a particle of mass $$\\mathrm{m}$$ is placed at the centre of the arc. The gravitational force on the particle by the wire is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{GmM} \\pi^2}{\\mathrm{~L}^2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{GMm} \\pi}{2 \\mathrm{~L}^2}$$\n",
      "0",
      "$$\\frac{2 \\mathrm{GmM} \\pi}{\\mathrm{L}^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{2 \\mathrm{GmM} \\pi}{\\mathrm{L}^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3vefj4",
    "question": "<p>Two satellite A and B go round a planet in circular orbits having radii 4R and R respectively. If the speed of $$\\mathrm{A}$$ is $$3 v$$, the speed of $$\\mathrm{B}$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$6 v$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{4}{3} v$$\n",
      "$$3 v$$\n",
      "$$12 v$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$6 v$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gse0c",
    "question": "<p>Two planets $$A$$ and $$B$$ having masses $$m_1$$ and $$m_2$$ move around the sun in circular orbits of $$r_1$$ and $$r_2$$ radii respectively. If angular momentum of $$A$$ is $$L$$ and that of $$B$$ is $$3 \\mathrm{~L}$$, the ratio of time period $$\\left(\\frac{T_A}{T_B}\\right)$$ is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left(\\frac{r_2}{r_1}\\right)^{\\frac{3}{2}}$$\n",
      "$$27\\left(\\frac{m_1}{m_2}\\right)^3$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{r_1}{r_2}\\right)^3$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{27}\\left(\\frac{m_2}{m_1}\\right)^3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "gravitation",
    "topic": "kepler's-law-and-universal-law-of-gravitation",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{27}\\left(\\frac{m_2}{m_1}\\right)^3$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "itoaTCzLm3bOEG1V",
    "question": "One $$kg$$ of a diatomic gas is at a pressure of $$8 \\times {10^4}\\,N/{m^2}.$$ The density of the gas is $$4kg/{m^3}$$. What is the energy of the gas due to its thermal motion ? ",
    "options": [
      "$$5 \\times {10^4}\\,J$$ ",
      "$$6 \\times {10^4}\\,J$$ ",
      "$$7 \\times {10^4}\\,J$$ ",
      "$$3 \\times {10^4}\\,J$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$$5 \\times {10^4}\\,J$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "cvb8OhdJxDNYfqIV",
    "question": "Three perfect gases at absolute temperatures $${T_1},\\,{T_2}$$ and $${T_3}$$ are mixed. The masses of molecules are $${m_1},{m_2}$$ and $${m_3}$$ and the number of molecules are $${n_1},$$ $${n_2}$$ and $${n_3}$$ respectively. Assuming no loss of energy, the final temperature of the mixture is: ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{n_1}{T_1} + {n_2}{T_2} + {n_3}{T_3}} \\over {{n_1} + {n_2} + {n_3}}}$$ ",
      "$${{{n_1}T_1^2 + {n_2}T_2^2 + {n_3}T_3^2} \\over {{n_1}{T_1} + {n_2}{T_2} + {n_3}{T_3}}}$$ ",
      "$${{n_1^2T_1^2 + n_2^2T_2^2 + n_3^2T_3^2} \\over {{n_1}{T_1} + {n_2}{T_2} + {n_3}{T_3}}}$$ ",
      "$${{\\left( {{T_1} + {T_2} + {T_3}} \\right)} \\over 3}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$${{{n_1}{T_1} + {n_2}{T_2} + {n_3}{T_3}} \\over {{n_1} + {n_2} + {n_3}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "FDAMkN5fSAaDcX32dcjFi",
    "question": "An ideal gas has molecules with 5 degrees of freedom. The ratio of specific heats at constant pressure (C<sub>p</sub> ) and at constant volume (C<sub>v</sub>) is :\n",
    "options": [
      "6",
      "$${7 \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$${5 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${7 \\over 5}$$  "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$${7 \\over 5}$$  "
  },
  {
    "id": "PGKTmHvWIYIXR6qqsZIsg",
    "question": "Two moles of helium are mixed with n moles of hydrogen. If  $${{Cp} \\over {Cv}} = {3 \\over 2}$$ for the mixture, then the value of n is : ",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "3",
      "2",
      "3 / 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "0Hs2slbFMnthp8c8bAjFf",
    "question": "A gas mixture consists of 3 moles of oxygen and 5 moles of argon at temperature T. considering only translational and rotational modes, the total internal energy of the system is :",
    "options": [
      "12 RT",
      "20 RT",
      "4 RT",
      "15 RT"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "15 RT"
  },
  {
    "id": "OPkaZS430TtlRW6nulQ2f",
    "question": "An ideal gas occupies a volume of 2m<sup>3</sup>  at a pressure of 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup> Pa. The energy of the gas is : ",
    "options": [
      "6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> J",
      "9$$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup> J",
      "3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>2</sup> J",
      "10<sup>8</sup> J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "9$$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup> J"
  },
  {
    "id": "9nf3gTTSQl39QuM4a0yuj",
    "question": "An HCl molecule has rotational, translational\nand vibrational motions. If the rms velocity of\nHCl molecules in its gaseous phase is $$\\overline v $$ , m is\nits mass and k<sub>B</sub> is Boltzmann constant, then its\ntemperature will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{m{{\\overline v }^2}} \\over {5{k_B}}}$$",
      "$${{m{{\\overline v }^2}} \\over {6{k_B}}}$$",
      "$${{m{{\\overline v }^2}} \\over {7{k_B}}}$$",
      "$${{m{{\\overline v }^2}} \\over {3{k_B}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$${{m{{\\overline v }^2}} \\over {7{k_B}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "9QIfFyuj1Z8TR45aMEH0d",
    "question": "The specific heats, C<sub>P</sub> and C<sub>V </sub> of a gas of\ndiatomic molecules, A, are given (in units of\nJ mol<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>) by 29 and 22, respectively.\nAnother gas of diatomic molecules, B, has the\ncorresponding values 30 and 21. If they are\ntreated as ideal gases, then :-",
    "options": [
      "A is rigid but B has a vibrational mode",
      "A has a vibrational mode but B has none",
      "A has one vibrational mode and B has two",
      "Both A and B have a vibrational mode each"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "A has a vibrational mode but B has none"
  },
  {
    "id": "RDmQjrHwITVPSW674bjgy2xukf3uj5cb",
    "question": "To raise the temperature of a certain mass of gas by 50<sup>o</sup>C at a constant pressure, 160 calories of\nheat is required. When the same mass of gas is cooled by 100<sup>o</sup>C at constant volume, 240 calories\nof heat is released. How many degrees of freedom does each molecule of this gas have (assume\ngas to be ideal)?",
    "options": [
      "6",
      "7",
      "5",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "6"
  },
  {
    "id": "jafpTQWd84pVQfYxiyjgy2xukfrp43ac",
    "question": "Molecules of an ideal gas are known to have three translational degrees of freedom and two\nrotational degrees of freedom.The gas is maintained at a temperature of T. The total internal\nenergy, U of a mole of this gas, and the value of <br/>$$\\gamma \\left( { = {{{C_p}} \\over {{C_v}}}} \\right)$$ are given, respectively by:",
    "options": [
      "U = $${5 \\over 2}RT$$ and $$\\gamma  = {7 \\over 5}$$",
      "U = 5RT and $$\\gamma  = {6 \\over 5}$$",
      "U = 5RT and $$\\gamma  = {7 \\over 5}$$",
      "U = $${5 \\over 2}RT$$ and $$\\gamma  = {6 \\over 5}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "U = $${5 \\over 2}RT$$ and $$\\gamma  = {7 \\over 5}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "5NBpzaifV77DCCQV4pjgy2xukev1nbvn",
    "question": "A gas mixture consists of 3 moles of oxygen\nand 5 moles of argon at temperature T.\nAssuming the gases to be ideal and the oxygen\nbond to be rigid, the total internal energy (in\nunits of RT) of the mixture is :",
    "options": [
      "11",
      "20",
      "15",
      "13"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "15"
  },
  {
    "id": "O373M1zCC6g9sU4ulkjgy2xuketz37vd",
    "question": "Match the $${{{C_P}} \\over {{C_V}}}$$ ratio for ideal gases with different type of molecules :\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\"><b>Molecule Type</b></th>\n<th class=\"tg-baqh\"><b>C<sub>P</sub>/C<sub>V</sub></b></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(A) Monatomic</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(I) 7/5</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(B) Diatomic rigid molecules </td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(II) 9/7</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(C) Diatomic non-rigid molecules</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(III) 4/3</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(D) Triatomic rigid molecules</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(IV) 5/3</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(II), (C)-(I), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "(A)-(IV), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "qDAq65pyHyvDYKnkvR7k9k2k5i891ed",
    "question": "Consider two ideal diatomic gases A and B at\nsome temperature T. Molecules of the gas A are\nrigid, and have a mass m. Molecules of the gas\nB have an additional vibrational mode, and\nhave a mass $${m \\over 4}$$\n. The ratio of the specific heats ($$C_V^A$$ and $$C_V^B$$ ) of gas A and B, respectively is :",
    "options": [
      "7 : 9",
      "5 : 7",
      "3 : 5",
      "5 : 9"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "5 : 7"
  },
  {
    "id": "pOdOf6VyXLRgLinVL31klryaxou",
    "question": "A diatomic gas, having $${C_p} = {7 \\over 2}R$$ and $${C_v} = {5 \\over 2}R$$, is heated at constant pressure. The ratio dU : dQ : dW : ",
    "options": [
      "5 : 7 : 3",
      "3 : 7 : 2",
      "5 : 7 : 2",
      "3 : 5 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "5 : 7 : 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "PesjmeqFYD1rQtwYSH1klt2kqz5",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : In a diatomic molecule, the rotational energy at a given temperature obeys Maxwell's distribution.<br/><br/>Statement II : In a diatomic molecule, the rotational energy at a given temperature equals the translational kinetic energy for each molecule.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "807Tx8PLagOu2pPq951kluljren",
    "question": "The internal energy (U), pressure (P) and volume (V) of an ideal gas are related as U $$=$$ 3PV + 4. The gas is :",
    "options": [
      "either monoatomic or diatomic.",
      "monoatomic only.",
      "polyatomic only.",
      "diatomic only."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "polyatomic only."
  },
  {
    "id": "LMJLGCnPVhCdO9GPCd1kmj17vjo",
    "question": "A polyatomic ideal gas has 24 vibrational modes. What is the value of $$\\gamma$$?",
    "options": [
      "1.37",
      "1.30",
      "1.03",
      "10.3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "1.03"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZPVUTefqFsJbdP5DMp1kmj1c1mr",
    "question": "Two ideal polyatomic gases at temperatures T<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>2</sub> are mixed so that there is no loss of energy. If F<sub>1</sub> and F<sub>2</sub>, m<sub>1</sub> and m<sub>2</sub>, n<sub>1</sub> and n<sub>2</sub> be the degrees of freedom, masses, number of molecules of the first and second gas respectively, the temperature of mixture of these two gases is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{n_1}{F_1}{T_1} + {n_2}{F_2}{T_2}} \\over {{F_1} + {F_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{n_1}{F_1}{T_1} + {n_2}{F_2}{T_2}} \\over {{n_1}{F_1} + {n_2}{F_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{n_1}{T_1} + {n_2}{T_2}} \\over {{n_1} + {n_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{n_1}{F_1}{T_1} + {n_2}{F_2}{T_2}} \\over {{n_1} + {n_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$${{{n_1}{F_1}{T_1} + {n_2}{F_2}{T_2}} \\over {{n_1}{F_1} + {n_2}{F_2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "eX8yeE0y1EWPcWf6JJ1kmkahn10",
    "question": "If one mole of the polyatomic gas is having two vibrational modes and $$\\beta$$ is the ratio of molar specific heats for polyatomic gas $$\\left( {\\beta  = {{{C_P}} \\over {{C_V}}}} \\right)$$ then the value of $$\\beta$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "1.02",
      "1.35",
      "1.2",
      "1.25"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "1.2"
  },
  {
    "id": "lRjiLALRPpRZfjdt4T1kmlhq3uw",
    "question": "What will be the average value of energy along one degree of freedom for an ideal gas in thermal equilibrium at a temperature T? (k<sub>B</sub> is Boltzmann constant)",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 2}{k_B}T$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}{k_B}T$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}{k_B}T$$",
      "$${k_B}T$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}{k_B}T$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqcqw5r",
    "question": "The correct relation between the degrees of freedom f and the ratio of specific heat $$\\gamma$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$$f = {2 \\over {\\gamma  - 1}}$$",
      "$$f = {2 \\over {\\gamma  + 1}}$$",
      "$$f = {{\\gamma  + 1} \\over 2}$$",
      "$$f = {1 \\over {\\gamma  + 1}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$$f = {2 \\over {\\gamma  - 1}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsvkz8e",
    "question": "What will be the average value of energy for a monoatomic gas in thermal equilibrium at temperature T?",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 2}{k_B}T$$",
      "$${k_B}T$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}{k_B}T$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}{k_B}T$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 2}{k_B}T$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56ur4mp",
    "question": "<p>According to kinetic theory of gases,</p>\n<p>A. The motion of the gas molecules freezes at 0$$^\\circ$$C.</p>\n<p>B. The mean free path of gas molecules decreases if the density of molecules is increased.</p>\n<p>C. The mean free path of gas molecules increases if temperature is increased keeping pressure constant.</p>\n<p>D. Average kinetic energy per molecule per degree of freedom is $${3 \\over 2}{k_B}T$$ (for monoatomic gases).</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and C only",
      "B and C only",
      "A and B only",
      "C and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "B and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59m787e",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of specific heats $$\\left( {{{{C_P}} \\over {{C_V}}}} \\right)$$ in terms of degree of freedom (f) is given by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {1 + {f \\over 3}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( {1 + {2 \\over f}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( {1 + {f \\over 2}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( {1 + {1 \\over f}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {1 + {2 \\over f}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i1565s",
    "question": "<p>A gas has $$n$$ degrees of freedom. The ratio of specific heat of gas at constant volume to the specific heat of gas at constant pressure will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$ \\frac{n}{n+2}$$",
      "$$ \\frac{n+2}{n}$$",
      "$$ \\frac{n}{2n+2}$$",
      "$$ \\frac{n}{n-2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$$ \\frac{n}{n+2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kn0ylm",
    "question": "<p>Which statements are correct about degrees of freedom ?</p>\n<p>(A) A molecule with n degrees of freedom has n$$^{2}$$ different ways of storing energy.</p>\n<p>(B) Each degree of freedom is associated with $$\\frac{1}{2}$$ RT average energy per mole.</p>\n<p>(C) A monatomic gas molecule has 1 rotational degree of freedom where as diatomic molecule has 2 rotational degrees of freedom.</p>\n<p>(D) $$\\mathrm{CH}_{4}$$ has a total of 6 degrees of freedom.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below : </p>",
    "options": [
      "(B) and (C) only",
      "(B) and (D) only",
      "(A) and (B) only",
      "(C) and (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "(B) and (D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo65oa8",
    "question": "Heat energy of $735 \\mathrm{~J}$ is given to a diatomic gas allowing the gas to expand at constant pressure.\n\nEach gas molecule rotates around an internal axis but do not oscillate. The increase in the internal\n\nenergy of the gas will be :",
    "options": [
      "$572 \\mathrm{~J}$",
      " $441 \\mathrm{~J}$",
      "$525 \\mathrm{~J}$",
      "$735 \\mathrm{~J}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$525 \\mathrm{~J}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtz1qik",
    "question": "<p>According to law of equipartition of energy the molar specific heat of a diatomic gas at constant volume where the molecule has one additional vibrational mode is :-</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{9}{2}R$$",
      "$$\\frac{5}{2}R$$",
      "$$\\frac{3}{2}R$$",
      "$$\\frac{7}{2}R$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{7}{2}R$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwr2dow",
    "question": "<p>Let $$\\gamma_1$$ be the ratio of molar specific heat at constant pressure and molar specific heat at constant volume of a monoatomic gas and $$\\gamma_2$$ be the similar ratio of diatomic gas. Considering the diatomic gas molecule as a rigid rotator, the ratio, $$\\frac{\\gamma_1}{\\gamma_2}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{35}{27}$$",
      "$$\\frac{25}{21}$$",
      "$$\\frac{21}{25}$$",
      "$$\\frac{27}{35}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{25}{21}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp07l1w",
    "question": "<p>The mean free path of molecules of a certain gas at STP is $$1500 \\mathrm{~d}$$, where $$\\mathrm{d}$$ is the diameter of the gas molecules. While maintaining the standard pressure, the mean free path of the molecules at $$373 \\mathrm{~K}$$ is approximately:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$750 \\mathrm{~d}$$",
      "$$1500 \\mathrm{~d}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{2049~ d}$$",
      "$$1098 \\mathrm{~d}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{2049~ d}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq223aw",
    "question": "<p>The rms speed of oxygen molecule in a vessel at particular temperature is $$\\left(1+\\frac{5}{x}\\right)^{\\frac{1}{2}} v$$, where $$v$$ is the average speed of the molecule. The value of $$x$$ will be:</p>\n<p>$$\\left(\\right.$$ Take $$\\left.\\pi=\\frac{22}{7}\\right)$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "8",
      "28",
      "27"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "28"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguxo6ar",
    "question": "<p>Three vessels of equal volume contain gases at the same temperature and pressure. The first vessel contains neon (monoatomic), the second contains chlorine (diatomic) and third contains uranium hexafloride (polyatomic). Arrange these on the basis of their root mean square speed $$\\left(v_{\\mathrm{rms}}\\right)$$ and choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}($$ mono $$)=\\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}($$ dia $$)=\\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}($$ poly $$)$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}$$ (mono) $$ > \\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}($$ dia $$) > \\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}$$ (poly)",
      "$$\\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}$$ (dia) $$ < \\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}$$ (poly) $$ < \\mathrm{v}_{\\text {rms }}$$ (mono)",
      "$$\\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}$$ (mono) $$ < \\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}$$ (dia) $$ < \\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}$$ (poly)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}$$ (mono) $$ > \\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}($$ dia $$) > \\mathrm{v}_{\\mathrm{rms}}$$ (poly)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyfa78e",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 625px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 267px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">3 Translational degrees of freedom</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Monoatomic gases</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">3 Translational, 2 rotational degrees of freedoms</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Polyatomic gases</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">3 Translational, 2 rotational and 1 vibrational degrees of freedom</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Rigid diatomic gases</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">3 Translational, 3 rotational and more than one vibrational degrees of freedom</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Nonrigid diatomic gases</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(III), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(II), (C)-(I), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(IV), (C)-(III), (D)-(II)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "(A)-(I), (B)-(III), (C)-(IV), (D)-(II)"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbkmth3",
    "question": "Two moles a monoatomic gas is mixed with six moles of a diatomic gas. The molar specific heat of the mixture at constant volume is :",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{3}{2} \\mathrm{R}$",
      "$\\frac{7}{4} \\mathrm{R}$",
      "$\\frac{5}{2} \\mathrm{R}$",
      "$\\frac{9}{4} \\mathrm{R}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$\\frac{9}{4} \\mathrm{R}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3ypyg",
    "question": "<p>The average kinetic energy of a monatomic molecule is $$0.414 \\mathrm{~eV}$$ at temperature :</p>\n<p>(Use $$K_B=1.38 \\times 10^{-23} \\mathrm{~J} / \\mathrm{mol}-\\mathrm{K}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "3000 K",
      "3200 K",
      "1600 K",
      "1500 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "3200 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd66tqi",
    "question": "<p>A gas mixture consists of 8 moles of argon and 6 moles of oxygen at temperature T. Neglecting all vibrational modes, the total internal energy of the system is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "29 RT",
      "27 RT",
      "20 RT",
      "21 RT"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "27 RT"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsflyhcu",
    "question": "<p>$$N$$ moles of a polyatomic gas $$(f=6)$$ must be mixed with two moles of a monoatomic gas so that the mixture behaves as a diatomic gas. The value of $$N$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "6",
      "2",
      "4",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg6302e",
    "question": "<p>If three moles of monoatomic gas $$\\left(\\gamma=\\frac{5}{3}\\right)$$ is mixed with two moles of a diatomic gas $$\\left(\\gamma=\\frac{7}{5}\\right)$$, the value of adiabatic exponent $$\\gamma$$ for the mixture is</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.35",
      "1.52",
      "1.40",
      "1.75"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "1.52"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erjlj",
    "question": "<p>The translational degrees of freedom $$\\left(f_t\\right)$$ and rotational degrees of freedom $$\\left(f_r\\right)$$ of $$\\mathrm{CH}_4$$ molecule are:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$f_t=2$$ and $$f_r=2$$\n",
      "$$f_t=3$$ and $$f_r=3$$\n",
      "$$f_t=3$$ and 4$f_r=2$$\n",
      "$$f_t=2$$ and $$f_r=3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$$f_t=3$$ and $$f_r=3$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gs2yl",
    "question": "<p>A mixture of one mole of monoatomic gas and one mole of a diatomic gas (rigid) are kept at room temperature $$(27^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C})$$. The ratio of specific heat of gases at constant volume respectively is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{3}{5}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{7}{5}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{5}{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{3}{5}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb295f4",
    "question": "<p>Energy of 10 non rigid diatomic molecules at temperature $$\\mathrm{T}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "35 RT",
      "$$\\frac{7}{2}$$ RT",
      "70 K<sub>B</sub>T",
      "35 K<sub>B</sub>T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "degree-of-freedom-and-law-of-equipartition-of-energy",
    "solution": "35 K<sub>B</sub>T"
  },
  {
    "id": "DaO8lQ0ROBSNJEVc",
    "question": "''Heat cannot by itself flow from a body at lower temperature to a body at higher temperature'' is a statement or consequence of :",
    "options": [
      "second law of thermodynamics",
      "conservation of momentum",
      "conservation of mass ",
      "first law of thermodynamics "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-engine,-second-law-of-thermodynamics-and-carnot-engine",
    "solution": "second law of thermodynamics"
  },
  {
    "id": "ebq7jDvSzMjj78Vk",
    "question": "A solid body of constant heat capacity $$1$$ $$J/{}^ \\circ C$$ is being heated by keeping it in contact with reservoirs in two ways:\n<br/>$$(i)$$  Sequentially keeping in contact with $$2$$ reservoirs such that each reservoir \n<br/>$$\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,$$supplies same amount of heat. \n<br/>$$(ii)$$ Sequentially keeping in contact with $$8$$ reservoirs such that each reservoir \n<br/>$$\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,\\,$$supplies same amount of heat. \n<br/>In both the cases body is brought from initial temperature $${100^ \\circ }C$$ to final temperature $${200^ \\circ }C$$. Entropy change of the body in the two cases respectively is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$ln2, 2ln2$$ ",
      "$$2ln2, 8ln2$$ ",
      "$$ln2, 4ln2$$ ",
      "$$ln2, ln2$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-engine,-second-law-of-thermodynamics-and-carnot-engine",
    "solution": "$$ln2, ln2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "BnmZYkFfYDNyoLUBzw1kmlwefq8",
    "question": "An ideal gas in a cylinder is separated by a piston in such a way that the entropy of one part is S<sub>1</sub> and that of the other part is S<sub>2</sub>. Given that S<sub>1</sub> &gt; S<sub>2</sub>. If the piston is removed then the total entropy of the system will be :",
    "options": [
      "S<sub>1</sub> $$-$$ S<sub>2</sub>",
      "$${{{S_1}} \\over {{S_2}}}$$",
      "S<sub>1</sub> $$\\times$$ S<sub>2</sub>",
      "S<sub>1</sub> + S<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-engine,-second-law-of-thermodynamics-and-carnot-engine",
    "solution": "S<sub>1</sub> + S<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "yLUyEKPYz5fH375RlF1krpnjo62",
    "question": "The entropy of any system is given by <br/>$$S = {\\alpha ^2}\\beta \\ln \\left[ {{{\\mu kR} \\over {J{\\beta ^2}}} + 3} \\right]$$ where $$\\alpha$$ and $$\\beta$$ are the constants. $$\\mu$$, J, k and R are no. of moles, mechanical equivalent of heat, Boltzmann constant and gas constant respectively. <br/>[Take $$S = {{dQ} \\over T}$$] <br/>Choose the incorrect option from the following :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\alpha$$ and J have the same dimensions.",
      "S and $$\\alpha$$ have different dimensions",
      "S, $$\\beta$$, k and $$\\mu$$R have the same dimensions",
      "$$\\alpha$$ and k have the same dimensions"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-engine,-second-law-of-thermodynamics-and-carnot-engine",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha$$ and k have the same dimensions"
  },
  {
    "id": "9bo2cjUWf49inj2l",
    "question": "Which of the following is more close to a black body? ",
    "options": [
      "black board paint ",
      "green leaves ",
      "black holes ",
      "red roses "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "black board paint "
  },
  {
    "id": "4nuBvzWOAdZ8p2PV",
    "question": "If mass-energy equivalence is taken into account, when water is cooled to form ice, the mass of water should ",
    "options": [
      "increase ",
      "remain unchanged ",
      "decrease ",
      "first increase then decrease "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "decrease "
  },
  {
    "id": "cxAlORaaQyDPNfje",
    "question": "Two spheres of the same material have radii $$1$$ $$m$$ and $$4$$ $$m$$ and temperatures $$4000$$ $$K$$ and $$2000$$ $$K$$ respectively. The ratio of the energy radiated per second by the first sphere to that by the second is ",
    "options": [
      "$$1:1$$ ",
      "$$16:1$$ ",
      "$$4:1$$ ",
      "$$1:9$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "$$1:1$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "lzigye0UC1JjRN6N",
    "question": "Infrared radiation is detected by ",
    "options": [
      "spectrometer ",
      "pyrometer ",
      "nanometer ",
      "photometer "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "pyrometer "
  },
  {
    "id": "Ftq3pX3kDVMovler",
    "question": "The earth radiates in the infra-red region of the spectrum. The spectrum is correctly given by ",
    "options": [
      "Rayleigh Jeans law ",
      "Planck's law of radiation ",
      "Stefan's law of radiation",
      "Wien's law "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "Wien's law "
  },
  {
    "id": "EZB4fpmf7oBd1OMJ",
    "question": "If the temperature of the sun were to increase from $$T$$ to $$2T$$ and its radius from $$R$$ to $$2R$$, then the ratio of the radiant energy received on earth to what it was previously will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$32$$ ",
      "$$16$$ ",
      "$$4$$ ",
      "$$64$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "$$64$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "2uSaCQcyh0jURp2q",
    "question": "Assuming the Sun to be a spherical body of radius $$R$$ at a temperature of $$TK$$, evaluate the total radiant powered incident of Earth at a distance $$r$$ from the Sun\n<p>Where r<sub>0</sub> is the radius of the Earth and $$\\sigma $$ is Stefan's constant.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4\\pi r_0^2{R^2}\\sigma {{{T^4}} \\over {{r^2}}}$$ ",
      "$$\\pi r_0^2{R^2}\\sigma {{{T^4}} \\over {{r^2}}}$$ ",
      "$$r_0^2{R^2}\\sigma {{{T^4}} \\over {4\\pi {r^2}}}$$ ",
      "$${R^2}\\sigma {{{T^4}} \\over {{r^2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "$$\\pi r_0^2{R^2}\\sigma {{{T^4}} \\over {{r^2}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "CZBbHg7fWexeDiVe",
    "question": "Three rods of Copper, Brass and Steel are welded together to form a $$Y$$ shaped structure. Area of cross - section of each rod $$ = 4c{m^2}.$$ End of copper rod is maintained at $${100^ \\circ }C$$ where as ends of brass and steel are kept at $${0^ \\circ }C$$. Lengths of the copper, brass and steel rods are $$46,$$ $$13$$ and $$12$$ $$cms$$ respectively. The rods are thermally insulated from surroundings excepts at ends. Thermal conductivities of copper, brass and steel are $$0.92, 0.26$$ and $$0.12$$ $$CGS$$ units respectively. Rate of heat flow through copper rod is:",
    "options": [
      "$$1.2$$ $$cal/s$$",
      "$$2.4$$ $$cal/s$$",
      "$$4.8$$ $$cal/s$$",
      "$$6.0$$ $$cal/s$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "$$4.8$$ $$cal/s$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "X7kmGjQQHpdY0IcEAluV9",
    "question": "A heat source at T = 10<sup>3</sup> K is connected to another heat reservoir at T = 10<sup>2</sup> K by a copper slab which is 1 mthick. Given that the thermal conductivity of copper is 0.1 WK<sup>–1</sup>m<sup>–1</sup>, the energy flux through it in the steady state is -",
    "options": [
      "200 Wm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "65  Wm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "120 Wm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "90 Wm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "90 Wm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "IePFxWpif4iMvXIYdhYDr",
    "question": "A cylinder of radius R is surrounded by a cylindrical shell of inner radius R and outer radius 2R. The thermal conductivity of the material of the inner cylinder is K<sub>1</sub> and the of the outer cylinder is K<sub>2</sub>. Assuming no loss of heat, the effective thermal conductivity of the system for heat flowing along the length of the cylinder is : \n",
    "options": [
      "K<sub>1</sub> + K<sub>2</sub> ",
      "$${{{K_1} + 3{K_2}} \\over 4}$$",
      "$${{{K_1} + {K_2}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{2{K_1} + 3{K_2}} \\over 5}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "$${{{K_1} + 3{K_2}} \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "E9NkG1T0M7tTbjjWl01kmj1h6nh",
    "question": "Two identical metal wires of thermal conductivities K<sub>1</sub> and K<sub>2</sub> respectively are connected in series. The effective thermal conductivity of the combination is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2{K_1}{K_2}} \\over {{K_1} + {K_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{K_1} + {K_2}} \\over {{K_1}{K_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{K_1} + {K_2}} \\over {2{K_1}{K_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{K_1}{K_2}} \\over {{K_1} + {K_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "$${{2{K_1}{K_2}} \\over {{K_1} + {K_2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjnr4zg",
    "question": "Two thin metallic spherical shells of radii r<sub>1</sub> and r<sub>2</sub> (r<sub>1</sub> &lt; r<sub>2</sub>) are placed with their centres coinciding. A material of thermal conductivity K is filled in the space between the shells. The inner shell is maintained at temperature $$\\theta$$<sub>1</sub> and the outer shell at temperature $$\\theta$$<sub>2</sub>($$\\theta$$<sub>1</sub> &lt; $$\\theta$$<sub>2</sub>). The rate at which heat flows radially through the material is :-",
    "options": [
      "$${{4\\pi K{r_1}{r_2}({\\theta _2} - {\\theta _1})} \\over {{r_2} - {r_1}}}$$",
      "$${{\\pi {r_1}{r_2}({\\theta _2} - {\\theta _1})} \\over {{r_2} - {r_1}}}$$",
      "$${{K({\\theta _2} - {\\theta _1})} \\over {{r_2} - {r_1}}}$$",
      "$${{K({\\theta _2} - {\\theta _1})({r_2} - {r_1})} \\over {4\\pi {r_1}{r_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "$${{4\\pi K{r_1}{r_2}({\\theta _2} - {\\theta _1})} \\over {{r_2} - {r_1}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i1373g",
    "question": "<p>An ice cube of dimensions $$60 \\mathrm{~cm} \\times 50 \\mathrm{~cm} \\times 20 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ is placed in an insulation box of wall thickness $$1 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. The box keeping the ice cube at $$0^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ of temperature is brought to a room of temperature $$40^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. The rate of melting of ice is approximately :</p>\n<p>(Latent heat of fusion of ice is $$3.4 \\times 10^{5} \\mathrm{~J} \\mathrm{~kg}^{-1}$$ and thermal conducting of insulation wall is $$0.05 \\,\\mathrm{Wm}^{-1 \\circ} \\mathrm{C}^{-1}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$61 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$",
      "$$61 \\times 10^{-5} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$",
      "$$208 \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$",
      "$$30 \\times 10^{-5} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "$$61 \\times 10^{-5} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jhh8jx",
    "question": "<p>Read the following statements :</p>\n<p>A. When small temperature difference between a liquid and its surrounding is doubled, the rate of loss of heat of the liquid becomes twice.</p>\n<p>B. Two bodies $$P$$ and $$Q$$ having equal surface areas are maintained at temperature $$10^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ and $$20^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. The thermal radiation emitted in a given time by $$\\mathrm{P}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Q}$$ are in the ratio $$1: 1.15$$.</p>\n<p>C. A Carnot Engine working between $$100 \\mathrm{~K}$$ and $$400 \\mathrm{~K}$$ has an efficiency of $$75 \\%$$.</p>\n<p>D. When small temperature difference between a liquid and its surrounding is quadrupled, the rate of loss of heat of the liquid becomes twice.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B, C only",
      "A, B only",
      "A, C only",
      "B, C, D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "A, B, C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh303j46",
    "question": "<p>A body cools in 7 minutes from $$60^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ to $$40^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. The temperature of the surrounding is $$10^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. The temperature of the body after the next 7 minutes will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$34^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$28^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$32^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$30^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "$$28^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vy00d",
    "question": "<p>On celcius scale the temperature of body increases by $$40^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. The increase in temperature on Fahrenheit scale is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$75^{\\circ} \\mathrm{F}$$\n",
      "$$70^{\\circ} \\mathrm{F}$$\n",
      "$$72^{\\circ} \\mathrm{F}$$\n",
      "$$68^{\\circ} \\mathrm{F}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "heat-transfer",
    "solution": "$$72^{\\circ} \\mathrm{F}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "XRCRiBlsQV1VCE8s",
    "question": "At what temperature is the $$r.m.s$$ velocity of a hydrogen molecule equal to that of an oxygen molecule at $${47^ \\circ }C?$$ ",
    "options": [
      "$$80K$$ ",
      "$$-73$$ $$K$$ ",
      "$$3$$ $$K$$ ",
      "$$20$$ $$K$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$20$$ $$K$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "m4xLDHoo8t3QStkL",
    "question": "Cooking gas containers are kept in a lorry moving with uniform speed. The temperature of the gas molecules inside will ",
    "options": [
      "increase ",
      "decrease ",
      "remain same ",
      "decrease for some, while increase for others "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "remain same "
  },
  {
    "id": "Wtincm2iDoaGeqaC",
    "question": "1 mole of a gas with $$\\gamma  = 7/5$$ is mixed with $$1$$ mole of a gas with $$\\gamma  = 5/3,$$ then the value of $$\\gamma $$ for the resulting mixture is ",
    "options": [
      "$$7/5$$ ",
      "$$2/5$$ ",
      "$$3/2$$ ",
      "$$12/7$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$3/2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "P4Acm3A1OxAjOz8l",
    "question": "One mole of ideal monatomic gas $$\\left( {\\gamma  = 5/3} \\right)$$ is mixed with one mole of diatomic gas $$\\left( {\\gamma  = 7/5} \\right)$$. What is $$\\gamma $$ for the mixture? $$\\gamma $$ Denotes the ratio of specific heat at constant pressure, to that at constant volume ",
    "options": [
      "$$35/23$$ ",
      "$$23/15$$ ",
      "$$3/2$$ ",
      "$$4/3$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$3/2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "CvgU46G7abcmnd4S",
    "question": "A gaseous mixture consists of $$16$$ $$g$$ of helium and $$16$$ $$g$$ of oxygen. The ratio $${{Cp} \\over {{C_v}}}$$ of the mixture is ",
    "options": [
      "$$1.62$$ ",
      "$$1.59$$ ",
      "$$1.54$$ ",
      "$$1.4$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$1.62$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "lUwj8MqZ20HXY9Sj",
    "question": "Two rigid boxes containing different ideal gases are placed on a table. Box A contains one mole of nitrogen at temperature $${T_0},$$ while Box contains one mole of helium at temperature $$\\left( {{7 \\over 3}} \\right){T_0}.$$ The boxes are then put into thermal contact with each other, and heat flows between them until the gases reach a common final temperature (ignore the heat capacity of boxes). Then, the final temperature of the gases, $${T_f}$$ in terms of $${T_0}$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$${T_f} = {3 \\over 7}{T_0}$$ ",
      "$${T_f} = {7 \\over 3}{T_0}$$ ",
      "$${T_f} = {3 \\over 2}{T_0}$$ ",
      "$${T_f} = {5 \\over 2}{T_0}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${T_f} = {3 \\over 2}{T_0}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "eot4OWRiDLKH5ynQ",
    "question": "If $${C_p}$$ and $${C_v}$$ denote the specific heats of nitrogen per unit mass at constant pressure and constant volume respectively, then ",
    "options": [
      "$${C_p} - {C_v} = 28R$$ ",
      "$${C_p} - {C_v} = R/28$$",
      "$${C_p} - {C_v} = R/14$$ ",
      "$${C_p} - {C_v} = R$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${C_p} - {C_v} = R/28$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "nQqlq6Qo56DBk2Y3",
    "question": "The speed of sound in oxygen $$\\left( {{O_2}} \\right)$$ at a certain temperature is $$460\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}.$$ The speed of sound in helium $$(He)$$ at the same temperature will be (assume both gases to be ideal) ",
    "options": [
      "$$1421\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$ ",
      "$$500\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$",
      "$$650\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$",
      "$$300\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$1421\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "vkKkodUJbwcBvU05",
    "question": "Consider an ideal gas confined in an isolated closed chamber. As the gas undergoes an adiabatic expansion, the average time of collision between molecules increases as $${V^q},$$ where $$V$$ is the volume of the gas. The value of $$q$$ is: $$\\left( {\\gamma  = {{{C_p}} \\over {{C_v}}}} \\right)$$ ",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\gamma  + 1} \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$${{\\gamma  - 1} \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$${{3\\gamma  + 5} \\over 6}$$ ",
      "$${{3\\gamma  - 5} \\over 6}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${{\\gamma  + 1} \\over 2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "DCoTCCZ9knY62yBW",
    "question": "The temperature of an open room of volume 30 m<sup>3</sup> increases from 17<sup>o</sup>C to 27<sup>o</sup>C due to the sunshine. The atmospheric pressure in the room remains 1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup> Pa. If N<sub>i</sub>\n and N<sub>f</sub> are the number of molecules in the room\nbefore and after heating, then N<sub>f</sub> – N<sub>i</sub> will be :",
    "options": [
      "- 1.61 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>23</sup>",
      "1.38 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>23</sup>",
      "2.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>25</sup>",
      "- 2.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>25</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "- 2.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>25</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "GG5jnHCbuhvtaHRT",
    "question": "C<sub>P</sub> and C<sub>v</sub> are specific heats at constant pressure and constant volume respectively. It is observed that <br/>C<sub>P</sub> – C<sub>v</sub> = a for hydrogen gas<br/> C<sub>P</sub> – C<sub>v</sub> = b for nitrogen gas<br/> The correct relation between a and b is  ",
    "options": [
      "a = 28 b",
      "a = 1/14 b",
      "a = b",
      "a = 14 b"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "a = 14 b"
  },
  {
    "id": "FE1WYEGVIc6GkHzaYB4P8",
    "question": "N moles of a diatomic gas in a cylinder are at a temperature T. Heat is supplied to the cylinder such that the temperature remains constant but n moles of the diatomic gas get converted into monoatomic gas. What is the change in the total kinetic energy of the gas ?",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$  nRT",
      "0",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$ nRT",
      "$${5 \\over 2}$$ nRT"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}$$  nRT"
  },
  {
    "id": "6tPz8WyqIeFT17d4XVKie",
    "question": "The value closest to the thermal velocity of a Helium atom at room temperature (300 K)  in ms<sup>-1</sup> is : \n<br/>[k<sub>B</sub> =1.4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-23</sup> J/K; m<sub>He</sub> = 7 $$ \\times $$ 10 <sup>-27</sup> kg ]",
    "options": [
      "1.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup>",
      "1.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup>",
      "1.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup>",
      "1.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "1.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "SiUiqscAgq9DjtfucRX02",
    "question": "Half mole of an ideal monoatomic gas is heated at constant pressure of 1 atm from 20<sup>o</sup>C to 90<sup>o</sup>C. Work done\nby gas is close to – (Gas constant R = 8.31 J/mol.K)",
    "options": [
      "581 J",
      "73 J",
      "146 J",
      "291 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "291 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "aAVEJjHVxfZv6fLGg53rsa0w2w9jx7f8ml3",
    "question": "A diatomic gas with rigid molecules does 10 J of work when expanded at constant pressure. What would be\nthe heat energy absorbed by the gas, in this process ?",
    "options": [
      "35 J",
      "30 J",
      "25 J",
      "40 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "35 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "UIYDiPk7re8pX8vYHm3rsa0w2w9jx3ostqk",
    "question": "Two moles of helium gas is mixed with three moles of hydrogen molecules (taken to be rigid). What is the\nmolar specific heat of mixture at constant volume ? (R = 8.3 J/mol K)",
    "options": [
      "21.6 J/mol K",
      "17.4 J/mol K",
      "15.7 J/mol K",
      "19.7 J/mol K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "17.4 J/mol K"
  },
  {
    "id": "v9sBRRddI5wqEP93Lg3rsa0w2w9jwzmkaqj",
    "question": "When heat Q is supplied to a diatomic gas of rigid molecules, at constant volume its temperature increases by\n$$\\Delta $$T. the heat required to produce the same change in temperature, at a constant pressure is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${7 \\over 5}Q$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}Q$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}Q$$",
      "$${5 \\over 3}Q$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${7 \\over 5}Q$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "CTr5hgdLmQoTzg5DJ118hoxe66ijvztk4ph",
    "question": "A 25 × 10<sup>–3</sup> m<sup>3</sup> volume cylinder is filled with\n1 mol of O<sub>2</sub> gas at room temperature (300K).\nThe molecular diameter of O<sub>2</sub>, and its root\nmean square speed, are found to be 0.3 nm, and\n200 m/s, respectively. What is the average\ncollision rate (per second) for an O<sub>2</sub> molecule ?",
    "options": [
      "~10<sup>13</sup>",
      "~10<sup>12</sup>",
      "~10<sup>11</sup>",
      "~10<sup>10</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "~10<sup>12</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "ujpmVbAmuT0MZd2xaM9Wv",
    "question": "For a given gas at 1 atm pressure, rms speed\nof the molecule is 200 m/s at 127°C. At 2 atm\npressure and at 227°C, the rms speed of the\nmolecules will be :",
    "options": [
      "100 m/s",
      "100 $$\\sqrt 5 $$ m/s",
      "80 $$\\sqrt 5 $$ m/s",
      "80 m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "100 $$\\sqrt 5 $$ m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "kZBDPe1Cq1cODFtZq19AY",
    "question": "The temperature, at which the root mean square\nvelocity of hydrogen molecules equals their\nescape velocity from the earth, is closest to :<br/>\n[Boltzmann Constant k<sub>B</sub> = 1.38 × 10<sup>–23</sup> J/K\nAvogadro Number N<sub>A</sub> = 6.02 × 10<sup>26</sup> /kg\nRadius of Earth : 6.4 × 10<sup>6</sup> m\nGravitational acceleration on Earth = 10ms<sup>–2</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "3 × 10<sup>5</sup> K",
      "10<sup>4</sup> K",
      "650 K",
      "800 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "10<sup>4</sup> K"
  },
  {
    "id": "JlIUmv2W7LyEKKFnAIyr5",
    "question": "A vertical closed cylinder is separated into two parts by a frictionless piston of mass m and of negligible thickness. The piston is free to move along the length of the cylinder. The length of the cylinder above the piston is $$\\ell $$<sub>1</sub>, and that below the piston is $$\\ell $$<sub>2</sub>, such that $$\\ell $$<sub>1</sub> &gt; $$\\ell $$<sub>2</sub>. Each part of the cylinder contains n moles of an ideal gas at equal temperature T. If the piston is stationary, its mass, m, will be given by : <br/>(R is universal gas constant and g is the acceleration due to gravity) ",
    "options": [
      "$${{nRT} \\over g}\\left[ {{{{\\ell _1} - {\\ell _2}} \\over {{\\ell _1}{\\ell _2}}}} \\right]$$",
      "$${{RT} \\over g}\\left[ {{{2{\\ell _1} + {\\ell _2}} \\over {{\\ell _1}{\\ell _2}}}} \\right]$$",
      "$${{nRT} \\over g}\\left[ {{1 \\over {{\\ell _2}}} + {1 \\over {{\\ell _1}}}} \\right]$$",
      "$${{RT} \\over {ng}}\\left[ {{{{\\ell _1} - 3{\\ell _2}} \\over {{\\ell _1}{\\ell _2}}}} \\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${{nRT} \\over g}\\left[ {{{{\\ell _1} - {\\ell _2}} \\over {{\\ell _1}{\\ell _2}}}} \\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "RuSGmRRXJ0ZX630YSSIeT",
    "question": "An ideal gas is enclosed in a cylinder at pressure of 2 atm and temperature 300 K. The mean time between two successive collisions is 6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–8</sup> s. If the pressure is doubled and temperature is increased to 500 K, the mean time between two successive collisions will be close to",
    "options": [
      "0.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> s",
      "4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> s",
      "3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> s",
      "2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> s"
  },
  {
    "id": "5pwy59byT9YR4rK8OqSV8",
    "question": "Two kg of a monoatomic gas is at a pressure of 4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>4</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup>. The density of the gas is 8 kg/m<sup>3</sup>. What is the order of energy of the gas due to its thermal motion ?",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>4</sup> J",
      "10<sup>3</sup> J",
      "10<sup>5</sup> J",
      "10<sup>6</sup> J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "10<sup>4</sup> J"
  },
  {
    "id": "uTilrpd98X6CJSFoVauSV",
    "question": "A 15 g mass of nitrogen gas is enclosed in a vessel at a temperature 27<sup>o</sup>C. Amount of heat transferred to the gas, so that rms  velocity of molecules is doubled, is about : [Take R = 8.3 J/K mole]",
    "options": [
      "0.9 kJ",
      "6 kJ ",
      "10 kJ ",
      "14 kJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "10 kJ "
  },
  {
    "id": "2jvUqHzYygn5u4guHuQCx",
    "question": "A mixture of 2 moles of helium gas (atomic mass = 4 u), and 1 mole of argon gas (atomic mass = 40 u) is kept at 300 K in a container. The ratio of their rms speeds $$\\left[ {{{{V_{rms}}\\,(helium)} \\over {{V_{rms}}\\,(\\arg on)}}} \\right],$$ is close to : ",
    "options": [
      "3.16",
      "0.32",
      "0.45",
      "2.24"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "3.16"
  },
  {
    "id": "ysYAdKtQiaarBXb8ox7k9k2k5hhekk9",
    "question": "Consider a mixture of n moles of helium gas\nand 2n moles of oxygen gas (molecules taken\nto be rigid) as an ideal gas. Its C<sub>P</sub>/C<sub>V</sub> value\nwill be :",
    "options": [
      "23/15",
      "67/45",
      "40/27",
      "19/13"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "19/13"
  },
  {
    "id": "MACCh4nSqypQKyWKt7jgy2xukg0b5qk1",
    "question": "In a dilute gas at pressure P and temperature T, the mean time between successive collisions of a\nmolecule varies with T as :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt T $$",
      "T",
      "$${1 \\over T}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt T }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt T }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "GJh69SLHEUOasOKiqpjgy2xukfgai58o",
    "question": "Number of molecules in a volume of 4 cm<sup>3</sup> of\na perfect monoatomic gas at some temperature\nT and at a pressure of 2 cm of mercury is close\nto? <br/>(Given, mean kinetic energy of a molecule\n<br/>(at T) is 4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–14</sup> erg, g = 980 cm/s<sup>2</sup>, density of\n<br/>mercury = 13.6 g/cm<sup>3</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "5.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>18</sup>",
      "4.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>16</sup>",
      "5.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>16</sup>",
      "4.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>18</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "4.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>18</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "3BcpB0BRnUUtFWQqQ6jgy2xukexs1a92",
    "question": "An ideal gas in a closed container is slowly\nheated. As its temperature increases, which of\nthe following statements are true?\n<br/>(A) the mean free path of the molecules\ndecreases.\n<br/>(B) the mean collision time between the\nmolecules decreases.\n<br/>(C) the mean free path remains unchanged.\n<br/>(D) the mean collision time remains unchanged.\n",
    "options": [
      "(C) and (D)\n",
      "(A) and (D)",
      "(B) and (C)",
      "(A) and (B)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "(B) and (C)"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZfN9md8GtxREfOhQBK7k9k2k5l8i62w",
    "question": "Two gases-argon (atomic radius 0.07 nm,\natomic weight 40) and xenon (atomic radius\n0.1 nm, atomic weight 140) have the same\nnumber density and are at the same\ntemperature. The raito of their respective mean\nfree times is closest to :",
    "options": [
      "2.3",
      "1.83",
      "4.67",
      "3.67"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "1.83"
  },
  {
    "id": "dw958HyEAv1F85NhVH7k9k2k5f77x3m",
    "question": "Under an adiabatic process, the volume of an ideal gas gets doubled. Consequently the mean\ncollision time between the gas molecule changes from $${\\tau _1}$$\n to $${\\tau _2}$$\n. If $${{{C_p}} \\over {{C_v}}} = \\gamma $$ for this gas then a good\nestimate for $${{{\\tau _2}} \\over {{\\tau _1}}}$$\n is given by :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left( 2 \\right)^{{{1 + \\gamma } \\over 2}}}$$",
      "2",
      "$${\\left( {{1 \\over 2}} \\right)^{{{1 + \\gamma } \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{1 \\over 2}} \\right)^\\gamma }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${\\left( 2 \\right)^{{{1 + \\gamma } \\over 2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "u4N2icvMVOxcFhCpQ51klrocwqf",
    "question": "On the basis of kinetic theory of gases, the gas exerts pressure because its molecules :",
    "options": [
      "continuously lose their energy till it reaches wall.",
      "are attracted by the walls of container.",
      "suffer change in momentum when impinge on the walls of container.",
      "continuously stick to the walls of container."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "suffer change in momentum when impinge on the walls of container."
  },
  {
    "id": "d1Dh1z6cmtypQABGHM1kmhp8r9s",
    "question": "The volume V of an enclosure contains a mixture of three gases, 16 g of oxygen, 28 g of nitrogen and 44 g of carbon dioxide at absolute temperature T. Consider R as universal gas constant. The pressure of the mixture of gases is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{3RT} \\over V}$$",
      "$${{4RT} \\over V}$$",
      "$${{88RT} \\over V}$$",
      "$${5 \\over 2}{{RT} \\over V}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${5 \\over 2}{{RT} \\over V}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "TCwXd5eQAWlgxYFmEc1kmip5f3b",
    "question": "Calculate the value of mean free path ($$\\lambda$$) for oxygen molecules at temperature 27$$^\\circ$$C and pressure 1.01 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> Pa. Assume the molecular diameter 0.3 nm and the gas is ideal. (k = 1.38 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$23</sup> JK<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "32 nm",
      "58 nm",
      "86 nm",
      "102 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "102 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "N3JuLFKtW3sxfqQhOM1kmlw1724",
    "question": "Consider a sample of oxygen behaving like an ideal gas. At 300 K, the ratio of root mean square (rms) velocity to the average velocity of gas molecule would be :<br/><br/>(Molecular weight of oxygen is 32g/mol; R = 8.3 J K<sup>$$-$$1</sup> mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{{3\\pi } \\over 8}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over 3}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{8 \\over 3}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{8\\pi } \\over 3}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{3\\pi } \\over 8}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "JjZRQITqX850Etxikg1krplnl0i",
    "question": "Consider a mixture of gas molecule of types A, B and C having masses m<sub>A</sub> &lt; m<sub>B</sub> &lt; m<sub>C</sub>. The ratio of their root mean square speeds at normal temperature and pressure is :",
    "options": [
      "$${v_A} = {v_B} \\ne {v_C}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {{v_A}}} &gt; {1 \\over {{v_B}}} &gt; {1 \\over {{v_C}}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {{v_A}}} &lt; {1 \\over {{v_B}}} &lt; {1 \\over {{v_C}}}$$",
      "$${v_A} = {v_B} = {v_C} = 0$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {{v_A}}} &lt; {1 \\over {{v_B}}} &lt; {1 \\over {{v_C}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krudowyj",
    "question": "For a gas C<sub>P</sub> $$-$$ C<sub>V</sub> = R in a state P and C<sub>P</sub> $$-$$ C<sub>V</sub> = 1.10 R in a state Q, T<sub>P</sub> and T<sub>Q</sub> are the temperatures in two different states P and Q respectively. Then",
    "options": [
      "T<sub>P</sub> = T<sub>Q</sub>",
      "T<sub>P</sub> &lt; T<sub>Q</sub>",
      "T<sub>P</sub> = 0.9 T<sub>Q</sub>",
      "T<sub>P</sub> &gt; T<sub>Q</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "T<sub>P</sub> &gt; T<sub>Q</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kryt8uuz",
    "question": "The number of molecules in one litre of an ideal gas at 300 K and 2 atmospheric pressure with mean kinetic energy 2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$9</sup> J per molecules is :",
    "options": [
      "0.75 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>11</sup>",
      "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>11</sup>",
      "1.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>11</sup>",
      "6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>11</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "1.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>11</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktacm6k5",
    "question": "The rms speeds of the molecules of Hydrogen, Oxygen and Carbon dioxide at the same temperature are V<sub>H</sub>, V<sub>O</sub> and V<sub>C</sub> respectively then :",
    "options": [
      "V<sub>H</sub> &gt; V<sub>O</sub> &gt; V<sub>C</sub>",
      "V<sub>C</sub> &gt; V<sub>O</sub> &gt; V<sub>H</sub>",
      "V<sub>H</sub> = V<sub>O</sub> &gt; V<sub>C</sub>",
      "V<sub>H</sub> = V<sub>O</sub> = V<sub>C</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "V<sub>H</sub> &gt; V<sub>O</sub> &gt; V<sub>C</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktbngtlc",
    "question": "A cylindrical container of volume 4.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> m<sup>3</sup> contains one mole of hydrogen and two moles of carbon dioxide. Assume the temperature of the mixture is 400 K. The pressure of the mixture of gases is :<br/><br/>[Take gas constant as 8.3 J mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup> K<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "249 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>1</sup> Pa",
      "24.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> Pa",
      "24.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> Pa",
      "24.9 Pa"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "24.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> Pa"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktdyy2yp",
    "question": "A balloon carries a total load of 185 kg at normal pressure and temperature of 27$$^\\circ$$C. What load will the balloon carry on rising to a height at which the barometric pressure is 45 cm of Hg and the temperature is $$-$$7$$^\\circ$$C. Assuming the volume constant?",
    "options": [
      "181.46 kg",
      "214.15 kg",
      "219.07 kg",
      "123.54 kg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "123.54 kg"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kte0lyrk",
    "question": "An ideal gas is expanding such that PT<sup>3</sup> = constant. The coefficient of volume expansion of the gas is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over T}$$",
      "$${2 \\over T}$$",
      "$${4 \\over T}$$",
      "$${3 \\over T}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${4 \\over T}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktflyluw",
    "question": "if the rms speed of oxygen molecules at 0$$^\\circ$$C is 160 m/s, find the rms speed of hydrogen molecules at 0$$^\\circ$$C.",
    "options": [
      "640 m/s",
      "40 m/s",
      "80 m/s",
      "332 m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "640 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth4rlyz",
    "question": "For an ideal gas the instantaneous change in pressure 'p' with volume 'v' is given by the equation $${{dp} \\over {dv}} =  - ap$$. If p = p<sub>0</sub> at  v =0 is the given boundary condition, then the maximum temperature one mole of gas can attain is : (Here R is the gas constant)",
    "options": [
      "$${{{p_0}} \\over {aeR}}$$",
      "$${{a{p_0}} \\over {eR}}$$",
      "infinity",
      "0$$^\\circ$$C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${{{p_0}} \\over {aeR}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjpk972",
    "question": "A mixture of hydrogen and oxygen has volume 500 cm<sup>3</sup>, temperature 300 K, pressure 400 kPa and mass 0.76 g. The ratio of masses of oxygen to hydrogen will be :-",
    "options": [
      "3 : 8",
      "3 : 16",
      "16 : 3",
      "8 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "16 : 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l546zhl8",
    "question": "<p>A cylinder of fixed capacity of 44.8 litres contains helium gas at standard temperature and pressure. The amount of heat needed to raise the temperature of gas in the cylinder by 20.0$$^\\circ$$C will be :</p>\n<p>(Given gas constant R = 8.3 JK<sup>$$-$$1</sup>-mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "249 J",
      "415 J",
      "498 J",
      "830 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "498 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l547fxhp",
    "question": "<p>In van der Waal equation $$\\left[ {P + {a \\over {{V^2}}}} \\right]$$ [V $$-$$ b] = RT; P is pressure, V is volume, R is universal gas constant and T is temperature. The ratio of constants $${a \\over b}$$ is dimensionally equal to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${P \\over V}$$",
      "$${V \\over P}$$",
      "PV",
      "PV<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "PV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54v5c4q",
    "question": "<p>A vessel contains 16g of hydrogen and 128g of oxygen at standard temperature and pressure. The volume of the vessel in cm<sup>3</sup> is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "72 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>",
      "32 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup>",
      "27 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup>",
      "54 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "27 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55k1zzq",
    "question": "<p>What will be the effect on the root mean square velocity of oxygen molecules if the temperature is doubled and oxygen molecule dissociates into atomic oxygen?</p>",
    "options": [
      "The velocity of atomic oxygen remains same",
      "The velocity of atomic oxygen doubles",
      "The velocity of atomic oxygen becomes half",
      "The velocity of atomic oxygen becomes four times"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "The velocity of atomic oxygen doubles"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57qkk8f",
    "question": "<p>A mixture of hydrogen and oxygen has volume 2000 cm<sup>3</sup>, temperature 300 K, pressure 100 kPa and mass 0.76 g. The ratio of number of moles of hydrogen to number of moles of oxygen in the mixture will be:</p>\n<p>[Take gas constant R = 8.3 JK<sup>$$-$$1</sup>mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 3}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 1}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 16}$$",
      "$${16 \\over 1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58bmg2b",
    "question": "<p>A thermally insulated vessel contains an ideal gas of molecular mass M and ratio of specific heats 1.4. Vessel is moving with speed v and is suddenly brought to rest. Assuming no heat is lost to the surrounding and vessel temperature of the gas increases by :</p>\n<p>(R = universal gas constant)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${{M{v^2}} \\over {7R}}$$",
      "$${{M{v^2}} \\over {5R}}$$",
      "2$${{M{v^2}} \\over {7R}}$$",
      "7$${{M{v^2}} \\over {5R}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${{M{v^2}} \\over {5R}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58ho01i",
    "question": "<p>A flask contains argon and oxygen in the ratio of 3 : 2 in mass and the mixture is kept at 27$$^\\circ$$C. The ratio of their average kinetic energy per molecule respectively will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 : 2",
      "9 : 4",
      "2 : 3",
      "1 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "1 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5akciog",
    "question": "<p>The relation between root mean square speed (v<sub>rms</sub>) and most probable sped (v<sub>p</sub>) for the molar mass M of oxygen gas molecule at the temperature of 300 K will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${v_{rms}} = \\sqrt {{2 \\over 3}} {v_p}$$",
      "$${v_{rms}} = \\sqrt {{3 \\over 2}} {v_p}$$",
      "$${v_{rms}} = {v_p}$$",
      "$${v_{rms}} = \\sqrt {{1 \\over 3}} {v_p}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$${v_{rms}} = \\sqrt {{3 \\over 2}} {v_p}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w2ab6v",
    "question": "<p>The pressure of the gas in a constant volume gas thermometer is 100 cm of mercury when placed in melting ice at 1 atm. When the bulb is placed in a liquid, the pressure becomes 180 cm of mercury. Temperature of the liquid is :</p>\n<p>(Given 0$$^\\circ$$C = 273 K)</p>",
    "options": [
      "300 K",
      "400 K",
      "600 K",
      "491 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "491 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f51n2q",
    "question": "<p>Sound travels in a mixture of two moles of helium and n moles of hydrogen. If rms speed of gas molecules in the mixture is $$\\sqrt2$$ times the speed of sound, then the value of n will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "2",
      "3",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gmsotu",
    "question": "<p>7 mol of a certain monoatomic ideal gas undergoes a temperature increase of $$40 \\mathrm{~K}$$ at constant pressure. The increase in the internal energy of the gas in this process is :</p>\n<p>(Given $$\\mathrm{R}=8.3 \\,\\mathrm{JK}^{-1} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "5810 J",
      "3486 J",
      "11620 J",
      "6972 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "3486 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jhlhju",
    "question": "<p>Same gas is filled in two vessels of the same volume at the same temperature. If the ratio of the number of molecules is $$1: 4$$, then</p>\n<p>A. The r.m.s. velocity of gas molecules in two vessels will be the same.</p>\n<p>B. The ratio of pressure in these vessels will be $$1: 4$$.</p>\n<p>C. The ratio of pressure will be $$1: 1$$.</p>\n<p>D. The r.m.s. velocity of gas molecules in two vessels will be in the ratio of $$1: 4$$.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and C only",
      "B and D only",
      "A and B only",
      "C and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "A and B only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6m9z6gc",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The average momentum of a molecule in a sample of an ideal gas depends on temperature.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The rms speed of oxygen molecules in a gas is $$v$$. If the temperature is doubled and the oxygen molecules dissociate into oxygen atoms, the rms speed will become $$2 v$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nri3bg",
    "question": "<p>A vessel contains $$14 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of nitrogen gas at a temperature of $$27^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. The amount of heat to be transferred to the gas to double the r.m.s speed of its molecules will be :</p>\n<p>Take $$\\mathrm{R}=8.32 \\mathrm{~J} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1} \\,\\mathrm{k}^{-1}$$.</p>",
    "options": [
      "2229 J",
      "5616 J",
      "9360 J",
      "13,104 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "9360 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rhrrge",
    "question": "<p>The root mean square speed of smoke particles of mass $$5 \\times 10^{-17} \\mathrm{~kg}$$ in their Brownian motion in air at NTP is approximately. [Given $$\\mathrm{k}=1.38 \\times 10^{-23} \\mathrm{JK}^{-1}$$]</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$60 \\mathrm{~mm} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$",
      "$$12 \\mathrm{~mm} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$",
      "$$15 \\mathrm{~mm} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$",
      "$$36 \\mathrm{~mm} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$15 \\mathrm{~mm} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldogfhjn",
    "question": "<p>$$\\left(P+\\frac{a}{V^{2}}\\right)(V-b)=R T$$ represents the equation of state of some gases. Where $$P$$ is the pressure, $$V$$ is the volume, $$T$$ is the temperature and $$a, b, R$$ are the constants. The physical quantity, which has dimensional formula as that of $$\\frac{b^{2}}{a}$$, will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Energy density",
      "Bulk modulus",
      "Modulus of rigidity",
      "Compressibility"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "Compressibility"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldogglba",
    "question": "<p>The average kinetic energy of a molecule of the gas is</p>",
    "options": [
      "proportional to volume",
      "dependent on the nature of the gas",
      "proportional to absolute temperature",
      "proportional to pressure"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "proportional to absolute temperature"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpmjfey",
    "question": "<p>The correct relation between $$\\gamma  = {{{c_p}} \\over {{c_v}}}$$ and temperature T is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\gamma \\propto T$$",
      "$$\\gamma \\propto {1 \\over {\\sqrt T }}$$",
      "$$\\gamma \\propto {1 \\over T}$$",
      "$$\\gamma \\propto T^\\circ $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$\\gamma \\propto T^\\circ $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqvp4sz",
    "question": "A flask contains hydrogen and oxygen in the ratio of $2: 1$ by mass at temperature $27^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$. The ratio of average kinetic energy per molecule of hydrogen and oxygen respectively is:",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "4 : 1",
      "1 : 4",
      "2 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "1 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr10ozk",
    "question": "<p>The pressure $$(\\mathrm{P})$$ and temperature ($$\\mathrm{T})$$ relationship of an ideal gas obeys the equation\n\n$$\\mathrm{PT}^{2}=$$ constant. The volume expansion coefficient of the gas will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3 T^{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3}{T^2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3}{T^3}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3}{T}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{3}{T}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsb4on3",
    "question": "<p>At 300 K, the rms speed of oxygen molecules is $$\\sqrt {{{\\alpha  + 5} \\over \\alpha }} $$ times to that of its average speed in the gas. Then, the value of $$\\alpha$$ will be</p>\n<p>(used $$\\pi  = {{22} \\over 7}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "27",
      "28",
      "24",
      "32"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "28"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldugujbl",
    "question": "<p>The root mean square velocity of molecules of gas is</p>",
    "options": [
      "Proportional to temperature ($$T$$)",
      "Inversely proportional to square root of temperature $$\\left( {\\sqrt {{1 \\over T}} } \\right)$$",
      "Proportional to square of temperature ($$T^2$$)",
      "Proportional to square root of temperature ($$\\sqrt T$$)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "Proportional to square root of temperature ($$\\sqrt T$$)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyeadfl",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The temperature of a gas is $$-73^\\circ$$C. When the gas is heated to $$527^\\circ$$C, the root mean square speed of the molecules is doubled.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The product of pressure and volume of an ideal gas will be equal to translational kinetic energy of the molecules.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the option given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnytfbn",
    "question": "A flask contains Hydrogen and Argon in the ratio $2: 1$ by mass. The temperature of the mixture is $30^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$. The ratio of average kinetic energy per molecule of the two gases ( $\\mathrm{K}$ argon/K hydrogen) is :\n<br/><br/>\n(Given: Atomic Weight of $\\mathrm{Ar}=39.9$ )\n",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{39.9}{2}$",
      "2",
      "39.9",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgozkn8g",
    "question": "<p>The initial pressure and volume of an ideal gas are P$$_0$$ and V$$_0$$. The final pressure of the gas when the gas is suddenly compressed to volume $$\\frac{V_0}{4}$$ will be :</p>\n<p>(Given $$\\gamma$$ = ratio of specific heats at constant pressure and at constant volume)</p>",
    "options": [
      "P$$_0$$(4)$$^{\\frac{1}{\\gamma}}$$",
      "P$$_0$$",
      "4P$$_0$$",
      "P$$_0$$(4)$$^{\\gamma}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "P$$_0$$(4)$$^{\\gamma}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrjg437",
    "question": "<p>If the r. m.s speed of chlorine molecule is $$490 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ at $$27^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$, the r. m. s speed of argon molecules at the same temperature will be (Atomic mass of argon $$=39.9 \\mathrm{u}$$, molecular mass of chlorine $$=70.9 \\mathrm{u}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$451.7 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$751.7 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$551.7 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$651.7 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$651.7 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsxcf9c",
    "question": "<p>The root mean square speed of molecules of nitrogen gas at $$27^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ is approximately : (Given mass of a nitrogen molecule $$=4.6 \\times 10^{-26} \\mathrm{~kg}$$ and take Boltzmann constant $$\\mathrm{k}_{\\mathrm{B}}=1.4 \\times 10^{-23} \\mathrm{JK}^{-1}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "91 m/s",
      "1260 m/s",
      "27.4 m/s",
      "523 m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "523 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvrb5w2",
    "question": "<p>A gas mixture consists of 2 moles of oxygen and 4 moles of neon at temperature T. Neglecting all vibrational modes, the total internal energy of the system will be,</p>",
    "options": [
      "4RT",
      "16RT",
      "8RT",
      "11RT"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "11RT"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqtlfw",
    "question": "<p>The temperature at which the kinetic energy of oxygen molecules becomes double than its value at $$27^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$627^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$927^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$327^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$",
      "$$1227^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$327^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh25jt13",
    "question": "<p>The number of air molecules per cm$$^3$$ increased from $$3\\times10^{19}$$ to $$12\\times10^{19}$$. The ratio of collision frequency of air molecules before and after the increase in number respectively is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.25",
      "0.25",
      "0.50",
      "0.75"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "0.25"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh2zqgi8",
    "question": "<p>The temperature of an ideal gas is increased from $$200 \\mathrm{~K}$$ to $$800 \\mathrm{~K}$$. If r.m.s. speed of gas at $$200 \\mathrm{~K}$$ is $$v_{0}$$. Then, r.m.s. speed of the gas at $$800 \\mathrm{~K}$$ will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$v_{0}$$",
      "$$2 v_{0}$$",
      "$$4 v_{0}$$",
      "$$\\frac{v_{0}}{4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$2 v_{0}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh30nbav",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of speed of sound in hydrogen gas to the speed of sound in oxygen gas at the same temperature is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: 1$$",
      "$$1: 2$$",
      "$$1: 4$$",
      "$$4: 1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$4: 1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsan06k0",
    "question": "If the root mean square velocity of hydrogen molecule at a given temperature and pressure is $2 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{s}$, the root mean square velocity of oxygen at the same condition in $\\mathrm{km} / \\mathrm{s}$ is :",
    "options": [
      "1.0",
      "1.5",
      "2.0",
      "0.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "0.5"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbl72nk",
    "question": "The pressure and volume of an ideal gas are related as $\\mathrm{PV}^{\\frac{3}{2}}=\\mathrm{K}$ (Constant). The work done when the gas is taken from state $A\\left(P_1, V_1, T_1\\right)$ to state $B\\left(P_2, V_2, T_2\\right)$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$2\\left(\\mathrm{P}_2 \\sqrt{\\mathrm{V}_2}-\\mathrm{P}_1 \\sqrt{\\mathrm{V}_1}\\right)$",
      "$2\\left(\\sqrt{\\mathrm{P}_1} \\mathrm{~V}_1-\\sqrt{\\mathrm{P}_2} \\mathrm{~V}_2\\right)$",
      "$2\\left(\\mathrm{P}_2 \\mathrm{~V}_2-\\mathrm{P}_1 \\mathrm{~V}_1\\right)$",
      "$2\\left(\\mathrm{P}_1 \\mathrm{~V}_1-\\mathrm{P}_2 \\mathrm{~V}_2\\right)$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$2\\left(\\mathrm{P}_1 \\mathrm{~V}_1-\\mathrm{P}_2 \\mathrm{~V}_2\\right)$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscpgjpr",
    "question": "<p>The equation of state of a real gas is given by $$\\left(\\mathrm{P}+\\frac{\\mathrm{a}}{\\mathrm{V}^2}\\right)(\\mathrm{V}-\\mathrm{b})=\\mathrm{RT}$$, where $$\\mathrm{P}, \\mathrm{V}$$ and $$\\mathrm{T}$$ are pressure, volume and temperature respectively and $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is the universal gas constant. The dimensions of $$\\frac{\\mathrm{a}}{\\mathrm{b}^2}$$ is similar to that of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "P",
      "RT",
      "PV",
      "R"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "P"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscpmq3f",
    "question": "<p>The total kinetic energy of 1 mole of oxygen at $$27^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ is :\n[Use universal gas constant $$(R)=8.31 \\mathrm{~J} /$$ mole K]</p>",
    "options": [
      "6232.5 J",
      "5670.5 J",
      "6845.5 J",
      "5942.0 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "6232.5 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd5uul8",
    "question": "<p>The speed of sound in oxygen at S.T.P. will be approximately: (given, $$R=8.3 \\mathrm{~JK}^{-1}, \\gamma=1.4$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "341 m/s",
      "333 m/s",
      "325 m/s",
      "315 m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "315 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse68uaj",
    "question": "<p>The parameter that remains the same for molecules of all gases at a given temperature is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "kinetic energy\n",
      "mass\n",
      "momentum\n",
      "speed"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "kinetic energy\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1r1av",
    "question": "<p>Two vessels $$A$$ and $$B$$ are of the same size and are at same temperature. A contains $$1 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of hydrogen and $$B$$ contains $$1 \\mathrm{~g}$$ of oxygen. $$\\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{A}}$$ and $$\\mathrm{P}_{\\mathrm{B}}$$ are the pressures of the gases in $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$ respectively, then $$\\frac{P_A}{P_B}$$ is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "32",
      "8",
      "16"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "16"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfls6eq",
    "question": "<p>The temperature of a gas having $$2.0 \\times 10^{25}$$ molecules per cubic meter at $$1.38 \\mathrm{~atm}$$ (Given, $$\\mathrm{k}=1.38 \\times 10^{-23} \\mathrm{JK}^{-1}$$) is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "500 K",
      "300 K",
      "200 K",
      "100 K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "500 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgdgm07",
    "question": "<p>At which temperature the r.m.s. velocity of a hydrogen molecule equal to that of an oxygen molecule at $$47^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "20 K",
      "80 K",
      "4 K",
      "$$-73$$ K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "20 K"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwco4g",
    "question": "<p>The temperature of a gas is $$-78^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ and the average translational kinetic energy of its molecules is $$\\mathrm{K}$$. The temperature at which the average translational kinetic energy of the molecules of the same gas becomes $$2 \\mathrm{~K}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-78^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$\n",
      "$$127^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$\n",
      "$$-39^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$\n",
      "$$117^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$117^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3veaso",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : The mean free path of gas molecules is inversely proportional to square of molecular diameter.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : Average kinetic energy of gas molecules is directly proportional to absolute temperature of gas.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v4o98",
    "question": "<p>If the collision frequency of hydrogen molecules in a closed chamber at $$27^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ is $$\\mathrm{Z}$$, then the collision frequency of the same system at $$127^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2} \\mathrm{Z}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{2}{\\sqrt{3}} \\mathrm{Z}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{3}{4} \\mathrm{Z}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{4}{3} \\mathrm{Z}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{2}{\\sqrt{3}} \\mathrm{Z}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s23wk",
    "question": "<p>If $$\\mathrm{n}$$ is the number density and $$\\mathrm{d}$$ is the diameter of the molecule, then the average distance covered by a molecule between two successive collisions (i.e. mean free path) is represented by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2} \\mathrm{n} \\pi \\mathrm{d}^2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2} n^2 \\pi^2 d^2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2 n \\pi d^2}}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{2} \\mathrm{n} \\pi \\mathrm{d}^2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2} \\mathrm{n} \\pi \\mathrm{d}^2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29efa",
    "question": "<p>A total of $$48 \\mathrm{~J}$$ heat is given to one mole of helium kept in a cylinder. The temperature of helium increases by $$2^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. The work done by the gas is:\nGiven, $$\\mathrm{R}=8.3 \\mathrm{~J} \\mathrm{~K}^{-1} \\mathrm{~mol}^{-1}$$.</p>",
    "options": [
      "23.1 J",
      "48 J",
      "24.9 J",
      "72.9 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "23.1 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57i7u",
    "question": "<p>A sample contains mixture of helium and oxygen gas. The ratio of root mean square speed of helium and oxygen in the sample, is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{2 \\sqrt{2}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{4}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{2 \\sqrt{2}}{1}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{32}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "kinetic-theory-of-gases-and-gas-laws",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{2 \\sqrt{2}}{1}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "p9pw0pPuGDcwMcYi",
    "question": "Heat given to a body which raises its temperature by $${1^ \\circ }C$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "water equivalent ",
      "thermal capacity ",
      "specific heat ",
      "temperature gradient "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "thermal capacity "
  },
  {
    "id": "PdZBrJ3r2oWdvvgs",
    "question": "Time taken by a $$836$$ $$W$$ heater to heat one litre of water from $$10{}^ \\circ C$$ to $$40{}^ \\circ C$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$150$$ $$s$$ ",
      "$$100$$ $$s$$ ",
      "$$50$$ $$s$$ ",
      "$$200$$ $$s$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "$$150$$ $$s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "w4tsdA6ByCH4Xlro",
    "question": "Assume that a drop of liquid evaporates by decreases in its surface energy, so that its temperature remains unchanged. What should be the minimum radius of the drop for this to be possible ? The surface tension is $$T,$$ density of liquid is $$\\rho $$ and $$L$$ is its latent heat of vaporization. ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\rho L/T$$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt {T/\\rho L} $$ ",
      "$$T/\\rho L$$ ",
      "$$2T/\\rho L$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "$$2T/\\rho L$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "73fG3Emr0PyubcHvpDd5u",
    "question": "200 g water is heated from 40<sup>o</sup>C to 60<sup>o</sup>C. Ignoring the slight expansion of water, the change in its internal energy is close to (Given specific heat of water = 4184 J/kg/K) :",
    "options": [
      "8.4 kJ",
      "4.2 kJ",
      "16.7 kJ",
      "167.4 kJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "16.7 kJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "m8buGfkTMHHXb97h",
    "question": "A copper ball of mass 100 gm is at a temperature T. It is dropped in a copper calorimeter of mass 100 gm,\nfilled with 170 gm of water at room temperature. Subsequently, the temperature of the system is found to\nbe 75<sup>o</sup>C. T is given by: (Given : room temperature = 30<sup>o</sup>C, specific heat of copper = 0.1 cal/gm<sup>o</sup>C) ",
    "options": [
      "825<sup>o</sup>C ",
      "800<sup>o</sup>C",
      "885<sup>o</sup>C",
      "1250<sup>o</sup>C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "885<sup>o</sup>C"
  },
  {
    "id": "PBqFAIUbQh46dmcET2nsP",
    "question": "In an experiment, a sphere of aluminium of mass 0.20 kg is heated upto 150<sup>o</sup><sup></sup>C. Immediately, it is put into water of volume 150 cc at 27<sup>o</sup>C kept in a calorimeter of water equivalent to 0.025 kg. Final temperature of the system is 40<sup>o</sup>C. The specific heat of aluminium is : (take 4.2 Joule = 1 calorie)\n",
    "options": [
      "378 J/kg $$-$$<sup>o</sup>C",
      "315 J/kg $$-$$<sup>o</sup>C",
      "476 J/kg $$-$$<sup>o</sup>C",
      "434 J/kg $$-$$<sup>o</sup>C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "434 J/kg $$-$$<sup>o</sup>C"
  },
  {
    "id": "Y9S8VSVchZtYzf6AAnCqc",
    "question": "An unknown metal of mass 192 g heated to a temperature of 100<sup>o</sup>C was immersed into a brass calorimeter of mass 128 g containing 240 g of water at a temperature of 8.4<sup>o</sup>C. Calculate the specific heat of the unknown metal if water temperature stabilizes at 21.5<sup>o</sup>C. (Specific heat of brass is 394 J kg<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "458 J kg<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>",
      "1232 J kg<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>",
      "654 J kg<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>",
      "916 J kg<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "916 J kg<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "xxbIhbYH4jJG4sIDBboVo",
    "question": "Ice at –20<sup>o</sup>C is added to 50 g of water at 40<sup>o</sup>C. When the temperature of the mixture reaches 0<sup>o</sup>C, it is found that 20 g of ice is still unmelted. The amount of ice added to the water was close to (Specific heat of water = 4.2J/g/<sup>o</sup>C Specific heat of Ice = 2.1J/g/<sup>o</sup>C Heat of fusion of water at 0<sup>o</sup>C= 334J/g)\n",
    "options": [
      "100 g",
      "60 g",
      "50 g",
      "40 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "40 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "DwfLvMCr0LpNvhouT8gC1",
    "question": "When 100 g of a liquid A at 100<sup>o</sup>C is added to 50 g of a liquid B at temperature 75<sup>o</sup>C, the temperature of the mixture becomes 90<sup>o</sup>C. The temperature of the mixture, if 100 g of liquid A at 100<sup>o</sup>C is added to 50 g of liquid B at 50<sup>o</sup>C, will be : ",
    "options": [
      "60<sup>o</sup>C",
      "70<sup>o</sup>C",
      "85<sup>o</sup>C",
      "80<sup>o</sup>C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "80<sup>o</sup>C"
  },
  {
    "id": "bfUiMaYwBtFrFmZZ3KdBX",
    "question": "A metal ball of mass 0.1 kg is heated upto 500<sup>o</sup>C and dropped into a vessel of heat capacity 800 JK<sup>–1</sup> and containing 0.5 kg water. The initial temperature of water and vessel is 30<sup>o</sup>C. What is the approximate percentage increment in the temperature of the water? [Specific Heat Capacities of water and metal are, respectively, 4200 Jkg<sup>–1</sup> and 400 Jkg<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>\n",
    "options": [
      "20%",
      "25%",
      "15%",
      "30%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "20%"
  },
  {
    "id": "9scdtfJGNx08W7qOuJB4F",
    "question": "A thermally insulated vessel contains 150g of\nwater at 0°C. Then the air from the vessel is\npumped out adiabatically. A fraction of water\nturns into ice and the rest evaporates at 0°C\nitself. The mass of evaporated water will be\nclosest to :\n(Latent heat of vaporization of water\n= 2.10 × 10<sup>6</sup> J kg<sup>–1</sup> and Latent heat of Fusion\nof water = 3.36 × 10<sup>5</sup> J kg<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "35 g",
      "130 g",
      "20 g",
      "150 g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "20 g"
  },
  {
    "id": "pukagGVR02XHr15lnwERI",
    "question": "A massless spring (k = 800 N/m), attached with\na mass (500 g) is completely immersed in 1 kg\nof water. The spring is stretched by 2 cm and\nreleased so that it starts vibrating. What would\nbe the order of magnitude of the change in the\ntemperature of water when the vibrations stop\ncompletely ? (Assume that the water container\nand spring receive negligible heat and specific\nheat of mass = 400 J/kg K, specific heat of\nwater = 4184 J/kg K)",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>–3</sup> K",
      "10<sup>–1</sup> K",
      "10<sup>–5</sup>K",
      "10<sup>–4 </sup>K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "10<sup>–5</sup>K"
  },
  {
    "id": "EAZwNsvKvmhHFGOaaB3rsa0w2w9jx3pfzz9",
    "question": "When M<sub>1</sub> gram of ice at –10<sup>o</sup>C (specific heat = 0.5 cal g<sup>–1</sup>\n<sup>o</sup>C<sup>–1</sup>\n) is added to M<sub>2</sub> gram of water at 50C, finally\nno ice is left and the water is at 0°C. The value of latent heat of ice, in cal g<sup>–1</sup>\n is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{50{M_2}} \\over {{M_1}}} - 5$$",
      "$${{50{M_2}} \\over {{M_1}}}$$",
      "$${{5{M_2}} \\over {{M_1}}} - 5$$",
      "$${{5{M_1}} \\over {{M_2}}} - 50$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "$${{50{M_2}} \\over {{M_1}}} - 5$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "wwRshZJkaDInCamqZP3rsa0w2w9jx6rc23k",
    "question": "One kg of water, at 20<sup>o</sup>C, heated in an electric kettle whose heating element has a mean (temperature\naveraged) resistance of 20 $$\\Omega $$. The rms voltage in the mains is 200 V. Ignoring heat loss from the kettle, time\ntaken for water to evaporate fully, is close to :\n[Specific heat of water = 4200 J/(kg <sup>o</sup>C), Latent heat of water = 2260 kJ/kg]",
    "options": [
      "10 minutes",
      "22 minutes",
      "3 minutes",
      "16 minutes"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "22 minutes"
  },
  {
    "id": "JZcpM9fe01VEwHAglwjgy2xukfdquq1c",
    "question": "A bullet of mass 5 g, travelling with a speed of\n210 m/s, strikes a fixed wooden target. One half\nof its kinetic energy is converted into heat in\nthe bullet while the other half is converted into\nheat in the wood. The rise of temperature of\nthe bullet if the specific heat of its material is\n0.030 cal/(g – <sup>o</sup>C) (1 cal = 4.2 × 10<sup>7</sup> ergs) close\nto :",
    "options": [
      "87.5 <sup>o</sup>C",
      "83.3 <sup>o</sup>C",
      "38.4 <sup>o</sup>C",
      "119.2 <sup>o</sup>C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "87.5 <sup>o</sup>C"
  },
  {
    "id": "bFlMPZTaYkrTxH2NMmjgy2xukf3vrusv",
    "question": "A calorimeter of water equivalent 20 g contains 180 g of water at 25<sup>o</sup>C. ‘m’ grams of steam at\n100<sup>o</sup>C is mixed in it till the temperature of the mixure is 31<sup>o</sup>C. The value of ‘m’ is close to :<br/>(Latent\nheat of water = 540 cal g<sup>–1</sup>, specific heat of water = 1 cal g<sup>–1</sup> <sup>o</sup>C<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "2.6",
      "2",
      "4",
      "3.2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "JAivoVHixP6yfzWUcGjgy2xuketxsk72",
    "question": "The specific heat of water<br/> = 4200 J kg<sup>-1</sup>K<sup>-1</sup> and the latent heat of<br/> ice = 3.4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup> J kg<sup>–1</sup>. 100 grams of ice at<br/> 0<sup>o</sup>C is placed in 200 g of water at 25<sup>o</sup>C. The <br/>amount of ice that will melt as the temperature<br/> of water reaches 0<sup>o</sup>C is close to (in grams) :",
    "options": [
      "63.8",
      "61.7",
      "69.3",
      "64.6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "61.7"
  },
  {
    "id": "uWx2vVr9cgMamH8hmF7k9k2k5dkln9i",
    "question": "Two moles of an ideal gas with $${{{C_P}} \\over {{C_V}}} = {5 \\over 3}$$\nare mixed with 3 moles of another ideal gas\nwith $${{{C_P}} \\over {{C_V}}} = {4 \\over 3}$$. The value of $${{{C_P}} \\over {{C_V}}}$$ for the\nmixture is :\n",
    "options": [
      "1.50",
      "1.45",
      "1.47",
      "1.42"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "1.42"
  },
  {
    "id": "gqLMEbACUGzGo3A1Yf1krplrqkm",
    "question": "The amount of heat needed to raise the temperature of 4 moles of  rigid diatomic gas from 0$$^\\circ$$ C to 50$$^\\circ$$ C when no work is done is ___________. (R is the universal gas constant).",
    "options": [
      "500 R",
      "250 R",
      "750 R",
      "175 R"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "500 R"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktbmyhe5",
    "question": "The temperature of equal masses of three different liquids x, y and z are 10$$^\\circ$$C, 20$$^\\circ$$C and 30$$^\\circ$$C respectively. The temperature of mixture when x is mixed with y is 16$$^\\circ$$C and that when y is mixed with z is 26$$^\\circ$$C. The temperature of mixture when x and z are mixed will be :",
    "options": [
      "28.32$$^\\circ$$C",
      "25.62$$^\\circ$$C",
      "23.84$$^\\circ$$C",
      "20.28$$^\\circ$$C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "23.84$$^\\circ$$C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfn90in",
    "question": "The height of victoria falls is 63 m. What is the difference in temperature of water at the top and at the bottom of fall?<br/><br/>[Given 1 cal = 4.2 J and specific heat of water = 1 cal g<sup>$$-$$1</sup> $$^\\circ$$0C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "0.147$$^\\circ$$ C",
      "14.76$$^\\circ$$ C",
      "1.476$$^\\circ$$ C",
      "0.014$$^\\circ$$ C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "0.147$$^\\circ$$ C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56utt40",
    "question": "<p>A lead bullet penetrates into a solid object and melts. Assuming that 40% of its kinetic energy is used to heat it, the initial speed of bullet is :</p>\n<p>(Given : initial temperature of the bullet = 127$$^\\circ$$C, Melting point of the bullet = 327$$^\\circ$$C, Latent heat of fusion of lead = 2.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup> J kg<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, Specific heat capacity of lead = 125 J/kg K)</p>",
    "options": [
      "125 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "500 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "250 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "600 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "500 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59m3hnv",
    "question": "<p>A copper block of mass 5.0 kg is heated to a temperature of 500$$^\\circ$$C and is placed on a large ice block. What is the maximum amount of ice that can melt? [Specific heat of copper : 0.39 J g<sup>$$-$$1</sup> $$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup> and latent heat of fusion of water : 335 J g<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.5 kg",
      "5.8 kg",
      "2.9 kg",
      "3.8 kg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "2.9 kg"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bc1d28",
    "question": "<p>A 100 g of iron nail is hit by a 1.5 kg hammer striking at a velocity of 60 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. What will be the rise in the temperature of the nail if one fourth of energy of the hammer goes into heating the nail?</p>\n<p>[Specific heat capacity of iron = 0.42 Jg<sup>$$-$$1</sup> $$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]</p>",
    "options": [
      "675$$^\\circ$$C",
      "1600$$^\\circ$$C",
      "16.07$$^\\circ$$C",
      "6.75$$^\\circ$$C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "16.07$$^\\circ$$C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lds9yjwc",
    "question": "<p>Heat energy of 184 kJ is given to ice of mass 600 g at $$-12^\\circ \\mathrm{C}$$. Specific heat of ice is $$\\mathrm{2222.3~J~kg^{-1^\\circ}~C^{-1}}$$ and latent heat of ice in 336 $$\\mathrm{kJ/kg^{-1}}$$</p>\n<p>A. Final temperature of system will be 0$$^\\circ$$C.</p>\n<p>B. Final temperature of the system will be greater than 0$$^\\circ$$C.</p>\n<p>C. The final system will have a mixture of ice and water in the ratio of 5 : 1.</p>\n<p>D. The final system will have a mixture of ice and water in the ratio of 1 : 5.</p>\n<p>E. The final system will have water only.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and E only",
      "B and D only",
      "A and C only",
      "A and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "A and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3f7nf",
    "question": "<p>$$0.08 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ air is heated at constant volume through $$5^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. The specific heat of air at constant volume is $$0.17 \\mathrm{~kcal} / \\mathrm{kg}^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ and $$\\mathrm{J}=4.18$$ joule/$$\\mathrm{~cal}$$. The change in its internal energy is approximately.</p>",
    "options": [
      "318 J",
      "298 J",
      "284 J",
      "142 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "284 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2957z",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : Dimensions of specific heat is $$[\\mathrm{L}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2} \\mathrm{~K}^{-1}]$$.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : Dimensions of gas constant is $$[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-1} \\mathrm{~K}^{-1}]$$.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement (I) is incorrect but statement (II) is correct\n",
      "Both statement (I) and statement (II) are incorrect\n",
      "Both statement (I) and statement (II) are correct\n",
      "Statement (I) is correct but statement (II) is incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "Statement (I) is correct but statement (II) is incorrect"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57cty",
    "question": "<p>The specific heat at constant pressure of a real gas obeying $$P V^2=R T$$ equation is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "R",
      "$$C_V+R$$\n",
      "$$C_V+\\frac{R}{2 V}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{R}{3}+C_V$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "specific-heat-capacity,-calorimetry-&-change-of-state",
    "solution": "$$C_V+\\frac{R}{2 V}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "Bdo5Wo5QGqFeXCm3",
    "question": "During an adiabatic process, the pressure of a gas is found to be proportional to the cube of its absolute temperature. The ratio $${C_p}/{C_V}$$ for the gas is ",
    "options": [
      "$${4 \\over 3}$$ ",
      "$$2$$ ",
      "$${5 \\over 3}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "cQ7bgxuWcaSB1sYG",
    "question": "The work of $$146$$ $$kJ$$ is performed in order to compress one kilo mole of gas adiabatically and in this process the temperature of the gas increases by $${7^ \\circ }C.$$ The gas is $$\\left( {R = 8.3J\\,\\,mo{l^{ - 1}}\\,{K^{ - 1}}} \\right)$$ ",
    "options": [
      "diatomic ",
      "triatomic ",
      "a mixture of monoatomic and diatomic ",
      "monoatomic"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "diatomic "
  },
  {
    "id": "qDsE9riSZq9oH9xq",
    "question": "Consider a spherical shell of radius $$R$$ at temperature $$T$$. The black body radiation inside it can be considered as an ideal gas of photons with internal energy per unit volume $$u = {U \\over V}\\, \\propto \\,{T^4}$$ and pressure $$p = {1 \\over 3}\\left( {{U \\over V}} \\right)$$ . If the shell now undergoes an adiabatic expansion the relation between $$T$$ and $$R$$ is: ",
    "options": [
      "$$T\\, \\propto {1 \\over R}$$ ",
      "$$T\\, \\propto {1 \\over {{R^3}}}$$ ",
      "$$T\\, \\propto \\,{e^{ - R}}$$ ",
      "$$T\\, \\propto \\,{e^{ - 3R}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$$T\\, \\propto {1 \\over R}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "9fYG3EF9zUCYN3zW",
    "question": "An ideal gas undergoes a quasi static, reversible process in which its molar heat capacity $$C$$ remains constant. If during this process the relation of pressure $$P$$ and volume $$V$$ is given by $$P{V^n} = $$ constant, then $$n$$ is given by (Here $${C_p}$$ and $${C_v}$$ are molar specific heat at constant pressure and constant volume, respectively:",
    "options": [
      "$$n = {{{C_p} - C} \\over {C - {C_v}}}$$ ",
      "$$n = {{C - {C_v}} \\over {C - {C_p}}}$$ ",
      "$$n = {{{C_p}} \\over {{C_v}}}$$ ",
      "$$n = {{C - {C_p}} \\over {C - {C_v}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$$n = {{C - {C_p}} \\over {C - {C_v}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "37LVjsorAZZAURzCyuJRO",
    "question": "The ratio of work done by an ideal monoatomic gas to the heat supplied to it\nin an isobaric process is :",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 5}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 5}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over 5}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "eHuZq3Bejv3eD1dq",
    "question": "Two moles of an ideal monatomic gas occupies a volume V at 27<sup>o</sup>C. The gas expands adiabatically to a\nvolume 2 V. Calculate (a) the final temperature of the gas and (b) change in its internal energy.",
    "options": [
      "(a) 195 K  (b) 2.7 kJ",
      "(a) 189 K (b) 2.7 kJ",
      "(a) 195 K (b) –2.7 kJ",
      "(a) 189 K (b) – 2.7 kJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "(a) 189 K (b) – 2.7 kJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "eAHGMSeknk5s3DfFL7Ptq",
    "question": "One mole of an ideal monoatomic gas is compressed isothermally in a rigid vessel to double its pressure at room temperature, $${27^ \\circ }C.$$ The work done on the gas will be : ",
    "options": [
      "$$300$$ $$R$$",
      "$$300$$ $$R$$ $$ln$$ $$6$$ ",
      "$$300$$ $$R$$ $$ln$$ $$2$$ ",
      "$$300$$ $$R$$ $$ln$$ $$7$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$$300$$ $$R$$ $$ln$$ $$2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "1jQOswd9eND7CNI0xG3rsa0w2w9jwzi4s2x",
    "question": "One mole of ideal gas passes through a process where pressure and volume obey the relation\n$$P = {P_0}\\left[ {1 - {1 \\over 2}{{\\left( {{{{V_0}} \\over V}} \\right)}^2}} \\right]$$.\nHere P<sub>0</sub> and V<sub>0</sub> are constants. Calculate the change in the temperature of the gas if its\nvolume changes form V<sub>0</sub> to 2V<sub>0</sub>",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 4}{{{P_0}{V_0}} \\over R}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}{{{P_0}{V_0}} \\over R}$$",
      "$${5 \\over 4}{{{P_0}{V_0}} \\over R}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}{{{P_0}{V_0}} \\over R}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$${5 \\over 4}{{{P_0}{V_0}} \\over R}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "db2z1YbN0RodtG5y4i18hoxe66ijvztlnmy",
    "question": "n moles of an ideal gas with constant volume\nheat capcity C<sub>V</sub> undergo an isobaric expansion\nby certain volume. The ratio of the work done\nin the process, to the heat supplied is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{nR} \\over {{C_V} - nR}}$$",
      "$${{4nR} \\over {{C_V} - nR}}$$",
      "$${{4nR} \\over {{C_V} + nR}}$$",
      "$${{nR} \\over {{C_V} + nR}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$${{nR} \\over {{C_V} + nR}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "PbkKJiwsz1Bvn7lHXHUZc",
    "question": "In a process, temperature and volume of one mole of an ideal monoatomic gas are varied according to the relation VT = K, where K is a constant. In this process the temperature of the gas is increased by $$\\Delta $$T. The\namount of heat absorbed by gas is (R is gas constant) : ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$ KR$$\\Delta $$T",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$ R$$\\Delta $$T",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$ R$$\\Delta $$T",
      "$${2K \\over 3}$$ $$\\Delta $$T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}$$ R$$\\Delta $$T"
  },
  {
    "id": "TlvR0hlvkD43IJNRYfvW6",
    "question": "A rigid diatomic ideal gas undergoes an adiabatic process at room temperature. The relation between temperature and volume for this process is TV<sup>x</sup>  = constant, then x is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${5 \\over 3}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 5}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 5}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over 5}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xO2KAckBRKc7N6yJvsjgy2xukfl3wcwy",
    "question": "In an adiabatic process, the density of a\ndiatomic gas becomes 32 times its initial value.\nThe final pressure of the gas is found to be n\ntimes the initial pressure. The value of n is :",
    "options": [
      "128",
      "32",
      "326",
      "$${1 \\over {32}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "128"
  },
  {
    "id": "yw27ZfrN1jXuiyVJNNjgy2xukfahogtq",
    "question": "Match the thermodynamic processes taking place in a system with the correct conditions. In the\ntable : $$\\Delta $$Q is the heat supplied, $$\\Delta $$W is the work done and $$\\Delta $$U is change in internal energy of the\nsystem.\n<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\"><b>Process</b></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\"><b>Condition</b>\n</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I) Adiabatic</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(1) $$\\Delta $$W = 0</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II) Isothermal</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(2) $$\\Delta $$Q = 0\n</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III) Isochoric</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(3) $$\\Delta $$U $$ \\ne $$ 0, $$\\Delta $$W $$ \\ne $$ 0,\n $$\\Delta $$Q $$ \\ne $$ 0</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV) Isobaric</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(4) $$\\Delta $$U = 0\n</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table>",
    "options": [
      "(I) - (1), (II) - (1), (III) - (2), (IV) - (3)",
      "(I) - (2), (II) - (4), (III) - (1), (IV) - (3)",
      "(I) - (1), (II) - (2), (III) - (4), (IV) - (4)",
      "(I) - (2), (II) - (1), (III) - (4), (IV) - (3)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "(I) - (2), (II) - (4), (III) - (1), (IV) - (3)"
  },
  {
    "id": "6z2uwDk0IqiA27WtDHjgy2xukf169bn6",
    "question": "A balloon filled with helium (32<sup>o</sup>C and 1.7 atm.)\nbursts. Immediately afterwards the expansion\nof helium can be considered as",
    "options": [
      "Irreversible adiabatic",
      "Reversible adiabatic",
      "Irreversible isothermal",
      "Reversible isothermal"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "Irreversible adiabatic"
  },
  {
    "id": "vbAyya031H3KKQdbIm7k9k2k5dtnp2f",
    "question": "A litre of dry air at STP expands adiabatically to a volume of 3 litres. If $$\\gamma $$ = 1.40, the work done by air is : (3<sup>1.4</sup> = 4.6555) [Take air to be an ideal gas]",
    "options": [
      "60.7 J",
      "100.8 J",
      "90.5 J",
      "48 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "90.5 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "Q9ZnZCWSeC2CyGzOuJ1klrh6cbf",
    "question": "Match List I with List II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Isothermal</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>Pressure constant</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Isochoric</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>Temperature constant</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Adiabatic</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>Volume constant</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Isobaric</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>Heat content is constant</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a) - (ii), (b) - (iii), (c) - (iv), (d) - (i)",
      "(a) - (ii), (b) - (iv), (c) - (iii), (d) - (i)",
      "(a) - (iii), (b) - (ii), (c) - (i), (d) - (iv)",
      "(a) - (i), (b) - (iii), (c) - (ii), (d) - (iv)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "(a) - (ii), (b) - (iii), (c) - (iv), (d) - (i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "ENeG2yFWa6drdsi2WH1kmlwacmy",
    "question": "For an adiabatic expansion of an ideal gas, the fractional change in its pressure is equal to (where $$\\gamma$$ is the ratio of specific heats) :",
    "options": [
      "$$ - {1 \\over \\gamma }{{dV} \\over V}$$",
      "$$ - \\gamma {V \\over {dV}}$$",
      "$$ - \\gamma {{dV} \\over V}$$",
      "$${{dV} \\over V}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$$ - \\gamma {{dV} \\over V}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kruk24vq",
    "question": "A monoatomic ideal gas, initially at temperature T<sub>1</sub> is enclosed in a cylinder fitted with a frictionless piston. The gas is allowed to expand adiabatically to a temperature T<sub>2</sub> by releasing the piston suddenly. If l<sub>1</sub> and l<sub>2</sub> are the lengths of the gas column, before and after the expansion respectively, then the value of $${{{T_1}} \\over {{T_2}}}$$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left( {{{{l_1}} \\over {{l_2}}}} \\right)^{{2 \\over 3}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{{l_2}} \\over {{l_1}}}} \\right)^{{2 \\over 3}}}$$",
      "$${{{l_2}} \\over {{l_1}}}$$",
      "$${{{l_1}} \\over {{l_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$${\\left( {{{{l_2}} \\over {{l_1}}}} \\right)^{{2 \\over 3}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks0k4p91",
    "question": "One mole of an ideal gas is taken through an adiabatic process where the temperature rises from 27$$^\\circ$$ C to 37$$^\\circ$$ C. If the ideal gas is composed of polyatomic molecule that has 4 vibrational modes, which of the following is true? [R = 8.314 J mol<sup>$$-$$1</sup> k<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "work done by the gas is close to 332 J",
      "work done on the gas is close to 582 J",
      "work done by the gas is close to 582 J",
      "work done on the gas is close to 332 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "work done on the gas is close to 582 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54uy534",
    "question": "<p>Starting with the same initial conditions, an ideal gas expands from volume V<sub>1</sub> to V<sub>2</sub> in three different ways. The work done by the gas is W<sub>1</sub> if the process is purely isothermal, W<sub>2</sub>, if the process is purely adiabatic and W<sub>3</sub> if the process is purely isobaric. Then, choose the correct option</p>",
    "options": [
      "W<sub>1</sub> < W<sub>2</sub> < W<sub>3</sub>",
      "W<sub>2</sub> < W<sub>3</sub> < W<sub>1</sub>",
      "W<sub>3</sub> < W<sub>1</sub> < W<sub>2</sub>",
      "W<sub>2</sub> < W<sub>1</sub> < W<sub>3</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "W<sub>2</sub> < W<sub>1</sub> < W<sub>3</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5693oxw",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : When $$\\mu$$ amount of an ideal gas undergoes adiabatic change from state (P<sub>1</sub>, V<sub>1</sub>, T<sub>1</sub>) to state (P<sub>2</sub>, V<sub>2</sub>, T<sub>2</sub>), then work done is $$W = {{\\mu R({T_2} - {T_1})} \\over {1 - \\gamma }}$$, where $$\\gamma  = {{{C_p}} \\over {{C_v}}}$$ and R = universal gas constant.</p>\n<p>Statement II : In the above case, when work is done on the gas, the temperature of the gas would rise.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w2lv8a",
    "question": "<p>A sample of monoatomic gas is taken at initial pressure of 75 kPa. The volume of the gas is then compressed from 1200 cm<sup>3</sup> to 150 cm<sup>3</sup> adiabatically. In this process, the value of workdone on the gas will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "79 J",
      "405 J",
      "4050 J",
      "9590 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "405 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dy5qp6",
    "question": "<p>A certain amount of gas of volume $$\\mathrm{V}$$ at $$27^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ temperature and pressure $$2 \\times 10^{7} \\mathrm{Nm}^{-2}$$ expands isothermally until its volume gets doubled. Later it expands adiabatically until its volume gets redoubled. The final pressure of the gas will be (Use $$\\gamma=1.5)$$ :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3.536 \\times 10^{5} \\mathrm{~Pa}$$",
      "$$3.536 \\times 10^{6} \\mathrm{~Pa}$$",
      "$$1.25 \\times 10^{6} \\mathrm{~Pa}$$",
      "$$1.25 \\times 10^{5} \\mathrm{~Pa}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$$3.536 \\times 10^{6} \\mathrm{~Pa}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gmtw8s",
    "question": "<p>A monoatomic gas at pressure $$\\mathrm{P}$$ and volume $$\\mathrm{V}$$ is suddenly compressed to one eighth of its original volume. The final pressure at constant entropy will be :\n</p>",
    "options": [
      "P",
      "8P",
      "32P",
      "64P"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "32P"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo6vs1n",
    "question": "A hypothetical gas expands adiabatically such that its volume changes from 08 litres to 27 litres. If the ratio of final pressure of the gas to initial pressure of the gas is $\\frac{16}{81}$. Then the ratio of $\\frac{\\mathrm{Cp}}{\\mathrm{Cv}}$ will be.",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{3}{1}$",
      "$\\frac{4}{3}$",
      "$\\frac{1}{2}$",
      "$\\frac{3}{2}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$\\frac{4}{3}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldofz995",
    "question": "<p>A sample of gas at temperature $$T$$ is adiabatically expanded to double its volume. The work done by the gas in the process is $$\\left(\\mathrm{given}, \\gamma=\\frac{3}{2}\\right)$$ :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$W=T R[\\sqrt{2}-2]$$",
      "$$W=\\frac{T}{R}[\\sqrt{2}-2]$$",
      "$$W=\\frac{R}{T}[2-\\sqrt{2}]$$",
      "$$W=R T[2-\\sqrt{2}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$$W=R T[2-\\sqrt{2}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr1avjg",
    "question": "<p>Heat is given to an ideal gas in an isothermal process.</p>\n<p>A. Internal energy of the gas will decrease.</p>\n<p>B. Internal energy of the gas will increase.</p>\n<p>C. Internal energy of the gas will not change.</p>\n<p>D. The gas will do positive work.</p>\n<p>E. The gas will do negative work.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "B and D only",
      "C and E only",
      "A and E only",
      "C and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "C and D only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtxm3m5",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 607px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 263px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Isothermal Process</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Work done by the gas decreases internal energy</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Adiabatic Process</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">No change in internal energy</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Isochoric Process</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">The heat absorbed goes partly to increase internal energy and partly to do work </td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Isobaric Process</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">No work is done on or by the gas</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-II, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-II, B-I, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldydw41j",
    "question": "<p>1 g of a liquid is converted to vapour at 3 $$\\times$$ 10$$^5$$ Pa pressure. If 10% of the heat supplied is used for increasing the volume by 1600 cm$$^3$$ during this phase change, then the increase in internal energy in the process will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4800 J",
      "4320 J",
      "432000 J",
      "4.32 $$\\times$$ 10$$^8$$ J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "4320 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswlsgn",
    "question": "<p>The Thermodynamic process, in which internal energy of the system remains constant is</p>",
    "options": [
      "Isobaric",
      "Isochoric",
      "Adiabatic",
      "Isothermal"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "Isothermal"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgxx0jl0",
    "question": "<p>Consider two containers A and B containing monoatomic gases at the same Pressure (P), Volume (V) and Temperature (T). The gas in A is compressed isothermally to $$\\frac{1}{8}$$ of its original volume while the gas in B is compressed adiabatically to $$\\frac{1}{8}$$ of its original volume. The ratio of final pressure of gas in B to that of gas in A is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{8}$$",
      "8$$^\\frac{3}{2}$$",
      "4",
      "8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh011ing",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I: If heat is added to a system, its temperature must increase.</p>\n<p>Statement II: If positive work is done by a system in a thermodynamic process, its volume must increase.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsamui7s",
    "question": "A diatomic gas $(\\gamma=1.4)$ does $200 \\mathrm{~J}$ of work when it is expanded isobarically. The heat given to the gas in the process is :",
    "options": [
      "$800 \\mathrm{~J}$",
      "$600 \\mathrm{~J}$",
      "$700 \\mathrm{~J}$",
      "$850 \\mathrm{~J}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$700 \\mathrm{~J}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscpchzv",
    "question": "<p>During an adiabatic process, the pressure of a gas is found to be proportional to the cube of its absolute temperature. The ratio of $$\\frac{\\mathrm{Cp}}{\\mathrm{Cv}}$$ for the gas is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{7}{5}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{9}{7}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{5}{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luy9cm2x",
    "question": "<p>The volume of an ideal gas $$(\\gamma=1.5)$$ is changed adiabatically from 5 litres to 4 litres. The ratio of initial pressure to final pressure is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{4}{5}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{8}{5 \\sqrt{5}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{2}{\\sqrt{5}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{16}{25}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{8}{5 \\sqrt{5}}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luyit8ee",
    "question": "<p>A sample of 1 mole gas at temperature $$T$$ is adiabatically expanded to double its volume. If adiab constant for the gas is $$\\gamma=\\frac{3}{2}$$, then the work done by the gas in the process is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{R} \\mathrm{T}[2+\\sqrt{2}]$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{RT}[2-\\sqrt{2}]$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{R}}{\\mathrm{T}}[2-\\sqrt{2}]$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{T}{R}[2+\\sqrt{2}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{RT}[2-\\sqrt{2}]$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2ersc0",
    "question": "<p>A sample of gas at temperature $$T$$ is adiabatically expanded to double its volume. Adiabatic constant for the gas is $$\\gamma=3 / 2$$. The work done by the gas in the process is:</p>\n<p>$$(\\mu=1 \\text { mole })$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$R T[2 \\sqrt{2}-1]$$\n",
      "$$R T[2-\\sqrt{2}]$$\n",
      "$$R T[1-2 \\sqrt{2}]$$\n",
      "$$R T[\\sqrt{2}-2]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$$R T[2-\\sqrt{2}]$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3vec1d",
    "question": "<p>A diatomic gas $$(\\gamma=1.4)$$ does $$100 \\mathrm{~J}$$ of work in an isobaric expansion. The heat given to the gas is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "150 J",
      "490 J",
      "350 J",
      "250 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "350 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s20vb",
    "question": "<p>During an adiabatic process, if the pressure of a gas is found to be proportional to the cube of its absolute temperature, then the ratio of $$\\frac{\\mathrm{C}_{\\mathrm{P}}}{\\mathrm{C}_{\\mathrm{V}}}$$ for the gas is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{5}{3}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{7}{5}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{9}{7}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermodynamics-process",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "msBvERiBooMmhO9m",
    "question": "<b>Statement - 1:</b> The temperature dependence of resistance is usually given as $$R = {R_0}\\left( {1 + \\alpha \\,\\Delta t} \\right).$$ The resistance of wire changes from $$100\\Omega $$  to $$150\\Omega $$ when its temperature is increased from $${27^ \\circ }C$$ to $${227^ \\circ }C$$. This implies that $$\\alpha  = 2.5 \\times {10^{ - 3}}/C.$$ \n<p><b>Statement - 2:</b> $$R = {R_0}\\left( {1 + \\alpha \\,\\Delta t} \\right)$$ is valid only when the change in the temperature $$\\Delta T$$ is small and $$\\Delta T = \\left( {R - {R_0}} \\right) &lt;  &lt; {R_0}.$$ </p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement - 1 is true, Statement - 2 is true; Statement - 2 is the correct explanation of Statement - 1",
      "Statement - 1 is true, Statement - 2 is true; Statement - 2 is not the correct explanation of Statement - 1",
      "Statement - 1 is false, Statement - 2 is true",
      "Statement - 1 is true, Statement - 2 is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "Statement - 1 is false, Statement - 2 is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "6YFVwjLK0Brr3s1U",
    "question": "A pendulum clock loses $$12$$ $$s$$ a day if the temperature is $${40^ \\circ }C$$ and gains $$4$$ $$s$$ a day if the temperature is $${20^ \\circ }C.$$ The temperature at which the clock will show correct time, and the co-efficient of linear expansion $$\\left( \\alpha  \\right)$$  of the metal of the pendulum shaft are respectively : ",
    "options": [
      "$${30^ \\circ }C;\\,\\,\\alpha  = 1.85 \\times {10^{ - 3}}/{}^ \\circ C$$ ",
      "$${55^ \\circ }C;\\,\\,\\alpha  = 1.85 \\times {10^{ - 2}}/{}^ \\circ C$$",
      "$${25^ \\circ }C;\\,\\,\\alpha  = 1.85 \\times {10^{ - 5}}/{}^ \\circ C$$",
      "$${60^ \\circ }C;\\,\\,\\alpha  = 1.85 \\times {10^{ - 4}}/{}^ \\circ C$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "$${25^ \\circ }C;\\,\\,\\alpha  = 1.85 \\times {10^{ - 5}}/{}^ \\circ C$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "cE2dTyqEJkwu2BREMOFsV",
    "question": "A simple pendulum made of a bob of mass <i>m</i> and a metallic wire of negligible mass has time period 2 s at T=0<sup>o</sup>C. If the temperature of the wire is increased and the corresponding change in its time period is\nplotted against its temperature, the resulting graph is a line of slope S. If the\ncoefficient of linear expansion of metal is $$\\alpha $$ then the value of S is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\alpha $$",
      "$${\\alpha  \\over 2}$$",
      "2$$\\alpha $$",
      "$${1 \\over \\alpha }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "OQw0DGU5ITOsOm5I",
    "question": "An external pressure P is applied on a cube at 0<sup>o</sup>C so that it is equally compressed from all sides. K is the\nbulk modulus of the material of the cube and $$\\alpha$$ is its coefficient of linear expansion. Suppose we want to\nbring the cube to its original size by heating. The temperature should be raised by: ",
    "options": [
      "$${P \\over {3\\alpha K}}$$ ",
      "$${P \\over {\\alpha K}}$$",
      "$${3 \\alpha \\over {P K}}$$",
      "3PK$$\\alpha$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "$${P \\over {3\\alpha K}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "jCMGKOq1PZGleFvceyXci",
    "question": "A compressive force, F is applied at the two ends of a long thin steel rod. It is heated, simultaneously, such that its temperature increases by $$\\Delta $$T. The net change in its length is zero. Let $$\\ell $$ be the length of the rod, A its area of cross-section,Y its Young’s modulus, and $$\\alpha $$ its coefficient of linear expansion. Then, F is equal to :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\ell $$<sup>2</sup> Y$$\\alpha $$ $$\\Delta $$T",
      "$$\\ell $$A Y$$\\alpha $$ $$\\Delta $$T",
      "A Y$$\\alpha $$ $$\\Delta $$T",
      "$${{AY} \\over {\\alpha \\,\\Delta T}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "A Y$$\\alpha $$ $$\\Delta $$T"
  },
  {
    "id": "PkfQ4yGV8oKsws68z31oe",
    "question": "A steel rail of length 5 m and area of cross section 40cm<sup>2</sup>\n is prevented from expanding along its length while the temperature rises\nby 10<sup>o</sup>C. If coefficient of linear expansion and Young’s modulus of steel are 1.2×10<sup>−5</sup>  K<sup>−1</sup>  and 2×10<sup>11</sup> Nm<sup>−2</sup> respectively, the force developed in the rail is approximately :\n",
    "options": [
      "2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>7</sup> N",
      "1  $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup> N",
      "2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>9</sup> N",
      "3  $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "1  $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>5</sup> N"
  },
  {
    "id": "D3NcFbtZorNToyDMnYLtC",
    "question": "A rod, of length L at room temperature and uniform area of cross section A, is made of a metal having coefficient of linear expansion $$\\alpha $$/<sup>o</sup>C. It is observed that an external compressive force F, is applied on each of its ends, prevents any change in the length of the rod, when its temperature rises by $$\\Delta $$TK. Young's modulus, Y, for this metal is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${F \\over {A\\alpha \\Delta T}}$$",
      "$${F \\over {A\\alpha (\\Delta T - 273)}}$$",
      "$${F \\over {2A\\alpha \\Delta T}}$$",
      "$${{2F} \\over {A\\alpha \\Delta T}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "$${F \\over {A\\alpha \\Delta T}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xixUBcsElOF06DLf7WOnG",
    "question": "Two rods A and B of identical dimensions are at temperature 30<sup>°</sup>C. If A is heated upto 180<sup>o</sup>C and B upto T<sup>o</sup>C, then the new lengths are the same. If the ratio of the coefficients of linear expansion of A and B is 4 : 3, then the value of T is ",
    "options": [
      "200<sup>o</sup>C",
      "270<sup>o</sup>C",
      "230<sup>o</sup>C",
      "250<sup>o</sup>C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "230<sup>o</sup>C"
  },
  {
    "id": "3WjYxzZgrMlBhhRb9OnF4",
    "question": "A thermometer graduated according to a linear scale reads a value x<sub>0</sub> when in contact with boiling water, and x<sub>0</sub>/3 when in contact with ice. What is the temperature of an object in <sup>o</sup>C, if this thermometer in the contact with the object reads x<sub>0</sub>/2 ?",
    "options": [
      "60",
      "35",
      "25",
      "40"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "25"
  },
  {
    "id": "vIS1W0UAHHPNaGLovy3rsa0w2w9jx3ob4pk",
    "question": "At 40<sup>o</sup> C, a brass wire of 1 mm radius is hung from the ceiling. A small mass, M is hung from the free end of\nthe wire. When the wire is cooled down from 40<sup>o</sup>C to 20<sup>o</sup>C it regains its original length of 0.2 m. The value\nof M is close to :\n(Coefficient of linear expansion and Young’s modulus of brass are 10<sup>–5</sup>\n/<sup>o</sup>C and 10<sup>11</sup> N/m\n<sup>2</sup>\n, respectively; g=\n10 ms<sup>–2</sup>\n)",
    "options": [
      "1.5 kg",
      "0.5 kg",
      "9 kg",
      "0.9 kg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "9 kg"
  },
  {
    "id": "QZOG01f63XnOZPoM2vjgy2xukfl319dk",
    "question": "Two different wires having lengths L<sub>1</sub> and L<sub>2</sub>,\nand respective temperature coefficient of linear\nexpansion $$\\alpha $$<sub>1</sub> and $$\\alpha $$<sub>2</sub>, are joined end-to-end.\nThen the effective temperature coefficient of\nlinear expansion is :",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\sqrt {{\\alpha _1}{\\alpha _2}} $$",
      "$$4{{{\\alpha _1}{\\alpha _2}} \\over {{\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2}}}{{{L_2}{L_1}} \\over {{{\\left( {{L_2} + {L_1}} \\right)}^2}}}$$",
      "$${{{\\alpha _1} + {\\alpha _2}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{{\\alpha _1}{L_1} + {\\alpha _2}{L_2}} \\over {{L_1} + {L_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "$${{{\\alpha _1}{L_1} + {\\alpha _2}{L_2}} \\over {{L_1} + {L_2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "yyC60k4DnxkwfO9w1xjgy2xukexrvjsd",
    "question": "When the temperature of a metal wire is\nincreased from 0<sup>o</sup>C to 10<sup>o</sup>C, its length\nincreases by 0.02%. The percentage change in\nits mass density will be closest to :",
    "options": [
      "0.008",
      "0.06",
      "0.8",
      "2.3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "0.06"
  },
  {
    "id": "nOINpzjUPZIIlg9XAV1klrhg8al",
    "question": "Each side of a box made of metal sheet in cubic shape is 'a' at room temperature 'T', the coefficient of linear expansion of the metal sheet is '$$\\alpha$$'. The metal sheet is heated uniformly, by a small temperature $$\\Delta$$T, so that its new temperature is T + $$\\Delta$$T. Calculate the increase in the volume of the metal box.",
    "options": [
      "3a<sup>3</sup>$$\\alpha$$$$\\Delta$$T",
      "4$$\\pi$$a<sup>3</sup>$$\\alpha$$$$\\Delta$$T",
      "$${{4 \\over 3}}$$$$\\pi$$a<sup>3</sup>$$\\alpha$$$$\\Delta$$T",
      "4a<sup>3</sup>$$\\alpha$$$$\\Delta$$T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "3a<sup>3</sup>$$\\alpha$$$$\\Delta$$T"
  },
  {
    "id": "JisOssqBPNfh4cC2bO1klrxlnfl",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.<br/><br/>Assertion A : When a rod lying freely is heated, no thermal stress is developed in it.<br/><br/>Reason R : On heating, the length of the rod increases.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "A is true but R is false",
      "A is false but R is true",
      "Both A and B are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "Both A and B are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54ukkoa",
    "question": "<p>At what temperature a gold ring of diameter 6.230 cm be heated so that it can be fitted on a wooden bangle of diameter 6.241 cm ? Both the diameters have been measured at room temperature (27$$^\\circ$$C).</p>\n<p>(Given : coefficient of linear thermal expansion of gold $$\\alpha$$<sub>L</sub> = 1.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> K<sup>$$-$$1</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "125.7$$^\\circ$$C",
      "91.7$$^\\circ$$C",
      "425.7$$^\\circ$$C",
      "152.7$$^\\circ$$C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "152.7$$^\\circ$$C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59m1icq",
    "question": "<p>A solid metallic cube having total surface area 24 m<sup>2</sup> is uniformly heated. If its temperature is increased by 10$$^\\circ$$C, calculate the increase in volume of the cube. (Given $$\\alpha$$ = 5.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> $$^\\circ$$C<sup>$$-$$1</sup>).</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>6</sup> cm<sup>3</sup>",
      "1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> cm<sup>3</sup>",
      "6.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>4</sup> cm<sup>3</sup>",
      "4.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> cm<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> cm<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguxgj70",
    "question": "<p>On a temperature scale '$$\\mathrm{X}$$', the boiling point of water is $$65^{\\circ} \\mathrm{X}$$ and the freezing point is $$-15^{\\circ} \\mathrm{X}$$. Assume that the $$\\mathrm{X}$$ scale is linear. The equivalent temperature corresponding to $$-95^{\\circ} \\mathrm{X}$$ on the Farenheit scale would be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-148^{\\circ} \\mathrm{F}$$",
      "$$-48^{\\circ} \\mathrm{F}$$",
      "$$-63^{\\circ} \\mathrm{F}$$",
      "$$-112^{\\circ} \\mathrm{F}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "$$-148^{\\circ} \\mathrm{F}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxt1h",
    "question": "<p>The resistances of the platinum wire of a platinum resistance thermometer at the ice point and steam point are $$8 \\Omega$$ and $$10 \\Omega$$ respectively. After inserting in a hot bath of temperature $$400^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$, the resistance of platinum wire is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "10 $$\\Omega$$",
      "16 $$\\Omega$$",
      "8 $$\\Omega$$",
      "2 $$\\Omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "thermometry-and-thermal-expansion",
    "solution": "16 $$\\Omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "VbcbsEYA92IvPgf7",
    "question": "Which of the following parameters does not characterize the thermodynamic state of mattter? ",
    "options": [
      "Temperature ",
      "Pressure ",
      "Work ",
      "Volume "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "Work "
  },
  {
    "id": "RLq4YosFZvKtBtcC",
    "question": "Two thermally insulated vessels $$1$$ and $$2$$ are filled with air at temperatures $$\\left( {{T_1},{T_2}} \\right),$$ volume $$\\left( {{V_1},{V_2}} \\right)$$ and pressure $$\\left( {{P_1},{P_2}} \\right)$$ respectively. If the value joining the two vessels is opened, the temperature inside the vessel at equilibrium will be",
    "options": [
      "$${T_1}{T_2}\\left( {{P_1}{V_1} + {P_2}{V_2}} \\right)/\\left( {{P_1}{V_1}{T_2} + {P_2}{V_2}{T_1}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( {{T_1} + {T_2}} \\right)/2$$ ",
      "$${{T_1} + {T_2}}$$ ",
      "$${T_1}{T_2}\\left( {{P_1}{V_1} + {P_2}{V_2}} \\right)/\\left( {{P_1}{V_1}{T_1} + {P_2}{V_2}{T_2}} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "$${T_1}{T_2}\\left( {{P_1}{V_1} + {P_2}{V_2}} \\right)/\\left( {{P_1}{V_1}{T_2} + {P_2}{V_2}{T_1}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Jmxp9s6IgC7sI2V0",
    "question": "Which of the following statements is <b>correct</b> for any thermodynamic system ?  ",
    "options": [
      "The change in entropy can never be zero",
      "Internal energy and entropy and state functions ",
      "The internal energy changes in all processes ",
      "The work done in an adiabatic process is always zero, "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "Internal energy and entropy and state functions "
  },
  {
    "id": "PmDqYapGVC61Vaxd",
    "question": "An insulated container of gas has two chambers separated  by an insulating partition. One of the chambers has volume $${V_1}$$ and contains ideal gas at pressure $${P_1}$$ and temperature $${T_1}$$. The other chamber has volume $${V_2}$$ and contains ideal gas at pressure $${P_2}$$ and temperature $${T_2}$$. If the partition is removed without doing any work on the gas, the final equilibrium temperature of the gas in the container will be ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{T_1}{T_2}\\left( {{P_1}{V_1} + {P_2}{V_2}} \\right)} \\over {{P_1}{V_1}{T_2} + {P_2}{V_2}{T_1}}}$$ ",
      "$${{{P_1}{V_1}{T_1} + {P_2}{V_2}{T_2}} \\over {{P_1}{V_1} + {P_2}{V_2}}}$$ ",
      "$${{{P_1}{V_1}{T_2} + {P_2}{V_2}{T_1}} \\over {{P_1}{V_1} + {P_2}{V_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{T_1}{T_2}\\left( {{P_1}{V_1} + {P_2}{V_2}} \\right)} \\over {{P_1}{V_1}{T_1} + {P_2}{V_2}{T_2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "$${{{T_1}{T_2}\\left( {{P_1}{V_1} + {P_2}{V_2}} \\right)} \\over {{P_1}{V_1}{T_2} + {P_2}{V_2}{T_1}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "3YZYD3TTq3QaD6mB",
    "question": "A thermally insulated vessel contains an ideal gas of molecular mass $$M$$ and ratio of specific heats $$\\gamma .$$ It is moving with speed $$v$$ and it's suddenly brought to rest. Assuming no heat is lost to the surroundings, Its temperature increases by: ",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\left( {\\gamma  - 1} \\right)} \\over {2\\gamma R}}M{v^2}K$$ ",
      "$${{\\gamma {M^2}v} \\over {2R}}K$$ ",
      "$${{\\left( {\\gamma  - 1} \\right)} \\over {2R}}M{v^2}K$$ ",
      "$${{\\left( {\\gamma  - 1} \\right)} \\over {2\\left( {\\gamma  + 1} \\right)R}}M{v^2}K$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "$${{\\left( {\\gamma  - 1} \\right)} \\over {2R}}M{v^2}K$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "fcs8i3JM6xyXAx18",
    "question": "$$100g$$ of water is heated from $${30^ \\circ }C$$ to $${50^ \\circ }C$$. Ignoring the slight expansion of the water, the change in its internal energy is (specific heat of water is $$4184$$ $$J/kg/K$$): ",
    "options": [
      "$$8.4$$ $$kJ$$ ",
      "$$84$$ $$kJ$$",
      "$$2.1$$ $$kJ$$ ",
      "$$4.2$$ $$kJ$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "$$8.4$$ $$kJ$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "0Otom2zDGN8dI3K4V618hoxe66ijvzmyznh",
    "question": "A cylinder with fixed capacity of 67.2 lit\ncontains helium gas at STP. The amount of heat\nneeded to raise the temperature of the gas by\n20°C is : [Given that R = 8.31 J mol<sup>–1</sup> K<sup>–1</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "374 J",
      "700 J",
      "748 J",
      "350 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "748 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "3L4Q827tOxhWqGHdNu1kmhod4hp",
    "question": "In thermodynamics, heat and work are :",
    "options": [
      "Path functions",
      "Point functions",
      "Extensive thermodynamics state variables",
      "Intensive thermodynamic state variables"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "Path functions"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktabqj29",
    "question": "An electric appliance supplies 6000 J/min heat to the system. If the system delivers a power of 90W. How long it would take to increase the internal energy by 2.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> J ?",
    "options": [
      "2.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>2</sup> s",
      "4.1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>1</sup> s",
      "2.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> s",
      "2.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>1</sup> s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "2.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>2</sup> s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldso98ll",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A: If $$d Q$$ and $$d W$$ represent the heat supplied to the system and the work done on the system respectively. Then according to the first law of thermodynamics $$d Q=d U-d W$$.</p>\n<p>Reason R: First law of thermodynamics is based on law of conservation of energy.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct but R is not the  correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the  correct explanation of A",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "A is not correct but R is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the  correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgux5x4q",
    "question": "<p>$$1 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ of water at $$100^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ is converted into steam at $$100^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ by boiling at atmospheric pressure. The volume of water changes from $$1.00 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~m}^{3}$$ as a liquid to $$1.671 \\mathrm{~m}^{3}$$ as steam. The change in internal energy of the system during the process will be</p>\n<p>(Given latent heat of vaporisaiton $$=2257 \\mathrm{~kJ} / \\mathrm{kg}$$, Atmospheric pressure = $$\\left.1 \\times 10^{5} \\mathrm{~Pa}\\right)$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "+ 2090 kJ",
      "$$-$$ 2426 kJ",
      "+ 2476 kJ",
      "$$-$$ 2090 kJ"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "+ 2090 kJ"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvrk9lj",
    "question": "<p>A gas is compressed adiabatically, which one of the following statement is NOT true.</p>",
    "options": [
      "There is no heat supplied to the system",
      "The temperature of the gas increases.",
      "There is no change in the internal energy",
      "The change in the internal energy is equal to the work done on the gas."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "There is no change in the internal energy"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh24e1qg",
    "question": "<p>A source supplies heat to a system at the rate of $$1000 \\mathrm{~W}$$. If the system performs work at a rate of $$200 \\mathrm{~W}$$. The rate at which internal energy of the system increases is</p>",
    "options": [
      "600 W",
      "1200 W",
      "500 W",
      "800 W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "heat-and-thermodynamics",
    "topic": "zeroth-and-first-law-of-thermodynamics",
    "solution": "800 W"
  },
  {
    "id": "huSV7dTOkSwVod0A",
    "question": "When forces $${F_1},\\,\\,{F_2},\\,\\,{F_3}$$ are acting on a particle of mass $$m$$ such that $${F_2}$$ and $${F_3}$$ are mutually perpendicular, then the particle remains stationary. If the force $${F_1}$$ is now removed then the acceleration of the particle is ",
    "options": [
      "$${F_1}/m$$ ",
      "$${F_2}{F_3}/m{F_1}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {F{}_2 - {F_3}} \\right)/m$$ ",
      "$${F_2}/m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "equilibrium-of-a-particle",
    "solution": "$${F_1}/m$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "h0QcVTf5Eey52BkU7eJH9",
    "question": "A mass of 10 kg is suspended vertically by a rope from the roof. When a horizontal force is applied on the rope at some point. the rope deviated at an angle of 45<sup>o</sup> at the roof point. If the suspended mass is at equilibrium, the magnitude of the force applied is (g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
    "options": [
      "200 N",
      "140 N",
      "70 N",
      "100 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "equilibrium-of-a-particle",
    "solution": "100 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ds2EggdH6UVePJ9Hkq7k9k2k5fauisj",
    "question": "A mass of 10 kg is suspended by a rope of length 4 m, from the ceiling. A force F is applied\nhorizontally at the mid point of the rope such that the top half of the rope makes an angle of 45<sup>o</sup>\nwith the vertical. Then F equal : (Take g = 10 ms<sup>–2</sup> and the rope to be massless)",
    "options": [
      "100 N",
      "75 N",
      "90 N",
      "70 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "equilibrium-of-a-particle",
    "solution": "100 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjomjm8",
    "question": "Statement : 1<br/><br/>If three forces $${\\overrightarrow F _1},{\\overrightarrow F _2}$$ and $${\\overrightarrow F _3}$$ are represented by three sides of a triangle and $${\\overrightarrow F _1} + {\\overrightarrow F _2} =  - {\\overrightarrow F _3}$$, then these three forces are concurrent forces and satisfy the condition for equilibrium.<br/><br/>Statement : 2<br/><br/>A triangle made up of three forces $${\\overrightarrow F _1}$$, $${\\overrightarrow F _2}$$ and $${\\overrightarrow F _3}$$ as its sides taken in the same order, satisfy the condition for translatory equilibrium.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement - I is false but Statement - II is true",
      "Statement - I is true but Statement - II is false",
      "Both Statement-I and Statement-II are false",
      "Both Statement-I and Statement-II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "equilibrium-of-a-particle",
    "solution": "Both Statement-I and Statement-II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrholky",
    "question": "<p>Three forces $$F_{1}=10 \\mathrm{~N}, F_{2}=8 \\mathrm{~N}, \\mathrm{~F}_{3}=6 \\mathrm{~N}$$ are acting on a particle of mass $$5 \\mathrm{~kg}$$. The forces $$\\mathrm{F}_{2}$$ and $$\\mathrm{F}_{3}$$ are applied perpendicularly so that particle remains at rest. If the force $$F_{1}$$ is removed, then the acceleration of the particle is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4.8 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$",
      "$$7 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$",
      "$$0.5 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "equilibrium-of-a-particle",
    "solution": "$$2 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "luyit9yv",
    "question": "<p>A heavy iron bar, of weight $$W$$ is having its one end on the ground and the other on the shoulder of a person. The bar makes an angle $$\\theta$$ with the horizontal. The weight experienced by the person is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$W \\sin \\theta$$\n",
      "$$W$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{W}{2}$$\n",
      "$$W \\cos \\theta$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "equilibrium-of-a-particle",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{W}{2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29599",
    "question": "<p>A body of weight $$200 \\mathrm{~N}$$ is suspended from a tree branch through a chain of mass $$10 \\mathrm{~kg}$$. The branch pulls the chain by a force equal to (if $$\\mathrm{g}=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$$) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "300 N",
      "100 N",
      "150 N",
      "200 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "equilibrium-of-a-particle",
    "solution": "300 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "XBQHMXZU6eEeK9y6",
    "question": "A marble block of mass $$2$$ $$kg$$ lying on ice when given a velocity of $$6$$ $$m/s$$ is stopped by friction in $$10$$ $$s.$$ Then the coefficient of friction is ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.02$$ ",
      "$$0.03$$ ",
      "$$0.04$$ ",
      "$$0.06$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "$$0.06$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "1f9VUaOzkDjf1d7B",
    "question": "A block rests on a rough inclined plane `making an angle of $${30^ \\circ }$$ with the horizontal. The coefficient of static friction between the block and the plane is $$0.8.$$ If the frictionless force on the block is $$10$$ $$N,$$ the mass of the block (in $$kg$$) is $$\\left( {take\\,\\,\\,g\\, = \\,10\\,\\,m/{s^2}} \\right)$$ ",
    "options": [
      "$$1.6$$ ",
      "$$4.0$$ ",
      "$$2.0$$",
      "$$2.5$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "$$2.0$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "rtT5xB5de04AZlEZ",
    "question": "A smooth block is released at rest on a $${45^ \\circ }$$ incline and then slides a distance $$'d'$$. The time taken to slide is $$'n'$$ times as much to slide on rough incline than on a smooth incline. The coefficient of friction is ",
    "options": [
      "$${\\mu _k} = \\sqrt {1 - {1 \\over {{n^2}}}} $$ ",
      "$${\\mu _k} = 1 - {1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$ ",
      "$${\\mu _k} = \\sqrt {1 - {1 \\over {{n^2}}}} $$ ",
      "$${\\mu _s} = 1 - {1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "$${\\mu _k} = 1 - {1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "PtBYu1fTP3vvAe51",
    "question": "Consider a car moving on a straight road with a speed of $$100$$ $$m/s$$. The distance at which car can be stopped is $$\\left[ {{\\mu _k} = 0.5} \\right]$$",
    "options": [
      "$$1000$$ $$m$$ ",
      "$$800$$ $$m$$ ",
      "$$400$$ $$m$$ ",
      "$$100$$ $$m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "$$1000$$ $$m$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "BddVGW1uYyT66w17",
    "question": "A block of mass $$m$$ is placed on a surface with a vertical cross section given by $$y = {{{x^3}} \\over 6}.$$ If the coefficient of friction is $$0.5,$$  the maximum height above the ground at which the block can be placed without slipping is:",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 6}m$$ ",
      "$${2 \\over 3}m$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 3}m$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 6}m$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Xhr5sr90E677hxNpu5ZMT",
    "question": "A rocket is fired vertically from the earth with an acceleration of 2g, where g is the\ngravitational acceleration. On an inclined plane inside the rocket, making an angle $$\\theta $$ with the horizontal, a point object of mass <i>m</i> is kept. The minimum coefficient of friction $$\\mu $$<sub>min</sub> between the mass and the inclined surface such that the mass does not move is :",
    "options": [
      "tan$$\\theta $$",
      "2tan$$\\theta $$",
      "3tan$$\\theta $$",
      "tan2$$\\theta $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "tan$$\\theta $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jq874BQpLYd6vzUxki8aa",
    "question": "A given object takes n times more time to slide down a $${45^ \\circ }$$ rough inclined plane as it takes to slide down a perfectly smooth $${45^ \\circ }$$ incline. The coefficient of kinetic friction between the object and the incline is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {2 - {n^2}}}$$ ",
      "$$1 - {1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {1 - {1 \\over {{n^2}}}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{1 \\over {1 - {n^2}}}} $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "$$1 - {1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "BuZdpmKL3tYjIoA6oPREZ",
    "question": "A body of mass 2 kg slides down with an acceleration of 3 m/s<sup>2</sup> on a rough inclined plane having a slope of $${30^o}$$. The external force required to take the same body up the plane with the same acceleration will be : (g = 10 m/s<sup>2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "14 N",
      "20 N",
      "6 N",
      "4 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "20 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "OSStcN4dq5uT9ZfUU3jgy2xukfrozb4z",
    "question": "An insect is at the bottom of a hemispherical ditch of radius 1 m. It crawls up the ditch but starts\nslipping after it is at height h from the bottom. If the coefficient of friction between the ground and\nthe insect is 0.75, then h is : \n<br/>(g = 10 ms<sup>–2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "0.45 m",
      "0.60 m",
      "0.20 m",
      "0.80 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "0.20 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c2wdv0",
    "question": "<p>A block of mass 10 kg starts sliding on a surface with an initial velocity of 9.8 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. The coefficient of friction between the surface and block is 0.5. The distance covered by the block before coming to rest is :</p>\n<p>[use g = 9.8 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]</p>",
    "options": [
      "4.9 m",
      "9.8 m",
      "12.5 m",
      "19.6 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "9.8 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jh0kik",
    "question": "<p>A bag is gently dropped on a conveyor belt moving at a speed of $$2 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. The coefficient of friction between the conveyor belt and bag is $$0.4$$. Initially, the bag slips on the belt before it stops due to friction. The distance travelled by the bag on the belt during slipping motion, is : [Take $$\\mathrm{g}=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{-2}$$ ]</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 m",
      "0.5 m",
      "3.2 m",
      "0.8 ms"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "0.5 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo6u481",
    "question": "A body of mass $10 \\mathrm{~kg}$ is moving with an initial speed of $20 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$. The body stops after $5 \\mathrm{~s}$ due to friction between body and the floor. The value of the coefficient of friction is: <br/><br/>(Take acceleration due to gravity $g=10 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$ )",
    "options": [
      "0.3",
      "0.2",
      "0.5",
      "0.4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "0.4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldog12tq",
    "question": "<p>A block of mass $$5 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is placed at rest on a table of rough surface. Now, if a force of $$30 \\mathrm{~N}$$ is applied in the direction parallel to surface of the table, the block slides through a distance of $$50 \\mathrm{~m}$$ in an interval of time $$10 \\mathrm{~s}$$. Coefficient of kinetic friction is (given, $$g=10 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$):</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.25",
      "0.75",
      "0.60",
      "0.50"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "0.50"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsab6xw",
    "question": "<p>The time taken by an object to slide down 45$$^\\circ$$ rough inclined plane is n times as it takes to slide down a perfectly smooth 45$$^\\circ$$ incline plane. The coefficient of kinetic friction between the object and the incline plane is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1 - {1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$",
      "$$1 + {1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {1 - {1 \\over {{n^2}}}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{1 \\over {1 - {n^2}}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "$$1 - {1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsoychw",
    "question": "<p>A block of mass $m$ slides down the plane inclined at angle $$30^{\\circ}$$ with an acceleration $$\\frac{g}{4}$$. The value of coefficient of kinetic friction will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{2 \\sqrt{3}-1}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{2 \\sqrt{3}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{2 \\sqrt{3}+1}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{2 \\sqrt{3}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscp0asi",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : The limiting force of static friction depends on the area of contact and independent of materials.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : The limiting force of kinetic friction is independent of the area of contact and depends on materials.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect\n",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg5qj2q",
    "question": "<p>A block of mass $$m$$ is placed on a surface having vertical crossection given by $$y=x^2 / 4$$. If coefficient of friction is 0.5, the maximum height above the ground at which block can be placed without slipping is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "1/2 m",
      "1/3 m",
      "1/6 m",
      "1/4 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "1/4 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3ve86t",
    "question": "<p>A given object takes $$\\mathrm{n}$$ times the time to slide down $$45^{\\circ}$$ rough inclined plane as it takes the time to slide down an identical perfectly smooth $$45^{\\circ}$$ inclined plane. The coefficient of kinetic friction between the object and the surface of inclined plane is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1-\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{n}^2}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{1-\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{n}^2}}$$\n",
      "$$1-n^2$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{1-n^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "$$1-\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{n}^2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s20wg",
    "question": "<p>A heavy box of mass $$50 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is moving on a horizontal surface. If co-efficient of kinetic friction between the box and horizontal surface is 0.3 then force of kinetic friction is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1470 N",
      "147 N",
      "1.47 N",
      "14.7 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "friction-force",
    "solution": "147 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "aWWfFnaJRzIC4zNN",
    "question": "A light string passing over a smooth light pulley connects two blocks of masses $${m_1}$$ and $${m_2}$$ (vertically). If the acceleration of the system is $$g/8$$, then the ratio of the masses is ",
    "options": [
      "$$8:1$$ ",
      "$$9:7$$ ",
      "$$4:3$$ ",
      "$$5:3$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "motion-of-connected-bodies",
    "solution": "$$9:7$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "sVFEgsQBtOfzoKRX",
    "question": "A block of mass $$M$$ is pulled along a horizontal frictionless surface by a rope of mass $$m.$$ If a force $$P$$ is applied at the free end of the rope, the force exerted by the rope on the block is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{Pm} \\over {M + m}}$$ ",
      "$${{Pm} \\over {M - m}}$$ ",
      "$$P$$ ",
      "$${{PM} \\over {M + m}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "motion-of-connected-bodies",
    "solution": "$${{PM} \\over {M + m}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "luyita5l",
    "question": "<p>A light unstretchable string passing over a smooth light pulley connects two blocks of masses $$m_1$$ and $$m_2$$. If the acceleration of the system is $$\\frac{g}{8}$$, then the ratio of the masses $$\\frac{m_2}{m_1}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$5: 3$$\n",
      "$$8: 1$$\n",
      "$$9: 7$$\n",
      "$$4: 3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "motion-of-connected-bodies",
    "solution": "$$9: 7$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc5836l",
    "question": "<p>A light string passing over a smooth light pulley connects two blocks of masses $$m_1$$ and $$m_2\\left(\\right.$$ where $$\\left.m_2&gt;m_1\\right)$$. If the acceleration of the system is $$\\frac{g}{\\sqrt{2}}$$, then the ratio of the masses $$\\frac{m_1}{m_2}$$ is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1+\\sqrt{5}}{\\sqrt{5}-1}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{3}+1}{\\sqrt{2}-1}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{2}-1}{\\sqrt{2}+1}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1+\\sqrt{5}}{\\sqrt{2}-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "motion-of-connected-bodies",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{2}-1}{\\sqrt{2}+1}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kmgbm9",
    "question": "<p>A block of mass M slides down on a rough inclined plane with constant velocity. The angle made by the incline plane with horizontal is $$\\theta$$. The magnitude of the contact force will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Mg",
      "$$\\mathrm{Mg} \\cos \\theta$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{Mg} \\sin \\theta+\\mathrm{Mg} \\cos \\theta}$$",
      "$$\\operatorname{Mg} \\sin \\theta \\sqrt{1+\\mu}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "motion-on-an-inclined-plane",
    "solution": "Mg"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kmjisk",
    "question": "<p>A block 'A' takes 2 s to slide down a frictionless incline of 30$$^\\circ$$ and length 'l', kept inside a lift going up with uniform velocity 'v'. If the incline is changed to 45$$^\\circ$$, the time taken by the block, to slide down the incline, will be approximately :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.66 s",
      "0.83 s",
      "1.68 s",
      "0.70 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "motion-on-an-inclined-plane",
    "solution": "1.68 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erypp",
    "question": "<p>A $$2 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ brick begins to slide over a surface which is inclined at an angle of $$45^{\\circ}$$ with respect to horizontal axis. The co-efficient of static friction between their surfaces is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "1.7",
      "0.5",
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "motion-on-an-inclined-plane",
    "solution": "1"
  },
  {
    "id": "diuKSXbhwS8den7U",
    "question": "A lift is moving down with acceleration $$a.$$ A man in the lift drops a ball inside the lift. The acceleration of the ball as observed by the man in the lift and a man standing stationary on the ground are respectively",
    "options": [
      "$$g,g$$ ",
      "$$g-a, g-a$$",
      "$$g-a, g$$ ",
      "$$a, g$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$$g-a, g$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ngTxARUoznWLIMIA",
    "question": "Two forces are such that the sum of their magnitudes is $$18$$ $$N$$ and their resultant is $$12$$ $$N$$ which is perpendicular to the smaller force. Then the magnitudes of the forces are ",
    "options": [
      "$$12N,$$ $$6N$$ ",
      "$$13N,$$ $$5N$$",
      "$$10N,$$ $$8N$$",
      "$$16N$$, $$2N.$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$$13N,$$ $$5N$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "JLiClepAffsb2IFf",
    "question": "A spring balance is attached to the ceiling of a lift. A man hangs his bag on the spring and the spring reads $$49$$ $$N,$$ when the lift is stationary. If the lift moves downward with an acceleration of $$5 m/{s^2}$$, the reading of the spring balance will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$24$$ $$N$$ ",
      "$$74$$ $$N$$ ",
      "$$15$$ $$N$$ ",
      "$$49$$ $$N$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$$24$$ $$N$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "HsgVEcvEfqI3xXKN",
    "question": "A rocket with a lift-off mass $$3.5 \\times {10^4}\\,\\,kg$$ is blasted upwards with an initial acceleration of $$10m/{s^2}.$$ Then the initial thrust of the blast is ",
    "options": [
      "$$3.5 \\times {10^5}N$$  ",
      "$$7.0 \\times {10^5}N$$ ",
      "$$14.0 \\times {10^5}N$$ ",
      "$$1.75 \\times {10^5}N$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$$3.5 \\times {10^5}N$$  "
  },
  {
    "id": "Ins6qPffV9dWXmB1",
    "question": "A light spring balance hangs from the hook of the other light spring balance and a block of mass $$M$$ $$kg$$ hangs from the former one. Then the true statement about the scale reading is ",
    "options": [
      "Both the scales read $$M$$ $$kg$$ each",
      "The scale of the lower one reads $$M$$ $$kg$$ and of the upper one zero ",
      "The reading of the two scales can be anything but the sum of the reading will be $$M$$ $$kg$$ ",
      "Both the scales read $$M/2$$ $$kg$$ each "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "Both the scales read $$M$$ $$kg$$ each"
  },
  {
    "id": "9ZfE7PONnMRU4a6X",
    "question": "A particle of mass 0.3 kg subjected to a force $$F=-kx$$ with $$k=15$$ $$N/m$$. What will be its initial acceleration if it is released from a point 20 cm away from the origin?",
    "options": [
      "$$15\\,\\,\\,\\,m/{s^2}$$ ",
      "$$3\\,\\,\\,m/{s^2}$$ ",
      "$$10\\,\\,\\,m/{s^2}$$ ",
      "$$5\\,\\,\\,m/{s^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$$10\\,\\,\\,m/{s^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "kQ3gPFzGjReG6774CXwiX",
    "question": "A particle of mass m is acted upon by a force F given by the empirical law\nF =$${R \\over {{t^2}}}\\,v\\left( t \\right).$$   If this law is to be tested experimentally by observing the motion starting from rest, the best way is to plot :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\upsilon $$(t) against t<sup>2</sup>",
      "log $$\\upsilon $$(t) against $${1 \\over {{t^2}}}$$ ",
      "log $$\\upsilon $$(t) against t",
      "log $$\\upsilon $$(t) against $${1 \\over {{t}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "log $$\\upsilon $$(t) against $${1 \\over {{t}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "f6vhxNJ6dyy1P1hv5j9CK",
    "question": "Two forces P and Q, of magnitude 2F and 3F, respectively, are at an angle $$\\theta $$ with each other. If the force Q is doubled, then their resultant also gets doubled. Then, the angle $$\\theta $$ is -",
    "options": [
      "90<sup>o</sup>",
      "60<sup>o</sup>",
      "30<sup>o</sup>",
      "120<sup>o</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "120<sup>o</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "mmMYBOLq3HtxZ5llhX18hoxe66ijvzmxskq",
    "question": "A ball is thrown upward with an initial velocity\nV<sub>0</sub> from the surface of the earth. The motion\nof the ball is affected by a drag force equal to\nm$$\\gamma $$u<sup>2</sup> (where m is mass of the ball, u is its\ninstantaneous velocity and $$\\gamma $$ is a constant).\nTime taken by the ball to rise to its zenith is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt {\\gamma g} }}{\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sqrt {{\\gamma  \\over g}} {V_0}} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt {\\gamma g} }}{ln}\\left( 1+ {\\sqrt {{\\gamma  \\over g}} {V_0}} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt {\\gamma g} }}{\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sqrt {{\\gamma  \\over g}} {V_0}} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt {2\\gamma g} }}{\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sqrt {{2\\gamma  \\over g}} {V_0}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt {\\gamma g} }}{\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {\\sqrt {{\\gamma  \\over g}} {V_0}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "0IWF3lt2qg3jMHJA7D3rsa0w2w9jwzhb4yb",
    "question": "A bullet of mass 20 g has an initial speed of 1 ms<sup>–1</sup>\n, just before it starts penetrating a mud wall of thickness\n20 cm. If the wall offers a mean resistance of 2.5 × 10<sup>–2</sup> N, the speed of the bullet after emerging from the\nother side of the wall is close to : ",
    "options": [
      "0.3 ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "0.1 ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "0.7 ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "0.4 ms<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "0.7 ms<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "3XOkph5GPWn2fQaiPfjgy2xukfl1my99",
    "question": "A spaceship in space sweeps stationary\ninterplanetary dust. As a result, its mass\n<br/>increases at a rate $${{dM\\left( t \\right)} \\over {dt}}$$ = bv<sup>2</sup>(t), where v(t) is\nits instantaneous velocity. The instantaneous\nacceleration of the satellite is :",
    "options": [
      "-bv<sup>3</sup>(t)",
      "$$ - {{2b{v^3}} \\over {M\\left( t \\right)}}$$",
      "$$ - {{b{v^3}} \\over {M\\left( t \\right)}}$$",
      "$$ - {{b{v^3}} \\over {2M\\left( t \\right)}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$$ - {{b{v^3}} \\over {M\\left( t \\right)}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "SKiYDsQD4Ct55N6cgGjgy2xukg0ikgo3",
    "question": "A particle moving in the xy plane experiences a velocity dependent force\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow F  = k\\left( {{v_y}\\widehat i + {v_x}\\widehat j} \\right)$$\n, where v<sub>x</sub>\nand v<sub>y</sub>\n are the <br/>x and y components of its velocity $$\\overrightarrow v $$\n. If $$\\overrightarrow a $$\n is the<br/> acceleration of the particle, then\n<br/>which of the following statements is true for the particle?",
    "options": [
      "kinetic energy of particle is constant in time",
      "quantity $$\\overrightarrow v  \\times \\overrightarrow a $$\n is constant in time",
      "quantity $$\\overrightarrow v .\\overrightarrow a $$\n is constant in time",
      "$$\\overrightarrow F $$ arises due to a magnetic field\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "quantity $$\\overrightarrow v  \\times \\overrightarrow a $$\n is constant in time"
  },
  {
    "id": "ulxLHuLXJPG9A6mOXgjgy2xukfaiunlm",
    "question": "A small ball of mass m is thrown upward with velocity u from the ground. The ball experiences a\nresistive force mkv<sup>2</sup>\n where v is its speed. The maximum height attained by the ball is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over k}{\\tan ^{ - 1}}{{k{u^2}} \\over {2g}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {2k}}{\\tan ^{ - 1}}{{k{u^2}} \\over g}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {2k}}\\ln \\left( {1 + {{k{u^2}} \\over g}} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over k}\\ln \\left( {1 + {{k{u^2}} \\over {2g}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {2k}}\\ln \\left( {1 + {{k{u^2}} \\over g}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "SnyVgljqbBEkhYYC5Y1klrnkrah",
    "question": "A particle is projected with velocity v<sub>0</sub> along x-axis. A damping force is acting on the particle which is proportional to the square of the distance from the origin i.e. ma = $$-$$ $$\\alpha$$x<sup>2</sup>. The distance at which the particle stops :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left[ {{{3mv_0^2} \\over {2\\alpha }}} \\right]^{{1 \\over 3}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{2{v_0}} \\over {3\\alpha }}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 3}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{3v_0^2} \\over {2\\alpha }}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{2v_0^2} \\over {3\\alpha }}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$${\\left[ {{{3mv_0^2} \\over {2\\alpha }}} \\right]^{{1 \\over 3}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw6mhih",
    "question": "A force $$\\overrightarrow F  = (40\\widehat i + 10\\widehat j)N$$ acts on a body of mass 5 kg. If the body starts from rest, its position vector $$\\overrightarrow r $$ at time t = 10 s, will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$(100\\widehat i + 400\\widehat j)m$$",
      "$$(100\\widehat i + 100\\widehat j)m$$",
      "$$(400\\widehat i + 100\\widehat j)m$$",
      "$$(400\\widehat i + 400\\widehat j)m$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$$(400\\widehat i + 100\\widehat j)m$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks19p4v2",
    "question": "A particle of mass M originally at rest is subjected to a force whose direction is constant but magnitude varies with time according to the relation <br/><br/>$$F = {F_0}\\left[ {1 - {{\\left( {{{t - T} \\over T}} \\right)}^2}} \\right]$$<br/><br/>Where F<sub>0</sub> and T are constants. The force acts only for the time interval 2T. The velocity v of the particle after time 2T is :",
    "options": [
      "2F<sub>0</sub>T/M",
      "F<sub>0</sub>T/2M",
      "4F<sub>0</sub>T/3M",
      "F<sub>0</sub>T/3M"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "4F<sub>0</sub>T/3M"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktaf4evo",
    "question": "The initial mass of a rocket is 1000 kg. Calculate at what rate the fuel should be burnt so that the rocket is given an acceleration of 20 ms<sup>-2</sup>. The gases come out at a relative speed of 500 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup> with respect to the rocket : [Use g = 10 m/s<sup>2</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "6.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>2</sup> kg s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "500 kg s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "10 kg s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "60 kg s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "60 kg s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54vduhg",
    "question": "<p>A block of mass M placed inside a box descends vertically with acceleration 'a'. The block exerts a force equal to one-fourth of its weight on the floor of the box. The value of 'a' will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${g \\over 4}$$",
      "$${g \\over 2}$$",
      "$${3g \\over 4}$$",
      "g"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$${3g \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55jqcwa",
    "question": "<p>A block of mass 2 kg moving on a horizontal surface with speed of 4 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup> enters a rough surface ranging from x = 0.5 m to x = 1.5 m. The retarding force in this range of rough surface is related to distance by F = $$-$$kx where k = 12 Nm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. The speed of the block as it just crosses the rough surface will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "zero",
      "1.5 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "2.0 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "2.5 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "2.0 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58bbgj4",
    "question": "<p>A person is standing in an elevator. In which situation, he experiences weight loss?</p>",
    "options": [
      "When the elevator moves upward with constant acceleration",
      "When the elevator moves downward with constant acceleration",
      "When the elevator moves upward with uniform velocity",
      "When the elevator moves downward with uniform velocity"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "When the elevator moves downward with constant acceleration"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbyej8",
    "question": "<p>An object of mass 5 kg is thrown vertically upwards from the ground. The air resistance produces a constant retarding force of 10 N throughout the motion. The ratio of time of ascent to the time of descent will be equal to : [Use g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>].</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 $$ : $$\\sqrt 3 $$",
      "$$\\sqrt 3 $$ : $$\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "2 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt 2 $$ : $$\\sqrt 3 $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gn6xt5",
    "question": "<p>A monkey of mass $$50 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ climbs on a rope which can withstand the tension (T) of $$350 \\mathrm{~N}$$. If monkey initially climbs down with an acceleration of $$4 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$ and then climbs up with an acceleration of $$5 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$. Choose the correct option $$\\left(g=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}\\right)$$.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$T=700 \\mathrm{~N}$$ while climbing upward",
      "$$T=350 \\mathrm{~N}$$ while going downward",
      "Rope will break while climbing upward",
      "Rope will break while going downward"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "Rope will break while climbing upward"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lds9gcsm",
    "question": "<p>A force acts for 20 s on a body of mass 20 kg, starting from rest, after which the force ceases and then body describes 50 m in the next 10 s. The value of force will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "40 N",
      "20 N",
      "5 N",
      "10 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "5 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyei7ng",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : An elevator can go up or down with uniform speed when its weight is balanced with the tension of its cable.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Force exerted by the floor of an elevator on the foot of a person standing on it  is more than his/her weight when the elevator goes down with increasing speed.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgny9f5p",
    "question": "The position vector of a particle related to time $t$ is given by\n<br/><br/>\n$\\vec{r}=\\left(10 t \\hat{i}+15 t^{2} \\hat{j}+7 \\hat{k}\\right) m$\n<br/><br/>\nThe direction of net force experienced by the particle is :",
    "options": [
      "Positive $x$ - axis",
      "Positive $y$ - axis",
      "Positive $z$ - axis",
      "In $x$ - $y$ plane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "Positive $y$ - axis"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswyy0y",
    "question": "<p>A body of mass $$500 \\mathrm{~g}$$ moves along $$\\mathrm{x}$$-axis such that it's velocity varies with displacement $$\\mathrm{x}$$ according to the relation $$v=10 \\sqrt{x} \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ the force acting on the body is:-</p>",
    "options": [
      "166 N",
      "5 N",
      "25 N",
      "125 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "25 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh01adu4",
    "question": "<p>At any instant the velocity of a particle of mass $$500 \\mathrm{~g}$$ is $$\\left(2 t \\hat{i}+3 t^{2} \\hat{j}\\right) \\mathrm{ms}^{-1}$$. If the force acting on the particle at $$t=1 \\mathrm{~s}$$ is $$(\\hat{i}+x \\hat{j}) \\mathrm{N}$$. Then the value of $$x$$ will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "4",
      "6",
      "3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsamcmv7",
    "question": "A body of mass $4 \\mathrm{~kg}$ experiences two forces $\\vec{F}_1=5 \\hat{i}+8 \\hat{j}+7 \\hat{k}$ and $\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{F}}_2=3 \\hat{i}-4 \\hat{j}-3 \\hat{k}$. The acceleration acting on the body is :",
    "options": [
      "$2 \\hat{i}+\\hat{j}+\\hat{k}$",
      "$4 \\hat{i}+2 \\hat{j}+2 \\hat{k}$",
      "$-2 \\hat{i}-\\hat{j}-\\hat{k}$",
      "$2 \\hat{i}+3 \\hat{j}+3 \\hat{k}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$2 \\hat{i}+\\hat{j}+\\hat{k}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsams161",
    "question": "A cricket player catches a ball of mass $120 \\mathrm{~g}$ moving with $25 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$ speed. If the catching process is completed in $0.1 \\mathrm{~s}$ then the magnitude of force exerted by the ball on the hand of player will be (in SI unit) :",
    "options": [
      "30",
      "24",
      "12",
      "25"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "30"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gs19s",
    "question": "<p>A player caught a cricket ball of mass $$150 \\mathrm{~g}$$ moving at a speed of $$20 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. If the catching process is completed in $$0.1 \\mathrm{~s}$$, the magnitude of force exerted by the ball on the hand of the player is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "150 N",
      "3 N",
      "30 N",
      "300 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "30 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5grwcr",
    "question": "<p>Three bodies A, B and C have equal kinetic energies and their masses are $$400 \\mathrm{~g}, 1.2 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ and $$1.6 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ respectively. The ratio of their linear momenta is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: \\sqrt{3}: 2$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{3}: \\sqrt{2}: 1$$\n",
      "$$1: \\sqrt{3}: \\sqrt{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{2} : \\sqrt{3}: 1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$$1: \\sqrt{3}: 2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v4nwq",
    "question": "<p>A wooden block of mass $$5 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ rests on a soft horizontal floor. When an iron cylinder of mass $$25 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is placed on the top of the block, the floor yields and the block and the cylinder together go down with an acceleration of $$0.1 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$. The action force of the system on the floor is equal to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "297 N",
      "291 N",
      "196 N",
      "294 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "291 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s20sm",
    "question": "<p>A particle moves in $$x$$-$$y$$ plane under the influence of a force $$\\vec{F}$$ such that its linear momentum is $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{p}}(\\mathrm{t})=\\hat{i} \\cos (\\mathrm{kt})-\\hat{j} \\sin (\\mathrm{kt})$$. If $$\\mathrm{k}$$ is constant, the angle between $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{F}}$$ and $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{p}}$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{3}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{4}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{6}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "newton's-laws-of-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\pi}{2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "Zdwyrk0wSeS0l84x",
    "question": "A block of mass $$m$$ is connected to another block of $$mass$$ $$M$$ by a spring (massless) of spring constant $$k.$$ The block are kept on a smooth horizontal plane. Initially the blocks are at rest and the spring is unstretched. Then a constant force $$F$$  starts acting on the block of mass $$M$$ to pull it. Find the force of the block of mass $$m.$$ ",
    "options": [
      "$${{MF} \\over {\\left( {m + M} \\right)}}$$ ",
      "$${{mF} \\over M}$$ ",
      "$${{\\left( {M + m} \\right)F} \\over m}$$ ",
      "$${{mF} \\over {\\left( {m + M} \\right)}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "spring-force",
    "solution": "$${{mF} \\over {\\left( {m + M} \\right)}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "lXexIz09ayYiSs8FQ73rsa0w2w9jx7ixwlm",
    "question": "A spring whose unstretched length is l has a force constant k. The spring is cut into two pieces of unstretched\nlengths l<sub>1</sub> and l<sub>2</sub> where, l<sub>1</sub> = nl<sub>2</sub> and n is an integer. The ratio k<sub>1</sub>/k<sub>2</sub> of the corresponding force constant, k<sub>1</sub> and\nk<sub>2</sub> will be :\n",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {{n^2}}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over n}$$",
      "n<sup>2</sup>",
      "n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "laws-of-motion",
    "topic": "spring-force",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over n}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "sPteMiYb0N0b1Xr6",
    "question": "A magnetic needle lying parallel to a magnetic field requires $$W$$ units of work to turn it through $${60^ \\circ }.$$ The torque needed to maintain the needle in this position will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt 3 \\,W$$ ",
      "$$W$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}W$$ ",
      "$$2W$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "bar-magnet-or-magnetic-dipole",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt 3 \\,W$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "FMEav1IEPCSCEKN8",
    "question": "The magnetic lines of force inside a bar magnet",
    "options": [
      "are from north-pole to south-pole of the magnet ",
      "do not exist ",
      "depend upon the area of cross-section of the bar magnet ",
      "are from south-pole to north-pole of the Magnet "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "bar-magnet-or-magnetic-dipole",
    "solution": "are from south-pole to north-pole of the Magnet "
  },
  {
    "id": "qV4VDlhcI7bU9ulG",
    "question": "The length of a magnet is large compared to its width and breadth. The time period of its oscillation in a vibration magnetometer is $$2s.$$ The magnet is cut along its length into three equal parts and these parts are then placed on each other with their like poles together. The time period of this combination  will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\sqrt 3 \\,s$$ ",
      "$${2 \\over 3}\\,\\,s$$ ",
      "$$2\\,s$$ ",
      "$${2 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}\\,s$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "bar-magnet-or-magnetic-dipole",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over 3}\\,\\,s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "mhzXiXTuZGuYVtGL",
    "question": "Two short bar magnets of length $$1$$ $$cm$$ each have magnetic moments $$1.20$$ $$A{m^2}$$  and $$1.00$$ $$A{m^2}$$ respectively. They are placed on a horizontal table parallel to each other with their $$N$$ poles pointing towards the South. They have a common magnetic equator and are separated by a distance of $$20.0$$ $$cm.$$  The value of the resultant horizontal magnetic induction at the mid-point $$O$$ of the line joining their centres is close to $$\\left( \\, \\right.$$ Horizontal component of earth's magnetic induction is $$3.6 \\times 10.5Wb/{m^2})$$",
    "options": [
      "$$3.6 \\times 10.5\\,\\,Wb/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$$2.56 \\times 10.4\\,\\,Wb/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$$3.50 \\times 10.4\\,\\,Wb/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$$5.80 \\times 10.4\\,Wb/{m^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "bar-magnet-or-magnetic-dipole",
    "solution": "$$2.56 \\times 10.4\\,\\,Wb/{m^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "pOQu5CXttZt86nBQ",
    "question": "A magnetic needle of magnetic moment 6.7 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> A m<sup>2</sup> and moment of inertia 7.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-6</sup> kg m<sup>2</sup> is\nperforming simple harmonic oscillations in a magnetic field of 0.01 T. Time taken for 10 complete oscillations is:",
    "options": [
      "8.76 s",
      "6.65 s ",
      "8.89 s",
      "6.98 s "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "bar-magnet-or-magnetic-dipole",
    "solution": "6.65 s "
  },
  {
    "id": "skH7KFy3WbDIneKvpqw1A",
    "question": "A magnet of total magnetic moment 10<sup>-2</sup> $${\\widehat i}$$ A-m<sup>2</sup> is placed in a time varying magnetic field, B$${\\widehat i}$$ (cos $$\\omega t$$)  where B  = 1 Tesla and $$\\omega $$ = 0.125 rad/s. The work done for reversing the direction of the magnetic moment at t = 1 second, is -",
    "options": [
      "0.014 J",
      "0.028 J",
      "0.01 J",
      "0.007 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "bar-magnet-or-magnetic-dipole",
    "solution": "0.014 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "dDhyuQwHaCnCoCxmHnjgy2xuketxlgem",
    "question": "A small bar magnet placed with its axis <br/>at 30<sup>o</sup> with an external field of 0.06 T <br/>experiences a torque of 0.018 Nm. The <br/>minimum work required to rotate it from its <br/>stable to unstable equilibrium position is :",
    "options": [
      "6.4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-2</sup> J",
      "9.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-3</sup> J",
      "7.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-2</sup> J",
      "11.7 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-3</sup> J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "bar-magnet-or-magnetic-dipole",
    "solution": "7.2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-2</sup> J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58huukt",
    "question": "<p>A bar magnet having a magnetic moment of 2.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> JT<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, is placed along the direction of uniform magnetic field of magnitude B \n = 14 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> T. The work done in rotating the magnet slowly through 60$$^\\circ$$ from the direction of field is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "14 J",
      "8.4 J",
      "4 J",
      "1.4 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "bar-magnet-or-magnetic-dipole",
    "solution": "14 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpjobc3",
    "question": "<p>A bar magnet with a magnetic moment $$5.0 \\mathrm{Am}^{2}$$ is placed in parallel position relative to a magnetic field of $$0.4 \\mathrm{~T}$$. The amount of required work done in turning the magnet from parallel to antiparallel position relative to the field direction is _____________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "zero",
      "1 J",
      "2 J",
      "4 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "bar-magnet-or-magnetic-dipole",
    "solution": "4 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvrck2h",
    "question": "<p>A bar magnet is released from rest along the axis of a very long vertical copper tube. After some time the magnet will</p>",
    "options": [
      "move down with almost constant speed",
      "move down with an acceleration equal to $$\\mathrm{g}$$",
      "move down with an acceleration greater than $$\\mathrm{g}$$",
      "oscillate inside the tube"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "bar-magnet-or-magnetic-dipole",
    "solution": "move down with almost constant speed"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2erjiy",
    "question": "<p>The magnetic moment of a bar magnet is $$0.5 \\mathrm{~Am}^2$$. It is suspended in a uniform magnetic field of $$8 \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{~T}$$. The work done in rotating it from its most stable to most unstable position is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4 \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{~J}$$\n",
      "$$16 \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{~J}$$\n",
      "$$8 \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{~J}$$\n",
      "Zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "bar-magnet-or-magnetic-dipole",
    "solution": "$$8 \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{~J}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "O7dDiQkrG322WKfx",
    "question": "A thin rectangular magnet suspended freely has a period of oscillation equal to $$T.$$ Now it is broken into two equal halves (each having half of the original length) and one piece is made to oscillate freely in the same field. If its period of oscillation is $$T',$$ the ratio $${{T'} \\over T}$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {2\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$$2$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 4}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "6WSZr8XzO1ftOsYxPeCal",
    "question": "A fighter plane of length 20 m, wing span (distance from tip of one wing to the tip of the other wing) of 15 m and height 5 m is flying towards east over Delhi. Its speed is 240 ms<sup>−1</sup>. The earth’s magnetic field over Delhi is 5 $$ \\times $$10<sup>−5</sup> T with the declination angle ~ 0<sup>o</sup> and dip of $$\\theta $$ such that sin $$\\theta $$ = 2/3 . If the voltage developed is V<sub>B</sub> between the lower and upper side of the plane and V<sub>W</sub> between the tips of the wings then V<sub>B</sub> and V<sub>W</sub> are close to :",
    "options": [
      "V<sub>B</sub> = 45 m<sub>V</sub>;  V<sub>W</sub> = 120 m<sub>V</sub> with right side of pilot at higher voltage",
      "V<sub>B</sub> = 45 m<sub>V</sub>;  V<sub>W</sub> = 120 m<sub>V</sub> with left side of pilot at higher voltage",
      "V<sub>B</sub> = 40 m<sub>V</sub>;  V<sub>W</sub> = 135 m<sub>V</sub> with right side of pilot at high voltage",
      "V<sub>B</sub> = 40 m<sub>V</sub>;  V<sub>W</sub> = 135 m<sub>V</sub> with left side of pilot at higher voltage"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "V<sub>B</sub> = 45 m<sub>V</sub>;  V<sub>W</sub> = 120 m<sub>V</sub> with left side of pilot at higher voltage"
  },
  {
    "id": "wW7I1LJwakQxcg5usjljn",
    "question": "At some location on earth, the horizontal component of earth’s magnetic field is 18 × 10<sup>–6</sup> T. At this location, magnetic needle of length 0.12 m and pole strength 1.8 Am is suspended from its mid-point using a thread, it makes 45<sup>o</sup> angle with horizontal in equilibrium. To keep this needle horizontal, the vertical force that should be applied at one of its ends is - ",
    "options": [
      "3.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> N",
      "1.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> N",
      "1.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> N",
      "6.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "6.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> N"
  },
  {
    "id": "D7s7WIQA48T6bBoyWh3rsa0w2w9jx3ox5th",
    "question": "A magnetic compass needle oscillates 30 times per minute at a place where the dip is 45<sup>o</sup>, and 40 times per\nminute where the dip is 30<sup>o</sup>. If B<sub>1</sub> and B<sub>2</sub> are respectively the total magnetic field due to the earth at the two\nplaces, then the ratio $${{{B_1}} \\over {{B_2}}}$$ is best given by :",
    "options": [
      "1.8",
      "2.2",
      "0.7",
      "3.6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "0.7"
  },
  {
    "id": "IRpj4ExeE8oPTxrF0c1kmhou325",
    "question": "A bar magnet of length 14 cm is placed in the magnetic meridian with its north pole pointing towards the geographic north pole. A neutral point is obtained at a distance of 18 cm from the center of the magnet. If B<sub>H</sub> = 0.4 G, the magnetic moment of the magnet is : (1G = 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> T)",
    "options": [
      "2.880 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>2</sup> J T<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "2.880 J T<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "2.880 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> J T<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "28.80 J T<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "2.880 J T<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqd4wnj",
    "question": "At an angle of 30$$^\\circ$$ to the magnetic meridian, the apparent dip is 45$$^\\circ$$. Find the true dip :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\sqrt 3 $$",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}{1 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}{2 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}{{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}{{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krstkhv7",
    "question": "Choose the correct option",
    "options": [
      "True dip is always equal to apparent dip.",
      "True dip is not mathematically related to apparent dip.",
      "True dip is less than the apparent dip.",
      "True dip is always greater than the apparent dip."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "True dip is less than the apparent dip."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l547l3c4",
    "question": "<p>At a certain place the angle of dip is 30$$^\\circ$$ and the horizontal component of earth's magnetic field is 0.5 G. The earth's total magnetic field (in G), at that certain place, is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt 3 $$",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f4wzmn",
    "question": "<p>An electron with energy 0.1 keV moves at right angle to the earth's magnetic field of 1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> Wbm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>. The frequency of revolution of the electron will be :</p>\n<p>(Take mass of electron = 9.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$31</sup> kg)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1.6 \\times 10^{5} \\mathrm{~Hz}$$",
      "$$5.6 \\times 10^{5} \\mathrm{~Hz}$$",
      "$$2.8 \\times 10^{6} \\mathrm{~Hz}$$",
      "$$1.8 \\times 10^{6} \\mathrm{~Hz}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "$$2.8 \\times 10^{6} \\mathrm{~Hz}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6ji3kv8",
    "question": "<p>Two bar magnets oscillate in a horizontal plane in earth's magnetic field with time periods of $$3 \\mathrm{~s}$$ and $$4 \\mathrm{~s}$$ respectively. If their moments of inertia are in the ratio of $$3: 2$$, then the ratio of their magnetic moments will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 : 1",
      "8 : 3",
      "1 : 3",
      "27 : 16"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "8 : 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6ji5x05",
    "question": "<p>A magnet hung at $$45^{\\circ}$$ with magnetic meridian makes an angle of $$60^{\\circ}$$ with the horizontal. The actual value of the angle of dip is -</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\sqrt{\\frac{3}{2}}\\right)$$",
      "$$\\tan ^{-1}(\\sqrt{6})$$",
      "$$\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\sqrt{\\frac{2}{3}}\\right)$$",
      "$$\n\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\sqrt{\\frac{1}{2}}\\right)\n$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "$$\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\sqrt{\\frac{3}{2}}\\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kna9gd",
    "question": "<p>A compass needle of oscillation magnetometer oscillates 20 times per minute at a place $$\\mathrm{P}$$ of $$\\operatorname{dip} 30^{\\circ}$$. The number of oscillations per minute become 10 at another place $$\\mathrm{Q}$$ of $$60^{\\circ}$$ dip. The ratio of the total magnetic field at the two places $$\\left(B_{Q}: B_{P}\\right)$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{3}: 4$$",
      "$$4: \\sqrt{3}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{3}: 2$$",
      "$$2: \\sqrt{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{3}: 4$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rhoxgq",
    "question": "<p>The vertical component of the earth's magnetic field is $$6 \\times 10^{-5} \\mathrm{~T}$$ at any place where the angle of dip is $$37^{\\circ}$$. The earth's resultant magnetic field at that place will be $$\\left(\\right.$$Given $$\\left.\\tan 37^{\\circ}=\\frac{3}{4}\\right)$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$8 \\times 10^{-5} \\mathrm{~T}$$",
      "$$6 \\times 10^{-5} \\mathrm{~T}$$",
      "$$5 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~T}$$",
      "$$1 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~T}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "earth-magnetism",
    "solution": "$$1 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~T}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lxi5dqpu8KT455Qj",
    "question": "Curie temperature is the temperature above which ",
    "options": [
      "a ferromagnetic material becomes paramagnetic ",
      "a paramagnetic material becomes diamagnetic ",
      "a ferromagnetic material becomes diamagnetic ",
      "a paramagnetic material becomes ferromagnetic "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "a ferromagnetic material becomes paramagnetic "
  },
  {
    "id": "WDtUzNJOuUtiySe6",
    "question": "The materials suitable for making electromagnets should have ",
    "options": [
      "high retentivity and low coercivity ",
      "low  retentivity and low coercivity ",
      "high retentivity and high coercivity ",
      "low  retentivity and high coercivity "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "low  retentivity and low coercivity "
  },
  {
    "id": "niRU9jARoFtaL7H1",
    "question": "A magnetic needle is kept in a non-uniform magnetic field. It experiences :",
    "options": [
      "neither a force nor a torque ",
      "a torque but not a force ",
      "a force but not a torque ",
      "a force and a torque "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "a force and a torque "
  },
  {
    "id": "ERT4YS8a74gtkmnb",
    "question": "Needles $${N_1}$$, $${N_2}$$ and $${N_3}$$ are made of ferromagnetic, a paramagnetic and a diamagnetic substance respectively. A magnet when brought close to them will ",
    "options": [
      "attract $${N_1}$$ and $${N_2}$$ strongly but repel $${N_3}$$ ",
      "attract $${N_1}$$ strongly, $${N_2}$$ weakly and repel $${N_3}$$ weakly ",
      "attract $${N_1}$$ strongly, but repel $${N_2}$$ and $${N_3}$$ weakly",
      "attract all three of them "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "attract $${N_1}$$ strongly, $${N_2}$$ weakly and repel $${N_3}$$ weakly "
  },
  {
    "id": "d9HAj6Cs5kMUufPN",
    "question": "Relative permittivity and permeability of a material $${\\varepsilon _r}$$ and $${\\mu _r},$$ respectively. Which of the following values of these quantities are allowed for a diamagnetic material? ",
    "options": [
      "$${\\varepsilon _r} = 0.5,\\,\\,{\\mu _r} = 1.5$$ ",
      "$${\\varepsilon _r} = 1.5,\\,\\,{\\mu _r} = 0.5$$ ",
      "$${\\varepsilon _r} = 0.5,\\,\\,{\\mu _r} = 0.5$$ ",
      "$${\\varepsilon _r} = 1.5,\\,\\,{\\mu _r} = 1.5$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "$${\\varepsilon _r} = 1.5,\\,\\,{\\mu _r} = 0.5$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "4A7SjeO13G5jJ1jE",
    "question": "The coercivity of a small magnet where the ferromagnet gets demagnetized is $$3 \\times {10^3}\\,A{m^{ - 1}}.$$ The current required to be passed in a solenoid of length $$10$$ $$cm$$ and number of turns $$100,$$ so that the magnet gets demagnetized when inside the solenoid, is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$30$$ $$mA$$ ",
      "$$60$$ $$mA$$ ",
      "$$3$$ $$A$$ ",
      "$$6A$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "$$3$$ $$A$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "KWhFEVUx8ymqDgdInkkN4",
    "question": "A bar magnet is demagnetized by inserting it inside a solenoid of length 0.2 m, 100 turns, and carrying a current of 5.2 A. The corecivity of the bar magnet is : ",
    "options": [
      "285 A/m",
      "2600 A/m",
      "520 A/m",
      "1200 A/m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "2600 A/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "FmwZBIlFV560WL4XuDfFJ",
    "question": "A paramagnetic substance in the form of a cube with sides 1 cm has a magnetic dipole moment of 20 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–6</sup> J/ T when a magnetic intensity of 60 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>3</sup> A/m is applied. Its magnetic susceptibility is \n",
    "options": [
      "3.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup>",
      "2.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–2</sup>",
      "4.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–2</sup>",
      "3.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "3.3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "SHuuvlT78BVdRd5uVbAKN",
    "question": "A paramagnetic material has 10<sup>28</sup> atoms/m<sup>3</sup>. Its magnetic susceptibility at temperature 350 K is 2.8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup>. Its susceptibility at 300 K is : ",
    "options": [
      "3.726 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup>",
      "2.672 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup>",
      "3.672 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup>",
      "3.267 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "3.267 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "9eWZ4t2Ln2EGpCaKVRjgy2xukfak0xk1",
    "question": "A paramagnetic sample shows a net magnetisation of 6 A/m when it is placed in an external\nmagnetic field of 0.4 T at a temperature of 4 K. When the sample is placed in an external magnetic\nfield of 0.3 T at a temperature of 24 K, then the magnetisation will be:\n",
    "options": [
      "4 A/m",
      "1 A/m",
      "0.75 A/m",
      "2.25 A/m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "0.75 A/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "j0qhupOGehQTL4vbnM1klrnx3h8",
    "question": "A soft ferromagnetic material is placed in an external magnetic field. The magnetic domains :",
    "options": [
      "may increase or decrease in size and change its orientation.",
      "increase in size but no change in orientation.",
      "decrease in size and changes orientation.",
      "have no relation with external magnetic field."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "may increase or decrease in size and change its orientation."
  },
  {
    "id": "zkHpx5JygAuEDEZmFm1klt2hx0y",
    "question": "In a ferromagnetic material, below the curie temperature, a domain is defined as :",
    "options": [
      "a macroscopic region with zero magnetization.",
      "a macroscopic region with saturation magnetization.",
      "a macroscopic region with randomly oriented magnetic dipoles.",
      "a macroscopic region with consecutive magnetic dipoles oriented in opposite direction."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "a macroscopic region with saturation magnetization."
  },
  {
    "id": "P1REhJODCQPR64Oq3W1kmlwi0i9",
    "question": "Which of the following statements are correct?<br/><br/>(A) Electric monopoles do not exist whereas magnetic monopoles exist.<br/><br/>(B) Magnetic field lines due to a solenoid at its ends and outside cannot be completely straight and confined.<br/><br/>(C) Magnetic field lines are completely confined within a toroid.<br/><br/>(D) Magnetic field lines inside a bar magnet are not parallel.<br/><br/>(E) $$\\chi $$ = $$-$$1 is the condition for a perfect diamagnetic material, where x is its magnetic susceptibility.<br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A) and (B) only",
      "(B) and (C) only",
      "(C) and (E) only",
      "(B) and (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "(C) and (E) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqe8g81",
    "question": "The magnetic susceptibility of a material of a rod is 499. Permeability in vacuum is 4$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> H/m. Absolute permeability of the material of the rod is :",
    "options": [
      "4$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> H/m",
      "2$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> H/m",
      "3$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> H/m",
      "$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> H/m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "2$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> H/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsuz3cm",
    "question": "Statement I : The ferromagnetic property depends on temperature. At high temperature, ferromagnet becomes paramagnet.<br/><br/>Statement II : At high temperature, the domain wall area of a ferromagnetic substance increases.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55k7ko4",
    "question": "<p>The space inside a straight current carrying solenoid is filled with a magnetic material having magnetic susceptibility equal to 1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup>. What is fractional increase in the magnetic field inside solenoid with respect to air as medium inside the solenoid?</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup>",
      "1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup>",
      "1.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup>",
      "2.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57pz5z4",
    "question": "<p>The susceptibility of a paramagnetic material is 99. The permeability of the material in Wb/A-m, is :</p>\n<p>[Permeability of free space $$\\mu$$<sub>0</sub> = 4$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> Wb/A-m]</p>",
    "options": [
      "4$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup>",
      "4$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup>",
      "4$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup>",
      "4$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "4$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59p2qm6",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : Susceptibilities of paramagnetic and ferromagnetic substances increase with decrease in temperature.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Diamagnetism is a result of orbital motions of electrons developing magnetic moments opposite to the applied magnetic field.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false.",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbqkw9",
    "question": "<p>The soft-iron is a suitable material for making an electromagnet. This is because soft-iron has</p>",
    "options": [
      "low coercivity and high retentivity.",
      "low coercivity  and low permeability.",
      "high permeability and low retentivity.",
      "high permeability and high retentivity."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "high permeability and low retentivity."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduhtztl",
    "question": "<p>A solenoid of 1200 turns is wound uniformly in a single layer on a glass tube 2 m long and 0.2 m in diameter. The magnetic intensity at the center of the solenoid when a current of 2 A flows through it is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{1~A~m^{-1}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{2.4\\times10^{-3}~A~m^{-1}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{1.2\\times10^{3}~A~m^{-1}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{2.4\\times10^{3}~A~m^{-1}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{1.2\\times10^{3}~A~m^{-1}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrihor0",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : The diamagnetic property depends on temperature.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The induced magnetic dipole moment in a diamagnetic sample is always opposite to the magnetizing field.</p>\n<p>In the light of given statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is true.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is false.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are False.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is true."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lguy26ih",
    "question": "<p>The free space inside a current carrying toroid is filled with a material of susceptibility $$2 \\times 10^{-2}$$. The percentage increase in the value of magnetic field inside the toroid will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.1%",
      "1%",
      "2%",
      "0.2%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "2%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvrqwqj",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : For diamagnetic substance, $$-1 \\leq \\chi &lt; 0$$, where $$\\chi$$ is the magnetic susceptibility.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Diamagnetic substances when placed in an external magnetic field, tend to move from stronger to weaker part of the field.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are False",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqpe9z",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Electromagnets are made of soft iron.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Soft iron has high permeability and low retentivity.</p>\n<p>In the light of above, statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gs8ij",
    "question": "<p>Paramagnetic substances:</p>\n<p>A. align themselves along the directions of external magnetic field.</p>\n<p>B. attract strongly towards external magnetic field.</p>\n<p>C. has susceptibility little more than zero.</p>\n<p>D. move from a region of strong magnetic field to weak magnetic field.</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A, B, C Only\n",
      "A, C Only\n",
      "A, B, C, D\n",
      "B, D Only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "magnetic-properties-of-matter",
    "solution": "A, C Only\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "VcuO2F4nkDvpy1BN",
    "question": "A current $$i$$ ampere flows along an infinitely long straight thin walled tube, then the magnetic induction at any point inside the tube is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\mu _0}} \\over {4\\pi }},{{2i} \\over r}$$ tesla",
      "zero ",
      "infinite ",
      "$${{2i} \\over r}$$ tesla "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "ampere's-circuital-law",
    "solution": "zero "
  },
  {
    "id": "Pq5oxzvCxCgfQOaJ",
    "question": "A current $$I$$ flows along the length of an infinitely long, straight, thin walled pipe. Then ",
    "options": [
      "the magnetic field at all points inside the pipe is the same, but not zero ",
      "the magnetic field is zero only on the axis of the pipe ",
      "the magnetic field is different at different points inside the pipe ",
      "the magnetic field at any point inside the pipe is zero "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "ampere's-circuital-law",
    "solution": "the magnetic field at any point inside the pipe is zero "
  },
  {
    "id": "Z1KF0Vi3wPIwHIri",
    "question": "A long straight wire of radius $$a$$ carries a steady current $$i.$$  The current is uniformly distributed across its cross section. The ratio of the magnetic field at $$a/2$$ and $$2a$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$1/2$$ ",
      "$$1/4$$ ",
      "$$4$$ ",
      "$$1$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "ampere's-circuital-law",
    "solution": "$$1$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "avMlH1RhAdrmbqPST07k9k2k5i7yq8c",
    "question": "A long, straight wire of radius a carries a current\ndistributed uniformly over its cross-section. The\nratio of the magnetic fields due to the wire at\ndistance\n$${a \\over 3}$$\nand 2$$a$$, respectively from the axis\nof the wire is :",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "ampere's-circuital-law",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over 3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5akmwj9",
    "question": "<p>A long straight wire with a circular cross-section having radius R, is carrying a steady current I. The current I is uniformly distributed across this cross-section. Then the variation of magnetic field due to current I with distance r (r &lt; R) from its centre will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "B $$\\propto$$ r<sup>2</sup>",
      "B $$\\propto$$ r",
      "B $$\\propto$$ $${1 \\over {{r^2}}}$$",
      "B $$\\propto$$ $${1 \\over {{r}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "ampere's-circuital-law",
    "solution": "B $$\\propto$$ r"
  },
  {
    "id": "luyit8bo",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : When currents vary with time, Newton's third law is valid only if momentum carried by the electromagnetic field is taken into account</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : Ampere's circuital law does not depend on Biot-Savart's law.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "ampere's-circuital-law",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3ve5u6",
    "question": "<p>A long straight wire of radius a carries a steady current I. The current is uniformly distributed across its cross section. The ratio of the magnetic field at $$\\frac{a}{2}$$ and $$2 a$$ from axis of the wire is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4: 1$$\n",
      "$$3: 4$$\n",
      "$$1: 1$$\n",
      "$$1: 4$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "ampere's-circuital-law",
    "solution": "$$1: 1$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v4nve",
    "question": "In a co-axial straight cable, the central conductor and the outer conductor carry equal currents in opposite directions. The magnetic field is zero :\n",
    "options": [
      "inside the outer conductor\n",
      "outside the cable\n",
      "in between the two conductors\n",
      "inside the inner conductor"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "ampere's-circuital-law",
    "solution": "outside the cable\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "WD0q2YvOYRHe34OB",
    "question": "If in a circular coil $$A$$ of radius $$R,$$ current $$I$$ is flowing and in another coil $$B$$ of  radius $$2R$$ a current $$2I$$ is flowing, then the ratio of the magnetic fields $${B_A}$$ and $${B_B}$$, produced by them will be",
    "options": [
      "$$1$$ ",
      "$$2$$ ",
      "$$1/2$$ ",
      "$$4$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$$1$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "WlHhKqTXJQRnMjVA",
    "question": "If a current is passed through a spring then the spring will ",
    "options": [
      "expand ",
      "compress ",
      "remains same ",
      "none of these "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "compress "
  },
  {
    "id": "YkefiN3lSqNIJjbG",
    "question": "The magnetic field due to a current carrying circular loop of radius $$3$$ $$cm$$ at a point on the axis at a distance of $$4$$ $$cm$$  from the centre is $$54\\,\\mu T.$$ What will be its value at the center of loop? ",
    "options": [
      "$$125\\,\\mu T$$ ",
      "$$150\\,\\mu T$$ ",
      "$$250\\,\\mu T$$ ",
      "$$75\\,\\mu T$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$$250\\,\\mu T$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "aMzGAKu0xbErsKMz",
    "question": "A long wire carries a steady current. It is bent into a circle of one turn and the magnetic field at the centre of the coil is $$B.$$ It is then bent into a circular loop of $$n$$ turns. The magnetic field at the center of the coil will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$2n$$ $$B$$",
      "$${n^2}\\,B$$ ",
      "$$nB$$ ",
      "$$2{n^2}\\,B$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$${n^2}\\,B$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "DEJ0ZORcycCycSqo",
    "question": "Two concentric coils each of radius equal to $$2$$ $$\\pi $$ $$cm$$ are placed at right  angles to each other. $$3$$ ampere and $$4$$ ampere  are the currents flowing in each coil respectively . The magnetic induction in Weber / $${m^2}$$ at the center of the coils will be \n<br/>$$\\left( {\\mu  = 4\\pi  \\times {{10}^{ - 7}}Wb/A.m} \\right)$$ ",
    "options": [
      "$${10^{ - 5}}$$ ",
      "$$12 \\times {10^{ - 5}}$$ ",
      "$$7 \\times {10^{ - 5}}$$",
      "$$5 \\times {10^{ - 5}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$$5 \\times {10^{ - 5}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "kTfJS2Muy0aneH3p",
    "question": "A long solenoid has $$200$$ turns per $$cm$$ and carries a current $$i.$$ The magnetic field at its center is $$6.28 \\times {10^{ - 2}}\\,\\,\\,Weber/{m^2}.$$ Another long solenoid has $$100$$ turns per $$cm$$ and it carries a current $${i \\over 3}$$. The value of the magnetic field at its center is ",
    "options": [
      "$$1.05 \\times {10^{ - 2}}\\,\\,Weber/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$$1.05 \\times {10^{ - 5}}\\,\\,Weber/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$$1.05 \\times {10^{ - 3}}\\,\\,Weber/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$$1.05 \\times {10^{ - 4}}\\,\\,Weber/{m^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$$1.05 \\times {10^{ - 2}}\\,\\,Weber/{m^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "1AGYz8zqqcvkX77q",
    "question": "Two identical conducting wires $$AOB$$ and $$COD$$ are placed at right angles to each other. The wire $$AOB$$ carries an electric current $${I_1}$$ and $$COD$$ carries a current $${I_2}$$. The magnetic field on a point lying at a distance $$d$$ from $$O$$, in a direction perpendicular to the plane of the wires $$AOB$$ and $$COD$$ , will be given by ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\mu _0}} \\over {2\\pi d}}\\left( {I_1^2 + I_2^2} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}} \\over {2\\pi }}{\\left( {{{{I_1} + {I_2}} \\over d}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}} \\over {2\\pi d}}{\\left( {I_1^2 + I_2^2} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}} \\over {2\\pi d}}\\left( {{I_1} + {I_2}} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$${{{\\mu _0}} \\over {2\\pi d}}{\\left( {I_1^2 + I_2^2} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "iNdr8BSAK0cZYxGI",
    "question": "A horizontal overhead powerline is at height of $$4m$$ from the ground and carries a current of $$100A$$ from east to west. The magnetic field directly below it on the ground is \n<br/>$$\\left( {{\\mu _0} = 4\\pi  \\times {{10}^{ - 7}}\\,\\,Tm\\,\\,{A^{ - 1}}} \\right)$$",
    "options": [
      "$$2.5 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\,T$$ southward ",
      "$$5 \\times {10^{ - 6}}\\,T$$ northward ",
      "$$5 \\times {10^{ - 6}}\\,T$$ southward ",
      "$$2.5 \\times {10^{ - 7}}\\,T$$ northward "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$$5 \\times {10^{ - 6}}\\,T$$ southward "
  },
  {
    "id": "e34tGaWytOB3jjc1",
    "question": "A current $$I$$ flows in an infinitely long wire with cross section in the form of a semi-circular ring of radius $$R.$$ The magnitude of the magnetic induction along its axis is: ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\mu _0}I} \\over {2{\\pi ^2}R}}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}I} \\over {2\\pi R}}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}I} \\over {4\\pi R}}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}I} \\over {{\\pi ^2}R}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$${{{\\mu _0}I} \\over {{\\pi ^2}R}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "gyP9zjrGP7grn9me",
    "question": "Two identical wires $$A$$ and $$B,$$ each of length $$'l'$$, carry the same current $$I$$. Wire $$A$$ is bent into a circle of radius $$R$$ and wire $$B$$ is bent to form a square of side $$'a'$$. If $${B_A}$$ and $${B_B}$$ are the values of magnetic fields at the centres of the circle and square respectively, then the ratio $${{{B_A}} \\over {{B_B}}}$$ is: ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\pi ^2}} \\over {16}}$$ ",
      "$${{{\\pi ^2}} \\over {8\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$${{{\\pi ^2}} \\over {8}}$$",
      "$${{{\\pi ^2}} \\over {16\\sqrt 2 }}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$${{{\\pi ^2}} \\over {8\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "liSnQLs1rbNsiHJs",
    "question": "The dipole moment of a circular loop carrying a current I, is m and the magnetic field at the centre of the\nloop is B<sub>1</sub>. When the dipole moment is doubled by keeping the current constant, the magnetic field at the\ncentre of the loop is $${{B_2}}$$. The ratio $${{{B_1}} \\over {{B_2}}}$$ is: ",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "$$\\sqrt 3 $$",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$$1 \\over \\sqrt 2 $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt 2 $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "iOVtqRFyzIOL0auuW4PAO",
    "question": "A current of 1 A is flowing on the sides of an equilateral triangle of side 4.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-2</sup> m. The magnetic field at the center of the triangle will be :",
    "options": [
      "2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-5</sup> Wb/m<sup>2</sup> ",
      "Zero",
      "8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-5</sup> Wb/m<sup>2</sup>",
      "4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-5</sup> Wb/m<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "4 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-5</sup> Wb/m<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "i7RjAPQQbWR7YrMMlf3rsa0w2w9jx3dntoy",
    "question": "A thin ring of 10 cm radius carries a uniformly distributed charge. The ring rotates at a constant angular\nspeed of 40 $$\\pi $$ rad s<sup>–1</sup>\n about its axis, perpendicular to its plane. If the magnetic field at its centre is 3.8 × 10<sup>–9</sup>\nT, then the charge carried by the ring is close to ($$\\mu $$<sub>0</sub> = 4$$\\pi $$ × 10<sup>–7</sup>\n N/A<sup>2</sup>\n).",
    "options": [
      "7 × 10<sup>–6</sup> C",
      "4 × 10<sup>–5</sup> C",
      "2 × 10<sup>–6</sup> C",
      "3 × 10<sup>–5</sup> C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "3 × 10<sup>–5</sup> C"
  },
  {
    "id": "TJteEvhVtRYzb5bZbW3rsa0w2w9jwzjyd8u",
    "question": "The magnitude of the magnetic field at the centre of an equilateral triangular loop of side 1 m which is\ncarrying a current of 10 A is : <br/>[Take $$\\mu $$<sub>0</sub> = 4$$\\pi $$ × 10<sup>–7</sup>\n NA<sup>–2</sup>] ",
    "options": [
      "3 $$\\mu $$T",
      "18 $$\\mu $$T",
      "9 $$\\mu $$T",
      "1 $$\\mu $$T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "18 $$\\mu $$T"
  },
  {
    "id": "ue0ZrEiwYks1ZfPOGqhdW",
    "question": "One of the two identical conducting wires of length L is bent in the form of a circular loop and the other one into a circular coil of N identical turns. If the same current is passed in both, the radio of the magnetic field at the central of the loop (B<sub>L</sub>) to that at the center of the coil (B<sub>C</sub>),  i.e. $${{{B_L}} \\over {{B_C}}}$$ will be : ",
    "options": [
      "N",
      "$${1 \\over N}$$",
      "N<sup>2</sup>",
      "$${1 \\over {{N^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {{N^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "gHQvNc1ZLPP8aXrrRLjgy2xukf24nnfz",
    "question": "Magnitude of magnetic field (in SI units) at the\ncentre of a hexagonal shape coil of side 10 cm,\n50 turns and carrying current I (Ampere) in\nunits of $${{{\\mu _0}I} \\over \\pi }$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "250$$\\sqrt 3 $$",
      "5$$\\sqrt 3 $$",
      "500$$\\sqrt 3 $$",
      "50$$\\sqrt 3 $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "500$$\\sqrt 3 $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "yQxQFbjWuaPDxeGEri1klrx359q",
    "question": "Magnetic fields at two points on the axis of a circular coil at a distance of 0.05 m and 0.2 m from the centre are in the ratio 8 : 1. The radius of coil is ________.",
    "options": [
      "1.0 m",
      "0.15 m",
      "0.2 m",
      "0.1 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "0.1 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "dmhKqMoSYyM95CbNG31kmj1zx26",
    "question": "A solenoid of 1000 turns per metre has a core with relative permeability 500. Insulated windings of the solenoid carry an electric current of 5A. The magnetic flux density produced by the solenoid is : (permeability of free space = 4$$\\pi$$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> H/m)",
    "options": [
      "$$\\pi$$T",
      "2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup>$$\\pi$$ T",
      "10<sup>$$-$$4</sup>$$\\pi$$ T",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 5}$$ T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$$\\pi$$T"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kta8799v",
    "question": "The fractional change in the magnetic field intensity at a distance 'r' from centre on the axis of current carrying coil of radius 'a' to the magnetic field intensity at the centre of the same coil is : (Take r &lt; a)",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 2}{{{a^2}} \\over {{r^2}}}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}{{{a^2}} \\over {{r^2}}}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}{{{r^2}} \\over {{a^2}}}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}{{{r^2}} \\over {{a^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 2}{{{r^2}} \\over {{a^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfn5nqx",
    "question": "A coaxial cable consists of an inner wire of radius 'a' surrounded by an outer shell of inner and outer radii 'b' and 'c' respectively. The inner wire carries an electric current i<sub>0</sub>, which is distributed uniformly across cross-sectional area. The outer shell carries an equal current in opposite direction and distributed uniformly. What will be the ratio of the magnetic field at a distance x from the axis when (i) x &lt; a and (ii) a &lt; x &lt; b ?",
    "options": [
      "$${{{x^2}} \\over {{a^2}}}$$",
      "$${{{a^2}} \\over {{x^2}}}$$",
      "$${{{x^2}} \\over {{b^2} - {a^2}}}$$",
      "$${{{b^2} - {a^2}} \\over {{x^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$${{{x^2}} \\over {{a^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth2q1zt",
    "question": "A coil having N turns is wound tightly in the form of a spiral with inner and outer radii 'a' and 'b' respectively. Find the magnetic field at centre, when a current I passes through coil:",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\mu _0}IN} \\over {2(b - a)}}{\\log _e}\\left( {{b \\over a}} \\right)$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}I} \\over 8}\\left[ {{{a + b} \\over {a - b}}} \\right]$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}I} \\over {4(a - b)}}\\left[ {{1 \\over a} - {1 \\over b}} \\right]$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}I} \\over 8}\\left( {{{a - b} \\over {a + b}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$${{{\\mu _0}IN} \\over {2(b - a)}}{\\log _e}\\left( {{b \\over a}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjmzsh5",
    "question": "A current of 1.5 A is flowing through a triangle, of side 9 cm each. The magnetic field at the centroid of the triangle is :<br/><br/>(Assume that the current is flowing in the clockwise direction.)",
    "options": [
      "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> T, outside the plane of triangle ",
      "$$2\\sqrt 3 $$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> T, outside the plane of triangle",
      "$$2\\sqrt 3 $$ $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> T, inside the plane of triangle",
      "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> T, inside the plane of triangle"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> T, inside the plane of triangle"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59p3xqc",
    "question": "<p>A long solenoid carrying a current produces a magnetic field B along its axis. If the current is doubled and the number of turns per cm is halved, the new value of magnetic field will be equal to</p>",
    "options": [
      "B",
      "2B",
      "4B",
      "$${B \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "B"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c4bmf5",
    "question": "<p>The magnetic field at the centre of a circular coil of radius r, due to current I flowing through it, is B. The magnetic field at a point along the axis at a distance $${r \\over 2}$$ from the centre is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "B/2",
      "2B",
      "$${\\left( {{2 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}} \\right)^3}B$$",
      "$${\\left( {{2 \\over {\\sqrt 3}}} \\right)^3}B$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$${\\left( {{2 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}} \\right)^3}B$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w2hdwb",
    "question": "<p>A coil of n number of turns wound tightly in the form of a spiral with inner and outer radii r<sub>1</sub> and r<sub>2</sub> respectively. When a current of strength I is passed through the coil, the magnetic field at its centre will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${{{\\mu _0}nI} \\over {2({r_2} - {r_1})}}$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}nI} \\over {{r_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}nI} \\over {{r_2} - {r_1}}}{\\log _e}{{{r_1}} \\over {{r_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}nI} \\over {2({r_2} - {r_1})}}{\\log _e}{{{r_2}} \\over {{r_1}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$${{{\\mu _0}nI} \\over {2({r_2} - {r_1})}}{\\log _e}{{{r_2}} \\over {{r_1}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gmluyc",
    "question": "<p>$$\\mathrm{B}_{X}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}_{\\mathrm{Y}}$$ are the magnetic fields at the centre of two coils $$\\mathrm{X}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Y}$$ respectively each carrying equal current. If coil $$X$$ has 200 turns and $$20 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ radius and coil $$Y$$ has 400 turns and $$20 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ radius, the ratio of $$B_{X}$$ and $$B_{Y}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "1 : 2",
      "2 : 1",
      "4 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "1 : 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nso1d9",
    "question": "<p>The magnetic field at the center of current carrying circular loop is $$B_{1}$$. The magnetic field at a distance of $$\\sqrt{3}$$ times radius of the given circular loop from the  center on its axis is $$B_{2}$$. The value of $$B_{1} / B_{2}$$ will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "9 : 4",
      "12 : $$\\sqrt5$$",
      "8 : 1",
      "5 : $$\\sqrt3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "8 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo6x4hj",
    "question": "A long conducting wire having a current I flowing through it, is bent into a circular coil of $\\mathrm{N}$ turns. Then it is bent into a circular coil of $\\mathrm{n}$ turns. The magnetic field is calculated at the centre of coils in both the cases. The ratio of the magnetic field in first case to that of second case is :",
    "options": [
      "$ N^{2}: n^{2}$",
      "$\\mathrm{N}: \\mathrm{n}$",
      "$\\mathrm{n}: \\mathrm{N}$",
      "$n^{2}: N^{2}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$ N^{2}: n^{2}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsanxdr",
    "question": "<p>The electric current in a circular coil of four turns produces a magnetic induction 32 T at its centre. The coil is unwound and is rewound into a circular coil of single turn, the magnetic induction at the centre of the coil by the same current will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 T",
      "4 T",
      "8 T",
      "16 T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "2 T"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwqnmpd",
    "question": "<p>A long solenoid is formed by winding 70 turns cm$$^{-1}$$. If 2.0 A current flows, then the magnetic field produced inside the solenoid is ____________ ($$\\mu_0=4\\pi\\times10^{-7}$$ TmA$$^{-1}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$88\\times10^{-4}$$ T",
      "$$1232\\times10^{-4}$$ T",
      "$$176\\times10^{-4}$$ T",
      "$$352\\times10^{-4}$$ T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "$$176\\times10^{-4}$$ T"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldydj6mi",
    "question": "<p>A circular loop of radius $$r$$ is carrying current I A. The ratio of magnetic field at the center of circular loop and at a distance r from the center of the loop on its axis is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3$$\\sqrt2$$ : 2",
      "1 : 3$$\\sqrt2$$",
      "2$$\\sqrt2$$ : 1",
      "1 : $$\\sqrt2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "2$$\\sqrt2$$ : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh24yfpg",
    "question": "<p>A long straight wire of circular cross-section (radius a) is carrying steady current I. The current I is uniformly distributed across this cross-section. The magnetic field is</p>",
    "options": [
      "uniform in the region $$r < a$$ and inversely proportional to distance $$r$$ from the axis, in the region $$r > a$$",
      "zero in the region $$r < a$$ and inversely proportional to $$r$$ in the region $$r > a$$",
      "directly proportional to $$r$$ in the region $$r < a$$ and inversely proportional to $$r$$ in the region $$r > a$$",
      "inversely proportional to $$r$$ in the region $$r < a$$ and uniform throughout in the region $$r > a$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "biot-savart's-law-and-magnetic-field-due-to-current-carrying-wire",
    "solution": "directly proportional to $$r$$ in the region $$r < a$$ and inversely proportional to $$r$$ in the region $$r > a$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "DaFGDCYOPs7FhyoY",
    "question": "Two long conductors, separated by a distance $$d$$ carry current $${I_1}$$ and $${I_2}$$ in the same direction. They exert a force $$F$$ on each other. Now the current in one of them is increased to two times and its direction is reversed. The distance is also increased to $$3d$$. The new value of the force between them is ",
    "options": [
      "$$ - {{2F} \\over 3}$$ ",
      "$${F \\over 3}$$ ",
      "$$-2F$$ ",
      "$$ - {F \\over 3}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "$$ - {{2F} \\over 3}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "nvrFinNnXyrHel6C",
    "question": "Two thin, long, parallel wires, separated by a distance $$'d'$$ carry a current of $$'i'$$ $$A$$ in the same direction. They will ",
    "options": [
      "repel each other with a force of $${\\mu _0}{i^2}/\\left( {2\\pi d} \\right)$$ ",
      "attract each other with a force of $${\\mu _0}{i^2}/\\left( {2\\pi d} \\right)$$ ",
      "repel each other with a force $$_0{i^2}/\\left( {2\\pi {d^2}} \\right)$$ ",
      "attract each other with a force of $${\\mu _0}{i^2}/\\left( {2\\pi {d^2}} \\right)$$  "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "attract each other with a force of $${\\mu _0}{i^2}/\\left( {2\\pi d} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "PgUpIGk8YOYt90whzkLyo",
    "question": "A magnetic dipole is acted upon by two magnetic fields which are inclined to each other at an angle of 75<sup>o</sup>. One of the fields has a magnitude of 15 mT. The dipole attains stable equilibrium at an angle of 30<sup>o</sup> with this field. The magnitude of the other field (in mT ) is close to ",
    "options": [
      "11",
      "36",
      "1",
      "1060"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "11"
  },
  {
    "id": "Drlzzr2yckzbHOLvHl6fy",
    "question": "A magnetic dipole in a constant magnetic field has :\n ",
    "options": [
      "maximum potential energy when the torque is maximum.\n",
      "zero potential energy when the torque is minimum.",
      "zero potential energy when the torque is maximum.\n",
      "minimum potential energy when the torque is maximum."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "zero potential energy when the torque is maximum.\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "oOaec27q1PPGSb1TLUOXI",
    "question": "A negative test charge is moving near a long straight wire carrying a current. The force acting on the test charge is parallel to the direction of the current. The motion of the charge is  : ",
    "options": [
      "away from the wire",
      "towards the wire",
      "parallel to the wire along the current",
      "parallel to the wire opposite to the current"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "towards the wire"
  },
  {
    "id": "2qeCNfqnysklKZZjcjP7T",
    "question": "A rectangular coil (Dimension 5 cm × 2.5 cm)\nwith 100 turns, carrying a current of 3 A in the\nclock-wise direction is kept centered at the\norigin and in the X-Z plane. A magnetic field\nof 1 T is applied along X-axis. If the coil is tilted\nthrough 45° about Z-axis, then the torque on\nthe coil is :",
    "options": [
      "0.42 Nm",
      "0.55 Nm",
      "0.38 Nm",
      "0.27\nNm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "0.27\nNm"
  },
  {
    "id": "TsixCqbp2jAzncJxD07k9k2k5l2kg1k",
    "question": "A small circular loop of conducting wire has\nradius a and carries current I. It is placed in a\nuniform magnetic field B perpendicular to its\nplane such that when rotated slightly about its\ndiameter and released, it starts performing\nsimple harmonic motion of time period T. If the\nmass of the loop is m then :",
    "options": [
      "$$T = \\sqrt {{{2m} \\over {IB}}} $$",
      "$$T = \\sqrt {{{\\pi m} \\over {IB}}} $$",
      "$$T = \\sqrt {{{\\pi m} \\over {2IB}}} $$",
      "$$T = \\sqrt {{{2\\pi m} \\over {IB}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "$$T = \\sqrt {{{2\\pi m} \\over {IB}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "z0jSA3ydEFG2cbKV67jgy2xukf15ar28",
    "question": "A charged particle carrying charge 1 $$\\mu $$C is moving<br/> with velocity $$\\left( {2\\widehat i + 3\\widehat j + 4\\widehat k} \\right)$$ ms<sup>–1</sup>. If an external\n<br/>magnetic field of $$\\left( {5\\widehat i + 3\\widehat j - 6\\widehat k} \\right)$$× 10<sup>–3</sup> T exists in the region where the particle is moving then the\n<br/>force on the particle is $$\\overrightarrow F $$\n × 10<sup>–9</sup> N. The vector $$\\overrightarrow F $$\nis :",
    "options": [
      "$${ - 0.30\\widehat i + 0.32\\widehat j - 0.09\\widehat k}$$",
      "$${ - 300\\widehat i + 320\\widehat j - 90\\widehat k}$$",
      "$${ - 30\\widehat i + 32\\widehat j - 9\\widehat k}$$",
      "$${ - 3.0\\widehat i + 3.2\\widehat j - 0.9\\widehat k}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "$${ - 30\\widehat i + 32\\widehat j - 9\\widehat k}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "w7TJS3KDVAdtQBc94fjgy2xukfganc8b",
    "question": "A square loop of side 2$$a$$, and carrying current\nI, is kept in XZ plane with its centre at origin.\nA long wire carrying the same current I is\nplaced parallel to the z-axis and passing\nthrough the point (0, b, 0), (b &gt;&gt; a). The\nmagnitude of the torque on the loop about zaxis is given by :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2{\\mu _0}{I^2}{a^2}} \\over {\\pi b}}$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}{I^2}{a^2}} \\over {2\\pi b}}$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}{I^2}{a^3}} \\over {2\\pi {b^2}}}$$",
      "$${{2{\\mu _0}{I^2}{a^3}} \\over {\\pi {b^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "$${{2{\\mu _0}{I^2}{a^2}} \\over {\\pi b}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "uIBTaJbFo3GFdZgSqzjgy2xukg0az5a0",
    "question": "A square loop of side 2$$a$$ and carrying current I is kept in xz plane with its centre at origin. A long\nwire carrying the same current I is placed parallel to z-axis and passing through point (0, b, 0),\n(b &gt;&gt; a). The magnitude of torque on the loop about z-axis will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2{\\mu _0}{I^2}{a^2}} \\over {\\pi b}}$$",
      "$${{2{\\mu _0}{I^2}{a^2}b} \\over {\\pi \\left( {{a^2} + {b^2}} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}{I^2}{a^2}b} \\over {2\\pi \\left( {{a^2} + {b^2}} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${{{\\mu _0}{I^2}{a^2}} \\over {2\\pi b}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "$${{2{\\mu _0}{I^2}{a^2}} \\over {\\pi b}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ATIiDeCu8dxdAfjFxA1kmkrlf0y",
    "question": "A loop of flexible wire of irregular shape carrying current is placed in an external magnetic field. Identify the effect of the field on the wire.",
    "options": [
      "Loop assumes circular shape with its plane normal to the field.",
      "Loop assumes circular shape with its plane parallel to the field.",
      "Wire gets stretched to become straight.",
      "Shape of the loop remains unchanged."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "Loop assumes circular shape with its plane normal to the field."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54v0hef",
    "question": "<p>Two long current carrying conductors are placed to each other at a distance of 8 cm between them. The magnitude of magnetic field produced at mid-point between the two conductors due to current flowing in them is 300 $$\\mu$$T. The equal current flowing in the two conductors is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "30A in the same direction.",
      "30A in the opposite direction.",
      "60A in the opposite direction.",
      "300A in the opposite direction."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "30A in the opposite direction."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55k8zrb",
    "question": "<p>Two parallel, long wires are kept 0.20 m apart in vacuum, each carrying current of x A in the same direction. If the force of attraction per meter of each wire is 2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> N, then the value of x is approximately :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "2.4",
      "1.4",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "1.4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbrxqi",
    "question": "<p>A proton, a deutron and an $$\\alpha$$-particle with same kinetic energy enter into a uniform magnetic field at right angle to magnetic field. The ratio of the radii of their respective circular paths is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : $$\\sqrt 2 $$ : $$\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "1 : 1 : $$\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 $$ : 1 : 1",
      "1 : $$\\sqrt 2 $$ : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "1 : $$\\sqrt 2 $$ : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c2otts",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : In an uniform magnetic field, speed and energy remains the same for a moving charged particle.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Moving charged particle experiences magnetic force perpendicular to its direction of motion.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A).",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is NOT the correct explanation of (A).",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false.",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dyoqw4",
    "question": "<p>Two charged particles, having same kinetic energy, are allowed to pass through a uniform magnetic field perpendicular to the direction of motion. If the ratio of radii of their circular paths is $$6: 5$$ and their respective masses ratio is $$9: 4$$. Then, the ratio of their charges will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "8 : 5",
      "5 : 4",
      "5 : 3",
      "8 : 7"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "5 : 4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gmheed",
    "question": "<p>A charge particle is moving in a uniform magnetic field $$(2 \\hat{i}+3 \\hat{j}) \\,\\mathrm{T}$$. If it has an acceleration of $$(\\alpha \\hat{i}-4 \\hat{j})\\, \\mathrm{m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$, then the value of $$\\alpha$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "6",
      "12",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "6"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kneiyi",
    "question": "<p>A cyclotron is used to accelerate protons. If the operating magnetic field is $$1.0 \\mathrm{~T}$$ and the radius of the cyclotron 'dees' is $$60 \\mathrm{~cm}$$, the kinetic energy of the accelerated protons in MeV will be :</p>\n<p>$$[\\mathrm{use} \\,\\,\\mathrm{m}_{\\mathrm{p}}=1.6 \\times 10^{-27} \\mathrm{~kg}, \\mathrm{e}=1.6 \\times 10^{-19} \\,\\mathrm{C}$$ ]</p>",
    "options": [
      "12",
      "18",
      "16",
      "32"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "18"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldydajd8",
    "question": "<p>Two long straight wires P and Q carrying equal current 10A each were kept parallel to each other at 5 cm distance. Magnitude of magnetic force experienced by 10 cm length of wire P is F$$_1$$. If distance between wires is halved and currents on them are doubled, force F$$_2$$ on 10 cm length of wire P will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{F_1}{8}$$",
      "10 F$$_1$$",
      "$$\\frac{F_1}{10}$$",
      "8 F$$_1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "8 F$$_1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp0hliq",
    "question": "<p>An electron is moving along the positive $$\\mathrm{x}$$-axis. If the uniform magnetic field is applied parallel to the negative z-axis, then</p>\n<p>A. The electron will experience magnetic force along positive y-axis</p>\n<p>B. The electron will experience magnetic force along negative y-axis</p>\n<p>C. The electron will not experience any force in magnetic field</p>\n<p>D. The electron will continue to move along the positive $$\\mathrm{x}$$-axis</p>\n<p>E. The electron will move along circular path in magnetic field</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and E only",
      "B and D only",
      "B and E only",
      "C and D only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "B and E only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswj9wf",
    "question": "<p>An electron is allowed to move with constant velocity along the axis of current carrying straight solenoid.</p>\n<p>A. The electron will experience magnetic force along the axis of the solenoid.</p>\n<p>B. The electron will not experience magnetic force.</p>\n<p>C. The electron will continue to move along the axis of the solenoid.</p>\n<p>D. The electron will be accelerated along the axis of the solenoid.</p>\n<p>E. The electron will follow parabolic path-inside the solenoid.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "B, C and D only",
      "B and C only",
      "A and D only",
      "B and E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "B and C only"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd5orfk",
    "question": "<p>A uniform magnetic field of $$2 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~T}$$ acts along positive $$Y$$-direction. A rectangular loop of sides $$20 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ and $$10 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ with current of $$5 \\mathrm{~A}$$ is in $$Y-Z$$ plane. The current is in anticlockwise sense with reference to negative $$X$$ axis. Magnitude and direction of the torque is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~N}$$- $$\\mathrm{m}$$ along negative $$Z$$-direction\n",
      "$$2 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~N}$$ - $$\\mathrm{m}$$ along positive $$X$$-direction\n",
      "$$2 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~N}$$ - $$\\mathrm{m}$$ along positive $$Y$$-direction\n",
      "$$2 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~N}$$ - $$\\mathrm{m}$$ along positive $$Z$$-direction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "force-and-torque-on-current-carrying-conductor",
    "solution": "$$2 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~N}$$- $$\\mathrm{m}$$ along negative $$Z$$-direction\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq23whb",
    "question": "<p>The source of time varying magnetic field may be</p>\n<p>(A) a permanent magnet</p>\n<p>(B) an electric field changing linearly with time</p>\n<p>(C) direct current</p>\n<p>(D) a decelerating charge particle</p>\n<p>(E) an antenna fed with a digital signal</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "(D) only",
      "(A) only",
      "(B) and (D) only",
      "(C) and (E) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-field-of-moving-charge",
    "solution": "(D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh016ns7",
    "question": "<p>A charge particle moving in magnetic field B, has the components of velocity along B as well as perpendicular to B. The path of the charge particle will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "helical path with the axis along magnetic field $$\\mathrm{B}$$",
      "straight along the direction of magnetic field $$\\mathrm{B}$$",
      "circular path",
      "helical path with the axis perpendicular to the direction of magnetic field B"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-field-of-moving-charge",
    "solution": "helical path with the axis along magnetic field $$\\mathrm{B}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "oJqaOE9TjfnZrMmEPPXr2",
    "question": "A charge q is spread uniformly over an insulated loop of radius r.  If it is rotated with an angular velocity $$\\omega $$ with resect to normal axis then the magnetic moment of the loop is : ",
    "options": [
      "q $$\\omega $$r<sup>2</sup>",
      "$${4 \\over 3}$$ q $$\\omega $$r<sup>2</sup>",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$ q $$\\omega $$r<sup>2</sup>",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$ q $$\\omega $$r<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-moment",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}$$ q $$\\omega $$r<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "DWnCemVRIjYUnDTsgPP9j",
    "question": "An insulating thin rod of length $$l$$ has a linear charge density $$\\rho \\left( x \\right)$$ = $${\\rho _0}{x \\over l}$$ on it. The rod is rotated about an axis passing through the origin (x = 0) and perpendicular to the rod. If the rod makes n rotations per second, then the time averaged magnetic moment of the rod is -",
    "options": [
      "$${\\pi  \\over 3}n\\rho {l^3}$$",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 4}n\\rho {l^3}$$",
      "$$n\\rho {l^3}$$ ",
      "$$\\pi n\\rho {l^3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-moment",
    "solution": "$${\\pi  \\over 4}n\\rho {l^3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "zctkNho8M3hSAoizBFZkd",
    "question": "A hoop and a solid cylinder of same mass and radius are made of a permanent magnetic material with their magnetic moment parallel to their respective axes. But the magnetic moment of hoop is twice of solid cylinder. They are placed in a uniform magnetic field in such a manner that their magnetic moments make a small angle with the field. If the oscillation periods of hoop and cylinder are T<sub>h</sub> and T<sub>c</sub> respectively, then - ",
    "options": [
      "T<sub>h</sub> = 1.5 T<sub>c</sub>",
      "T<sub>h</sub> = T<sub>c</sub> ",
      "T<sub>h</sub> = 2T<sub>c</sub> ",
      "T<sub>h</sub> = 0.5 T<sub>c</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-moment",
    "solution": "T<sub>h</sub> = T<sub>c</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "PizvXf9IurDfSmeCbKck5",
    "question": "A circular coil having N turns and radius r\ncarries a current I. It is held in the XZ plane in\na magnetic field B$${\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge  }$$ . The torque on the coil due\nto the magnetic field is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{B{r^2}I} \\over {\\pi N}}$$",
      "B$$\\pi $$r<sup>2</sup>IN",
      "Zero",
      "$${{B\\pi{r^2}I} \\over { N}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-moment",
    "solution": "B$$\\pi $$r<sup>2</sup>IN"
  },
  {
    "id": "R1fpR3Et0NXNzqMI3k3rsa0w2w9jwziets2",
    "question": "A square loop is carrying a steady current I and the magnitude of its magnetic dipole moment is m. if this\nsquare loop is changed to a circular loop and it carries the same current, the magnitude of the magnetic dipole\nmoment of circular loop will be: ",
    "options": [
      "$${m \\over \\pi }$$",
      "$${{3m} \\over \\pi }$$",
      "$${{2m} \\over \\pi }$$",
      "$${{4m} \\over \\pi }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-moment",
    "solution": "$${{4m} \\over \\pi }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "FIA4lmu30DoiGg7s2bjgy2xukfahce4k",
    "question": "A circular coil has moment of inertia 0.8 kg m<sup>2</sup>\n around any diameter and is carrying current to\nproduce a magnetic moment of 20 Am<sup>2</sup>\n. The coil is kept initially in a vertical position and it can\nrotate freely around a horizontal diameter. When a uniform magnetic field of 4 T is applied along the\nvertical,it starts rotating around its horizontal diameter. The angular speed the coil acquires after\nrotating by 60<sup>o</sup> will be:",
    "options": [
      "10 $$\\pi $$ rad s<sup>–1</sup>",
      "20 $$\\pi $$ rad s<sup>–1</sup>",
      "$$10{\\left( 3 \\right)^{1/4}}$$ rad s<sup>–1</sup>",
      "20 rad s<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-moment",
    "solution": "$$10{\\left( 3 \\right)^{1/4}}$$ rad s<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "NHTCnOkEnWQEmeBkFljgy2xukfl3q9zw",
    "question": "An iron rod of volume 10<sup>–3</sup> m<sup>3</sup> and relative\npermeability 1000 is placed as core in a\nsolenoid with 10 turns/cm. If a current of 0.5 A\nis passed through the solenoid, then the\nmagnetic moment of the rod will be :",
    "options": [
      "5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>2</sup> Am<sup>2</sup>",
      "0.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>2</sup> Am<sup>2</sup>",
      "500 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>2</sup> Am<sup>2</sup>",
      "50 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>2</sup> Am<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-moment",
    "solution": "5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>2</sup> Am<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "7ex2GeeMpa163y6Q0Cjgy2xukg09scko",
    "question": "A charged particle going around in a circle can be considered to be a current loop. A particle of\nmass m carrying charge q is moving in a plane with speed v under the influence of magnetic field $$\\overrightarrow B $$.\nThe magnetic moment of this moving particle:",
    "options": [
      "$${{m{v^2}\\overrightarrow B } \\over {2{B^2}}}$$",
      "-$${{m{v^2}\\overrightarrow B } \\over {2{B^2}}}$$",
      "-$${{m{v^2}\\overrightarrow B } \\over {{B^2}}}$$",
      "-$${{m{v^2}\\overrightarrow B } \\over {2\\pi {B^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-moment",
    "solution": "-$${{m{v^2}\\overrightarrow B } \\over {2{B^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpkb8vo",
    "question": "<p>A rod with circular cross-section area $$2 \\mathrm{~cm}^{2}$$ and length $$40 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ is wound uniformly with 400 turns of an insulated wire. If a current of $$0.4 \\mathrm{~A}$$ flows in the wire windings, the total magnetic flux produced inside windings is $$4 \\pi \\times 10^{-6} \\mathrm{~Wb}$$. The relative permeability of the rod is</p>\n<p>(Given : Permeability of vacuum $$\\mu_{0}=4 \\pi \\times 10^{-7} \\mathrm{NA}^{-2}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{5}{16}$$",
      "125",
      "$$\\frac{32}{5}$$",
      "12.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-moment",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{5}{16}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr26gfm",
    "question": "<p>The magnetic moments associated with two closely wound circular coils $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$ of radius $$\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{A}}=10$$ $$\\mathrm{cm}$$ and $$\\mathrm{r}_{\\mathrm{B}}=20 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ respectively are equal if : (Where $$\\mathrm{N}_{\\mathrm{A}}, \\mathrm{I}_{\\mathrm{A}}$$ and $$\\mathrm{N}_{\\mathrm{B}}, \\mathrm{I}_{\\mathrm{B}}$$ are number of turn and current of $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$ respectively)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4 \\mathrm{~N}_{\\mathrm{A}} \\mathrm{I}_{\\mathrm{A}}=\\mathrm{N}_{\\mathrm{B}} \\mathrm{I}_{\\mathrm{B}}$$",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~N}_{\\mathrm{A}} \\mathrm{I}_{\\mathrm{A}}=\\mathrm{N}_{\\mathrm{B}} \\mathrm{I}_{\\mathrm{B}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{N}_{\\mathrm{A}}=2 \\mathrm{~N}_{\\mathrm{B}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{N}_{\\mathrm{A}} \\mathrm{I}_{\\mathrm{A}}=4 \\mathrm{~N}_{\\mathrm{B}} \\mathrm{I}_{\\mathrm{B}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-moment",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{N}_{\\mathrm{A}} \\mathrm{I}_{\\mathrm{A}}=4 \\mathrm{~N}_{\\mathrm{B}} \\mathrm{I}_{\\mathrm{B}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtzeohw",
    "question": "<p>For a moving coil galvanometer, the deflection in the coil is 0.05 rad when a current of 10 mA is passes through it. If the torsional constant of suspension wire is $$4.0\\times10^{-5}\\mathrm{N~m~rad^{-1}}$$, the magnetic field is 0.01T and the number of turns in the coil is 200, the area of each turn (in cm$$^2$$) is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.5",
      "2.0",
      "0.5",
      "1.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "magnetic-moment",
    "solution": "1.0"
  },
  {
    "id": "WoHSqfJ9YhjtYb6d",
    "question": "The time period of a charged particle undergoing a circular motion in a uniform magnetic field is independent of its ",
    "options": [
      "speed ",
      "mass ",
      "charge ",
      "magnetic induction "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "speed "
  },
  {
    "id": "oz4aSIdP398XDmLy",
    "question": "If an electron and a proton having same momentum enter perpendicular to a magnetic field, then ",
    "options": [
      "curved path of electron and proton will be same (ignoring the sense of revolution) ",
      "they will move undeflected ",
      "curved path of electron is more curved than that of the proton ",
      "path of proton is more curved."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "curved path of electron and proton will be same (ignoring the sense of revolution) "
  },
  {
    "id": "v0t6m0y8QTPXGOyR",
    "question": "A particle of mass $$M$$ and charge $$Q$$ moving with velocity $$\\overrightarrow v $$ describe a circular path of radius $$R$$ when subjected to a uniform transverse magnetic field of induction $$B.$$ The network done by the field when the particle completes one full circle is ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {{{M{v^2}} \\over R}} \\right)2\\pi R$$ ",
      "zero ",
      "$$B\\,\\,Q\\,2\\pi R$$ ",
      "$$B\\,Qv\\,2\\pi R$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "zero "
  },
  {
    "id": "Ut3FfAhiljX1f0sO",
    "question": "A particle of charge $$ - 16 \\times {10^{ - 18}}$$ coulomb moving with velocity $$10m{s^{ - 1}}$$ along the $$x$$-axis enters a region where a magnetic field of induction $$B$$ is along the $$y$$-axis, and an electric field of magnitude $${10^4}V/m$$ is along the negative $$z$$-axis. If the charged particle continues moving along the $$x$$-axis, the magnitude of $$B$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$${10^3}Wb/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$${10^5}Wb/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$${10^{16}}Wb/{m^2}$$ ",
      "$${10^{ - 3}}Wb/{m^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$${10^3}Wb/{m^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "3T315GLeBvEfQ4bL",
    "question": "A uniform electric field and a uniform magnetic field are acting along the same direction in a certain region. If an electron is projected along the direction of the fields with a certain velocity then ",
    "options": [
      "its velocity will increase ",
      "Its velocity will decrease ",
      "it will turn towards left of a direction of motion ",
      "it will turn  towards right of direction of motion "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "Its velocity will decrease "
  },
  {
    "id": "fMKsHQ9vzJQezDA8",
    "question": "A charged particle of mass $$m$$ and charge $$q$$ travels on a circular path of radius $$r$$ that is perpendicular to a magnetic field $$B.$$ The time taken by the particle to complete one revolution is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{2\\pi {q^2}B} \\over m}$$ ",
      "$${{2\\pi mq} \\over B}$$ ",
      "$${{2\\pi m} \\over {qB}}$$ ",
      "$${{2\\pi qB} \\over m}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$${{2\\pi m} \\over {qB}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "5sKeXZMKLAq6wH9x",
    "question": "In a region, steady and uniform electric and magnetic fields are present. These two fields are parallel to each other. A charged particle is released from rest in this region. The path of the particle will be a",
    "options": [
      "helix ",
      "straight line ",
      "ellipse ",
      "circle "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "straight line "
  },
  {
    "id": "v8i5CSQx8aqHN0vI",
    "question": "A charged particle with charge $$q$$ enters a region of constant, uniform and mutually orthogonal fields $$\\overrightarrow E $$ and $$\\overrightarrow B $$ with a velocity $$\\overrightarrow v $$ perpendicular to both $$\\overrightarrow E $$ and $$\\overrightarrow B, $$ and comes out without any change in magnitude or direction of $$\\overrightarrow v $$. Then ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow v  = \\overrightarrow B  \\times \\overrightarrow E /{E^2}$$ ",
      "$$\\overrightarrow v  = \\overrightarrow E  \\times \\overrightarrow B /{B^2}$$ ",
      "$$\\overrightarrow v  = \\overrightarrow B  \\times \\overrightarrow E /{B^2}$$ ",
      "$$\\overrightarrow v  = \\overrightarrow E  \\times \\overrightarrow B /{E^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow v  = \\overrightarrow E  \\times \\overrightarrow B /{B^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "mR02r09kEHwQ2JAA",
    "question": "A charged particle moves through a magnetic field perpendicular to its direction. Then ",
    "options": [
      "Kinetic energy changes but the momentum is constant ",
      "the momentum changes but the kinetic energy is constant ",
      "both momentum and kinetic energy of the particle are not constant ",
      "both momentum and kinetic energy of the particle are constant "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "the momentum changes but the kinetic energy is constant "
  },
  {
    "id": "Z7qZVyyY6ldy6RGo",
    "question": "Proton, deuteron and alpha particle of same kinetic energy are moving in circular trajectories in a constant magnetic field. The radii of proton, denuteron and alpha particle are  respectively $${r_p},{r_d}$$ and $${r_\\alpha }$$.  Which one of the following relation is correct? ",
    "options": [
      "$${r_\\alpha } = {r_p} = {r_d}$$ ",
      "$${r_\\alpha } = {r_p} &lt; {r_d}$$ ",
      "$${r_\\alpha } &gt; {r_d} &gt; {r_p}$$ ",
      "$${r_\\alpha } = {r_d} &gt; {r_p}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$${r_\\alpha } = {r_p} &lt; {r_d}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "jxdyQ6JihE8vcBRQJbQFO",
    "question": "In a certain region static electric and magnetic fields exist. The magnetic field is given by $$\\overrightarrow B  = {B_0}\\left( {\\widehat i + 2\\widehat j - 4\\widehat k} \\right)$$ . If a test charge moving with a velocity $$\\overrightarrow \\upsilon   = {\\upsilon _0}\\left( {3\\widehat i - \\widehat j + 2\\widehat k} \\right)$$ experiences no force in that region, then the electric field in the region, in SI units, is :\n",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow E  =  - {\\upsilon _0}\\,{B_0}\\left( {3\\widehat i - 2\\widehat j - 4\\widehat k} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E  =  - {\\upsilon _0}\\,{B_0}\\left( {\\widehat i + \\widehat j + 7\\widehat k} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E  = {\\upsilon _0}\\,{B_0}\\left( {14\\widehat j + 7\\widehat k} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow E  =  - {\\upsilon _0}\\,{B_0}\\left( {14\\widehat j + 7\\widehat k} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow E  =  - {\\upsilon _0}\\,{B_0}\\left( {14\\widehat j + 7\\widehat k} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "YG1ipWqGon3ZiT8o",
    "question": "An electron, a proton and an alpha particle having the same kinetic energy are moving in circular orbits of\nradii r<sub>e</sub>, r<sub>p</sub>, r$$_\\alpha$$ respectively in a uniform magnetic field B. The relation between r<sub>e</sub>, r<sub>p</sub>, r$$_\\alpha$$ is:  ",
    "options": [
      "r<sub>e</sub> &lt; r$$_\\alpha$$ &lt; r<sub>p</sub>",
      "r<sub>e</sub> &gt; r<sub>p</sub> = r$$_\\alpha$$",
      "r<sub>e</sub> &lt; r<sub>p</sub> = r$$_\\alpha$$",
      "r<sub>e</sub> &lt; r<sub>p</sub> &lt; r$$_\\alpha$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "r<sub>e</sub> &lt; r<sub>p</sub> = r$$_\\alpha$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "hGv8KjfmOp16zCFU9zh5r",
    "question": "A particle having the same charge as of electron moves in a ciurcular path of radius 0.5 cm under the influence of a magnetic field 0f 0.5 T. If an electric field of 100 V/m makes it to move in a straight path, then the mass of the particle is (Given charge of electron = 1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10$$-$$<sup>19</sup>C)",
    "options": [
      "9.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$31</sup> kg",
      "1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$27</sup> kg",
      "1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$19</sup> kg",
      "2.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$24</sup> kg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "2.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$24</sup> kg"
  },
  {
    "id": "teeU6YJyPE1qwtbOggba5",
    "question": "In an experiment, electrons are accelerated, from rest, by applying a voltage of 500 V. Calculate the radius of the path if a magnetic field 100 mT is then applied. [Charge of the electron = 1.6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–19</sup> C Mass of the electron = 9.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–31</sup> kg] ",
    "options": [
      "7.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> m",
      "7.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> m",
      "7.5 m",
      "7.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "7.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> m"
  },
  {
    "id": "iAmybRMkOBHuVkSVj1SOR",
    "question": "The region between y = 0 and y = d contains a magnetic field $$\\overrightarrow B  = B\\widehat z$$.  A particle of mass m and charge q enters the region with a velocity $$\\overrightarrow v  = v\\widehat i.$$ If d $$=$$ $${{mv} \\over {2qB}},$$ the acceleration of the charged particle at the point of its emergence at the other side is : \n",
    "options": [
      "$${{qvB} \\over m}\\left( -{{{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}\\widehat i - {1 \\over 2}\\widehat j} \\right)$$",
      "$${{qvB} \\over m}\\left( {{1 \\over 2}\\widehat i - {{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}\\widehat j} \\right)$$",
      "$${{qvB} \\over m}\\left( {{{ - \\widehat j + \\widehat i} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}} \\right)$$",
      "$${{qvB} \\over m}\\left( {{{\\widehat j + \\widehat i} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$${{qvB} \\over m}\\left( -{{{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}\\widehat i - {1 \\over 2}\\widehat j} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "OYiLvoW9ryQMdU4T8VOf2",
    "question": "A particle of mass m and charge q is in an electric and magnetic field given by\n<br/>$$\\overrightarrow E  = 2\\widehat i + 3\\widehat j;\\,\\,\\,\\overrightarrow B  = 4\\widehat j + 6\\widehat k.$$\n<br/><br/>The charged particle is shifted from he origin to the point P(x = 1; y = 1) along a straight path. The magnitude of the total work done is :",
    "options": [
      "(2.5) q",
      "(0.35) q",
      "(0.15) q",
      "5 q"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "5 q"
  },
  {
    "id": "lAxukhrRP7yjilTrpanlb",
    "question": "A proton and an $$\\alpha $$-particle (with their masses in the ratio of 1 : 4 and charges in the ratio of 1 : 2) are accelerated from rest through a potential difference V. If a uniform magnetic field (B) is set up perpendicular to their velocities, the ratio of the radii r<sub>p</sub> : r<sub>$$\\alpha $$</sub> of the circular paths described by them will be ; ",
    "options": [
      "$$1:\\sqrt 3 $$",
      "1 : 3",
      "$$1:\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "1 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$$1:\\sqrt 2 $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xWqgc29lzk7NdmzBN618hoxe66ijvznewue",
    "question": "A proton, an electron, and a Helium nucleus,\nhave the same energy. They are in circular\norbits in a plane due to magnetic field\nperpendicualr to the plane. Let r<sub>p</sub>, r<sub>e</sub> and r<sub>He</sub> be\ntheir respective radii, then",
    "options": [
      "r<sub>e</sub> &lt; r<sub>p</sub> &lt; r<sub>He</sub>",
      "r<sub>e </sub>&lt; r<sub>p </sub>= r<sub>He</sub>",
      "r<sub>e</sub> &gt; r<sub>p</sub> &gt; r<sub>He</sub>",
      "r<sub>e</sub> &gt; r<sub>p</sub> = r<sub>He</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "r<sub>e </sub>&lt; r<sub>p </sub>= r<sub>He</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "P3IG6oQEjh1clZLcPYjgy2xukfroqfgp",
    "question": "An electron is moving along +x direction with a velocity of 6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>6</sup>\n ms<sup>–1</sup>. It enters a region of uniform\nelectric field of 300 V/cm pointing along +y direction. The magnitude and direction of the magnetic\nfield set up in this region such that the electron keeps moving along the x direction will be :",
    "options": [
      "3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup> T, along –z direction ",
      "5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> T, along –z direction ",
      "5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> T, along +z direction ",
      "3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–4</sup> T, along +z direction "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> T, along +z direction "
  },
  {
    "id": "u58TQpoeoKjvwh0SYojgy2xukfrt30bu",
    "question": "A particle of charge q and mass m is moving with a velocity $$ - v\\widehat i$$ (v $$ \\ne $$ 0) towards a large screen\nplaced in the Y - Z plane at a distance d. If there is a magnetic field $$\\overrightarrow B  = {B_0}\\widehat k$$\n, the maximum value of v\nfor which the particle will not hit the screen is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2qd{B_0}} \\over m}$$",
      "$${{qd{B_0}} \\over {3m}}$$",
      "$${{qd{B_0}} \\over {2m}}$$",
      "$${{qd{B_0}} \\over {m}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$${{qd{B_0}} \\over {m}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Sof0CpNW0oYg8v0zHSjgy2xukev3chc8",
    "question": "A beam of protons with speed 4 × 10<sup>5</sup> ms<sup>–1</sup>\nenters a uniform magnetic field of 0.3 T at an\nangle of 60° to the magnetic field. The pitch of\nthe resulting helical path of protons is close to :\n<br/>(Mass of the proton = 1.67 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–27</sup> kg, charge\n<br/>of the proton = 1.69 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–19</sup> C)",
    "options": [
      "2 cm",
      "12 cm",
      "5 cm",
      "4 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "4 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "lyPUniC3ncJ9t0zHgM7k9k2k5gv6z8m",
    "question": "Photon with kinetic energy of 1MeV moves\nfrom south to north. It gets an acceleration of\n10<sup>12</sup> m/s<sup>2</sup> by an applied magnetic field (west to\neast). The value of magnetic field : (Rest mass\nof proton is 1.6 × 10<sup>–27</sup> kg) :",
    "options": [
      "0.71mT",
      "7.1mT",
      "0.071mT",
      "71mT"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "0.71mT"
  },
  {
    "id": "VPKVoc6rAwW1VD5guH7k9k2k5f5pv7d",
    "question": "A particle of mass m and charge q has an initial velocity $$\\overrightarrow v  = {v_0}\\widehat j$$\n. If an electric field $$\\overrightarrow E  = {E_0}\\widehat i$$\n and\nmagnetic field $$\\overrightarrow B  = {B_0}\\widehat i$$\n act on the particle, its speed will double after a time:",
    "options": [
      "$${{3m{v_0}} \\over {q{E_0}}}$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt 2 m{v_0}} \\over {q{E_0}}}$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt 3 m{v_0}} \\over {q{E_0}}}$$",
      "$${{2m{v_0}} \\over {q{E_0}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$${{\\sqrt 3 m{v_0}} \\over {q{E_0}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "RfQ4e49iMRXffj5wIf1klrwuhzn",
    "question": "A proton, a deuteron and an $$\\alpha$$ particle are moving with same momentum in a uniform magnetic field. The ratio of magnetic forces acting on them is _________ and their speed is _______, in the ratio.",
    "options": [
      "2 : 1 : 1 and 4 : 2 : 1",
      "4 : 2 : 1 and 2 : 1 : 1",
      "1 : 2 : 4 and 2 : 1 : 1",
      "1 : 2 : 4 and 1 : 1 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "2 : 1 : 1 and 4 : 2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "kDrLrq5o2c3K8WOPuZ1kmip7mtw",
    "question": "A charge Q is moving $$\\overrightarrow {dl} $$ distance in the magnetic field $$\\overrightarrow {B} $$. Find the value of work done by $$\\overrightarrow {B} $$.",
    "options": [
      "Zero",
      "$$-$$1",
      "Infinite",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "Zero"
  },
  {
    "id": "D0jAySzWBvwUwcOQpr1kmlwcext",
    "question": "A proton and an $$\\alpha$$-particle, having kinetic energies K<sub>p</sub> and K<sub>$$\\alpha$$</sub> respectively, enter into a magnetic field at right angles.<br/><br/>The ratio of the radii of trajectory of proton to that of $$\\alpha$$-particle is 2 : 1. The ratio of K<sub>p</sub> : K<sub>$$\\alpha$$</sub> is :",
    "options": [
      "8 : 1",
      "4 : 1",
      "1 : 8",
      "1 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "4 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "FHjoZQLTmfNqRQWwKq1krpl002t",
    "question": "A deuteron and an alpha particle having equal kinetic energy enter perpendicularly into a magnetic field. Let r<sub>d</sub> and r<sub>$$\\alpha$$</sub> be their respective radii of circular path. The value of $${{{r_d}} \\over {{r_\\alpha }}}$$ is equal to :",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "2",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt 2 $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw733z8",
    "question": "Two ions having same mass have charges in the ratio 1 : 2. They are projected normally in a uniform magnetic field with their speeds in the ratio 2 : 3. The ratio of the radii of their circular trajectories is :",
    "options": [
      "1 : 4",
      "4 : 3",
      "3 : 1",
      "2 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "4 : 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kte69jp5",
    "question": "Two ions of masses 4 amu and 16 amu have charges +2e and +3e respectively. These ions pass through the region of constant perpendicular magnetic field. The kinetic energy of both ions is same. Then :",
    "options": [
      "lighter ion will be deflected less than heavier ion",
      "lighter ion will be deflected more than heavier ion",
      "both ions will be deflected equally",
      "no ion will be deflected"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "lighter ion will be deflected more than heavier ion"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l547812a",
    "question": "<p>A charge particle moves along circular path in a uniform magnetic field in a cyclotron. The kinetic energy of the charge particle increases to 4 times its initial value. What will be the ratio of new radius to the original radius of circular path of the charge particle :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "1 : 2",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54v8asd",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p><b>Statement I</b> : The electric force changes the speed of the charged particle and hence changes its kinetic energy; whereas the magnetic force does not change the kinetic energy of the charged particle.</p>\n<p><b>Statement II </b>: The electric force accelerates the positively charged particle perpendicular to the direction of electric field. The magnetic force accelerates the moving charged particle along the direction of magnetic field.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "Statement I is correct but Statement II is incorrect."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58bwspu",
    "question": "<p>A proton and an alpha particle of the same velocity enter in a uniform magnetic field which is acting perpendicular to their direction of motion. The ratio of the radii of the circular paths described by the alpha particle and proton is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 4",
      "4 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "2 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w2th4o",
    "question": "<p>A cyclotron is working at a frequency of 10 MHz. If the radius of its dees is 60 cm. The maximum kinetic energy of accelerated proton will be :</p>\n<p>(Take : e = 1.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$19</sup> C, m<sub>p</sub> = 1.67 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$27</sup> kg)</p>",
    "options": [
      "7.4 MeV",
      "14.86 MeV",
      "7.4 GeV",
      "704 GeV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "7.4 MeV"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc32bux",
    "question": "<p>A proton moving with a constant velocity passes through a region of space without any change in its velocity. If $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{E}}$$ and $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}$$ represent the electric and magnetic fields respectively, then the region of space may have :</p>\n<p>(A) $$\\mathrm{E}=0, \\mathrm{~B}=0$$<?p>\n<p>(B) $$\\mathrm{E}=0, \\mathrm{~B} \\neq 0$$</p>\n<p>(C) $$\\mathrm{E} \\neq 0, \\mathrm{~B}=0$$</p>\n<p>(D) $$\\mathrm{E} \\neq 0, \\mathrm{~B} \\neq 0$$</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p></p>",
    "options": [
      "(A), (B) and (C) only",
      "(A), (C) and (D) only",
      "(A), (B) and (D) only",
      "(B), (C) and (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "(A), (B) and (D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfm35m3",
    "question": "<p>Two particles $$X$$ and $$Y$$ having equal charges are being accelerated through the same potential difference. Thereafter they enter normally in a region of uniform magnetic field and describes circular paths of radii $$R_1$$ and $$R_2$$ respectively. The mass ratio of $$X$$ and $$Y$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left(\\frac{R_1}{R_2}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{R_2}{R_1}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{R_2}{R_1}\\right)^2$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{R_1}{R_2}\\right)^2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$$\\left(\\frac{R_1}{R_2}\\right)^2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwcs49",
    "question": "<p>A proton and a deutron $$(q=+\\mathrm{e}, m=2.0 \\mathrm{u})$$ having same kinetic energies enter a region of uniform magnetic field $$\\vec{B}$$, moving perpendicular to $$\\vec{B}$$. The ratio of the radius $$r_d$$ of deutron path to the radius $$r_p$$ of the proton path is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: 2$$\n",
      "$$1: 1$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{2}: 1$$\n",
      "$$1: \\sqrt{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{2}: 1$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxk95",
    "question": "<p>An electron is projected with uniform velocity along the axis inside a current carrying long solenoid. Then :</p>",
    "options": [
      "the electron will experience a force at $$45^{\\circ}$$ to the axis and execute a helical path.\n",
      "the electron will be accelerated along the axis.\n",
      "the electron path will be circular about the axis.\n",
      "the electron will continue to move with uniform velocity along the axis of the solenoid."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "the electron will continue to move with uniform velocity along the axis of the solenoid."
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s23vh",
    "question": "<p>The electrostatic force $$\\left(\\vec{F_1}\\right)$$ and magnetic force $$\\left(\\vec{F}_2\\right)$$ acting on a charge $$q$$ moving with velocity $$v$$ can be written :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\vec{F}_1=q \\vec{B}, \\vec{F}_2=q(\\vec{B} \\times \\vec{v})$$",
      "$$\\vec{F}_1=q \\vec{V} \\cdot \\vec{E}, \\vec{F}_2=q(\\vec{B} \\cdot \\vec{V})$$\n",
      "$$\\vec{F}_1=q \\vec{E}, \\vec{F}_2=q(\\vec{V} \\times \\vec{B})$$\n",
      "$$\\vec{F}_1=q \\vec{E}, \\vec{F}_2=q(\\vec{B} \\times \\vec{V})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "motion-of-charged-particle-inside-magnetic-field",
    "solution": "$$\\vec{F}_1=q \\vec{E}, \\vec{F}_2=q(\\vec{V} \\times \\vec{B})$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "uxH4yPevE4UqwfbsYX6cZ",
    "question": "To know the resistance G of a galvanometer by half deflection method, a battery of emf V<sub>E</sub> and resistance R is used to deflect the galvanometer by angle $$\\theta $$. If a shunt of resistance S is needed to get half deflection then G, R and S are related by the equation :",
    "options": [
      "2S (R + G) = RG",
      "S (R + G) = RG",
      "2S = G",
      "2G = S"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "moving-coil-galvanometer",
    "solution": "S (R + G) = RG"
  },
  {
    "id": "i8pSsyXVoRGZM78gF6zAq",
    "question": "A moving coil galvanometer has a coil with\n175 turns and area 1 cm<sup>2</sup>. It uses a torsion band\nof torsion constant 10<sup>–6</sup> N-m/rad. The coil is\nplaced in a maganetic field B parallel to its\nplane. The coil deflects by 1° for a current of\n1 mA. The value of B (in Tesla) is\napproximately :-",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>–4</sup>",
      "10<sup>–2</sup>",
      "10<sup>–1</sup>",
      "10<sup>–3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "moving-coil-galvanometer",
    "solution": "10<sup>–3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6ma6x90",
    "question": "<p>The current sensitivity of a galvanometer can be increased by :</p>\n<p>(A) decreasing the number of turns</p>\n<p>(B) increasing the magnetic field</p>\n<p>(C) decreasing the area of the coil</p>\n<p>(D) decreasing the torsional constant of the spring</p>\n<p>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(B) and (C) only",
      "(C) and (D) only",
      "(A) and (C) only",
      "(B) and (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "magnetics",
    "topic": "moving-coil-galvanometer",
    "solution": "(B) and (D) only"
  },
  {
    "id": "LRr2aKrWHi1D7pDg",
    "question": "A boy playing on the roof of a 10 m high building throws a ball with a speed of 10 m/s at an\nangle of $$30^\\circ $$ with the horizontal. How far from the throwing point will the ball be at the height\nof 10 m from the ground?\n$$\\left[ {g = 10m/{s^2},\\sin 30^\\circ  = {1 \\over 2},\\cos 30^\\circ  = {{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}} \\right]$$",
    "options": [
      "5.20 m",
      "4.33 m",
      "2.60 m",
      "8.66 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "8.66 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "RGEl2z5XwI22hTpF",
    "question": "A projectile can have the same range 'R' for two angles of projection. If T<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>2</sub> be the time\nof flights in the two cases, then the product of the two time of flights is directly proportional to",
    "options": [
      "R",
      "$${1 \\over R}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {{R^2}}}$$",
      "$${R^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "R"
  },
  {
    "id": "gEIilE53zPLVu7ub",
    "question": "A ball is thrown from a point with a speed ν<sub>0</sub> at an angle of projection θ. From the same point\nand at the same instant person starts running with a constant speed $${{{v_0}} \\over 2}$$ to catch the ball.\nWill the person be able to catch the ball? If yes, what should be the angle of projection θ?",
    "options": [
      "No",
      "Yes, $$30^\\circ $$",
      "Yes, $$60^\\circ $$",
      "Yes, $$45^\\circ $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "Yes, $$60^\\circ $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "c0mxFZH47FebQVdS",
    "question": "A particle is moving with velocity $$\\overrightarrow v  = k\\left( {y\\widehat i + x\\widehat j} \\right)$$, where K is a constant. The general equation for its path is",
    "options": [
      "y = x<sup>2</sup> + constant",
      "y<sup>2</sup> = x + constant",
      "xy = constant",
      "y<sup>2</sup> = x<sup>2</sup> + constant"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "y<sup>2</sup> = x<sup>2</sup> + constant"
  },
  {
    "id": "MELyuSXzxqi9f8q1",
    "question": "A water fountain on the ground sprinkles water all around it. If the speed of water coming out of the\nfountain is v, the total area around the fountain that gets wet is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\pi {{{v^4}} \\over {{g^2}}}$$",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 2}{{{v^4}} \\over {{g^2}}}$$",
      "$$\\pi {{{v^2}} \\over {{g^2}}}$$",
      "$$\\pi {{{v^2}} \\over g}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\pi {{{v^4}} \\over {{g^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "haPdUvKfscDSHeJt",
    "question": "A boy can throw a stone up to a maximum height of 10 m. The maximum horizontal distance that the boy\ncan throw the same stone up to will be",
    "options": [
      "$$20\\sqrt 2 $$ m",
      "10 m",
      "$$10\\sqrt 2 $$ m",
      "20 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "20 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "xyWMmXYRgE7jKZJV",
    "question": "A projectile is given an initial velocity of $$\\left( {\\widehat i + 2\\widehat j} \\right)$$ m/s, where $${\\widehat i}$$ is along the ground and $${\\widehat j}$$ is along the\nvertical. If g = 10 m/s<sup>2</sup>, the equation of its trajectory is: ",
    "options": [
      "y = x - 5x<sup>2</sup>",
      "y = 2x - 5x<sup>2</sup>",
      "4y = 2x - 5x<sup>2</sup>",
      "4y = 2x - 25x<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "y = 2x - 5x<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "3kApqFurJe6TMWclaiRfv",
    "question": "Two guns A and B can fire bullets at speeds 1 km/s and 2 km/s respectively. From a point on a horizontal ground, they are fired in all possible directions. The ratio of maximum areas covered by the bullets fired by the two guns, on the ground is -\n",
    "options": [
      "1 : 16",
      "1 : 8",
      "1 : 2",
      "1 : 4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "1 : 16"
  },
  {
    "id": "QOwadpx2jFaE8RI05e3rsa0w2w9jx3aboes",
    "question": "A shell is fired from a fixed artillery gun with an initial speed u such that it hits the target on the ground at a\ndistance R from it. If t<sub>1</sub> and t<sub>2</sub> are the values of the time taken by it to hit the target in two possible ways, the\nproduct t<sub>1</sub>t<sub>2</sub> is -",
    "options": [
      "$${{2R} \\over g}$$",
      "$${R \\over g}$$",
      "$${R \\over {2g}}$$",
      "$${R \\over {4g}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$${{2R} \\over g}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1jmv4n4kvg5j2lwmpD3rsa0w2w9jx3m3zs1",
    "question": "The trajectory of a projectile near the surface of the earth is given as y = 2x – 9x<sup>2</sup>\n. If it were launched at an\nangle $$\\theta $$<sub>0</sub> with speed v<sub>0</sub> then (g = 10 ms<sup>–2</sup>) :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\theta _0} = {\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{1 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}} \\right)$$ and $${v_0} = {5 \\over 3}$$ ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "$${\\theta _0} = {\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{2 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}} \\right)$$ and $${v_0} = {3 \\over 5}$$ ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "$${\\theta _0} = {\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{2 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}} \\right)$$ and $${v_0} = {3 \\over 5}$$ ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "$${\\theta _0} = {\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{1 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}} \\right)$$ and $${v_0} = {5 \\over 3}$$ ms<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$${\\theta _0} = {\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{1 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}} \\right)$$ and $${v_0} = {5 \\over 3}$$ ms<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "RS2kF4dWR8yra2pq6r3rsa0w2w9jx7pix10",
    "question": "Two particles are projected from the same point with the same speed u such that they have the same range R,\nbut different maximum heights, h<sub>1</sub> and h<sub>2</sub>. Which of the following is correct ?",
    "options": [
      "R<sup>2</sup>\n = h<sub>1</sub>h<sub>2</sub>",
      "R<sup>2</sup>\n = 16 h<sub>1</sub>h<sub>2</sub> ",
      "R<sup>2</sup>\n = 4 h<sub>1</sub>h<sub>2</sub>",
      "R<sup>2</sup> = 2h<sub>1</sub>h<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "R<sup>2</sup>\n = 16 h<sub>1</sub>h<sub>2</sub> "
  },
  {
    "id": "RYaTrkX64f11MNp5vg1klulspsw",
    "question": "The trajectory of a projectile in a vertical plane is y = $$\\alpha$$x $$-$$ $$\\beta$$x<sup>2</sup>, where $$\\alpha$$ and $$\\beta$$ are constants and x &amp; y are respectively the horizontal and vertical distances of the projectile from the point of projection. The angle of projection $$\\theta$$ and the maximum height attained H are respectively given by :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\alpha ,{{{\\alpha ^2}} \\over {4\\beta }}$$",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\alpha ,{{4{\\alpha ^2}} \\over \\beta }$$",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{\\beta  \\over \\alpha }} \\right),{{{\\alpha ^2}} \\over \\beta }$$",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\beta ,{{{\\alpha ^2}} \\over {2\\beta }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\alpha ,{{{\\alpha ^2}} \\over {4\\beta }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktbq4cbo",
    "question": "A bomb is dropped by fighter plane flying horizontally. To an observer sitting in the plane, the trajectory of the bomb is a :",
    "options": [
      "hyperbola",
      "parabola in the direction of motion of plane",
      "straight line vertically down the plane",
      "parabola in a direction opposite to the motion of plane"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "straight line vertically down the plane"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfndfkj",
    "question": "A player kicks a football with an initial speed of 25 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup> at an angle of 45$$^\\circ$$ from the ground. What are the maximum height and the time taken by the football to reach at the highest point during motion ? (Take g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "h<sub>max</sub> = 10 m<br><br>T = 2.5 s",
      "h<sub>max</sub> = 15.625 m<br><br>T = 3.54 s",
      "h<sub>max</sub> = 15.625 m<br><br>T = 1.77 s",
      "h<sub>max</sub> = 3.54 m<br><br>T = 0.125 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "h<sub>max</sub> = 15.625 m<br><br>T = 1.77 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth0r2rj",
    "question": "A helicopter is flying horizontally with a speed 'v' at an altitude 'h' has to drop a food packet for a man on the ground. What is the distance of helicopter from the man when the food packet is dropped?",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{{2gh{v^2} + 1} \\over {{h^2}}}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {2gh{v^2} + {h^2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{2{v^2}h} \\over g} + {h^2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{2gh} \\over {{v^2}}} + {h^2}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{2{v^2}h} \\over g} + {h^2}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktmncywt",
    "question": "The ranges and heights for two projectiles projected with the same initial velocity at angles 42$$^\\circ$$ and 48$$^\\circ$$ with the horizontal are R<sub>1</sub>, R<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>1</sub>, H<sub>2</sub> respectively. Choose the correct option :",
    "options": [
      "R<sub>1</sub> &gt; R<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>1</sub> = H<sub>2</sub>",
      "R<sub>1</sub> = R<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>1</sub> &lt; H<sub>2</sub>",
      "R<sub>1</sub> &lt; R<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>1</sub> &lt; H<sub>2</sub>",
      "R<sub>1</sub> = R<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>1</sub> = H<sub>2</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "R<sub>1</sub> = R<sub>2</sub> and H<sub>1</sub> &lt; H<sub>2</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54vi0gs",
    "question": "<p>A person can throw a ball upto a maximum range of 100 m. How high above the ground he can throw the same ball?</p>",
    "options": [
      "25 m",
      "50 m",
      "100 m",
      "200 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "50 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57pde0b",
    "question": "<p>A projectile is launched at an angle '$$\\alpha$$' with the horizontal with a velocity 20 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. After 10 s, its inclination with horizontal is '$$\\beta$$'. The value of tan$$\\beta$$ will be : (g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>).</p>",
    "options": [
      "tan$$\\alpha$$ + 5sec$$\\alpha$$",
      "tan$$\\alpha$$ $$-$$ 5sec$$\\alpha$$",
      "2tan$$\\alpha$$ $$-$$ 5sec$$\\alpha$$",
      "2tan$$\\alpha$$ $$+$$ 5sec$$\\alpha$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "tan$$\\alpha$$ $$-$$ 5sec$$\\alpha$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59ltdki",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements. One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Two identical balls A and B thrown with same velocity 'u' at two different angles with horizontal attained the same range R. IF A and B reached the maximum height h<sub>1</sub> and h<sub>2</sub> respectively, then $$R = 4\\sqrt {{h_1}{h_2}} $$</p>\n<p>Reason R : Product of said heights.</p>\n<p>$${h_1}{h_2} = \\left( {{{{u^2}{{\\sin }^2}\\theta } \\over {2g}}} \\right)\\,.\\,\\left( {{{{u^2}{{\\cos }^2}\\theta } \\over {2g}}} \\right)$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "Both A and R are true and R is the correct explanation of A."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c2upa5",
    "question": "<p>A projectile is projected with velocity of 25 m/s at an angle $$\\theta$$ with the horizontal. After t seconds its inclination with horizontal becomes zero. If R represents horizontal range of the projectile, the value of $$\\theta$$ will be :</p>\n<p>[use g = 10 m/s<sup>2</sup>]</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 2}{\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{5{t^2}} \\over {4R}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}{\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{4R} \\over {5{t^2}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{4{t^2}} \\over {5R}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\cot ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{R \\over {20{t^2}}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$${\\cot ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{R \\over {20{t^2}}}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w1teip",
    "question": "<p>At t = 0, truck, starting from rest, moves in the positive x-direction at uniform acceleration of 5 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>. At t = 20 s, a ball is released from the top of the truck. The ball strikes the ground in 1 s after the release. The velocity of the ball, when it strikes the ground, will be :</p>\n<p>(Given g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$100\\widehat i - 10\\widehat j$$",
      "$$10\\widehat i - 100\\widehat j$$",
      "$$100\\widehat i$$",
      "$$ - 10\\widehat j$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$$100\\widehat i - 10\\widehat j$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w1xu86",
    "question": "<p>Two projectiles P<sub>1</sub> and P<sub>2</sub> thrown with speed in the ratio $$\\sqrt3$$ : $$\\sqrt2$$, attain the same height during their motion. If P<sub>2</sub> is thrown at an angle of 60$$^\\circ$$ with the horizontal, the angle of projection of P<sub>1</sub> with horizontal will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "15$$^\\circ$$",
      "30$$^\\circ$$",
      "45$$^\\circ$$",
      "60$$^\\circ$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "45$$^\\circ$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f59icd",
    "question": "<p>A ball is projected from the ground with a speed 15 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup> at an angle $$\\theta$$ with horizontal so that its range and maximum height are equal, <br/>then 'tan $$\\theta$$' will be equal to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 4}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$",
      "2",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gn91d5",
    "question": "<p>Two projectiles thrown at $$30^{\\circ}$$ and $$45^{\\circ}$$ with the horizontal respectively, reach the maximum height in same time. The ratio of their initial velocities is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: \\sqrt{2}$$",
      "$$2: 1$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{2}: 1$$",
      "$$1: 2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{2}: 1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i08jhz",
    "question": "<p>Two projectiles are thrown with same initial velocity making an angle of $$45^{\\circ}$$ and  $$30^{\\circ}$$ with the horizontal respectively. The ratio of their respective ranges will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: \\sqrt{2}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{2}: 1$$",
      "$$2: \\sqrt{3}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{3}: 2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$$2: \\sqrt{3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldofpzui",
    "question": "<p>A child stands on the edge of the cliff $$10 \\mathrm{~m}$$ above the ground and throws a stone horizontally with an initial speed of $$5 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$. Neglecting the air resistance, the speed with which the stone hits the ground will be $$\\mathrm{ms}^{-1}$$ (given, $$g=10 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$ ).</p>",
    "options": [
      "20",
      "25",
      "30",
      "15"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "15"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpjmv71",
    "question": "<p>The initial speed of a projectile fired from ground is $$\\mathrm{u}$$. At the highest point during its motion, the speed of projectile is $$\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2} u$$. The time of flight of the projectile is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{u}{g}$$",
      "$$\\frac{2u}{g}$$",
      "$$\\frac{u}{2g}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt3u}{g}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{u}{g}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtymbtk",
    "question": "<p>Two objects are projected with same velocity 'u' however at different angles $$\\alpha$$ and $$\\beta$$ with the horizontal. If $$\\alpha+\\beta=90^\\circ$$, the ratio of horizontal range of the first object to the 2nd object will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 2",
      "4 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "1 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldye79sy",
    "question": "<p>The maximum vertical height to which a man can throw a ball is 136 m. The maximum horizontal distance upto which he can throw the same ball is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "136 m",
      "272 m",
      "68 m",
      "192 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "272 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswxwfv",
    "question": "<p>A projectile is projected at $$30^{\\circ}$$ from horizontal with initial velocity $$40 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$. The velocity of the projectile at $$\\mathrm{t}=2 \\mathrm{~s}$$ from the start will be : (Given $$g=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$20 \\sqrt{3} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$",
      "Zero",
      "$$20 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$",
      "$$40 \\sqrt{3} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$$20 \\sqrt{3} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvrj2my",
    "question": "<p>Two projectiles are projected at $$30^{\\circ}$$ and $$60^{\\circ}$$ with the horizontal with the same speed. The ratio of the maximum height attained by the two projectiles respectively is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: \\sqrt{3}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{3}: 1$$",
      "1 : 3",
      "$$2: \\sqrt{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "1 : 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgxx3mgg",
    "question": "<p>The range of the projectile projected at an angle of 15$$^\\circ$$ with horizontal is 50 m. If the projectile is projected with same velocity at an angle of 45$$^\\circ$$ with horizontal, then its range will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "50$$\\sqrt2$$ m",
      "100 m",
      "100$$\\sqrt2$$ m",
      "50 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "100 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqw4iu",
    "question": "<p>The trajectory of projectile, projected from the ground is given by $$y=x-\\frac{x^{2}}{20}$$. Where $$x$$ and $$y$$ are measured in meter. The maximum height attained by the projectile will be.</p>",
    "options": [
      "10 m",
      "5 m",
      "200 m",
      "10$$\\sqrt2$$ m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "5 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh01di29",
    "question": "<p>Two projectiles A and B are thrown with initial velocities of $$40 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ and $$60 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ at angles $$30^{\\circ}$$ and $$60^{\\circ}$$ with the horizontal respectively. The ratio of their ranges respectively is $$\\left(g=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}\\right)$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4: 9$$",
      "$$2: \\sqrt{3}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{3}: 2$$",
      "$$1: 1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$$4: 9$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh24d4cw",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : When a body is projected at an angle $$45^{\\circ}$$, it's range is maximum.</p>\n<p>Reason R : For maximum range, the value of $$\\sin 2 \\theta$$ should be equal to one.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is false",
      "$$\\mathbf{A}$$ is false but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is true",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are correct and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxm48",
    "question": "<p>The co-ordinates of a particle moving in $$x$$-$$y$$ plane are given by : $$x=2+4 \\mathrm{t}, y=3 \\mathrm{t}+8 \\mathrm{t}^2$$.</p>\n<p>The motion of the particle is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "uniform motion along a straight line.\n",
      "non-uniformly accelerated.\n",
      "uniformly accelerated having motion along a straight line.\n",
      "uniformly accelerated having motion along a parabolic path."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "uniformly accelerated having motion along a parabolic path."
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3vec4o",
    "question": "<p>The angle of projection for a projectile to have same horizontal range and maximum height is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$\\tan ^{-1}(2)$$\n",
      "$$\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{4}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$\\tan ^{-1}(4)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "projectile-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\tan ^{-1}(4)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "yCYxrhsJ1NECSxo9Tnjgy2xukfyym9zb",
    "question": "When a car is at rest, its driver sees rain drops falling on it vertically. When driving the car with\nspeed v, he sees that rain drops are coming at an angle 60° from the horizontal. On further\nincreasing the speed of the car to (1 + $$\\beta $$)v, this angle changes to 45<sup>o</sup>. The value of $$\\beta $$ is close to :",
    "options": [
      "0.50",
      "0.73",
      "0.37",
      "0.41"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "rain-man-problems",
    "solution": "0.73"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57pfsna",
    "question": "<p>A girl standing on road holds her umbrella at 45$$^\\circ$$ with the vertical to keep the rain away. If she starts running without umbrella with a speed of 15$$\\sqrt2$$ kmh<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, the rain drops hit her head vertically. The speed of rain drops with respect to the moving girl is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "30 kmh<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "$${{25} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ kmh<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "$${{30} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ kmh<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "25 kmh<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "rain-man-problems",
    "solution": "$${{30} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ kmh<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "K6sHbSdpjPN2aJY5",
    "question": "A particle is moving eastwards with a velocity of 5 m/s. In 10 seconds the velocity\nchanges to 5 m/s northwards. The average acceleration in this time is",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 2}m{s^{ - 2}}$$ towards north",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}m{s^{ - 2}}$$ towards north-east",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}m{s^{ - 2}}$$  towards north-west",
      "zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}m{s^{ - 2}}$$  towards north-west"
  },
  {
    "id": "pBN5sjfn3CUEa9mv",
    "question": "A particle has an initial velocity $$3\\widehat i + 4\\widehat j$$ and an acceleration of $$0.4\\widehat i + 0.3\\widehat j$$. Its speed after 10 s is:",
    "options": [
      "$$7\\sqrt 2 $$ units",
      "7 units",
      "8.5 units",
      "10 units"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "$$7\\sqrt 2 $$ units"
  },
  {
    "id": "9R0OtET7V64zgBCSal1ms",
    "question": "A particle is moving with a velocity\n<br/><br/>$$\\overrightarrow v \\, = K(y\\widehat i + x\\widehat j),$$ where K is a constant. \n<br/><br/>The general equation for its path is : ",
    "options": [
      "y = x<sup>2</sup> + constant",
      "y<sup>2</sup> = x + constant ",
      "y<sup>2</sup> = x<sup>2</sup> + constant",
      "xy = constant"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "y<sup>2</sup> = x<sup>2</sup> + constant"
  },
  {
    "id": "IEMsrMGJtZxDTzgVgsHBJ",
    "question": "The position co-ordinates of a particle moving in a 3-D coordinate system is given by \n<br/>x = a cos$$\\omega $$t\n<br/>y = a sin$$\\omega $$t  and\n<br/>z = a$$\\omega $$t\n<br/><br/>The speed of the particle is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt 2 \\,a\\omega $$",
      "$$a\\omega $$",
      "$$\\sqrt 3 \\,a\\omega $$",
      "2a$$\\omega $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt 2 \\,a\\omega $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "EX0cmRwaf0Nbuoj1pnaQd",
    "question": "A person standing on an open ground hears the sound of a jet aeroplane, coming from north at an angle 60<sup>o</sup> with ground level. But he finds the aeroplane right vertically above his position. If v is the speed of sound, speed of the plane is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}$$v",
      "$${{2v} \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$",
      "v",
      "$${v \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "$${v \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "sdkRni7JNbzv7DlroNM0I",
    "question": "Ship A is sailing towards north-east with\nvelocity $$\\mathop v\\limits^ \\to   = 30\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge   + 50\\mathop j\\limits^ \\wedge  $$ km/hr where $$\\mathop i\\limits^ \\wedge  $$ points\neast and $$\\mathop j\\limits^ \\wedge  $$ , north. Ship B is at a distance of\n80 km east and 150 km north of Ship A and\nis sailing towards west at 10 km/hr. A will be\nat minimum distance from B in :",
    "options": [
      "2.2 hrs",
      "4.2 hrs",
      "2.6 hrs",
      "3.2 hrs"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "2.6 hrs"
  },
  {
    "id": "FallPqJDbo23S96oK07k9k2k5hhu0w3",
    "question": "A particle moves such that its position\nvector $$\\overrightarrow r \\left( t \\right) = \\cos \\omega t\\widehat i + \\sin \\omega t\\widehat j$$ where $$\\omega $$ is a constant and t is time. Then which of the following statements is true for the velocity\n$$\\overrightarrow v \\left( t \\right)$$ and acceleration $$\\overrightarrow a \\left( t \\right)$$ of the particle :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow v $$ and $$\\overrightarrow a $$ both are perpendicular to $$\\overrightarrow r $$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow v $$ and $$\\overrightarrow a $$ both are parallel to $$\\overrightarrow r $$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow v $$ is perpendicular to  $$\\overrightarrow r $$ and $$\\overrightarrow a $$ is directed\ntowards the origin",
      "$$\\overrightarrow v $$ is perpendicular to $$\\overrightarrow r $$ and $$\\overrightarrow a $$ is directed\naway from the origin"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow v $$ is perpendicular to  $$\\overrightarrow r $$ and $$\\overrightarrow a $$ is directed\ntowards the origin"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZxjUBxMWqDW8EEUc0z7k9k2k5l8xvqh",
    "question": "A particle starts from the origin at t = 0 with an\n<br/>initial velocity of 3.0 $$\\widehat i$$ m/s and moves in the\n<br/>x-y plane with a constant acceleration\n$$\\left( {6\\widehat i + 4\\widehat j} \\right)$$ m/s<sup>2</sup> . The x-coordinate of the\nparticle at the instant when its y-coordinate is\n32 m is D meters. The value of D is :-",
    "options": [
      "40",
      "32",
      "50",
      "60"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "60"
  },
  {
    "id": "hDRWmi5w2yihs2aXhHjgy2xukf6dfz1n",
    "question": "Starting from the origin at time t = 0, with initial velocity 5$$\\widehat j$$ ms<sup>-1</sup> , a particle moves in the x-y plane\nwith a constant acceleration of $$\\left( {10\\widehat i + 4\\widehat j} \\right)$$ ms<sup>-2</sup>. At time t, its coordinates are (20 m, y<sub>0</sub>\n m). The\nvalues of t and y<sub>0</sub> are, respectively:\n",
    "options": [
      "5s and 25 m",
      "2s and 18 m",
      "2s and 24 m",
      "4s and 52 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "2s and 18 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "vqJtPg0eqiAK91QJmL1kmioyfet",
    "question": "A mosquito is moving with a velocity $$\\overrightarrow v  = 0.5{t^2}\\widehat i + 3t\\widehat j + 9\\widehat k$$ m/s and accelerating in uniform conditions. What will be the direction of mosquito after 2 s?",
    "options": [
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{\\sqrt {85} } \\over 6}\\right)$$ from y-axis",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{5 \\over 2}} \\right)$$ from y-axis",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{2 \\over 3}} \\right)$$ from x-axis",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{5 \\over 2}} \\right)$$ from x-axis"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{\\sqrt {85} } \\over 6}\\right)$$ from y-axis"
  },
  {
    "id": "pluW1uWZzhcGoy2coR1krpltdw4",
    "question": "A butterfly is flying with a velocity $$4\\sqrt 2 $$ m/s in North-East direction. Wind is slowly blowing at 1 m/s from North to South. The resultant displacement of the butterfly in 3 seconds is :",
    "options": [
      "$$12\\sqrt 2 $$ m",
      "20 m",
      "3 m",
      "15 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "15 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6npzmwm",
    "question": "<p>At time $$t=0$$ a particle starts travelling from a height $$7 \\hat{z} \\mathrm{~cm}$$ in a plane keeping z coordinate constant. At any instant of time it's position along the $$\\hat{x}$$ and $$\\hat{y}$$ directions are defined as $$3 \\mathrm{t}$$ and $$5 \\mathrm{t}^{3}$$ respectively. At t = 1s acceleration of the particle will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-30 \\hat{y}$$",
      "$$30 \\hat{y}$$",
      "$$3 \\hat{x}+15 \\hat{y}$$",
      "$$3 \\hat{x}+15 \\hat{y}+7 \\hat{z}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "$$30 \\hat{y}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc2sfsy",
    "question": "<p>Position of an ant ($$\\mathrm{S}$$ in metres) moving in $$\\mathrm{Y}$$-$$\\mathrm{Z}$$ plane is given by $$S=2 t^2 \\hat{j}+5 \\hat{k}$$ (where $$t$$ is in second). The magnitude and direction of velocity of the ant at $$\\mathrm{t}=1 \\mathrm{~s}$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$16 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ in $$y$$-direction\n",
      "$$4 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ in $$x$$-direction\n",
      "$$9 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ in $$\\mathrm{z}$$-direction\n",
      "$$4 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ in $$y$$-direction"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-two-dimension",
    "solution": "$$4 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ in $$y$$-direction"
  },
  {
    "id": "mG1tloVLkEn6UfkpdErqQ",
    "question": "The stream of a river is flowing with a speed\nof 2km/h. A swimmer can swim at a speed of\n4km/h. What should be the direction of the\nswimmer with respect to the flow of the river to\ncross the river straight ?",
    "options": [
      "150°",
      "120°",
      "60°",
      "90°"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-plane",
    "topic": "river-boat-problems",
    "solution": "120°"
  },
  {
    "id": "DM0Ps3OxhqEIO1tJC8e0I",
    "question": "The position vector of a particle changes with\ntime according to the relation\n$$\\overrightarrow r (t) = 15{t^2}\\widehat i + (4 - 20{t^2})\\widehat j$$<br/> What is the\nmagnitude of the acceleration at t = 1 ?",
    "options": [
      "50",
      "25",
      "40",
      "100"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-acceleration-and-instantaneous-acceleration",
    "solution": "50"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqeux5",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements</p>\n<p>Statement I : Area under velocity- time graph gives the distance travelled by the body in a given time.</p>\n<p>Statement II : Area under acceleration- time graph is equal to the change in velocity- in the given time.</p>\n<p>In the light of given statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are False.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is true.",
      "Statement I is correct but Statement II is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-acceleration-and-instantaneous-acceleration",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is true."
  },
  {
    "id": "ldquqh93",
    "question": "A vehicle travels $4 \\mathrm{~km}$ with speed of $3 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$ and another $4 \\mathrm{~km}$ with speed of $5 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$, then its average speed is",
    "options": [
      "$3.75 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$",
      "$4.25 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$",
      "$3.50 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$",
      "$4.00 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-speed-and-instantaneous-speed",
    "solution": "$3.75 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduhkejs",
    "question": "<p>A car travels a distance of '$$x$$' with speed $$v_1$$ and then same distance '$$x$$' with speed $$v_2$$ in the same direction. The average speed of the car is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${{{v_1}{v_2}} \\over {2({v_1} + {v_2})}}$$",
      "$${{2{v_1}{v_2}} \\over {{v_1} + {v_2}}}$$",
      "$${{2x} \\over {{v_1} + {v_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{v_1} + {v_2}} \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-speed-and-instantaneous-speed",
    "solution": "$${{2{v_1}{v_2}} \\over {{v_1} + {v_2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgoye1mh",
    "question": "<p>The distance travelled by an object in time $$t$$ is given by $$s=(2.5) t^{2}$$. The instantaneous speed of the object at $$\\mathrm{t}=5 \\mathrm{~s}$$ will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$5 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$",
      "$$12.5 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$",
      "$$62.5 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$",
      "$$25 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-speed-and-instantaneous-speed",
    "solution": "$$25 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "luyita7s",
    "question": "<p>A particle moving in a straight line covers half the distance with speed $$6 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. The other half is covered in two equal time intervals with speeds $$9 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ and $$15 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ respectively. The average speed of the particle during the motion is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "9.2 m/s",
      "8.8 m/s",
      "10 m/s",
      "8 m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-speed-and-instantaneous-speed",
    "solution": "8 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc5838s",
    "question": "<p>A train starting from rest first accelerates uniformly up to a speed of $$80 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$$ for time $$t$$, then it moves with a constant speed for time $$3 t$$. The average speed of the train for this duration of journey will be (in $$\\mathrm{km} / \\mathrm{h}$$) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "70",
      "40",
      "30",
      "80"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-speed-and-instantaneous-speed",
    "solution": "70"
  },
  {
    "id": "dLNi3PAPf18R3gA5",
    "question": "The co-ordinates of a moving particle at any time 't' are given by x = $$\\alpha $$t<sup>3</sup> and y = βt<sup>3</sup>. The speed to the particle at time 't' is given by",
    "options": [
      "$$3t\\sqrt {{\\alpha ^2} + {\\beta ^2}} $$",
      "$$3{t^2}\\sqrt {{\\alpha ^2} + {\\beta ^2}} $$",
      "$${t^2}\\sqrt {{\\alpha ^2} + {\\beta ^2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{\\alpha ^2} + {\\beta ^2}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-velocity-and-instantaneous-velocity",
    "solution": "$$3{t^2}\\sqrt {{\\alpha ^2} + {\\beta ^2}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krwa2r8z",
    "question": "The instantaneous velocity of a particle moving in a straight line is given as $$V = \\alpha t + \\beta {t^2}$$, where $$\\alpha$$ and $$\\beta$$ are constants. The distance travelled by the particle between 1s and 2s is :",
    "options": [
      "3$$\\alpha$$ + 7$$\\beta$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}\\alpha  + {7 \\over 3}\\beta $$",
      "$${\\alpha  \\over 2} + {\\beta  \\over 3}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}\\alpha  + {7 \\over 2}\\beta $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-velocity-and-instantaneous-velocity",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 2}\\alpha  + {7 \\over 3}\\beta $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p41lxu",
    "question": "<p>If $$\\mathrm{t}=\\sqrt{x}+4$$, then $$\\left(\\frac{\\mathrm{d} x}{\\mathrm{~d} t}\\right)_{\\mathrm{t}=4}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "zero",
      "8",
      "16"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-velocity-and-instantaneous-velocity",
    "solution": "zero"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtxhh99",
    "question": "<p>The distance travelled by a particle is related to time t as $$x=4\\mathrm{t}^2$$. The velocity of the particle at t=5s is :-</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{25~ms^{-1}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{20~ms^{-1}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{8~ms^{-1}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{40~ms^{-1}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-velocity-and-instantaneous-velocity",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{40~ms^{-1}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnxvqd2",
    "question": "The position of a particle related to time is given by $x=\\left(5 t^{2}-4 t+5\\right) \\mathrm{m}$. The magnitude of velocity of the particle at $t=2 s$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "$14 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$",
      "$16 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$",
      "$10 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$",
      "$06 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$\n"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-velocity-and-instantaneous-velocity",
    "solution": "$16 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvr2x57",
    "question": "<p>A person travels $$x$$ distance with velocity $$v_{1}$$ and then $$x$$ distance with velocity $$v_{2}$$ in the same direction. The average velocity of the person is $$\\mathrm{v}$$, then the relation between $$v, v_{1}$$ and $$v_{2}$$ will be.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathbf{V}=\\mathbf{V}_{1}+\\mathbf{V}_{2}$$",
      "$$V=\\frac{v_{1}+V_{2}}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{v}}=\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{v}_{1}}+\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{v}_{2}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{2}{\\mathrm{~V}}=\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{v}_{1}}+\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{v}_{2}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "average-velocity-and-instantaneous-velocity",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{2}{\\mathrm{~V}}=\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{v}_{1}}+\\frac{1}{\\mathrm{v}_{2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "vR5XKzMNCb4t4dNl",
    "question": "Speeds of two identical cars are $$u $$ and $$4$$$$u $$ at the specific instant. The ratio of the respective distances in which the two cars are stopped from that instant is :",
    "options": [
      "$$1:1$$ ",
      "$$1:4$$",
      "$$1:8$$  ",
      "$$1:16$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$$1:16$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Vgq2zysrfFM5zUnT",
    "question": "A car, moving with a speed of 50 km/hr, can be stopped by brakes after at least 6 m. If the\nsame car is moving at a speed of 100 km/hr, the minimum stopping distance is",
    "options": [
      "12 m",
      "18 m",
      "24 m",
      "6 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "24 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "kEn7LbtD3nafqy6u",
    "question": "An automobile travelling with speed of 60 km/h, can brake to stop within a distance of 20 m.\nIf the car is going twice as fast, i.e 120 km/h, the stopping distance will be",
    "options": [
      "60 m",
      "40 m",
      "20 m",
      "80 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "80 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "FJLr8Z4hwAqCn4QY",
    "question": "A car starting from rest accelerates at the rate f through a distance S, then continues\nat constant speed for time t and then decelerates at the rate $${f \\over 2}$$ to come to rest. If the\ntotal distance traversed is 15 S, then",
    "options": [
      "$$S = {1 \\over 6}f{t^2}$$",
      "$$S = ft$$",
      "$$S = {1 \\over 4}f{t^2}$$",
      "$$S = {1 \\over 72}f{t^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$$S = {1 \\over 72}f{t^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "E5RyZp8ButbOCV2F4tLAR",
    "question": "An automobile, travelling at $$40\\,$$ km/h, can be stopped at a distance of $$40\\,$$ m by applying brakes. If the same automobile is travelling at $$80\\,$$ km/h, the minimum stopping distance, in metres, is (assume no skidding) :",
    "options": [
      "$$45\\,$$ m",
      "$$100\\,$$ m",
      "$$150\\,$$ m",
      "$$160\\,$$ m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$$160\\,$$ m"
  },
  {
    "id": "s5pd1xyXZdDWWlbt8dedb",
    "question": "In a car race on straight road, car A takes a time t less than car B at the finish and passes finishing point with a speed '$$\\upsilon $$' more than that of car B. Both the cars start from rest and travel with constant acceleration a<sub>1</sub> and a<sub>2</sub> respectively. Then '$$\\upsilon $$' is equal  to : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{2{a_1}{a_2}} \\over {{a_1} + {a_2}}}t$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {2{a_1}{a_2}} t$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{a_1}{a_2}} t$$",
      "$${{{a_1} + {a_2}} \\over 2}t$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{a_1}{a_2}} t$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "U3xcTPNDrF9q7GuLFq5g4",
    "question": "A particle moves from the point $$\\left( {2.0\\widehat i + 4.0\\widehat j} \\right)$$ m, at t = 0, with an initial velocity $$\\left( {5.0\\widehat i + 4.0\\widehat j} \\right)$$ ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. It is acted upon by a constant force which produces a constant acceleration $$\\left( {4.0\\widehat i + 4.0\\widehat j} \\right)$$ ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>.  What is the distance of the particle from the origin at time 2 s?",
    "options": [
      "15 m",
      "$$20\\sqrt 2 $$ m",
      "$$10\\sqrt 2 $$ m",
      "5 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$$20\\sqrt 2 $$ m"
  },
  {
    "id": "ypLfTlJ7kSZWdRZxbp1klrxixol",
    "question": "An engine of a train, moving with uniform acceleration, passes the signal-post with velocity u and the last compartment with velocity v. The velocity with which middle point of the train passes the signal post is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{u + v} \\over 2}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{v^2} - {u^2}} \\over 2}} $$",
      "$${{v - u} \\over 2}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{v^2} + {u^2}} \\over 2}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{{v^2} + {u^2}} \\over 2}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lBrfl6CGumvivDoYF1klukhpye",
    "question": "A scooter accelerates from rest for time t<sub>1</sub> at constant rate a<sub>1</sub> and then retards at constant rate a<sub>2</sub> for time t<sub>2</sub> and comes to rest. The correct value of $${{{t_1}} \\over {{t_2}}}$$ wil be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{a_1} + {a_2}} \\over {{a_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{a_1} + {a_2}} \\over {{a_1}}}$$",
      "$${{{a_2}} \\over {{a_1}}}$$",
      "$${{{a_1}} \\over {{a_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$${{{a_2}} \\over {{a_1}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lyhEKI3Puvr1IK36cr1kmj1t82f",
    "question": "A car accelerates from rest at a constant rate $$\\alpha$$ for some time after which it decelerates at a constant rate $$\\beta$$ to come to rest. If the total time elapsed is t seconds, the total distance travelled is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{4\\alpha \\beta } \\over {(\\alpha  + \\beta )}}{t^2}$$",
      "$${{2\\alpha \\beta } \\over {(\\alpha  + \\beta )}}{t^2}$$",
      "$${{\\alpha \\beta } \\over {2(\\alpha  + \\beta )}}{t^2}$$",
      "$${{\\alpha \\beta } \\over {4(\\alpha  + \\beta )}}{t^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$${{\\alpha \\beta } \\over {2(\\alpha  + \\beta )}}{t^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54uibr0",
    "question": "<p>A small toy starts moving from the position of rest under a constant acceleration. If it travels a distance of 10m in t s, the distance travelled by the toy in the next t s will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "10 m",
      "20 m",
      "30 m",
      "40 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "30 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kmlo5h",
    "question": "<p>The velocity of the bullet becomes one third after it penetrates 4 cm in a wooden block. Assuming that bullet is facing a constant resistance during its motion in the block. The bullet stops completely after travelling at (4 + x) cm inside the block. The value of x is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.0",
      "1.0",
      "0.5",
      "1.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "0.5"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh2zn7yx",
    "question": "<p>A particle starts with an initial velocity of $$10.0 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ along $$x$$-direction and accelerates uniformly at the rate of $$2.0 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$. The time taken by the particle to reach the velocity of $$60.0 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ is __________.</p>",
    "options": [
      "30s",
      "6s",
      "3s",
      "25s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "25s"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1tqy7",
    "question": "<p>A body starts moving from rest with constant acceleration covers displacement $$S_1$$ in first $$(p-1)$$ seconds and $$\\mathrm{S}_2$$ in first $$p$$ seconds. The displacement $$\\mathrm{S}_1+\\mathrm{S}_2$$ will be made in time :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(2 p+1) s$$\n",
      "$$(2 p-1) s$$\n",
      "$$\\left(2 p^2-2 p+1\\right) s$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\left(2 p^2-2 p+1\\right)} s$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{\\left(2 p^2-2 p+1\\right)} s$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwdjas",
    "question": "<p>Two cars are travelling towards each other at speed of $$20 \\mathrm{~m} \\mathrm{~s}^{-1}$$ each. When the cars are $$300 \\mathrm{~m}$$ apart, both the drivers apply brakes and the cars retard at the rate of $$2 \\mathrm{~m} \\mathrm{~s}^{-2}$$. The distance between them when they come to rest is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "25 m",
      "100 m",
      "50 m",
      "200 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "100 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxlz6",
    "question": "<p>A body travels $$102.5 \\mathrm{~m}$$ in $$\\mathrm{n}^{\\text {th }}$$ second and $$115.0 \\mathrm{~m}$$ in $$(\\mathrm{n}+2)^{\\text {th }}$$ second. The acceleration is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$6.25 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$$\n",
      "$$5 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$$\n",
      "$$12.5 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$$\n",
      "$$9 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "constant-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$$6.25 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "iftt7Ukg32iOqpz9",
    "question": "From a building two balls A and B  are thrown such that A is thrown upwards and B downwards ( both vertically with the same speed ). If v<sub>A</sub> and v<sub>B</sub> are their respective velocities on reaching the ground, then",
    "options": [
      "$${v_B} &gt; {v_A}$$",
      "$${v_A} = {v_B}$$",
      "$${v_A} &gt; {v_B}$$",
      "their velocities depend on their masses."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "$${v_A} = {v_B}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "5G6RV43sxKpCukvA",
    "question": "A ball is released from the top of a tower of height h meters. It takes T seconds to reach the\nground. What is the position of the ball in $${T \\over 3}$$ seconds?",
    "options": [
      "$${{8h} \\over 9}$$ meters from the ground ",
      "$${{7h} \\over 9}$$ meters from the ground",
      "$${h \\over 9}$$ meters from the ground",
      "$${{7h} \\over {18}}$$ meters from the ground"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "$${{8h} \\over 9}$$ meters from the ground "
  },
  {
    "id": "s5yFHVnS9AwaD1zV",
    "question": "A parachutist after bailing out falls $$50$$ $$m$$ without friction.  When parachute opens, it decelerates at $$2\\,\\,m/{s^2}.$$ He reaches the ground with a speed of $$3$$ $$m/s$$. At what height, did he bail out? ",
    "options": [
      "$$182$$ $$m$$ ",
      "$$91$$ $$m$$ ",
      "$$111$$ $$m$$ ",
      "$$293$$ $$m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "$$293$$ $$m$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Zf24hR1sRpoTHEVm",
    "question": "From a tower of height H, a particle is thrown vertically upwards with a speed u. The time taken by the\nparticle, to hit the ground, is n times that taken by it to reach the highest point of its path. The relation\nbetween H, u and n is:",
    "options": [
      "2gH = n<sup>2</sup>u<sup>2</sup>",
      "gH = (n - 2)<sup>2</sup>u<sup>2</sup>",
      "2gH = nu<sup>2</sup>(n - 2)",
      "gH = (n - 2)u<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "2gH = nu<sup>2</sup>(n - 2)"
  },
  {
    "id": "9Q4t9C2UiF8BVKwVtBjgy2xukff4b06s",
    "question": "A helicopter rises from rest on the ground\nvertically upwards with a constant acceleration\ng. A food packet is dropped from the helicopter\nwhen it is at a height h. The time taken by the\npacket to reach the ground is close to :\n<br/>[g is the\nacceleration due to gravity]",
    "options": [
      "t = 3.4$$\\sqrt {\\left( {{h \\over g}} \\right)} $$",
      "t = 1.8$$\\sqrt {\\left( {{h \\over g}} \\right)} $$",
      "t = $$\\sqrt {{{2h} \\over {3g}}} $$",
      "t = $${2 \\over 3}\\sqrt {\\left( {{h \\over g}} \\right)} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "t = 3.4$$\\sqrt {\\left( {{h \\over g}} \\right)} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "P4WZ7GFDfyZUjOf5HX1klt3asx3",
    "question": "A stone is dropped from the top of a building. When it crosses a point 5 m below the top, another stone starts to fall from a point 25 m below the top. Both stones reach the bottom of building simultaneously. The height of the building is :",
    "options": [
      "50 m",
      "25 m",
      "45 m",
      "35 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "45 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "gqd82wyBUQe34jbXuu1kmkb1992",
    "question": "A rubber ball is released from a height of 5 m above the floor. It bounces back repeatedly, always rising to $${{81} \\over {100}}$$ of the height through which it falls. Find the average speed of the ball. (Take g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "2.50 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "3.0 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "2.0 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "3.50 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "2.50 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krumd918",
    "question": "Water droplets are coming from an open tap at a particular rate. The spacing between a droplet observed at 4<sup>th</sup> second after its fall to the next droplet is 34.3 m. At what rate the droplets are coming from the tap ? (Take g = 9.8 m/s<sup>2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "3 drops / 2 sconds",
      "2 drops / second",
      "1 drop / second",
      "1 drop / 7 seconds"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "1 drop / second"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw8z197",
    "question": "A balloon was moving upwards with a uniform velocity of 10 m/s. An object of finite mass is dropped from the balloon when it was at a height of 75 m from the ground level. The height of the balloon from the ground when object strikes the ground was around :<br/><br/>(takes the value of g as 10 m/s<sup>2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "300 m",
      "200 m",
      "125 m",
      "250 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "125 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krywvo88",
    "question": "A ball is thrown up with a certain velocity so that it reaches a height 'h'. Find the ratio of the two different times of the ball reaching $${h \\over 3}$$ in both the directions.",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\sqrt 2  - 1} \\over {\\sqrt 2  + 1}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 3}$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt 3  - \\sqrt 2 } \\over {\\sqrt 3  + \\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt 3  - 1} \\over {\\sqrt 3  + 1}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "$${{\\sqrt 3  - \\sqrt 2 } \\over {\\sqrt 3  + \\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfjn3tk",
    "question": "Water drops are falling from a nozzle of a shower onto the floor, from a height of 9.8 m. The drops fall at a regular interval of time. When the first drop strikes the floor, at that instant, the third drop begins to fall. Locate the position of second drop from the floor when the first drop strikes the floor.",
    "options": [
      "4.18 m",
      "2.94 m",
      "2.45 m",
      "7.35 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "7.35 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l546s71c",
    "question": "<p>Two balls A and B are placed at the top of 180 m tall tower. Ball A is released from the top at t = 0 s. Ball B is thrown vertically down with an initial velocity 'u' at t = 2 s. After a certain time, both balls meet 100 m above the ground. Find the value of 'u' in ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. [use g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>] :</p>",
    "options": [
      "10",
      "15",
      "20",
      "30"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "30"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6m9o0g8",
    "question": "<p>A NCC parade is going at a uniform speed of $$9 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$$ under a mango tree on which a monkey is sitting at a height of $$19.6 \\mathrm{~m}$$. At any particular instant, the monkey drops a mango. A cadet will receive the mango whose distance from the tree at time of drop is: (Given $$g=9.8 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "5 m",
      "10 m",
      "19.8 m",
      "24.5 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "5 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p3zz09",
    "question": "<p>A ball is thrown up vertically with a certain velocity so that, it reaches a maximum height h. Find the ratio of the times in which it is at height $$\\frac{h}{3}$$ while going up and coming down respectively.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{2}-1}{\\sqrt{2}+1}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{3}-\\sqrt{2}}{\\sqrt{3}+\\sqrt{2}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{3}-1}{\\sqrt{3}+1}$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{3}-\\sqrt{2}}{\\sqrt{3}+\\sqrt{2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rgv1ad",
    "question": "<p>A juggler throws balls vertically upwards with same initial velocity in air. When the first ball reaches its highest position, he throws the next ball. Assuming the juggler throws n balls per second, the maximum height the balls can reach is</p>",
    "options": [
      "g/2n",
      "g/n",
      "2gn",
      "g/2n<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "g/2n<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rhc7vi",
    "question": "<p>A ball is released from a height h. If $$t_{1}$$ and $$t_{2}$$ be the time required to complete first half and second half of the distance respectively. Then, choose the correct relation between $$t_{1}$$ and $$t_{2}$$.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$t_{1}=(\\sqrt{2}) t_{2}$$",
      "$$t_{1}=(\\sqrt{2}-1) t_{2}$$",
      "$$t_{2}=(\\sqrt{2}+1) t_{1}$$",
      "$$t_{2}=(\\sqrt{2}-1) t_{1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "$$t_{2}=(\\sqrt{2}-1) t_{1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrikj40",
    "question": "<p>A ball is thrown vertically upward with an initial velocity of $$150 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. The ratio of velocity after $$3 \\mathrm{~s}$$ and $$5 \\mathrm{~s}$$ is $$\\frac{x+1}{x}$$. The value of $$x$$ is ___________.</p>\n<p>$$\\left\\{\\right.$$ take, $$\\left.g=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}\\right\\}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-5$$",
      "10",
      "5",
      "6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "5"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb2956u",
    "question": "<p>A body projected vertically upwards with a certain speed from the top of a tower reaches the ground in $$t_1$$. If it is projected vertically downwards from the same point with the same speed, it reaches the ground in $$t_2$$. Time required to reach the ground, if it is dropped from the top of the tower, is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{t}_1+\\mathrm{t}_2}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{t}_1 \\mathrm{t}_2}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{\\mathrm{t}_1}{\\mathrm{t}_2}}$$\n",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{t}_1-\\mathrm{t}_2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "motion-under-gravity",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{\\mathrm{t}_1 \\mathrm{t}_2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "zrxJySXVzbi7z7PxEaecR",
    "question": "A car is standing 200 m behind a bus, which is also at rest. The two start moving at the same instant but with different forward accelerations. The bus has acceleration 2 m/s<sup>2</sup>  and the car has acceleration 4 m/s<sup>2</sup> . The car will catch up with the bus after a time of :\n",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {110} \\,s$$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt {120} \\,s$$",
      "$$10\\,\\,\\sqrt 2 \\,s$$ ",
      "15 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-one-dimension",
    "solution": "$$10\\,\\,\\sqrt 2 \\,s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "UtGRbCl8eCFVeewELsQAz",
    "question": "A passenger train of length 60 m travels at a speed of 80 km/hr. Another freight train of length 120 m travels at a speed of 30 km/hr. The ratio of times taken by the passenger train to completely cross the freight train when : (i) they are moving in the same direction , and (ii) in the opposite direction is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{25} \\over {11}}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{11} \\over 5}$$",
      "$${5 \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-one-dimension",
    "solution": "$${{11} \\over 5}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "FCDZHjWtZcXdqQfoSijgy2xukev1krmx",
    "question": "Train A and train B are running on parallel\ntracks in the opposite directions with speeds of\n36 km/hour and 72 km/hour, respectively. A\nperson is walking in train A in the direction\nopposite to its motion with a speed of 1.8 km/\nhour. Speed (in ms<sup>–1</sup>) of this person as\nobserved from train B will be close to : <br/>(take the\ndistance between the tracks as negligible)",
    "options": [
      "30.5 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "29.5 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "31.5 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "28.5 ms<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-one-dimension",
    "solution": "29.5 ms<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqarmk6",
    "question": "A boy reaches the airport and finds that the escalator is not working. He walks up the stationary escalator in time t<sub>1</sub>. If he remains stationary on a moving escalator then the escalator takes him up in time t<sub>2</sub>. The time taken by him to walk up on the moving escalator will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{t_1}{t_2}} \\over {{t_2} - {t_1}}}$$",
      "$${{{t_1} + {t_2}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{{t_1}{t_2}} \\over {{t_2} + {t_1}}}$$",
      "$${t_2} - {t_1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-one-dimension",
    "solution": "$${{{t_1}{t_2}} \\over {{t_2} + {t_1}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59lv0ce",
    "question": "<p>Two buses P and Q start from a point at the same time and move in a straight line and their positions are represented by $${X_P}(t) = \\alpha t + \\beta {t^2}$$ and $${X_Q}(t) = ft - {t^2}$$. At what time, both the buses have same velocity?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\alpha  - f} \\over {1 + \\beta }}$$",
      "$${{\\alpha  + f} \\over {2(\\beta  - 1)}}$$",
      "$${{\\alpha  + f} \\over {2(1 + \\beta )}}$$",
      "$${{f - \\alpha } \\over {2(1 + \\beta )}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-one-dimension",
    "solution": "$${{f - \\alpha } \\over {2(1 + \\beta )}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp0lhqz",
    "question": "<p>A passenger sitting in a train A moving at $$90 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$$ observes another train $$\\mathrm{B}$$ moving in the opposite direction for $$8 \\mathrm{~s}$$. If the velocity of the train B is $$54 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$$, then length of train B is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "80 m",
      "200 m",
      "120 m",
      "320 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-one-dimension",
    "solution": "320 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq2how7",
    "question": "<p>Two trains 'A' and 'B' of length '$$l$$' and '$$4 l$$' are travelling into a tunnel of length '$$\\mathrm{L}$$' in parallel tracks from opposite directions with velocities $$108 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$$ and $$72 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$$, respectively. If train 'A' takes $$35 \\mathrm{~s}$$ less time than train 'B' to cross the tunnel then. length '$$L$$' of tunnel is :</p>\n<p>(Given $$\\mathrm{L}=60 l$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "900 m",
      "1200 m",
      "1800 m",
      "2700 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-one-dimension",
    "solution": "1800 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsamvrk0",
    "question": "<p>Train A is moving along two parallel rail tracks towards north with speed $$72 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$$ and train B is moving towards south with speed $$108 \\mathrm{~km} / \\mathrm{h}$$. Velocity of train B with respect to A and velocity of ground with respect to B are (in $$\\mathrm{ms}^{-1}$$):</p>",
    "options": [
      "-50 and -30",
      "-50 and 30",
      "-30 and 50",
      "50 and -30"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "relative-motion-in-one-dimension",
    "solution": "-50 and 30"
  },
  {
    "id": "G62rUQ4WvQn4wwUv",
    "question": "The relation between time t and distance x is t = ax<sup>2</sup> + bx where a and b are constants.\nThe acceleration is",
    "options": [
      "2bv<sup>3</sup>",
      "-2abv<sup>2</sup>",
      "2av<sup>2</sup>",
      "-2av<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "variable-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "-2av<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "uY6K2wAVhD70ftdr",
    "question": "A particle located at x = 0 at time t = 0, starts moving along the positive x-direction with a velocity\n'v' that varies as $$v = \\alpha \\sqrt x $$. The displacement of the particle varies with time as ",
    "options": [
      "t<sup>2</sup>",
      "t",
      "t<sup>1/2</sup>",
      "t<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "variable-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "t<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "NfUCxiBo2rJMDUKn",
    "question": "The velocity of a particle is v = v<sub>0</sub> + gt + ft<sup>2</sup>. If its position is x = 0 at t = 0, then its displacement after unit time (t = 1) is",
    "options": [
      "v<sub>0</sub> + g/2 + f",
      "v<sub>0</sub> + 2g + 3f",
      "v<sub>0</sub> + g/2 + f/3",
      "v<sub>0</sub> + g + f"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "variable-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "v<sub>0</sub> + g/2 + f/3"
  },
  {
    "id": "fuuwDAtRMqLM5A4w",
    "question": "An object, moving with a speed of 6.25 m/s, is decelerated at a rate given by :\n<br/>$${{dv} \\over {dt}} =  - 2.5\\sqrt v $$ where v is the instantaneous speed. The time taken by the object, to come to rest, would be :",
    "options": [
      "2 s",
      "4 s",
      "8 s",
      "1 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "variable-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "2 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "VmhYRHaJiN9y2G0KU3fD6",
    "question": "The position of a particle as a function of time\nt, is given by<br/>x(t) = at + bt<sup>2</sup> – ct<sup>3</sup><br/>\nwhere a, b and c are constants. When the\nparticle attains zero acceleration, then its\nvelocity will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$a + {{{b^2}} \\over {c}}$$",
      "$$a + {{{b^2}} \\over {4c}}$$",
      "$$a + {{{b^2}} \\over {3c}}$$",
      "$$a + {{{b^2}} \\over {2c}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "variable-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$$a + {{{b^2}} \\over {3c}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xilgUXOlQLZMwr8DE13rsa0w2w9jx6le17d",
    "question": "A particle is moving with speed v = b$$\\sqrt x $$ along positive x-axis. Calculate the speed of the particle at\ntime t = $$\\tau $$(assume that the particle is at origin t = 0) \n",
    "options": [
      "$${{{b^2}\\tau } \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$${{b^2}\\tau }$$",
      "$${{{b^2}\\tau } \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{{b^2}\\tau } \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "variable-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$${{{b^2}\\tau } \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xuIndchfXveJFsmLrS1kmkarpkg",
    "question": "The velocity of a particle is v = v<sub>0</sub> + gt + Ft<sup>2</sup>. Its position is x = 0 at t = 0; then its displacement after time (t = 1) is :",
    "options": [
      "v<sub>0</sub> + g + f",
      "v<sub>0</sub> + $${g \\over 2}$$ + $${F \\over 3}$$",
      "v<sub>0</sub> + 2g + 3F",
      "v<sub>0</sub> + $${g \\over 2}$$ + F"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "variable-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "v<sub>0</sub> + $${g \\over 2}$$ + $${F \\over 3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw6css0",
    "question": "The relation between time t and distance x for a moving body is given as t = mx<sup>2</sup> + nx, where m and n are constants. The retardation of the motion is : (When v stands for velocity)",
    "options": [
      "2 mv<sup>3</sup>",
      "2 mnv<sup>3</sup>",
      "2nv<sup>3</sup>",
      "2n<sup>2</sup>v<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "variable-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "2 mv<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse66y4y",
    "question": "<p>The relation between time '$$t$$' and distance '$$x$$' is $$t=\\alpha x^2+\\beta x$$, where $$\\alpha$$ and $$\\beta$$ are constants. The relation between acceleration $$(a)$$ and velocity $$(v)$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$a=-5 \\alpha v^5$$\n",
      "$$a=-3 \\alpha v^2$$\n",
      "$$a=-2 \\alpha v^3$$\n",
      "$$a=-4 \\alpha v^4$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "variable-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "$$a=-2 \\alpha v^3$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsflwghv",
    "question": "<p>A particle is moving in a straight line. The variation of position '$$x$$' as a function of time '$$t$$' is given as $$x=\\left(t^3-6 t^2+20 t+15\\right) m$$. The velocity of the body when its acceleration becomes zero is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "6 m/s",
      "10 m/s",
      "8 m/s",
      "4 m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "motion-in-a-straight-line",
    "topic": "variable-acceleration-motion",
    "solution": "8 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "JkHVxcDj4uuPeWCB",
    "question": "A cylinder of height $$20$$ $$m$$ is completely filled with water. The velocity of efflux of water (in $$m{s^{ - 1}}$$) through a small hole on the side wall of the cylinder near its bottom is ",
    "options": [
      "$$10$$ ",
      "$$20$$ ",
      "$$25.5$$ ",
      "$$5$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$20$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "3xRnUDU1F67DjjNy",
    "question": "Spherical balls of radius $$R$$ are falling in a viscous fluid of viscosity $$\\eta $$ with a velocity $$v.$$ The retarding viscous force acting on the spherical ball is ",
    "options": [
      "inversely proportional to both radius $$R$$ and velocity $$v$$ ",
      "directly proportional to both radius $$R$$ and velocity $$v$$ ",
      "directly proportional to $$R$$ but inversely proportional to $$v$$ ",
      "inversely proportional to $$R,$$ but directly proportional to velocity $$v$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "directly proportional to both radius $$R$$ and velocity $$v$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "sVk2AaQkeLyh6qNm",
    "question": "If the terminal speed of a sphere of gold (density $$ = 19.5\\,\\,kg/{m^3}$$) is $$0.2$$ $$m/s$$ in a viscous liquid (density $$ = 1.5\\,\\,kg/{m^3}$$, find the terminal speed of a sphere of silver (density $$ = 10.5\\,\\,kg/{m^3}$$) of the same size in the same liquid",
    "options": [
      "$$0.4$$ $$m/s$$ ",
      "$$0.133$$ $$m/s$$ ",
      "$$0.1$$ $$m/s$$ ",
      "$$0.2$$ $$m/s$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$0.1$$ $$m/s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "uq8SZDqVxZWn6vtw",
    "question": "A spherical solid ball of volume $$V$$ is made of a material of density $${\\rho _1}$$. It is falling through a liquid of density $${\\rho _2}\\left( {{\\rho _2} &lt; {\\rho _1}} \\right)$$. Assume that the liquid applies a viscous force on the ball that is proportional to the square of its speed $$v,$$ i.e., $${F_{viscous}} =  - k{v^2}\\left( {k &gt; 0} \\right).$$ The terminal speed of the ball is ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{{Vg\\left( {{\\rho _1} - {\\rho _2}} \\right)} \\over k}} $$ ",
      "$${{{Vg{\\rho _1}} \\over k}}$$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{Vg{\\rho _1}} \\over k}} $$ ",
      "$${{Vg\\left( {{\\rho _1} - {\\rho _2}} \\right)} \\over k}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{Vg\\left( {{\\rho _1} - {\\rho _2}} \\right)} \\over k}} $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "a1gAWb3hDAhAJ0QG",
    "question": "Water is flowing continuously from a tap having an internal diameter $$8 \\times {10^{ - 3}}\\,\\,m.$$ The water velocity as it leaves the tap is $$0.4\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$ . The diameter of the water stream at a distance $$2 \\times {10^{ - 1}}\\,\\,m$$ below the tap is close to : ",
    "options": [
      "$$7.5 \\times {10^{ - 3}}m$$ ",
      "$$9.6 \\times {10^{ - 3}}m$$ ",
      "$$3.6 \\times {10^{ - 3}}m$$ ",
      "$$5.0 \\times {10^{ - 3}}m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$3.6 \\times {10^{ - 3}}m$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "lDWnjJ6foMzKFqoMnliOq",
    "question": "Two tubes of radii r<sub>1</sub>  and r<sub>2</sub>, and lengths l<sub>1</sub> and l<sub>2</sub> , respectively, are connected in series\nand a liquid flows through each of them in stream line conditions. P<sub>1</sub>  and P<sub>2</sub>  are pressure differences across the two tubes. \n<br/><br/>If P<sub>2</sub>  is 4P<sub>1</sub>  and l<sub>2</sub>\n is $${{{1_1}} \\over 4}$$, then the radius r<sub>2</sub> will be equal to :\n",
    "options": [
      "r<sub>1</sub>",
      "2r<sub>1</sub>",
      "4r<sub>1</sub> ",
      "$${{{r_1}} \\over 2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$${{{r_1}} \\over 2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "6b3uqOdsIiRkTBUOom2VA",
    "question": "The top of a water tank is open to air and its water level is mainted. It is giving out 0.74 m<sup>3</sup> water per minute through a circular opening of 2 cm radius in its wall. The depth of the center of the opening from the level of water in the tank is close to : ",
    "options": [
      "6.0 m",
      "4.8 m",
      "9.6 m",
      "2.9 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "4.8 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "lcunR0RKhClnAONLIE5Ep",
    "question": "Water flows into a large tank with flat bottom at the rate of 10<sup>–4</sup>m<sup>3</sup>s<sup>–1</sup>. Water is also leaking out of a hole ofarea 1 cm<sup>2</sup> at its bottom. If the height of the water in the tank remains steady, then this height is -",
    "options": [
      "2.9 cm",
      "5.1 cm",
      "4 cm",
      "1.7 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "5.1 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "rxt0Fog6gwyvaU1QQ4b5p",
    "question": "Water from a pipe is coming at a rate of\n100 litres per minute. If the radius of the pipe\nis 5 cm, the Reynolds number for the flow is\nof the order of : (density of water = 1000 kg/m<sup>3</sup>,\ncoefficient of viscosity of water = 1mPas)",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>6</sup>",
      "10<sup>4</sup>",
      "10<sup>3</sup>",
      "10<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "10<sup>4</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "2zRpE5bM3prv0h6pd33rsa0w2w9jwzia0nc",
    "question": "Water from a tap emerges vertically downwards with an initial speed of 1.0 ms<sup>–1</sup>\n. The cross-sectional area of\nthe tap is 10<sup>–4</sup> m<sup>2</sup>. Assume that the pressure is constant throughout the stream of water and that the flow is streamlined. The cross-sectional area of the stream, 0.15 m below the tap would be : (Take g = 10 ms<sup>–2</sup>)\n",
    "options": [
      "5 × 10<sup>–4</sup> m<sup>2</sup>",
      "2 × 10<sup>–5</sup> m<sup>2</sup>",
      "5 × 10<sup>–5</sup> m<sup>2</sup>",
      "1 × 10<sup>–5</sup> m<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "5 × 10<sup>–5</sup> m<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "V1d70uFZ8ROvCIn9CQ3rsa0w2w9jx7g9mqj",
    "question": "A solid sphere, of radius R acquires a terminal velocity v<sub>1</sub> when falling (due to gravity) through a viscous\nfluid having a coefficient of viscosity . The sphere is broken into 27 identical solid spheres. If each of these\nspheres acquires a terminal velocity, v<sub>2</sub>, when falling through the same fluid, the ratio (v<sub>1</sub>/v<sub>2</sub>) equals :\n",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 9}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {27}}$$",
      "27",
      "9"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "9"
  },
  {
    "id": "Qu6TMjO4cpKn4QSDdNjgy2xukg0bwhjs",
    "question": "A fluid is flowing through a horizontal pipe of varying cross-section, with<br/> speed v ms<sup>–1</sup> at a point\nwhere the pressure is P pascal. At another point where pressure is $${P \\over 2}$$\n Pascal its speed is V ms<sup>–1</sup>. If\nthe density of the fluid is $$\\rho $$ kg m<sup>–3</sup> and the flow is streamline, then V is equal to :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{P \\over {2\\rho }} + {v^2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{P \\over \\rho } + {v^2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{2P} \\over \\rho } + {v^2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{P \\over \\rho } + {v}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{P \\over \\rho } + {v^2}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "eBVwJxHh1HpMhfPbOXjgy2xukfl4r23l",
    "question": "In an experiment to verify Stokes law, a small\nspherical ball of radius r and density $$\\rho $$ falls\nunder gravity through a distance h in air before\nentering a tank of water. If the terminal velocity\nof the ball inside water is same as its velocity\njust before entering the water surface, then the\nvalue of h is proportional to :\n<br/>(ignore viscosity of air)",
    "options": [
      "r",
      "r<sup>4</sup>",
      "r<sup>3</sup>",
      "r<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "r<sup>4</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "pFf55H5aTHZtf74zJ1jgy2xukfambwaa",
    "question": "Two identical cylindrical vessels are kept on the ground and each contain the same liquid of density\nd. The area of the base of both vessels is S but the height of liquid in one vessel is x<sub>1</sub>\n and in the\nother, x<sub>2</sub>\n. When both cylinders are connected through a pipe of negligible volume very close to the\nbottom, the liquid flows from one vessel to the other until it comes to equilibrium at a new height.\nThe change in energy of the system in the process is:",
    "options": [
      "gdS(x<sub>2</sub> + x<sub>1</sub>)<sup>2</sup>",
      "gdS$$\\left( {x_2^2 + x_1^2} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}gdS{\\left( {{x_2} - {x_1}} \\right)^2}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 4}gdS{\\left( {{x_2} - {x_1}} \\right)^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 4}gdS{\\left( {{x_2} - {x_1}} \\right)^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "nVfXdosI464ErbTnj17k9k2k5f810o1",
    "question": "An ideal fluid flows (laminar flow) through a pipe of non-uniform diameter. The maximum and\nminimum diameters of the pipes are 6.4 cm and 4.8 cm, respectively. The ratio of the minimum\nand the maximum velocities of fluid in this pipe is :\n",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 4}$$",
      "$${9 \\over {16}}$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{81} \\over {256}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$${9 \\over {16}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Cpsh7fqMj5qcaIUJqN1kmioeu2t",
    "question": "What will be the nature of flow of water from a circular tap, when its flow rate increased from 0.18 L/min to 0.48 L/min? The radius of the tap and viscosity of water are 0.5 cm and 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> Pa s, respectively. (Density of water : 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "Steady flow to unsteady flow",
      "Unsteady to steady flow",
      "Remains turbulent flow",
      "Remains steady flow"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "Steady flow to unsteady flow"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks0jzxi2",
    "question": "A raindrop with radius R = 0.2 mm falls from a cloud at a height h = 2000 m above the ground. Assume that the drop is spherical throughout its fall and the force of buoyance may be neglected, then the terminal speed attained by the raindrop is :<br/><br/>[Density of water f<sub>w</sub> = 1000 kg m<sup>$$-$$3</sup> and Density of air f<sub>a</sub> = 1.2 kg m<sup>$$-$$3</sup>, g = 10 m/s<sup>2</sup>, Coefficient of viscosity of air = 1.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> Nsm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "250.6 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "43.56 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "4.94 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "14.4 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "4.94 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kte6glqk",
    "question": "In Millikan's oil drop experiment, what is viscous force acting on an uncharged drop of radius 2.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> m and density 1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> kgm<sup>$$-$$3</sup> ? Take viscosity of liquid = 1.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> Nsm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>. (Neglect buoyancy due to air).",
    "options": [
      "3.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$11</sup> N",
      "3.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$10</sup> N",
      "1.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$10</sup> N",
      "5.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$10</sup> N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "3.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$10</sup> N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55jyzkp",
    "question": "<p>A water drop of radius 1 $$\\mu$$m falls in a situation where the effect of buoyant force is negligible. Co-efficient of viscosity of air is 1.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> Nsm<sup>$$-$$2</sup> and its density is negligible as compared to that of water 10<sup>6</sup> gm<sup>$$-$$3</sup>. Terminal velocity of the water drop is :</p>\n<p>(Take acceleration due to gravity = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "145.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "118.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "132.6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "123.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "123.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l568efpf",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R.</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Product of Pressure (P) and time (t) has the same dimension as that of coefficient of viscosity.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Coefficient of viscosity = $${{Force} \\over {Velocity\\,gradient}}$$</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are true, and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "Both A and R are true but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is true but R is false.",
      "A is false but R is true."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "A is true but R is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56ufwdj",
    "question": "<p>When a ball is dropped into a lake from a height 4.9 m above the water level, it hits the water with a velocity v and then sinks to the bottom with the constant velocity v. It reaches the bottom of the lake 4.0 s after it is dropped. The approximate depth of the lake is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "19.6 m",
      "29.4 m",
      "39.2 m",
      "73.5 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "29.4 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57pxfvm",
    "question": "<p>The velocity of a small ball of mass 'm' and density d<sub>1</sub>, when dropped in a container filled with glycerin, becomes constant after some time. If the density of glycerin is d<sub>2</sub>, then the viscous force acting on the ball, will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$mg\\left( {1 - {{{d_1}} \\over {{d_2}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$$mg\\left( {1 - {{{d_2}} \\over {{d_1}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$$mg\\left( {{{{d_1}} \\over {{d_2}}} - 1} \\right)$$",
      "$$mg\\left( {{{{d_2}} \\over {{d_1}}} - 1} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$mg\\left( {1 - {{{d_2}} \\over {{d_1}}}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58hmu8q",
    "question": "<p>If p is the density and $$\\eta$$ is coefficient of viscosity of fluid which flows with a speed v in the pipe of diameter d, the correct formula for Reynolds number R<sub>e</sub> is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${R_e} = {{\\eta d} \\over {\\rho v}}$$",
      "$${R_e} = {{\\rho v} \\over {\\eta d}}$$",
      "$${R_e} = {{\\rho vd} \\over \\eta }$$",
      "$${R_e} = {\\eta  \\over {\\rho vd}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$${R_e} = {{\\rho vd} \\over \\eta }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5akad4b",
    "question": "<p>The terminal velocity (v<sub>t</sub>) of the spherical rain drop depends on the radius (r) of the spherical rain drop as :</p>",
    "options": [
      "r<sup>1/2</sup>",
      "r",
      "r<sup>2</sup>",
      "r<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "r<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w210bb",
    "question": "<p>An air bubble of negligible weight having radius r rises steadily through a solution of density $$\\sigma$$ at speed v. The coefficient of viscosity of the solution is given by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\eta  = {{4r\\sigma g} \\over {9v}}$$",
      "$$\\eta  = {{2{r^2}\\sigma g} \\over {9v}}$$",
      "$$\\eta  = {{2\\pi {r^2}\\sigma g} \\over {9v}}$$",
      "$$\\eta  = {{2{r^2}\\sigma g} \\over {3\\pi v}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$\\eta  = {{2{r^2}\\sigma g} \\over {9v}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6m9r89x",
    "question": "<p>A balloon has mass of $$10 \\mathrm{~g}$$ in air. The air escapes from the balloon at a uniform rate with velocity $$4.5 \\mathrm{~cm} / \\mathrm{s}$$. If the balloon shrinks in $$5 \\mathrm{~s}$$ completely. Then, the average force acting on that balloon will be (in dyne).</p>",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "9",
      "12",
      "18"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "9"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsaqrqk",
    "question": "<p>A fully loaded boeing aircraft has a mass of $$5.4\\times10^5$$ kg. Its total wing area is 500 m$$^2$$. It is in level flight with a speed of 1080  km/h. If the density of air $$\\rho$$ is 1.2 kg m$$^{-3}$$, the fractional increase in the speed of the air on the upper surface of the wing relative to the lower surface in percentage will be. ($$\\mathrm{g=10~m/s^2}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "16",
      "8",
      "6",
      "10"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "10"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgozs7t5",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A : A spherical body of radius $$(5 \\pm 0.1) \\mathrm{mm}$$ having a particular density is falling through a liquid of constant density. The percentage error in the calculation of its terminal velocity is $$4 \\%$$.</p>\n<p>Reason R : The terminal velocity of the spherical body falling through the liquid is inversely proportional to its radius.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is false but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is true",
      "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is false",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is NOT the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$",
      "Both $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ are true and $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is the correct explanation of $$\\mathbf{A}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{A}$$ is true but $$\\mathbf{R}$$ is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyq4u8n",
    "question": "<p>A hydraulic automobile lift is designed to lift vehicles of mass $$5000 \\mathrm{~kg}$$. The area of cross section of the cylinder carrying the load is $$250 \\mathrm{~cm}^{2}$$. The maximum pressure the smaller piston would have to bear is $$\\left[\\right.$$ Assume $$\\left.g=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}\\right]$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$20 \\times 10^{+6} \\mathrm{~Pa}$$",
      "$$200 \\times 10^{+6} \\mathrm{~Pa}$$",
      "$$2 \\times 10^{+5} \\mathrm{~Pa}$$",
      "$$2 \\times 10^{+6} \\mathrm{~Pa}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$2 \\times 10^{+6} \\mathrm{~Pa}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh24geed",
    "question": "<p>A small ball of mass $$\\mathrm{M}$$ and density $$\\rho$$ is dropped in a viscous liquid of density $$\\rho_{0}$$. After some time, the ball falls with a constant velocity. What is the viscous force on the ball ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{F}=\\mathrm{Mg}\\left(1-\\frac{\\rho_{\\mathrm{O}}}{\\rho}\\right)$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{F}=\\mathrm{Mg}\\left(1+\\frac{\\rho}{P_{o}}\\right)$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{F}=\\mathrm{Mg}\\left(1+\\frac{\\rho_{\\mathrm{o}}}{\\rho}\\right)$$",
      "$$F=M g\\left(1 \\pm \\rho \\rho_{0}\\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{F}=\\mathrm{Mg}\\left(1-\\frac{\\rho_{\\mathrm{O}}}{\\rho}\\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd68gpq",
    "question": "<p>A small spherical ball of radius $$r$$, falling through a viscous medium of negligible density has terminal velocity '$$v$$'. Another ball of the same mass but of radius $$2 r$$, falling through the same viscous medium will have terminal velocity:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4 \\mathrm{v}$$\n",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~V}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{v}{4}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{v}}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{v}}{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwderb",
    "question": "<p>A spherical ball of radius $$1 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~m}$$ and density $$10^5 \\mathrm{~kg} / \\mathrm{m}^3$$ falls freely under gravity through a distance $$h$$ before entering a tank of water, If after entering in water the velocity of the ball does not change, then the value of $$h$$ is approximately:</p>\n<p>(The coefficient of viscosity of water is $$9.8 \\times 10^{-6} \\mathrm{~N} \\mathrm{~s} / \\mathrm{m}^2$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "2518 m",
      "2396 m",
      "2249 m",
      "2296 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "2518 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gse1i",
    "question": "<p>Correct Bernoulli's equation is (symbols have their usual meaning) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$P+\\frac{1}{2} \\rho g h+\\frac{1}{2} \\rho v^2=$$ constant\n",
      "$$P+m g h+\\frac{1}{2} m v^2=$$ constant\n",
      "$$P+\\rho g h+\\rho v^2=$$ constant\n",
      "$$P+\\rho g h+\\frac{1}{2} \\rho v^2=$$ constant"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$P+\\rho g h+\\frac{1}{2} \\rho v^2=$$ constant"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57nro",
    "question": "<p>A small ball of mass $$m$$ and density $$\\rho$$ is dropped in a viscous liquid of density $$\\rho_0$$. After sometime, the ball falls with constant velocity. The viscous force on the ball is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$m g\\left(1-\\frac{\\rho_0}{\\rho}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$m g\\left(\\frac{\\rho_0}{\\rho}-1\\right)$$\n",
      "$$m g\\left(1-\\rho \\rho_0\\right)$$\n",
      "$$m g\\left(1+\\frac{\\rho}{\\rho_0}\\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "fluid-flow,-bernoulli's-principle-and-viscosity",
    "solution": "$$m g\\left(1-\\frac{\\rho_0}{\\rho}\\right)$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "RiPAAa5xJCjViIwD",
    "question": "A wire fixed at the upper end stretches by length $$l$$ by applying a force $$F.$$ The work done in stretching is ",
    "options": [
      "$$2Fl$$ ",
      "$$Fl$$ ",
      "$${F \\over {2l}}$$ ",
      "$${{Fl} \\over 2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$${{Fl} \\over 2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "5c7wvUHfFHzyXpmW",
    "question": "A wire elongates by $$l$$ $$mm$$ when a LOAD $$W$$ is hanged from it. If the wire goes over a pulley and two weights $$W$$ each are hung at the two ends, the elongation of the wire will be (in $$mm$$) ",
    "options": [
      "$$l$$ ",
      "$$2l$$ ",
      "zero ",
      "$$l/2$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$l$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "4E6505zL8Y7DJqxT",
    "question": "Two wires are made of the same material and have the same volume. However wire $$1$$ has cross-sectional area $$A$$ and wire $$2$$ has cross-sectional area $$3A.$$ If the length of wire $$1$$ increases by $$\\Delta x$$ on applying force $$F,$$ how much force is needed to stretch wire $$2$$ by the same amount?",
    "options": [
      "$$4F$$ ",
      "$$6F$$ ",
      "$$9F$$",
      "$$F$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$9F$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "HYPrE568wzdj69p3ZyqSw",
    "question": "A thin 1 m long rod has a radius of 5 mm. A force of 50 $$\\pi $$kN is applied at one end to determine its Young’s modulus. Assume that the force is exactly known. If the least count in the measurement of all lengths is 0.01 mm, which of the following statements is <b>false</b> ?",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\Delta \\gamma } \\over \\gamma }$$ gets minimum contribution\nfrom the uncertainty in the length.",
      "The figure of merit is the largest for the length of the rod.",
      "The maximum value of $$\\gamma $$ that can be determined is 2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup> ",
      "$${{\\Delta \\gamma } \\over \\gamma }$$ gets its maximum contribution\nfrom the uncertainty in strain "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "The maximum value of $$\\gamma $$ that can be determined is 2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>14</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "zdD0wVmKXtdZg2E0Owa42",
    "question": "A uniformly tapering conical wire is made from a material of Young’s modulus\nY and has a normal, unextended length L. The radii, at the upper and lower ends of this conical wire, have values R and 3 R, respectively. The upper end of the wire is fixed to a rigid support and a mass M is suspended from its lower end. The equilibrium extended length, of this wire, would equal :",
    "options": [
      "L $$\\left( {1 + {2 \\over 9}{{Mg} \\over {\\pi Y{R^2}}}} \\right)$$",
      "L $$\\left( {1 + {1 \\over 3}{{Mg} \\over {\\pi Y{R^2}}}} \\right)$$",
      "L $$\\left( {1 + {1 \\over 9}{{Mg} \\over {\\pi Y{R^2}}}} \\right)$$",
      "L $$\\left( {1 + {2 \\over 3}{{Mg} \\over {\\pi Y{R^2}}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "L $$\\left( {1 + {1 \\over 3}{{Mg} \\over {\\pi Y{R^2}}}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "5Fr2EmRJzoJz60RU",
    "question": "A man grows into a giant such that his linear dimensions increase by a factor of 9. Assuming that his\ndensity remains same, the stress in the leg will change by a factor of : ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {81}}$$",
      "9",
      "$${1 \\over {9}}$$",
      "81"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "9"
  },
  {
    "id": "E1fhHHnC7NNfj8KM",
    "question": "A solid sphere of radius r made of a soft material of bulk modulus K is surrounded by a liquid in a\ncylindrical container. A massless piston of area a floats on the surface of the liquid, covering entire cross\nsection of cylindrical container. When a mass m is placed on the surface of the piston to compress the\nliquid, the fractional decrement in the radius of the sphere, $$\\left( {{dr \\over r}} \\right)$$ is:",
    "options": [
      "$${{mg} \\over {Ka}}$$ ",
      "$${{Ka} \\over {mg}}$$ ",
      "$${{Ka} \\over {3mg}}$$ ",
      "$${{mg} \\over {3Ka}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$${{mg} \\over {3Ka}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "pQmuuIPkaW6Q6sjbtuD2Y",
    "question": "A load of mass M kg is suspended from a steel wire of length 2m and radius 1.0 mm in Searle's apparatus\nexperiment. The increase in length produced in the wire is 4.0 mm. Now the load is fully immersed in a liquid of relative density 2. The relative density of the material of load is 8. \n<br/><br/>The new value of increase in length of the steel wire is: \n",
    "options": [
      "5.0 mm",
      "zero",
      "3.0 mm",
      "4.0 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "3.0 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "u3IuZmrPwS8FDDq1e28y6",
    "question": "A steel wire having a radius of 2.0 mm,\ncarrying a load of 4 kg, is hanging from a\nceiling. Given that g = 3.1 p ms<sup>–2</sup>, what will be\nthe tensile stress that would be developed in the\nwire ?",
    "options": [
      "3.1 × 10<sup>6</sup> Nm<sup>–2</sup>",
      "6.2 × 10<sup>6</sup> Nm<sup>–2</sup>",
      "4.8 × 10<sup>6</sup> Nm<sup>–2</sup>",
      "5.2 × 10<sup>6</sup> Nm<sup>–2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "3.1 × 10<sup>6</sup> Nm<sup>–2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "sfjvWDEF1lrWPk7u3xrf2",
    "question": "Young's moduli of two wires A and B are in the\nratio 7 : 4. Wire A is 2 m long and has radius R.\nWire B is 1.5 m long and has radius 2 mm. If\nthe two wires stretch by the same length for a\ngiven load, then the value of R is close to :-",
    "options": [
      "1.7 mm",
      "1.9 mm",
      "1.3 mm",
      "1.5 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "1.7 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "5AuQ1lpbd5dl3vApLN3rsa0w2w9jwzkr8qb",
    "question": "In an experiment, brass and steel wires of length 1 m each with areas of cross section 1mm<sup>2</sup>\n are used. The\nwires are connected in series and one end of the combined wire is connected to a rigid support and other end\nis subjected to elongation. The stress required to produce a net elongation of 0.2 mm is,\n[Given, the Young's Modulus for steel and brass are, respectively, 120 × 10<sup>9</sup>\n N/m<sup>2</sup>\n and 60 × 10<sup>9</sup>\n N/m<sup>2</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "8.0 × 10<sup>6</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup>",
      "1.2 × 10<sup>6</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup>",
      "0.2 × 10<sup>6</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup>",
      "1.8 × 10<sup>6</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "8.0 × 10<sup>6</sup> N/m<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "mc6HbLgr5N2zZ8U0vN3rsa0w2w9jx7ibh2q",
    "question": "A uniform cylindrical rod of length L and radius r, is made from a material whose Young’s modulus of\nElasticity equals Y. When this rod is heated by temperature T and simultaneously subjected to a net\nlongitudinal compressional force F, its length remains unchanged. The coefficient of volume expansion, of\nthe material of the rod, is (nearly) equal to : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{3F} \\over {\\left( {\\pi {r^2}YT} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${{6F} \\over {\\left( {\\pi {r^2}YT} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${F \\over {\\left( {3\\pi {r^2}YT} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${9F\\left( {\\pi {r^2}YT} \\right)}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$${{3F} \\over {\\left( {\\pi {r^2}YT} \\right)}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "QHDq0apaUDoblbX1Z9jgy2xukfajwke5",
    "question": "A cube of metal is subjected to a hydrostatic pressure of 4 GPa. The percentage change in the\nlength of the side of the cube is close to :\n<br/>(Given bulk modulus of metal, B = 8 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>10</sup> Pa)",
    "options": [
      "0.6",
      "20",
      "1.67",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "1.67"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ekt0hrzV4m2WY3xc7Kjgy2xukfrp9ah0",
    "question": "An object of mass m is suspended at the end of a massless wire of length L and area of crosssection A. Young modulus of the material of the wire is Y. If the mass is pulled down slightly its\nfrequency of oscillation along the vertical direction is :",
    "options": [
      "$$f = {1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\sqrt {{{YA} \\over {mL}}} $$",
      "$$f = {1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\sqrt {{{mL} \\over {YA}}} $$",
      "$$f = {1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\sqrt {{{YL} \\over {mA}}} $$",
      "$$f = {1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\sqrt {{{mA} \\over {YL}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$f = {1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\sqrt {{{YA} \\over {mL}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "YXotwE6VkXcHCifO5o1klrhu9ll",
    "question": "If Y, K and $$\\eta $$ are the values of Young's modulus, bulk modulus and modulus of rigidity of any material respectively. Choose the correct relation for these parameters.",
    "options": [
      "$$Y = {{9K\\eta } \\over {3K - \\eta }}N/{m^2}$$",
      "$$Y = {{9K\\eta } \\over {2\\eta  + 3K}}N/{m^2}$$",
      "$$\\eta  = {{3YK} \\over {9K + Y}}N/{m^2}$$",
      "$$K = {{Y\\eta } \\over {9\\eta  - 3Y}}N/{m^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$K = {{Y\\eta } \\over {9\\eta  - 3Y}}N/{m^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "HJBUayuAzuAhaoYvJH1kltjallu",
    "question": "The normal density of a material is $$\\rho$$ and its bulk modulus of elasticity is K. The magnitude of increase in density of material, when a pressure P is applied uniformly on all sides, will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\rho K} \\over P}$$",
      "$${{PK} \\over \\rho }$$",
      "$${{\\rho P} \\over K}$$",
      "$${K \\over {\\rho P}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$${{\\rho P} \\over K}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "tNRj6vkhfycBqnaLWg1klulog2u",
    "question": "The length of metallic wire is l<sub>1</sub> when tension in it is T<sub>1</sub>. It is l<sub>2</sub> when the tension is T<sub>2</sub>. The original length of the wire will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{T_1}{l_1} - {T_2}{l_2}} \\over {{T_2} - {T_1}}}$$",
      "$${{{l_1} + {l_2}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{{T_2}{l_1} + {T_1}{l_2}} \\over {{T_1} + {T_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{T_2}{l_1} - {T_1}{l_2}} \\over {{T_2} - {T_1}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$${{{T_2}{l_1} - {T_1}{l_2}} \\over {{T_2} - {T_1}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krpoemx3",
    "question": "The value of tension in a long thin metal wire has been changed from T<sub>1</sub> to T<sub>2</sub>. The lengths of the metal wire at two different values of tension T<sub>1</sub> and T<sub>2</sub> are l<sub>1</sub> and l<sub>2</sub> respectively. The actual length of the metal wire is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{l_1} + {l_2}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{T_1}{T_2}{l_1}{l_2}} $$",
      "$${{{T_1}{l_2} - {T_2}{l_1}} \\over {{T_1} - {T_2}}}$$",
      "$${{{T_1}{l_1} - {T_2}{l_2}} \\over {{T_1} - {T_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$${{{T_1}{l_2} - {T_2}{l_1}} \\over {{T_1} - {T_2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqb43b2",
    "question": "The length of a metal wire is l<sub>1</sub>, when the tension in it is T<sub>1</sub> and is l<sub>2</sub> when the tension is T<sub>2</sub>. The natural length of the wire is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{l_1}{l_2}} $$",
      "$${{{l_1}{T_2} - {l_2}{T_1}} \\over {{T_2} - {T_1}}}$$",
      "$${{{l_1}{T_2} + {l_2}{T_1}} \\over {{T_2} + {T_1}}}$$",
      "$${{{l_1} + {l_2}} \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$${{{l_1}{T_2} - {l_2}{T_1}} \\over {{T_2} - {T_1}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krukd8y4",
    "question": "Two wires of same length and radius are joined end to end and loaded. The Young's modulii of the materials of the two wires are Y<sub>1</sub> and Y<sub>2</sub>. The combination behaves as a single wire then its Young's modulus is :",
    "options": [
      "$$Y = {{2{Y_1}{Y_2}} \\over {3({Y_1} + {Y_2})}}$$",
      "$$Y = {{2{Y_1}{Y_2}} \\over {{Y_1} + {Y_2}}}$$",
      "$$Y = {{{Y_1}{Y_2}} \\over {2({Y_1} + {Y_2})}}$$",
      "$$Y = {{{Y_1}{Y_2}} \\over {{Y_1} + {Y_2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$Y = {{2{Y_1}{Y_2}} \\over {{Y_1} + {Y_2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth46c6p",
    "question": "A uniform heavy rod of weight 10 kg ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>, cross-sectional area 100 cm<sup>2</sup> and length 20 cm is hanging from a fixed support. Young modulus of the material of the rod is 2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>11</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>. Neglecting the lateral contraction, find the elongation of rod due to its own weight.",
    "options": [
      "2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$9</sup> m",
      "5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> m",
      "4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup> m",
      "5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$10</sup> m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$10</sup> m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjmub5w",
    "question": "Four identical hollow cylindrical columns of mild steel support a big structure of mass 50 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> kg. The inner and outer radii of each column are 50 cm and 100 cm respectively. Assuming uniform local distribution, calculate the compression strain of each column. [Use Y = 2.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>11</sup> Pa, g = 9.8 m/s<sup>2</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "3.60 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$8</sup>",
      "2.60 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup>",
      "1.87 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup>",
      "7.07 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "2.60 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5471gh6",
    "question": "<p>A wire of length L is hanging from a fixed support. The length changes to L<sub>1</sub> and L<sub>2</sub> when masses 1 kg and 2 kg are suspended respectively from its free end. Then the value of L is equal to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{L_1}{L_2}} $$",
      "$${{{L_1} + {L_2}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$$2{L_1} - {L_2}$$",
      "$$3{L_1} - 2{L_2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$2{L_1} - {L_2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbwgkf",
    "question": "<p>Potential energy as a function of r is given by $$U = {A \\over {{r^{10}}}} - {B \\over {{r^5}}}$$, where r is the interatomic distance, A and B are positive constants. The equilibrium distance between the two atoms will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left( {{A \\over B}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 5}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{B \\over A}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 5}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{2A \\over B}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 5}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{B \\over 2A}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 5}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$${\\left( {{2A \\over B}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 5}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c2lxov",
    "question": "<p>The bulk modulus of a liquid is 3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>. The pressure required to reduce the volume of liquid by 2% is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "12 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "6 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i1u0sy",
    "question": "<p>The area of cross section of the rope used to lift a load by a crane is $$2.5 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~m}^{2}$$. The maximum lifting capacity of the crane is 10 metric tons. To increase the lifting capacity of the crane to 25 metric tons, the required area of cross section of the rope should be :</p>\n<p>(take $$g=10 \\,m s^{-2}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$6.25\\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~m}^{2}$$",
      "$$10\\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~m}^{2}$$",
      "$$1\\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~m}^{2}$$",
      "$$1.67\\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~m}^{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$6.25\\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~m}^{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6kmts29",
    "question": "<p>A steel wire of length $$3.2 \\mathrm{~m}\\left(\\mathrm{Y}_{\\mathrm{s}}=2.0 \\times 10^{11} \\,\\mathrm{Nm}^{-2}\\right)$$ and a copper wire of length $$4.4 \\mathrm{~m}\\left(\\mathrm{Y}_{\\mathrm{c}}=1.1 \\times 10^{11} \\,\\mathrm{Nm}^{-2}\\right)$$, both of radius $$1.4 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ are connected end to end. When stretched by a load, the net elongation is found to be $$1.4 \\mathrm{~mm}$$. The load applied, in Newton, will be: $$\\quad\\left(\\right.$$ Given $$\\pi=\\frac{22}{7}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "360",
      "180",
      "1080",
      "154"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "154"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6m9vr2u",
    "question": "<p>The force required to stretch a wire of cross-section $$1 \\mathrm{~cm}^{2}$$ to double its length will be : (Given Yong's modulus of the wire $$=2 \\times 10^{11} \\mathrm{~N} / \\mathrm{m}^{2}$$)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1 \\times 10^{7} \\mathrm{~N}$$",
      "$$1.5 \\times 10^{7} \\mathrm{~N}$$",
      "$$2 \\times 10^{7} \\mathrm{~N}$$",
      "$$2.5 \\times 10^{7} \\mathrm{~N}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$2 \\times 10^{7} \\mathrm{~N}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p4eiz0",
    "question": "<p>If the length of a wire is made double and radius is halved of its respective values. Then, the Young's modulus of the material of the wire will :</p>",
    "options": [
      "remain same",
      "become 8 times its initial value",
      "become $$\\frac{1}{4}$$ of its initial value",
      "become 4 times its initial value"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "remain same"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnwwl5p",
    "question": "<p>The Young's modulus of a steel wire of length $$6 \\mathrm{~m}$$ and cross-sectional area $$3 \\mathrm{~mm}^{2}$$, is $$2 \\times 10^{11}~\\mathrm{N} / \\mathrm{m}^{2}$$. The wire is suspended from its support on a given planet. A block of mass $$4 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is attached to the free end of the wire. The acceleration due to gravity on the planet is $$\\frac{1}{4}$$ of its value on the earth. The elongation of wire is (Take $$g$$ on the earth $$=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$) :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.1 cm",
      "1 cm",
      "0.1 mm",
      "1 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "0.1 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo64ik0",
    "question": "For a solid rod, the Young's modulus of elasticity is $3.2 \\times 10^{11} \\mathrm{Nm}^{-2}$ and density is $8 \\times 10^3 \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m}^{-3}$. The velocity of longitudinal wave in the rod will be.",
    "options": [
      "$3.65 \\times 10^3 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$",
      "$6.32 \\times 10^3 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$",
      "$18.96 \\times 10^3 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$",
      "$145.75 \\times 10^3 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$6.32 \\times 10^3 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo76lhf",
    "question": "Under the same load, wire A having length $5.0 \\mathrm{~m}$ and cross section $2.5 \\times 10^{-5} \\mathrm{~m}^{2}$ stretches\n\nuniformly by the same amount as another wire B of length $6.0 \\mathrm{~m}$ and a cross section of $3.0 \\times 10^{-5}$\n\n$\\mathrm{m}^{2}$ stretches. The ratio of the Young's modulus of wire A to that of wire $B$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "$1: 2$",
      "$1: 4$",
      "$1: 1$",
      "$1: 10$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$1: 1$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldquvoem",
    "question": "A force is applied to a steel wire 'A', rigidly clamped at one end. As a result elongation in the wire is $0.2 \\mathrm{~mm}$. If same force is applied to another steel wire ' $\\mathrm{B}$ ' of double the length and a diameter $2.4$ times that of the wire ' $\\mathrm{A}$ ', the elongation in the wire ' $\\mathrm{B}$ ' will be (wires having uniform circular cross sections)",
    "options": [
      "$6 .9 \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{~mm}$",
      "$6.06 \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{~mm}$",
      "$2.77 \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{~mm}$",
      "$3.0 \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{~mm}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$6 .9 \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{~mm}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr0y4nb",
    "question": "<p>Choose the correct relationship between Poisson ratio $$(\\sigma)$$, bulk modulus (K) and modulus of rigidity $$(\\eta)$$ of a given solid object :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sigma=\\frac{3 K+2 \\eta}{6 K+2 \\eta}$$",
      "$$\\sigma=\\frac{3 K-2 \\eta}{6 K+2 \\eta}$$",
      "$$\\sigma=\\frac{6 K+2 \\eta}{3 K-2 \\eta}$$",
      "$$\\sigma=\\frac{6 K-2 \\eta}{3 K-2 \\eta}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$\\sigma=\\frac{3 K-2 \\eta}{6 K+2 \\eta}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwrer3c",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R</p>\n<p>Assertion A : Steel is used in the construction of buildings and bridges.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Steel is more elastic and its elastic limit is high.</p>\n<p>In the light of above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is not correct but R is correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyd0l6c",
    "question": "<p>A 100 m long wire having cross-sectional area $$\\mathrm{6.25\\times10^{-4}~m^2}$$ and Young's modulus is $$\\mathrm{10^{10}~Nm^{-2}}$$ is subjected to a load of 250 N, then the elongation in the wire will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{6.25\\times10^{-6}~m}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{4\\times10^{-3}~m}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{4\\times10^{-4}~m}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{6.25\\times10^{-3}~m}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{4\\times10^{-3}~m}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnx23k6",
    "question": "A wire of length ' $L$ ' and radius ' $r$ ' is clamped rigidly at one end. When the other end of the wire is pulled by a force $f$, its length increases by ' $l$ '. Another wire of same material of length ' $2 \\mathrm{~L}$ ' and radius ' $2 r$ ' is pulled by a force ' $2 f$ '. Then the increase in its length will be :",
    "options": [
      "$2 l$",
      "$4 l$",
      "$l$",
      "$l / 2$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "$l$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq2fq2p",
    "question": "<p>Under isothermal condition, the pressure of a gas is given by $$\\mathrm{P}=a \\mathrm{~V}^{-3}$$, where $$a$$ is a constant and $$\\mathrm{V}$$ is the volume of the gas. The bulk modulus at constant temperature is equal to</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{P}{2}$$",
      "2 P",
      "3 P",
      "P"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "3 P"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvruaf1",
    "question": "<p>Young's moduli of the material of wires A and B are in the ratio of $$1: 4$$, while its area of cross sections are in the ratio of $$1: 3$$. If the same amount of load is applied to both the wires, the amount of elongation produced in the wires $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$ will be in the ratio of</p>\n<p>[Assume length of wires A and B are same]</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 12",
      "1 : 36",
      "12 : 1",
      "36 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "12 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh028g0a",
    "question": "<p>An aluminium rod with Young's modulus $$Y=7.0 \\times 10^{10} \\mathrm{~N} / \\mathrm{m}^{2}$$ undergoes elastic strain of $$0.04 \\%$$. The energy per unit volume stored in the rod in SI unit is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "5600",
      "2800",
      "11200",
      "8400"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "5600"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsblcutl",
    "question": "With rise in temperature, the Young's modulus of elasticity :",
    "options": [
      "changes erratically",
      "increases",
      "decreases",
      "remains unchanged"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "decreases"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscp7t6k",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : The property of body, by virtue of which it tends to regain its original shape when the external force is removed, is Elasticity.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : The restoring force depends upon the bonded inter atomic and inter molecular force of solid.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A) is false but (R) is true\n",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)\n",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)\n",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsflradt",
    "question": "<p>A wire of length $$L$$ and radius $$r$$ is clamped at one end. If its other end is pulled by a force $$F$$, its length increases by $$l$$. If the radius of the wire and the applied force both are reduced to half of their original values keeping original length constant, the increase in length will become:</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 times",
      "4 times",
      "3 times",
      "$$\\frac{3}{2}$$ times"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "2 times"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgx5dwc",
    "question": "<p>Young's modules of material of a wire of length '$$L$$' and cross-sectional area $$A$$ is $$Y$$. If the length of the wire is doubled and cross-sectional area is halved then Young's modules will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 Y",
      "2 Y",
      "$$\\mathrm{\\frac{Y}{4}}$$",
      "Y"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "Y"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gsk3x",
    "question": "<p>Young's modulus is determined by the equation given by $$\\mathrm{Y}=49000 \\frac{\\mathrm{m}}{\\mathrm{l}} \\frac{\\mathrm{dyne}}{\\mathrm{cm}^2}$$ where $$M$$ is the mass and $$l$$ is the extension of wire used in the experiment. Now error in Young modules $$(Y)$$ is estimated by taking data from $$M-l$$ plot in graph paper. The smallest scale divisions are $$5 \\mathrm{~g}$$ and $$0.02 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ along load axis and extension axis respectively. If the value of $M$ and $l$ are $$500 \\mathrm{~g}$$ and $$2 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ respectively then percentage error of $$Y$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2%",
      "0.02%",
      "0.5%",
      "0.2%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "2%"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s212a",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 703px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 252px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I<br/></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II<br/></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A force that restores an elastic body of unit area to its original state</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Bulk modulus</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Two equal and opposite forces parallel to opposite faces</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Young's modulus</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Forces perpendicular everywhere to the surface per unit area same everywhere</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Stress</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Two equal and opposite forces perpendicular to opposite faces Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Shear modulus</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(II), (C)-(III), (D)-(I)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)\n",
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(III)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(I), (C)-(II), (D)-(IV)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "mechanical-properties-of-solids",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "w7r7nIfnfp8jOQI2",
    "question": "According to Newton's law of cooling, the rate of cooling of a body is proportional to $${\\left( {\\Delta \\theta } \\right)^n},$$  where $${\\Delta \\theta }$$ is the difference of the temperature of the body and the surrounding, and $$n$$ is equal to :",
    "options": [
      "two ",
      "three ",
      "four ",
      "one "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "newton's-law-of-cooling",
    "solution": "one "
  },
  {
    "id": "upiqi3NbJ5zDvUnNC00u8",
    "question": "A body takes 10 minutes to cool from 60<sup>o</sup>C to 50<sup>o</sup>C. The tempertature of surroundings is constant at 25<sup>o</sup>C. Then, the temperature of the body after next 10 minutes will be approximately : ",
    "options": [
      "47<sup>o</sup>C",
      "41<sup>o</sup>C",
      "45<sup>o</sup>C",
      "43<sup>o</sup>C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "newton's-law-of-cooling",
    "solution": "43<sup>o</sup>C"
  },
  {
    "id": "MAgu0hk6JnFC0J1nI6jgy2xukf3uh1th",
    "question": "A metallic sphere cools from 50<sup>o</sup>C to 40<sup>o</sup> in 300 s. If atmospheric temperature around is 20<sup>o</sup>C,\nthen the sphere’s temperature after the next 5 minutes will be close to :\n",
    "options": [
      "35<sup>o</sup>C",
      "31<sup>o</sup>C",
      "33<sup>o</sup>C",
      "28<sup>o</sup>C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "newton's-law-of-cooling",
    "solution": "33<sup>o</sup>C"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kryxujac",
    "question": "A body takes 4 min. to cool from 61$$^\\circ$$ C to 59$$^\\circ$$ C. If the temperature of the surroundings is 30$$^\\circ$$ C, the time taken by the body to cool from 51$$^\\circ$$ C to 49$$^\\circ$$ C is :",
    "options": [
      "4 min.",
      "3 min.",
      "8 min.",
      "6 min."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "newton's-law-of-cooling",
    "solution": "6 min."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduhzscr",
    "question": "<p>A bowl filled with very hot soup cools from 98$$^\\circ$$C to 86$$^\\circ$$C in 2 minutes when the room temperature is 22$$^\\circ$$C. How long it will take to cool from 75$$^\\circ$$C to 69$$^\\circ$$C?</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 minutes",
      "0.5 minute",
      "1.4 minutes",
      "1 minute"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "newton's-law-of-cooling",
    "solution": "1.4 minutes"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrhpyqf",
    "question": "<p>A body cools from $$80^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ to $$60^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ in 5 minutes. The temperature of the surrounding is $$20^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. The time it takes to cool from $$60^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ to $$40^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "500 s",
      "$$\\frac{25}{3} \\mathrm{~S}$$",
      "450 s",
      "420 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "newton's-law-of-cooling",
    "solution": "500 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "CZSy5f20vTaNvEZY",
    "question": "A uniform cylinder of length $$L$$ and mass $$M$$ having cross-sectional area $$A$$ is suspended, with its length vertical, from a fixed point by a mass-less spring such that it is half submerged in a liquid of density $$\\sigma $$ at equilibrium position. The extension $${x_0}$$ of the spring when it is in equilibrium is: ",
    "options": [
      "$${{Mg} \\over k}$$ ",
      "$${{Mg} \\over k}\\left( {1 - {{LA\\sigma } \\over M}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${{Mg} \\over k}\\left( {1 - {{LA\\sigma } \\over {2M}}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${{Mg} \\over k}\\left( {1 + {{LA\\sigma } \\over M}} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "$${{Mg} \\over k}\\left( {1 - {{LA\\sigma } \\over {2M}}} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "SYDzQFOHq2tXWOE9",
    "question": "An open glass tube is immersed in mercury in such a way that a length of $$8$$ $$cm$$ extends above the mercury level. The open end of the tube is then closed and scaled and the tube is raised vertically up by additional $$46$$ $$cm$$. What will be length of the air column above mercury in the tube now? (Atmospheric pressure $$=76$$ $$cm$$ of $$Hg$$)",
    "options": [
      "$$16$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$22$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$38$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$6$$ $$cm$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "$$16$$ $$cm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "e0y6LNdqEoe1snKqV7SEa",
    "question": "A thin uniform tube is bent into a circle of radius $$r$$ in the vertical plane. Equal volumes of two immiscible liquids, whose densities are $${\\rho _1}$$ and $${\\rho _2}$$ $$\\left( {{\\rho _1} &gt; {\\rho _2}} \\right),$$ fill half the circle. The angle $$\\theta $$ between the radius vector passing through the common interface and the vertical is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\theta  = {\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\pi \\left( {{{{\\rho _1}} \\over {{\\rho _2}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\theta  = {\\tan ^{ - 1}}{\\pi  \\over 2}\\left( {{{{\\rho _1}} \\over {{\\rho _2}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\theta  = {\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{{\\rho _1} - {\\rho _2}} \\over {{\\rho _1} + {\\rho _2}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\theta  = {\\tan ^{ - 1}}{\\pi  \\over 2}\\left( {{{{\\rho _1} + {\\rho _2}} \\over {{\\rho _1} - {\\rho _2}}}} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "$$\\theta  = {\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{{\\rho _1} - {\\rho _2}} \\over {{\\rho _1} + {\\rho _2}}}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "5uTPayYBrNWKq8LoJTfsO",
    "question": "When an air bubble of radius r rises from the bottom to the surface of a lake its radius becomes $${{5r} \\over 4}.$$ Taking the atmospheric pressure to be equal to 10 m height of water column, the depth of the lake would approximately be (ignore the surface tension and the effect of temperature) :",
    "options": [
      "11.2 m",
      "8.7 m",
      "9.5 m",
      "10.5 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "9.5 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "41V8MqKuvjHMKW4MdOPFy",
    "question": "A long cylindrical vessel is half filled with a liquid. When the vessel is rotated about its own vertical axis, the liquid rises up near the wall. If the radius of vessel is 5 cm and its rotational speed is 2 rotations per second, then the difference in the heights between the centre and the sides, in cm, will be : ",
    "options": [
      "2.0 ",
      "1.2",
      "0.1",
      "0.4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "2.0 "
  },
  {
    "id": "xsVgjVvBsUzi3gIJvQ3rsa0w2w9jx7hxz6e",
    "question": "The number density of molecules of a gas depends on their distance r from the origin as, $$n\\left( r \\right) = {n_0}{e^{ - \\alpha {r^4}}}$$.\nThen the total number of molecules is proportional to :",
    "options": [
      "$${n_0}{\\alpha ^{ - 3/4}}$$",
      "$${n_0}{\\alpha ^{ - 3}}$$",
      "$${n_0}{\\alpha ^{1/4}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{n_0}} {\\alpha ^{1/2}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "$${n_0}{\\alpha ^{ - 3/4}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "qAMP5Xl7FDpqMigDdw3rsa0w2w9jwzm5p8w",
    "question": "A cubical block of side 0.5 m floats on water with 30% of its volume under water. What is the maximum\nweight that can be put on the block without fully submerging it under water? [Take, density of water = 10<sup>3</sup>\nkg/m<sup>3</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "30.1 kg",
      "87.5 kg",
      "65.4 kg",
      "46.3 kg"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "87.5 kg"
  },
  {
    "id": "BLERHm2bQTRneJf51y3rsa0w2w9jwziirp5",
    "question": "A submarine experiences a pressure of 5.05 × 10<sup>6</sup>\n Pa at a depth of d<sub>1</sub> in a sea. When it goes further to a depth\nof d<sub>2</sub>, it experiences a pressure of 8.08 × 10<sup>6</sup>\n Pa. Then d<sub>2</sub> –d<sub>1</sub> is approximately (density of water = 10<sup>3</sup>\n kg/m<sup>3</sup>\nand acceleration due to gravity = 10 ms<sup>–2</sup>\n) :",
    "options": [
      "600 m",
      "400 m",
      "300 m",
      "500 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "300 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "KMjeyUxDxZZQMay33DVU1",
    "question": "A wooden block floating in a bucket of water\nhas 4/5 of its volume submerged. When certain\namount of an oil is poured into the bucket, it\nis found that the block is just under the oil\nsurface with half of its volume under water and\nhalf in oil. The density of oil relative to that of\nwater is :-",
    "options": [
      "0.8",
      "0.7",
      "0.6",
      "0.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "0.6"
  },
  {
    "id": "MSQZ5Ki0MybDlwwK8bgrV",
    "question": "A simple pendulum oscillating in air has period\nT. The bob of the pendulum is completely\nimmersed in a non-viscous liquid. The density\nof the liquid is\n1/16 th of the material of the bob.\nIf the bob is inside liquid all the time, its period\nof oscillation in this liquid is :",
    "options": [
      "$$2T\\sqrt {{1 \\over {10}}} $$",
      "$$4T\\sqrt {{1 \\over {14}}} $$",
      "$$4T\\sqrt {{1 \\over {15}}} $$",
      "$$2T\\sqrt {{1 \\over {14}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "$$4T\\sqrt {{1 \\over {15}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "oUZOjCPR8sYeAJ8zSh5mM",
    "question": "A liquid of density $$\\rho $$ is coming out of a hose pipe of radius a with horizontal speed $$\\upsilon $$ and hits a mesh. 50% of\nthe liquid passes through the mesh unaffected. 25% looses all of its momentum and 25% comes back with the same speed. The resultant pressure on the mesh will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 4}\\rho {v^2}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}\\rho {v^2}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}\\rho {v^2}$$",
      "$$\\rho {v^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 4}\\rho {v^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "PVvrWFVoYt1GSjaJx9jgy2xukff4ggcd",
    "question": "A hollow spherical shell at outer radius R floats\njust submerged under the water surface. The\ninner radius of the shell is r. If the specific\ngravity of the shell material is $${{27} \\over 8}$$ w.r.t water,\nthe value of r is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2} \\over 3}$$R",
      "$${{4} \\over 9}$$R",
      "$${{1} \\over 3}$$R",
      "$${{8} \\over 9}$$R"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "$${{8} \\over 9}$$R"
  },
  {
    "id": "D6cuCx03Gk4g2jMh80jgy2xukf6hhz70",
    "question": "A air bubble of radius 1 cm in water has an upward acceleration 9.8 cm s<sup>–2</sup>. The density of water is\n1 gm cm<sup>–3</sup> and water offers negligible drag force on the bubble. The mass of the bubble is (g = 980\ncm/s<sup>2</sup>).",
    "options": [
      "1.52 gm",
      "4.51 gm",
      "3.15 gm",
      "4.15 gm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "4.15 gm"
  },
  {
    "id": "6X6JjUH6s2v9TFYYiS7k9k2k5gxu6av",
    "question": "A leak proof cylinder of length 1m, made of\na metal which has very low coefficient of\nexpansion is floating vertically in water at 0°C\nsuch that its height above the water surface is\n20 cm. When the temperature of water is\nincreased to 4°C, the height of the cylinder\nabove the water surface becomes 21 cm. The\ndensity of water at T = 4°C, relative to the\ndensity at T = 0°C is close to :",
    "options": [
      "1.04",
      "1.26",
      "1.01",
      "1.03"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "1.01"
  },
  {
    "id": "5qA8VP0uw25yF897537k9k2k5guwz42",
    "question": "Consider a solid sphere of radius R and mass\ndensity<br/> $$\\rho \\left( r \\right) = {\\rho _0}\\left( {1 - {{{r^2}} \\over {{R^2}}}} \\right)$$ , $$0 &lt; r \\le R$$<br/> The\nminimum density of a liquid in which it will\nfloat is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2{\\rho _0}} \\over 3}$$",
      "$${{2{\\rho _0}} \\over 5}$$",
      "$${{{\\rho _0}} \\over 5}$$",
      "$${{{\\rho _0}} \\over 3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "$${{2{\\rho _0}} \\over 5}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "tZ4xOxTSc85rJR1oGM1kmhna31e",
    "question": "The pressure acting on a submarine is 3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> Pa at a certain depth. If the depth is doubled, the percentage increase in the pressure acting on the submarine would be : <br/><br/>(Assume that atmospheric pressure is 1 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> Pa density of water is 10<sup>3</sup> kg m<sup>$$-$$3</sup>, g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "$${{200} \\over 5}$$%",
      "$${{200} \\over 3}$$%",
      "$${{3} \\over 200}$$%",
      "$${{5} \\over 200}$$%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "$${{200} \\over 3}$$%"
  },
  {
    "id": "5vK8rlj4pgurq9vk4Y1kmkbvztj",
    "question": "An object is located at 2 km beneath the surface of the water. If the fractional compression $${{\\Delta V} \\over V}$$ is 1.36%, the ratio of hydraulic stress to the corresponding hydraulic strain will be ____________. [Given : density of water is 1000 kgm<sup>$$-$$3</sup> and g = 9.8 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "1.44 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "1.44 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "1.96 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>7</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "2.26 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "1.44 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>9</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f4dsu7",
    "question": "<p>A drop of liquid of density $$\\rho$$ is floating half immersed in a liquid of density $${\\sigma}$$ and surface tension $$7.5 \\times 10^{-4}$$ Ncm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. The radius of drop in $$\\mathrm{cm}$$ will be :</p>\n<p>(g = 10 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\n\\frac{15}{\\sqrt{(2 \\rho-\\sigma)}}\n$$",
      "$$\\frac{15}{\\sqrt{(\\rho-\\sigma)}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3}{2 \\sqrt{(\\rho-\\sigma)}}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3}{20 \\sqrt{(2 \\rho-\\sigma)}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "$$\n\\frac{15}{\\sqrt{(2 \\rho-\\sigma)}}\n$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jh308s",
    "question": "<p>Two cylindrical vessels of equal cross-sectional area $$16 \\mathrm{~cm}^{2}$$ contain water upto heights $$100 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ and $$150 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ respectively. The vessels are interconnected so that the water levels in them become equal. The work done by the force of gravity during the process, is [Take, density of water $$=10^{3} \\mathrm{~kg} / \\mathrm{m}^{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{g}=10 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$ ] :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.25 J",
      "1 J",
      "8 J",
      "12 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "1 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nq1ikm",
    "question": "<p>A pressure-pump has a horizontal tube of cross sectional area $$10 \\mathrm{~cm}^{2}$$ for the outflow of water at a speed of $$20 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. The force exerted on the vertical wall just in front of the tube which stops water horizontally flowing out of the tube, is :</p>\n<p>[given: density of water $$=1000 \\mathrm{~kg} / \\mathrm{m}^{3}$$]</p>",
    "options": [
      "300 N",
      "500 N",
      "250 N",
      "400 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "400 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldspkn0n",
    "question": "<p>A bicycle tyre is filled with air having pressure of $$270 ~\\mathrm{kPa}$$ at $$27^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. The approximate pressure of the air in the tyre when the temperature increases to $$36^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "262 kPa",
      "360 kPa",
      "270 kPa",
      "278 kPa"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "278 kPa"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgxwszgi",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : Pressure in a reservoir of water is same at all points at the same level of water.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The pressure applied to enclosed water is transmitted in all directions equally.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh2zv88f",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A: When you squeeze one end of a tube to get toothpaste out from the other end, Pascal's principle is observed.</p>\n<p>Reason R: A change in the pressure applied to an enclosed incompressible fluid is transmitted undiminished to every portion of the fluid and to the walls of its container.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A",
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "Both A and B are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "Both A and B are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "luy9cm0f",
    "question": "<p>A sphere of relative density $$\\sigma$$ and diameter $$D$$ has concentric cavity of diameter $$d$$. The ratio of $$\\frac{D}{d}$$, if it just floats on water in a tank is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left(\\frac{\\sigma-2}{\\sigma+2}\\right)^{1 / 3}$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{\\sigma+1}{\\sigma-1}\\right)^{1 / 3}$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{\\sigma-1}{\\sigma}\\right)^{1 / 3}$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{\\sigma}{\\sigma-1}\\right)^{1 / 3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "pressure,-density,-pascal's-law-and-archimede's-principle",
    "solution": "$$\\left(\\frac{\\sigma}{\\sigma-1}\\right)^{1 / 3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "S6j9UNcdkfJJNxbl",
    "question": "If $$S$$ is stress and $$Y$$ is young's modulus of material of a wire, the energy stored in the wire per unit volume is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{S^2}} \\over {2Y}}$$ ",
      "$$2{S^2}Y$$ ",
      "$${S \\over {2Y}}$$ ",
      "$${{2Y} \\over {{S^2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "stress-strain-curve,-thermal-stress-and-elastic-pe",
    "solution": "$${{{S^2}} \\over {2Y}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "kCA7h1B83EeX5iDX",
    "question": "The pressure that has to be applied to the ends of a steel wire of length $$10$$ $$cm$$ to keep its length constant when its temperature is raised by $${100^ \\circ }C$$ is: \n(For steel Young's modulus is $$2 \\times {10^{11}}\\,\\,N{m^{ - 2}}$$ and coefficient of thermal expansion is $$1.1 \\times {10^{ - 5}}\\,{K^{ - 1}}$$ )",
    "options": [
      "$$2.2 \\times {10^8}\\,\\,Pa$$",
      "$$2.2 \\times {10^9}\\,\\,Pa$$",
      "$$2.2 \\times {10^7}\\,\\,Pa$$",
      "$$2.2 \\times {10^6}\\,\\,Pa$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "stress-strain-curve,-thermal-stress-and-elastic-pe",
    "solution": "$$2.2 \\times {10^8}\\,\\,Pa$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "IgaETLABE4gqyEzTmMyzl",
    "question": "A boy's catapult is made of rubber cord which\nis 42 cm long, with 6 mm diameter of\ncross-section and of negligible mass. The boy\nkeeps a stone weighing 0.02kg on it and\nstretches the cord by 20 cm by applying a\nconstant force. When released, the stone flies\noff with a velocity of 20 ms<sup>–1</sup>. Neglect the\nchange in the area of cross-section of the cord\nwhile stretched. The Young's modulus of\nrubber is closest to:",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>4</sup> Nm<sup>–2</sup>",
      "10<sup>6</sup> Nm<sup>–2</sup>",
      "10<sup>8</sup> Nm<sup>–2</sup>",
      "10<sup>3</sup> Nm<sup>–2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "stress-strain-curve,-thermal-stress-and-elastic-pe",
    "solution": "10<sup>6</sup> Nm<sup>–2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "l0FYcefgpmcQI4b0Bn3rsa0w2w9jwzmniit",
    "question": "The elastic limit of brass is 379 MPa. What should be the minimum diameter of a brass rod if it is to support\na 400 N load without exceeding its elastic limit?",
    "options": [
      "1.16 mm",
      "1.36 mm",
      "1.00 mm",
      "0.90 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "stress-strain-curve,-thermal-stress-and-elastic-pe",
    "solution": "1.16 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "mUVu0LQl0pp0OSnnBE7k9k2k5lcepvz",
    "question": "Two steel wires having same length are\nsuspended from a ceiling under the same load.\nIf the ratio of their energy stored per unit\nvolume is 1 : 4, the ratio of their diameters is:",
    "options": [
      "1 : 2",
      "2 : 1",
      "$$1:\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 :1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "stress-strain-curve,-thermal-stress-and-elastic-pe",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt 2 :1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "KmsyQpLUo41ombZ4",
    "question": "If two soap bubbles of different radii are connected by a tube",
    "options": [
      "air flows from the smaller bubble to the bigger ",
      "air flows from bigger bubble to the smaller bubble till the sizes are interchanged ",
      "air flows from the bigger bubble to the smaller bubble till the sizes become equal",
      "there is no flow of air. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "air flows from the smaller bubble to the bigger "
  },
  {
    "id": "RochDBwLIGJ7tkF5",
    "question": "A $$20$$ $$cm$$ long capillary tube is dipped in water. The water rises up to $$8$$ $$cm.$$ If the entire arrangement is put in a freely falling elevator the length of water column in the capillary tube will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$10$$ $$cm$$",
      "$$8$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$20$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$4$$ $$cm$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$20$$ $$cm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "aEVEi303RlWoi8YE",
    "question": "Work done in increasing the size of a soap bubble from a radius of $$3$$ $$cm$$ to $$5$$ $$cm$$ is nearly (Surface tension of soap solution $$ = 0.03N{m^{ - 1}},$$ ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.2\\pi mJ$$ ",
      "$$2\\pi mJ$$",
      "$$0.4\\pi mJ$$",
      "$$4\\pi mJ$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$0.4\\pi mJ$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "h2ksQg8poRTZ5YzJ2h8du",
    "question": "A small soap bubble of radius 4 cm is trapped inside another bubble of radius 6 cm without any contact. Let P<sub>2</sub> be the pressure inside the inner bubble and P<sub>0</sub>, the pressure outside the outer bubble. Radius of another bubble with pressure difference P<sub>2</sub> $$-$$ P<sub>0</sub> between its inside and outside would be :",
    "options": [
      "12 cm",
      "2.4 cm",
      "6 cm",
      "4.8 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "2.4 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "cUGhY12csjJJqT3L5I6fk",
    "question": "If 'M' is the mass of water that rises in a capillary\ntube of radius 'r', then mass of water which will\nrise in a capillary tube of radius '2r' is :",
    "options": [
      "M",
      "4M",
      "M/2",
      "2M"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "2M"
  },
  {
    "id": "RKRHNK8a2zSJnr3btU18hoxe66ijvztv1aj",
    "question": "The ratio of surface tensions of mercury and\nwater is given to be 7.5 while the ratio of thier\ndensities is 13.6. Their contact angles, with\nglass, are close to 135° and 0°, respectively. It\nis observed that mercury gets depressed by an\namount h in a capillary tube of radius r<sub>1</sub>, while\nwater rises by the same amount h in a capillary\ntube of radius r<sub>2</sub>. The ratio, (r<sub>1</sub>/r<sub>2</sub>), is then close\nto :",
    "options": [
      "2/5",
      "2/3",
      "3/5",
      "4/5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "2/5"
  },
  {
    "id": "ay8zb98JpEnVWbL9Jr7k9k2k5l21i38",
    "question": "A small spherical droplet of density d is floating\nexactly half immersed in a liquid of density $$\\rho $$\nand surface tension T. The radius of the droplet\nis (take note that the surface tension applies an\nupward force on the droplet) :",
    "options": [
      "$$r = \\sqrt {{T \\over {\\left( {d - \\rho } \\right)g}}} $$",
      "$$r = \\sqrt {{{2T} \\over {3\\left( {d + \\rho } \\right)g}}} $$",
      "$$r = \\sqrt {{T \\over {\\left( {d + \\rho } \\right)g}}} $$",
      "$$r = \\sqrt {{{3T} \\over {\\left( {2d - \\rho } \\right)g}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$r = \\sqrt {{{3T} \\over {\\left( {2d - \\rho } \\right)g}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "XVXC9Lo2BAsuewvfurjgy2xukexyd31v",
    "question": "A capillary tube made of glass of radius 0.15\nmm is dipped vertically in a beaker filled with\nmethylene iodide (surface tension = 0.05 Nm<sup>–1</sup>,\ndensity = 667 kg m<sup>–3</sup>) which rises to height h in\nthe tube. It is observed that the two tangents\ndrawn from liquid-glass interfaces (from opp.\nsides of the capillary) make an angle of 60<sup>o</sup>\nwith one another. Then h is close to (g = 10 ms<sup>–2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "0.049 m",
      "0.087 m",
      "0.137 m",
      "0.172 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "0.087 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "WCbuQ6qzqUleoGJsCRjgy2xukf16b0fg",
    "question": "Pressure inside two soap bubbles are 1.01 and 1.02 atmosphere, respectively. The ratio of their\nvolumes is :",
    "options": [
      "4 : 1",
      "8 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "0.8 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "8 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "JzEmdvixnuKKnFjwmV1klthg4fm",
    "question": "A large number of water drops, each of radius r, combine to have a drop of radius R. If the surface tension is T and mechanical equivalent of heat is J, the rise in heat energy per unit volume will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2T} \\over J}\\left( {{1 \\over r} - {1 \\over R}} \\right)$$",
      "$${{3T} \\over J}\\left( {{1 \\over r} - {1 \\over R}} \\right)$$",
      "$${{3T} \\over rJ}$$",
      "$${{2T} \\over rJ}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$${{3T} \\over J}\\left( {{1 \\over r} - {1 \\over R}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "9PMEpoC49IEQPypIur1kmj1q3c8",
    "question": "When two soap bubbles of radii a and b (b &gt; a) coalesce, the radius of curvature of common surface is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{b - a} \\over {ab}}$$",
      "$${{a + b} \\over {ab}}$$",
      "$${{ab} \\over {a + b}}$$",
      "$${{ab} \\over {b - a}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$${{ab} \\over {b - a}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqdlzso",
    "question": "Two small drops of mercury each of radius R coalesce to form a single large drop. The ratio of total surface energy before and after the change is :",
    "options": [
      "$${2^{{1 \\over 3}}}:1$$",
      "$$1:{2^{{1 \\over 3}}}$$",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$${2^{{1 \\over 3}}}:1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw9i5jn",
    "question": "Two spherical soap bubbles of radii r<sub>1</sub> and r<sub>2</sub> in vacuum combine under isothermal conditions. The resulting bubble has a radius equal to :",
    "options": [
      "$${{{r_1}{r_2}} \\over {{r_1} + {r_2}}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{r_1}{r_2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {r_1^2 + r_2^2} $$",
      "$${{{r_1} + {r_2}} \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {r_1^2 + r_2^2} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kta95ui1",
    "question": "Two narrow bores of diameter 5.0 mm and 8.0 mm are joined together to form a U-shaped tube open at both ends. If this U-tube contains water, what is the difference in the level of two limbs of the tube. [Take surface tension of water T = 7.3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> Nm<sup>$$-$$1</sup>, angle of contact = 0, g = 10 ms<sup>2</sup> and density of water = 1.0 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> kg m<sup>$$-$$3</sup>]",
    "options": [
      "3.62 mm",
      "2.19 mm",
      "5.34 mm",
      "4.97 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "2.19 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5690g3o",
    "question": "<p>A water drop of diameter 2 cm is broken into 64 equal droplets. The surface tension of water is 0.075 N/m. In this process the gain in surface energy will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> J",
      "1.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> J",
      "1.9 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> J",
      "9.4 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "2.8 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$4</sup> J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gmwos9",
    "question": "<p>A water drop of radius $$1 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ is broken into 729 equal droplets. If surface tension of water is 75 dyne/ $$\\mathrm{cm}$$, then the gain in surface energy upto first decimal place will be :</p>\n<p>(Given $$\\pi=3.14$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$8.5 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$",
      "$$8.2 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$",
      "$$7.5 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$",
      "$$5.3 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$7.5 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p4d4b7",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A): Clothes containing oil or grease stains cannot be cleaned by water wash.</p>\n<p>Reason (R): Because the angle of contact between the oil/grease and water is obtuse.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the option given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldogkwe0",
    "question": "<p>A mercury drop of radius $$10^{-3}~\\mathrm{m}$$ is broken into 125 equal size droplets. Surface tension of mercury is $$0.45~\\mathrm{Nm}^{-1}$$. The gain in surface energy is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$28\\times10^{-5}~\\mathrm{J}$$",
      "$$17.5\\times10^{-5}~\\mathrm{J}$$",
      "$$5\\times10^{-5}~\\mathrm{J}$$",
      "$$2.26\\times10^{-5}~\\mathrm{J}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$2.26\\times10^{-5}~\\mathrm{J}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpm86x9",
    "question": "<p>If 1000 droplets of water of surface tension $$0.07 \\mathrm{~N} / \\mathrm{m}$$, having same radius $$1 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ each, combine to from a single drop. In the process the released surface energy is :-</p>\n<p>$$\\left( {\\mathrm{Take}\\,\\pi  = {{22} \\over 7}} \\right)$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$7 .92 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$",
      "$$7 .92 \\times 10^{-6} \\mathrm{~J}$$",
      "$$8 .8 \\times 10^{-5} \\mathrm{~J}$$",
      "$$9 .68 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$7 .92 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldr0udq1",
    "question": "<p>The height of liquid column raised in a capillary tube of certain radius when dipped in liquid A vertically is, $$5 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. If the tube is dipped in a similar manner in another liquid $$\\mathrm{B}$$ of surface tension and density double the values of liquid $$\\mathrm{A}$$, the height of liquid column raised in liquid $$\\mathrm{B}$$ would be __________ m.</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.05",
      "0.20",
      "0.5",
      "0.10"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "0.05"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldso6nz9",
    "question": "<p>Surface tension of a soap bubble is $$2.0 \\times 10^{-2} \\mathrm{Nm}^{-1}$$. Work done to increase the radius of soap bubble from $$3.5 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ to $$7 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ will be:</p>\n<p>Take $$\\left[\\pi=\\frac{22}{7}\\right]$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$18 .48 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$",
      "$$5.76 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$",
      "$$0.72 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$",
      "$$9.24 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$18 .48 \\times 10^{-4} \\mathrm{~J}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldugs59u",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 691px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 271px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Surface tension</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{kg~m^{-1}~s^{-1}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Pressure</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{kg~ms^{-1}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Viscosity</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{kg~m^{-1}~s^{-2}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Impulse</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{kg~s^{-2}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I",
      "A-I, B-I, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwrq11a",
    "question": "<p>The frequency ($$\\nu$$) of an oscillating liquid drop may depend upon radius ($$r$$) of the drop, density ($$\\rho$$) of liquid and the surface tension (s) of the liquid as $$\\nu=r^a\\rho^b s^c$$. The values of a, b and c respectively are</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {{3 \\over 2},{1 \\over 2}, - {1 \\over 2}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( { - {3 \\over 2}, - {1 \\over 2},{1 \\over 2}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( {{3 \\over 2}, - {1 \\over 2},{1 \\over 2}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\left( { - {3 \\over 2},{1 \\over 2},{1 \\over 2}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$\\left( { - {3 \\over 2}, - {1 \\over 2},{1 \\over 2}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswvd5r",
    "question": "<p>Eight equal drops of water are falling through air with a steady speed of $$10 \\mathrm{~cm} / \\mathrm{s}$$. If the drops coalesce, the new velocity is:-</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$40 \\mathrm{~cm} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$16 \\mathrm{~cm} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$10 \\mathrm{~cm} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$5 \\mathrm{~cm} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$40 \\mathrm{~cm} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh00rp0f",
    "question": "<p>An air bubble of volume $$1 \\mathrm{~cm}^{3}$$ rises from the bottom of a lake $$40 \\mathrm{~m}$$ deep to the surface at a temperature of $$12^{\\circ} \\mathrm{C}$$. The atmospheric pressure is $$1 \\times 10^{5} \\mathrm{~Pa}$$ the density of water is $$1000 \\mathrm{~kg} / \\mathrm{m}^{3}$$ and $$\\mathrm{g}=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$. There is no difference of the temperature of water at the depth of $$40 \\mathrm{~m}$$ and on the surface. The volume of air bubble when it reaches the surface will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4 \\mathrm{~cm}^{3}$$",
      "$$3 \\mathrm{~cm}^{3}$$",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~cm}^{3}$$",
      "$$5 \\mathrm{~cm}^{3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$5 \\mathrm{~cm}^{3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsamqzfu",
    "question": "A big drop is formed by coalescing 1000 small droplets of water. The surface energy will become :",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{1}{100}$ th",
      "$\\frac{1}{10}$ th",
      "100 times",
      "10 times"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$\\frac{1}{10}$ th"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc2ulli",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) :Viscosity of gases is greater than that of liquids.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : Surface tension of a liquid decreases due to the presence of insoluble impurities.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is correct but statement II is incorrect\n",
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1inbp",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : If a capillary tube is immersed first in cold water and then in hot water, the height of capillary rise will be smaller in hot water.</p>\n<p>Statement II : If a capillary tube is immersed first in cold water and then in hot water, the height of capillary rise will be smaller in cold water.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsflhccd",
    "question": "<p>A small liquid drop of radius $$R$$ is divided into 27 identical liquid drops. If the surface tension is $$T$$, then the work done in the process will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4 \\pi \\mathrm{R}^2 \\mathrm{~T}$$\n",
      "$$8 \\pi R^2 \\mathrm{~T}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{8} \\pi R^2 T$$\n",
      "$$3 \\pi R^2 \\mathrm{~T}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$8 \\pi R^2 \\mathrm{~T}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwe3fy",
    "question": "<p>The excess pressure inside a soap bubble is thrice the excess pressure inside a second soap bubble. The ratio between the volume of the first and the second bubble is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: 9$$\n",
      "$$1: 27$$\n",
      "$$1: 81$$\n",
      "$$1: 3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$1: 27$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2es16x",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : The contact angle between a solid and a liquid is a property of the material of the solid and liquid as well.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The rise of a liquid in a capillary tube does not depend on the inner radius of the tube.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false.\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true.\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true.\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false."
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3oh5",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : When a capillary tube is dipped into a liquid, the liquid neither rises nor falls in the capillary. The contact angle may be $$0^{\\circ}$$.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The contact angle between a solid and a liquid is a property of the material of the solid and liquid as well.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statement, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true and Statement II is false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29ehp",
    "question": "<p>Pressure inside a soap bubble is greater than the pressure outside by an amount : (given : $$\\mathrm{R}=$$ Radius of bubble, $$\\mathrm{S}=$$ Surface tension of bubble)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{S}{R}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{4 \\mathrm{~S}}{\\mathrm{R}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{4 \\mathrm{R}}{\\mathrm{S}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{2 S}{R}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "properties-of-matter",
    "topic": "surface-tension,-excess-pressure-and-capillarity",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{4 \\mathrm{~S}}{\\mathrm{R}}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "74sEsWoySBVGwUIk",
    "question": "Initial angular velocity of a circular disc of mass $$M$$ is $${\\omega _1}.$$ Then two small spheres of mass $$m$$ are attached gently to diametrically opposite points on the edge of the disc. What is the final angular velocity  of the disc?",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left( {{{M + m} \\over M}} \\right)\\,\\,{\\omega _1}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {{{M + m} \\over m}} \\right)\\,\\,{\\omega _1}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {{M \\over {M + 4m}}} \\right)\\,\\,{\\omega _1}$$ ",
      "$$\\left( {{M \\over {M + 2m}}} \\right)\\,\\,{\\omega _1}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$$\\left( {{M \\over {M + 4m}}} \\right)\\,\\,{\\omega _1}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "KZnaV6RylgRhrevz",
    "question": "A particle performing uniform circular motion has angular frequency is doubled &amp; its kinetic energy halved, then the new angular momentum is ",
    "options": [
      "$${L \\over 4}$$ ",
      "$$2L$$ ",
      "$$4L$$ ",
      "$${L \\over 2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$${L \\over 4}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "2yrP77y91dEoBdH3",
    "question": "A solid sphere is rotating in free space. If the radius of the sphere is increased keeping mass same which on of the following will not be affected ? ",
    "options": [
      "Angular velocity ",
      "Angular momentum ",
      "Moment of inertia ",
      "Rotational kinetic energy "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "Angular momentum "
  },
  {
    "id": "5l4RYg5NGcZktK2L",
    "question": "A thin circular ring of mass $$m$$ and radius $$R$$ is rotating about its axis with a constant angular velocity $$\\omega $$. Two objects each of mass $$M$$ are attached gently to the opposite ends of a diameter of the ring. The ring now rotates with an angular velocity $$\\omega ' = $$ ",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\omega \\left( {m + 2M} \\right)} \\over m}$$ ",
      "$${{\\omega \\left( {m - 2M} \\right)} \\over {\\left( {m + 2M} \\right)}}$$ ",
      "$${{\\omega m} \\over {\\left( {m + M} \\right)}}$$ ",
      "$${{\\omega m} \\over {\\left( {m + 2M} \\right)}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$${{\\omega m} \\over {\\left( {m + 2M} \\right)}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "QQ11TAciudDuQhyM",
    "question": "Angular momentum of the particle rotating with a central force is constant due to",
    "options": [
      "constant torque",
      "constant force ",
      "constant linear momentum",
      "zero torque "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "zero torque "
  },
  {
    "id": "0P1oWpeepv5X83HE",
    "question": "A thin horizontal circular disc is rotating about a vertical axis passing through its center. An insect is at rest at a point near the rim of the disc. The insect now moves along a diameter of the disc to reach its other end. During the journey of the insect, the angular speed of the disc.",
    "options": [
      "continuously decreases ",
      "continuously increases ",
      "first increases and then decreases ",
      "remains unchanged "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "first increases and then decreases "
  },
  {
    "id": "pArPnFOcPLv5DIR5",
    "question": "A hoop of radius $$r$$ and mass $$m$$ rotating with an angular velocity $${\\omega _0}$$ is placed on a rough horizontal surface. The initial velocity of the center of the hoop is zero. What will be the velocity of the center of the hoop when it cases to slip?",
    "options": [
      "$${{r{\\omega _0}} \\over 4}$$ ",
      "$${{r{\\omega _0}} \\over 3}$$",
      "$${{r{\\omega _0}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${r{\\omega _0}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$${{r{\\omega _0}} \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "2KZ8qDYvVby0twN7",
    "question": "A bob of mass $$m$$ attached to an inextensible string of length $$l$$ is suspended from a vertical support. The bob rotates in a horizontal circle with an angular speed $$\\omega \\,rad/s$$ about the vertical. About the point of suspension:",
    "options": [
      "angular momentum is conserved ",
      "angular momentum changes in magnitude but not in direction. ",
      "angular momentum changes in direction but not in magnitude. ",
      "angular momentum changes both in direction and magnitude. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "angular momentum changes in direction but not in magnitude. "
  },
  {
    "id": "VK6Sm9R4lqQmcdH1T63rsa0w2w9jx3mfm29",
    "question": "A person of mass M is, sitting on a swing of length L and swinging with an angular amplitude $$\\theta $$<sub>0</sub>. If the\nperson stands up when the swing passes through its lowest point, the work done by him, assuming that his\ncenter of mass moves by a distance $$\\ell $$($$\\ell $$ &lt;&lt; L), is close to;\n",
    "options": [
      "mg$$\\ell $$(1 + $$\\theta $$<sub>0</sub><sup>2</sup>)",
      "mg$$\\ell $$",
      "mg$$\\ell $$(1 + $${{\\theta _0^2} \\over 2}$$)",
      "mg$$\\ell $$(1 - $$\\theta $$<sub>0</sub><sup>2</sup>)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "mg$$\\ell $$(1 + $$\\theta $$<sub>0</sub><sup>2</sup>)"
  },
  {
    "id": "n2loNcUjIP1k2lGyy23rsa0w2w9jwzk8ih4",
    "question": "The time dependence of the position of a particle of mass m = 2 is given by $$\\overrightarrow r \\left( t \\right) = 2t\\widehat i - 3{t^2}\\widehat j$$\n. Its angular\nmomentum, with respect to the origin, at time t = 2 is",
    "options": [
      "36 $$\\widehat k$$",
      "- 48 $$\\widehat k$$",
      "$$ - 34\\left( {\\widehat k - \\widehat i} \\right)$$",
      "$$48\\left( {\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "- 48 $$\\widehat k$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "z1qdq6HCwPf3AM1IfK3rsa0w2w9jwzjh440",
    "question": "A solid sphere of mass M and radius R is divided into two unequal parts. The first part has a mass of $${{7M} \\over 8}$$\nand is converted into a uniform disc of radius 2R. The second part is converted into a uniform solid sphere.\nLet I<sub>1</sub> be the moment of inertia of the disc about its axis and I<sub>2</sub> be the moment of inertia of the new sphere\nabout its axis. The ratio I<sub>1</sub>/I<sub>2</sub> is given by :",
    "options": [
      "65",
      "140",
      "185",
      "285"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "140"
  },
  {
    "id": "OcTjHmAdk2nhPme9embPM",
    "question": "A thin smooth rod of length L and mass M is\nrotating freely with angular speed $$\\omega $$<sub>0</sub> about an\naxis perpendicular to the rod and passing\nthrough its center. Two beads of mass m and\nnegligible size are at the center of the rod\ninitially. The beads are free to slide along the\nrod. The angular speed of the system , when\nthe beads reach the opposite ends of the rod,\nwill be :-",
    "options": [
      "$${{M{\\omega _0}} \\over {M + 3m}}$$",
      "$${{M{\\omega _0}} \\over {M + m}}$$",
      "$${{M{\\omega _0}} \\over {M + 6m}}$$",
      "$${{M{\\omega _0}} \\over {M + 2m}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$${{M{\\omega _0}} \\over {M + 6m}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "EZjw0xKukrq96OTweT4Ds",
    "question": "An electric dipole is formed by two equal and\nopposite charges q with separation d. The\ncharges have same mass m. It is kept in a\nuniform electric field E. If it is slightly rotated\nfrom its equilibrium orientation, then its angular\nfrequency $$\\omega$$ is :-",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{{qE} \\over {md}}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{qE} \\over {2md}}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{qE} \\over {-2md}}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{2qE} \\over {md}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{2qE} \\over {md}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "0jF0u1j47RGMUIQmtSBcR",
    "question": "If the angular momentum of a planet of mass m, moving around the Sun in a circular orbit is L, about the center of the Sun, its areal velocity is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${L \\over m}$$",
      "$${4L \\over m}$$",
      "$${L \\over 2m}$$",
      "$${2L \\over m}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$${L \\over 2m}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "uR7FEcBbUtA0FRhi44jgy2xukff3xry6",
    "question": "A wheel is rotating freely with an angular speed\n$$\\omega $$ on a shaft. The moment of inertia of the\nwheel is I and the moment of inertia of the\nshaft is negligible. Another wheel of moment of\ninertia 3I initially at rest is suddenly coupled to\nthe same shaft. The resultant fractional loss in\nthe kinetic energy of the system is :",
    "options": [
      "0",
      "$${5 \\over 6}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Z1v8NC8U95YrjXGxT6jgy2xukexxod6m",
    "question": "Two uniform circular discs are rotating\nindependently in the same direction around\ntheir common axis passing through their\ncentres. The moment of inertia and angular\nvelocity of the first disc are 0.1 kg-m<sup>2</sup> and 10\nrad s<sup>–1</sup> respectively while those for the second\none are 0.2 kg-m<sup>2</sup> and 5 rad s<sup>–1</sup> respectively. At\nsome instant they get stuck together and start\nrotating as a single system about their common\naxis with some angular speed. The kinetic\nenergy of the combined system is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{20} \\over 3}J$$",
      "$${{5} \\over 3}J$$",
      "$${{10} \\over 3}J$$",
      "$${{2} \\over 3}J$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$${{20} \\over 3}J$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xgguUJAR2MMkuQ4aev7k9k2k5gveqgd",
    "question": "Consider a uniform rod of mass M = 4m and\nlength $$\\ell $$ pivoted about its centre. A mass m\nmoving with velocity v making angle $$\\theta  = {\\pi  \\over 4}$$ to\nthe rod's long axis collides with one end of the\nrod and sticks to it. The angular speed of the\nrod-mass system just after the collision is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{3\\sqrt 2 } \\over 7}{v \\over \\ell }$$",
      "$${3 \\over 7}{v \\over \\ell }$$",
      "$${3 \\over {7\\sqrt 2 }}{v \\over \\ell }$$",
      "$${4 \\over 7}{v \\over \\ell }$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$${{3\\sqrt 2 } \\over 7}{v \\over \\ell }$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "WuHXW7gUgdMYj1BN9V1kluncx9i",
    "question": "A cord is wound round the circumference of wheel of radius r. The axis of the wheel is horizontal and the moment of inertia about it is I. A weight mg is attached to the cord at the end. The weight falls from rest. After falling through a distance 'h', the square of angular velocity of wheel will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2mgh} \\over {I + 2m{r^2}}}$$",
      "$${{2mgh} \\over {I + m{r^2}}}$$",
      "2gh",
      "$${{2gh} \\over {I + m{r^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$${{2mgh} \\over {I + m{r^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "IerYEirovFn3oJiZwY1kmkr269n",
    "question": "A thin circular ring of mass M and radius r is rotating about its axis with an angular speed $$\\omega$$. Two particles having mass m each are now attached at diametrically opposite points. The angular speed of the ring will become :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\omega {M \\over {M + m}}$$",
      "$$\\omega {{M + 2m} \\over M}$$",
      "$$\\omega {M \\over {M + 2m}}$$",
      "$$\\omega {{M - 2m} \\over {M + 2m}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$$\\omega {M \\over {M + 2m}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfjwrjv",
    "question": "Two discs have moments of inertia I<sub>1</sub> and I<sub>2</sub> about their respective axes perpendicular to the plane and passing through the centre. They are rotating with angular speeds, $$\\omega$$<sub>1</sub> and $$\\omega$$<sub>2</sub> respectively and are brought into contact face to face with their axes of rotation coaxial. The loss in kinetic energy of the system in the process is given by : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{I_1}{I_2}} \\over {({I_1} + {I_2})}}{({\\omega _1} - {\\omega _2})^2}$$",
      "$${{{{({I_1} - {I_2})}^2}{\\omega _1}{\\omega _2}} \\over {2({I_1} + {I_2})}}$$",
      "$${{{I_1}{I_2}} \\over {2({I_1} + {I_2})}}{({\\omega _1} - {\\omega _2})^2}$$",
      "$${{{{({\\omega _1} - {\\omega _2})}^2}} \\over {2({I_1} + {I_2})}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$${{{I_1}{I_2}} \\over {2({I_1} + {I_2})}}{({\\omega _1} - {\\omega _2})^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth5aj8v",
    "question": "Angular momentum of a single particle moving with constant speed along circular path :",
    "options": [
      "changes in magnitude but remains same in the direction",
      "remains same in magnitude and direction",
      "remains same in magnitude but changes in the direction",
      "is zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "remains same in magnitude and direction"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58bgm1n",
    "question": "<p>A thin circular ring of mass M and radius R is rotating with a constant angular velocity 2 rads<sup>$$-$$1</sup> in a horizontal plane about an axis vertical to its plane and passing through the center of the ring. If two\nobjects each of mass m be attached gently to the\nopposite ends of a diameter of ring, the ring will then rotate with an angular velocity (in rads<sup>$$-$$1</sup>).</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${M \\over {(M + m)}}$$",
      "$${{(M + 2m)} \\over {2M}}$$",
      "$${{2M} \\over {(M + 2m)}}$$",
      "$${{2(M + 2m)} \\over M}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$${{2M} \\over {(M + 2m)}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvr89zh",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements: one is labelled as Assertion $$\\mathbf{A}$$ and the other is labelled as Reason $$\\mathbf{R}$$</p>\n<p>Assertion A : An electric fan continues to rotate for some time after the current is switched off.</p>\n<p>Reason R : Fan continues to rotate due to inertia of motion.</p>\n<p>In the light of above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "A is not correct but R is correct",
      "A is correct but R is not correct",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A",
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgd0f2p",
    "question": "<p>A particle of mass $$\\mathrm{m}$$ is projected with a velocity '$$\\mathrm{u}$$' making an angle of $$30^{\\circ}$$ with the horizontal. The magnitude of angular momentum of the projectile about the point of projection when the particle is at its maximum height $$\\mathrm{h}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{mu}^3}{\\sqrt{2} \\mathrm{~g}}$$\n",
      "zero\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{2} \\frac{\\mathrm{mu}^2}{\\mathrm{~g}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{16} \\frac{\\mathrm{mu}^3}{\\mathrm{~g}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{3}}{16} \\frac{\\mathrm{mu}^3}{\\mathrm{~g}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3vefxa",
    "question": "<p>A thin circular disc of mass $$\\mathrm{M}$$ and radius $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is rotating in a horizontal plane about an axis passing through its centre and perpendicular to its plane with angular velocity $$\\omega$$. If another disc of same dimensions but of mass $$\\mathrm{M} / 2$$ is placed gently on the first disc co-axially, then the new angular velocity of the system is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{4}{5} \\omega$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{5}{4} \\omega$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{3}{2} \\omega$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{2}{3} \\omega$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "angular-momentum",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{2}{3} \\omega$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "atNumTaIjE3kMyJr",
    "question": "A solid sphere, a hollow sphere and a ring are released from top of an inclined plane (frictionless) so that they slide down the plane. Then maximum acceleration down the plane is for (no rolling) ",
    "options": [
      "solid sphere ",
      "hollow sphere ",
      "ring ",
      "all same "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "all same "
  },
  {
    "id": "nbiRKpbN7QLxHsp0",
    "question": "An annular ring with inner and outer radii $${R_1}$$ and $${R_2}$$ is rolling without slipping with a uniform angular speed. The ratio of the forces experienced by the two particles situated on the inner and outer parts of the ring, $${{{F_1}} \\over {{F_2}}}\\,$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left( {{{{R_1}} \\over {{R_2}}}} \\right)^2}$$ ",
      "$${{{{R_2}} \\over {{R_1}}}}$$",
      "$${{{{R_1}} \\over {{R_2}}}}$$ ",
      "$$1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "$${{{{R_1}} \\over {{R_2}}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "KQJHwKrZeCnzHTDE",
    "question": "A round uniform body of radius $$R,$$ mass $$M$$ and moment of inertia $$I$$ rolls down (without slipping) an inclined plane making an angle $$\\theta $$ with the horizontal. Then its acceleration is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{g\\,\\sin \\theta } \\over {1 - M{R^2}/I}}$$ ",
      "$${{g\\,\\sin \\theta } \\over {1 + I/M{R^2}}}$$ ",
      "$${{g\\,\\sin \\theta } \\over {1 + M{R^2}/I}}$$ ",
      "$${{g\\,\\sin \\theta } \\over {1 - I/M{R^2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "$${{g\\,\\sin \\theta } \\over {1 + I/M{R^2}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "SkXe9OycfhSpUpyH",
    "question": "A mass $$m$$ hangs with the help of a string wrapped around a pulley on a frictionless bearing. The pulley has mass $$m$$ and radius $$R.$$ Assuming pulley to be a perfect uniform circular disc, the acceleration of the mass $$m,$$ if the string does not slip on the pulley, is: ",
    "options": [
      "$$g$$ ",
      "$${2 \\over 3}g$$ ",
      "$${g \\over 3}$$ ",
      "$${3 \\over 2}g$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over 3}g$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "81boHpwGhVR7Pk6TRTQBO",
    "question": "Concrete mixture is made by mixing cement, stone and sand in a rotating\ncylindrical drum. If the drum rotates too fast, the ingredients remain stuck to the wall of the drum and proper mixing of ingredients does not take place. The maximum rotational speed of the drum in revolutions per minute(rpm) to ensure proper mixing is close to : \n<br/><br/>(Take the radius of the drum to be 1.25 m and its axle to be horizontal) :",
    "options": [
      "0.4",
      "1.3",
      "8.0",
      "27.0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "27.0"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZOIYD1k9JaLRduLLgyo8B",
    "question": "A homogeneous solid cylindrical roller of radius R and mass M is pulled on a cricket pitch by a horizontal force. Assuming rolling without slipping, angular acceleration of the cylinder is -\n",
    "options": [
      "$${F \\over {2mR}}$$",
      "$${2F \\over {3mR}}$$",
      "$${3F \\over {2mR}}$$",
      "$${F \\over {3mR}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "$${2F \\over {3mR}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "TiZmOQnPzFnqfLMyGc5uA",
    "question": "The following bodies are made to roll up\n(without slipping) the same inclined plane from\na horizontal plane. : (i) a ring of radius R, (ii)\na solid cylinder of radius\nR/2 and (iii) a solid\nsphere of radius\nR/4 . If in each case, the speed\nof the centre of mass at the bottom of the incline\nis same, the ratio of the maximum heights they\nclimb is :",
    "options": [
      "20 : 15 : 14",
      "4 : 3 : 2",
      "2 : 3 : 4",
      "10 : 15 : 7"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "20 : 15 : 14"
  },
  {
    "id": "9jCyQhEAs6eWjkTr4Q7k9k2k5hhldlt",
    "question": "A uniform sphere of mass 500 g rolls without\nslipping on a plane horizontal surface with its\ncentre moving at a speed of 5.00 cm/s. Its\nkinetic energy is :",
    "options": [
      "8.75 × 10<sup>–3</sup> J",
      "1.13 × 10<sup>–3</sup> J",
      "8.75 × 10<sup>–4</sup> J",
      "6.25 × 10<sup>–4</sup> J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "8.75 × 10<sup>–4</sup> J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqchuow",
    "question": "A body rolls down an inclined plane without slipping. The kinetic energy of rotation is 50% of its translational kinetic energy. The body is :",
    "options": [
      "Solid sphere",
      "Solid cylinder",
      "Hollow cylinder",
      "Ring"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "Solid cylinder"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsu72qd",
    "question": "Consider a situation in which a ring, a solid cylinder and a solid sphere roll down on the same inclined plane without slipping. Assume that they start rolling from rest and having identical diameter.<br/><br/>The correct statement for this situation is",
    "options": [
      "All of them will have same velocity.",
      "The ring has greatest and the cylinder has the least velocity of the centre of mass at the bottom of the inclined plane.",
      "The sphere has the greatest and the ring has the least velocity of the centre of mass at the bottom of the inclined plane.",
      "The cylinder has the greatest and the sphere has the least velocity of the centre of mass at the bottom of the inclined plane."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "The sphere has the greatest and the ring has the least velocity of the centre of mass at the bottom of the inclined plane."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55joigw",
    "question": "<p>A ball is spun with angular acceleration $$\\alpha$$ = 6t<sup>2</sup> $$-$$ 2t where t is in second and $$\\alpha$$ is in rads<sup>$$-$$2</sup>. At t = 0, the ball has angular velocity of 10 rads<sup>$$-$$1</sup> and angular position of 4 rad. The most appropriate expression for the angular position of the ball is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 2}{t^4} - {t^2} + 10t$$",
      "$${{{t^4}} \\over 2} - {{{t^3}} \\over 3} + 10t + 4$$",
      "$${{2{t^4}} \\over 3} - {{{t^3}} \\over 6} + 10t + 12$$",
      "$$2{t^4} - {{{t^3}} \\over 2} + 5t + 4$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "$${{{t^4}} \\over 2} - {{{t^3}} \\over 3} + 10t + 4$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56uiw7b",
    "question": "<p>One end of a massless spring of spring constant k and natural length l<sub>0</sub> is fixed while the other end is connected to a small object of mass m lying on a frictionless table. The spring remains horizontal on the table. If the object is made to rotate at an angular velocity $$\\omega$$ about an axis passing through fixed end, then the elongation of the spring will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${{k - m{\\omega ^2}{l_0}} \\over {m{\\omega ^2}}}$$",
      "$${{m{\\omega ^2}{l_0}} \\over {k + m{\\omega ^2}}}$$",
      "$${{m{\\omega ^2}{l_0}} \\over {k - m{\\omega ^2}}}$$",
      "$${{k + m{\\omega ^2}{l_0}} \\over {m{\\omega ^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "$${{m{\\omega ^2}{l_0}} \\over {k - m{\\omega ^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58hgpl0",
    "question": "<p>A solid spherical ball is rolling on a frictionless horizontal plane surface about its axis of symmetry. The ratio of rotational kinetic energy of the ball to its total kinetic energy is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${2 \\over 5}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 7}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 5}$$",
      "$${7 \\over 10}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over 7}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dxzpz1",
    "question": "<p>A solid cylinder and a solid sphere, having same mass $$M$$ and radius $$R$$, roll down the same inclined plane from top without slipping. They start from rest. The ratio of velocity of the solid cylinder to that of the solid sphere, with which they reach the ground, will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{5}{3}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{4}{5}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{3}{5}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{14}{15}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "combined-translational-and-rotational-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{\\frac{14}{15}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "JtkUq44cynQYPh0c",
    "question": "Moment of inertia of a circular wire of mass $$M$$ and radius $$R$$ about its diameter is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{M{R^2}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$$M{R^2}$$ ",
      "$$2M{R^2}$$ ",
      "$${{M{R^2}} \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${{M{R^2}} \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "V3JegbNrsTWtXNtV",
    "question": "A circular disc $$X$$ of radius $$R$$ is made from an  iron plate of thickness $$t,$$ and another disc $$Y$$ of radius $$4$$ $$R$$ is made from an iron plate of thickness $${t \\over 4}.$$ Then the relation between the moment of inertia $${I_X}$$  and  $${I_Y}$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$${I_Y} = 32{I_X}$$ ",
      "$${I_Y} = 16{I_X}$$",
      "$${I_Y} = {I_X}$$",
      "$${I_Y} = 64{I_X}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${I_Y} = 64{I_X}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "vnOj5CKUn7CTtjDi",
    "question": "One solid sphere $$A$$ and another hollow sphere $$B$$ are of same mass and same outer radii. Their moment of inertia about their diameters are respectively $${I_A}$$ and $${I_B}$$ such that ",
    "options": [
      "$${I_A} &lt; {I_B}$$  ",
      "$${I_A} &gt; {I_B}$$ ",
      "$${I_A} = {I_B}$$ ",
      "$${{{I_A}} \\over {{I_B}}} = {{{d_A}} \\over {{d_B}}}$$\nwhere $${d_A}$$ and $${d_B}$$ are their densities."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${I_A} &lt; {I_B}$$  "
  },
  {
    "id": "TwPowX0a7PgaEvAY",
    "question": "The moment of inertia of a uniform semicircular disc of mass $$M$$ and radius $$r$$ about a line perpendicular to the plane of the disc through the center is ",
    "options": [
      "$${2 \\over 5}M{r^2}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 4}Mr$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}M{r^2}$$ ",
      "$$M{r^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}M{r^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "WH2jIqhtfbspNMF1",
    "question": "Four point masses, each of value $$m,$$ are placed at the corners of a square $$ABCD$$ of side $$l$$. The moment of inertia of this system about an axis passing through $$A$$ and parallel to $$BD$$  is ",
    "options": [
      "$$2m{l^2}$$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt 3 m{l^2}$$ ",
      "$$3m{l^2}$$ ",
      "$$m{l^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$$3m{l^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ZTrPc4vdtmcrBxoR",
    "question": "Consider a uniform square plate of side $$' a '$$ and mass $$'m'$$. The moment of inertia of this plate about an axis perpendicular to its plane and passing through one of its corners is ",
    "options": [
      "$${5 \\over 6}m{a^2}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 12}m{a^2}$$",
      "$${7 \\over 12}m{a^2}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}m{a^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over 3}m{a^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "22tooMeZBtDgsgfY",
    "question": "A thin uniform rod of length $$l$$ and mass $$m$$ is swinging freely about a horizontal axis passing through its end. Its maximum angular speed is $$\\omega $$. Its center of mass rises to a maximum height of:",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 6}\\,\\,{{l\\omega } \\over g}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}\\,\\,{{{l^2}{\\omega ^2}} \\over g}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 6}\\,\\,{{{l^2}{\\omega ^2}} \\over g}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 3}\\,\\,{{{l^2}{\\omega ^2}} \\over g}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 6}\\,\\,{{{l^2}{\\omega ^2}} \\over g}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "a6lKQHUSUq7mYL0t",
    "question": "From a solid sphere of mass $$M$$ and radius $$R$$ a cube of maximum possible volume is cut. Moment of inertia of cube about an axis passing through its center and perpendicular to one of its face is:  ",
    "options": [
      "$${{4M{R^2}} \\over {9\\sqrt {3\\pi } }}$$ ",
      "$${{4M{R^2}} \\over {3\\sqrt {3\\pi } }}$$ ",
      "$${{M{R^2}} \\over {32\\sqrt {2\\pi } }}$$ ",
      "$${{M{R^2}} \\over {16\\sqrt {2\\pi } }}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${{4M{R^2}} \\over {9\\sqrt {3\\pi } }}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "vZk3cBXR23HJs2Pg",
    "question": "The moment of inertia of a uniform cylinder of length $$l$$ and radius R about its perpendicular bisector is $$I$$.\nWhat is the ratio $${l \\over R}$$ such that the moment of inertia is minimum?",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over 2}} $$ ",
      "$${{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}$$",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over 2}} $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Car9pLGRIDoZfpmHFy18hoxe66ijvzn5oc0",
    "question": "Two coaxial discs, having moments of inertia\nI<sub>1</sub> and I<sub>1</sub>/2, are rotating with respective angular\nvelocities $$\\omega $$<sub>1 </sub> and\n$$\\omega $$<sub>1</sub>/2\n, about their common axis.\nThey are brought in contact with each other and\nthereafter they rotate with a common angular\nvelocity. If E<sub>f</sub> and E<sub>i</sub> are the final and initial total\nenergies, then  (E<sub>f</sub> - E<sub>i</sub>) is:",
    "options": [
      "$${{{I_1}\\omega _1^2} \\over {24}}$$",
      "$${{{I_1}\\omega _1^2} \\over {12}}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 8}{I_1}\\omega _1^2$$",
      "$${{{I_1}\\omega _1^2} \\over {6}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${{{I_1}\\omega _1^2} \\over {24}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "byPYPbwFgB0CXsY4IZ18hoxe66ijvzn0x28",
    "question": "A thin disc of mass M and radius R has mass\nper unit area $$\\sigma $$(r) = kr<sup>2</sup> where r is the distance\nfrom its centre. Its moment of inertia about an\naxis going through its centre of mass and\nperpendicular to its plane is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{M{R^2}} \\over 3}$$",
      "$${{M{R^2}} \\over 6}$$",
      "$${{2M{R^2}} \\over 3}$$",
      "$${{M{R^2}} \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${{2M{R^2}} \\over 3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ANiozDvSSiYK3aYNBxrC5",
    "question": "Moment of inertia of a body about a given axis\nis 1.5 kg m<sup>2</sup>. Initially the body is at rest. In order\nto produce a rotational kinetic energy of\n1200 J, the angular accleration of 20 rad/s<sup>2</sup>\nmust be applied about the axis for a\nduration of :-",
    "options": [
      "2.5 s",
      "3 s",
      "5s",
      "2 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "2 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "oZMeF2P5AgHl84kp3cyQY",
    "question": "A stationary horizontal disc is free to rotate\nabout its axis. When a torque is applied on it,\nits kinetic energy as a function of $$\\theta $$, where $$\\theta $$\nis the angle by which it has rotated, is given as\nk$$\\theta $$<sup>2</sup>. If its moment of inertia is I then the\nangular acceleration of the disc is :",
    "options": [
      "$${k \\over {4I}}\\theta $$",
      "$${k \\over {I}}\\theta $$",
      "$${k \\over {2I}}\\theta $$",
      "$${2k \\over {I}}\\theta $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${2k \\over {I}}\\theta $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "8yqzWUAQ844P7o6At6Iif",
    "question": "A thin circular plate of mass M and radius R\nhas its density varying as $$\\rho $$(r) = $$\\rho $$<sub>0</sub>r with $$\\rho $$<sub>0</sub> as\nconstant and r is the distance from its centre.\nThe moment of Inertia of the circular plate about\nan axis perpendicular to the plate and passing\nthrough its edge is I = aMR<sup>2</sup>. The value of the\ncoefficient a is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${8 \\over 5}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 5}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${8 \\over 5}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ysXBZyKjbUp7UJb3f0DUM",
    "question": "Let the moment of inertia of a hollow cylinder of length 30 cm (inner radius 10 cm and outer radius 20 cm), about its axis be I. The radius of a thin cylinder of the same mass such that its moment of inertia about its axis is also I, is :",
    "options": [
      "16 cm",
      "12 cm",
      "14 cm",
      "18 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "16 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "VNPKX8Peju0Jhnpzopjgy2xukg0bmoa7",
    "question": "The linear mass density of a thin rod AB of length L varies from A to B as\n<br/>$$\\lambda \\left( x \\right) = {\\lambda _0}\\left( {1 + {x \\over L}} \\right)$$,  where\nx is the distance from A. If M is the mass of the rod then its moment of inertia about an axis passing\nthrough A and perpendicular to the rod is :",
    "options": [
      "$${2 \\over 5}M{L^2}$$",
      "$${5 \\over {12}}M{L^2}$$",
      "$${7 \\over {18}}M{L^2}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 7}M{L^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${7 \\over {18}}M{L^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "zT4AYz1QoP2zM4t8cfjgy2xukfl1siq0",
    "question": "A ring is hung on a nail. It can oscillate, without\nslipping or sliding <br/>(i) in its plane with a time\nperiod T<sub>1</sub> and, <br/>(ii) back and forth in a direction\nperpendicular to its plane, <br/>with a period T<sub>2</sub>. The\nratio $${{{T_1}} \\over {{T_2}}}$$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\sqrt 2 } \\over 3}$$",
      "$${2 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}$$",
      "$${3 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "qgdOpGBjkYAFKHd8zUjgy2xukfaj3opk",
    "question": "Consider two uniform discs of the same thickness and different radii R<sub>1</sub>\n = R and<br/> R<sub>2</sub>\n = $$\\alpha $$R made of\nthe same material. If the ratio of their moments of inertia I<sub>1</sub>\n and I<sub>2</sub>\n, respectively, about their axes\nis I<sub>1</sub>\n : I<sub>2</sub>\n = 1 : 16 then the value of $$\\alpha $$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "2",
      "$$2\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "WSwHvNT1JkSyc3iWsGjgy2xukf14dc5f",
    "question": "Moment of inertia of a cylinder of mass M,\nlength L and radius R about an axis passing\nthrough its centre and perpendicular to the\naxis of the cylinder is<br/> I = $$M\\left( {{{{R^2}} \\over 4} + {{{L^2}} \\over {12}}} \\right)$$. If such a\ncylinder is to be made for a given mass of a\nmaterial, the ratio $${L \\over R}$$ for it to have minimum\npossible I is",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over 2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{2 \\over 3}} $$",
      "$${{2 \\over 3}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over 2}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "2p0E2TIZzrOYy5YhX67k9k2k5djt7ib",
    "question": "The radius of gyration of a uniform rod of length $$l$$, about an axis passing through a\npoint $${l \\over 4}$$ away from the centre of the rod,\nand perpendicular to it, is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 8}l$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}l$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{7 \\over {48}}} l$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over 8}} l$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{7 \\over {48}}} l$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "mmd27YeQWLKUu4xQ2u7k9k2k5f5eapa",
    "question": "Mass per unit area of a circular disc of radius $$a$$ depends on the distance r from its centre as $$\\sigma \\left( r \\right)$$ = A + Br\n. The moment of inertia of the disc about the axis, perpendicular to the plane and\nassing through its centre is:",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\pi {a^4}\\left( {{A \\over 4} + {{aB} \\over 5}} \\right)$$",
      "$$\\pi {a^4}\\left( {{A \\over 4} + {{aB} \\over 5}} \\right)$$",
      "$$2\\pi {a^4}\\left( {{{aA} \\over 4} + {B \\over 5}} \\right)$$",
      "$$2\\pi {a^4}\\left( {{A \\over 4} + {B \\over 5}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$$2\\pi {a^4}\\left( {{A \\over 4} + {{aB} \\over 5}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "D69V8gdvhXmgTfrdPW1klrifuhg",
    "question": "Moment of inertia (M. I.) of four bodies, having same mass and radius, are reported as; <br/><br/>I<sub>1</sub> = M.I. of thin circular ring about its diameter,<br/><br/>I<sub>2</sub> = M.I. of circular disc about an axis perpendicular to disc and going through the centre,<br/><br/>I<sub>3</sub> = M.I. of solid cylinder about its axis and<br/><br/>I<sub>4</sub> = M.I. of solid sphere about its diameter.<br/><br/>Then :",
    "options": [
      "I<sub>1</sub> = I<sub>2</sub> = I<sub>3</sub> &gt; I<sub>4</sub>",
      "I<sub>1</sub> + I<sub>3</sub> &lt; I<sub>2</sub> + I<sub>4</sub>",
      "I<sub>1</sub> = I<sub>2</sub> = I<sub>3</sub> &lt; I<sub>4</sub>",
      "I<sub>1</sub> + I<sub>2</sub> = I<sub>3</sub> + $${5 \\over 2}$$ I<sub>4</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "I<sub>1</sub> = I<sub>2</sub> = I<sub>3</sub> &gt; I<sub>4</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "LF4awbZatQIQqlimkF1klthd0p0",
    "question": "Four identical solid spheres each of mass 'm' and radius 'a' are placed with their centres on the four corners of a square of side 'b'. The moment of inertia of the system about one side of square where the axis of rotation is parallel to the plane of the square is :",
    "options": [
      "$${4 \\over 5}m{a^2}$$",
      "$${8 \\over 5}m{a^2} + m{b^2}$$",
      "$${4 \\over 5}m{a^2} + 2m{b^2}$$",
      "$${8 \\over 5}m{a^2} + 2m{b^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${8 \\over 5}m{a^2} + 2m{b^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "GggYuVILuLH4LnAfDQ1kmlvtyoe",
    "question": "Consider a uniform wire of mass M and length L. It is bent into a semicircle. Its moment of inertia about a line perpendicular to the plane of the wire passing through the center is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 4}{{M{L^2}} \\over {{\\pi ^2}}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}{{M{L^2}} \\over {{\\pi ^2}}}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 5}{{M{L^2}} \\over {{\\pi ^2}}}$$",
      "$${{M{L^2}} \\over {{\\pi ^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${{M{L^2}} \\over {{\\pi ^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krudvskt",
    "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion A and the other is labelled as Reason R. <br/><br/>Assertion A : Moment of inertia of a circular disc of mass 'M' and radius 'R' about X, Y axes (passing through its plane) and Z-axis which is perpendicular to its plane were found to be I<sub>x</sub>, I<sub>y</sub> and I<sub>z</sub> respectively. The respectively radii of gyration about all the three axes will be the same.<br/><br/>Reason R : A rigid body making rotational motion has fixed mass and shape. In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both A and R are correct but R is NOT the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is not correct but R is correct.",
      "A is correct but R is not correct.",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "A is not correct but R is correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1krytnal1",
    "question": "<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List-I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List-II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(a) MI of the rod (length L, Mass M, about an axis $$ \\bot $$ to the rod passing through the midpoint)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(i) $$8M{L^2}/3$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(b) MI of the rod (length L, Mass 2M, about an axis $$ \\bot $$ to the rod passing through one of its end)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(ii) $$M{L^2}/3$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(c) MI of the rod (length 2L, Mass M, about an axis $$ \\bot $$ to the rod passing through its midpoint)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(iii) $$M{L^2}/12$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(d) MI of the rod (Length 2L, Mass 2M, about an axis $$ \\bot $$ to the rod passing through one of its end)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">(iv) $$2M{L^2}/3$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iii), (d)-(iv)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(ii), (d)-(i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kte0gtvo",
    "question": "Moment of inertia of a square plate of side l about the axis passing through one of the corner and perpendicular to the plane of square plate is given by :",
    "options": [
      "$${{M{l^2}} \\over 6}$$",
      "$${M{l^2}}$$",
      "$${{M{l^2}} \\over {12}}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}M{l^2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over 3}M{l^2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjn2zdu",
    "question": "A system consists of two identical spheres each of mass 1.5 kg and radius 50 cm at the end of light rod. The distance between the centres of the two spheres is 5 m. What will be the moment of inertia of the system about an axis perpendicular to the rod passing through its midpoint?",
    "options": [
      "18.75 kgm<sup>2</sup>",
      "1.905 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> kgm<sup>2</sup>",
      "19.05 kgm<sup>2</sup>",
      "1.875 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> kgm<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "19.05 kgm<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l568o323",
    "question": "<p>Match List-I with List-II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 577px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 43px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 277px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 205px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-0pky\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-c3ow\">List-II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Moment of inertia of solid sphere of radius R about any tangent.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${5 \\over 3}M{R^2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Moment of inertia of hollow sphere of radius (R) about any tangent.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${7 \\over 5}M{R^2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Moment of inertia of circular ring of radius (R) about its diameter.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${1 \\over 4}M{R^2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Moment of inertia of circular disc of radius (R) about any diameter.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$${1 \\over 2}M{R^2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A - II, B - I, C - IV, D - III",
      "A - I, B - II, C - IV, D - III",
      "A - II, B - I, C - III, D - IV",
      "A - I, B - II, C - III, D - IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "moment-of-inertia",
    "solution": "A - II, B - I, C - IV, D - III"
  },
  {
    "id": "CIUadGcAS8eenG8f",
    "question": "Let $$\\overrightarrow F $$  be the force acting on a particle having position vector $$\\overrightarrow r ,$$ and $$\\overrightarrow \\tau  $$ be the torque of this force about the origin. Then ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow {r.} \\overrightarrow \\tau  = 0\\,\\,$$ and $$\\overrightarrow {F.} \\overrightarrow \\tau  \\ne 0\\,\\,$$ ",
      "$$\\overrightarrow {r.} \\vec \\tau \\ne 0{\\mkern 1mu} {\\mkern 1mu} $$ and $$\\overrightarrow {F.} \\overrightarrow \\tau  = 0\\,\\,$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow {r.} \\vec \\tau \\ne 0{\\mkern 1mu} $$ and $$\\overrightarrow {F.} \\overrightarrow \\tau  \\ne 0$$ ",
      "$$\\overrightarrow {r.} \\vec \\tau = 0{\\mkern 1mu} $$ and $$\\overrightarrow {F.} \\overrightarrow \\tau  = 0\\,\\,$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "torque",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow {r.} \\vec \\tau = 0{\\mkern 1mu} $$ and $$\\overrightarrow {F.} \\overrightarrow \\tau  = 0\\,\\,$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "xmtiN91wgRQTentL",
    "question": "A pulley of radius $$2$$ $$m$$ is rotated about its axis by a force $$F = \\left( {20t - 5{t^2}} \\right)$$ newton (where $$t$$ is measured in seconds)  applied tangentially. If the moment of inertia of the pulley about its axis of rotation is $$10kg$$-$${m^2}$$ the number of rotation made by the pulley before its direction of motion is reversed, is:",
    "options": [
      "more than $$3$$ but less than $$6$$ ",
      "more than $$6$$ but less than $$9$$ ",
      "more than $$9$$ ",
      "less than $$3$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "torque",
    "solution": "more than $$3$$ but less than $$6$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "MJRqack07GUqVV3WcQzZQ",
    "question": "In a physical balance working on the principle of moments, when 5 mg weight is placed on the left pan, the beam becomes horizontal. Both the empty pans of the balance are of equal mass. Which of the following statements is <b>correct</b> ?\n",
    "options": [
      "Left arm is longer than the right arm",
      "Both the arms are of same length",
      "Left arm is shorter than the right arm",
      "Every object that is weighed using this balance appears lighter than its\nactual weight."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "torque",
    "solution": "Left arm is shorter than the right arm"
  },
  {
    "id": "lIeeCoZEUWeWBWBfNL18hoxe66ijvzncp98",
    "question": "A particle of mass m is moving along a\ntrajectory given by<br/>\nx = x<sub>0</sub> + a cos$$\\omega $$<sub>1</sub>t<br/>\ny = y<sub>0</sub> + b sin$$\\omega $$<sub>2</sub>t<br/>\nThe torque, acting on the particle about the\norigin, at t = 0 is :",
    "options": [
      "Zero",
      "+my<sub>0</sub>a $$\\omega _1^2$$$$\\widehat k$$",
      "$$ - m\\left( {{x_0}b\\omega _2^2 - {y_0}a\\omega _1^2} \\right)\\widehat k$$",
      "m (–x<sub>0</sub>b + y<sub>0</sub>a) $$\\omega _1^2$$$$\\widehat k$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "torque",
    "solution": "+my<sub>0</sub>a $$\\omega _1^2$$$$\\widehat k$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "7IgcOr0hYSrQ4geKwMzue",
    "question": "The magnitude of torque on a particle of mass 1 kg is 2.5 Nm about the origin. If the force acting on it is 1 N, and the distance of the particle from the origin is 5m, the angle between the force and the position vector is (in radians) :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\pi  \\over 8}$$",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 6}$$",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 4}$$",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "torque",
    "solution": "$${\\pi  \\over 6}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "99ytypmVzB3HdMTD16VFF",
    "question": "To mop-clean a floor, a cleaning machine presses a circular mop of radius R vertically down with a total force F and rotates it with a constant angular speed about its axis. If the force F is distributed uniformly over the mop and if coefficient of friction between the mop and the floor is $$\\mu $$, the torque, applied by the machine on the mop is - \n",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mu $$FR/2",
      "$$\\mu $$FR/3",
      "$$\\mu $$FR/6",
      "$${2 \\over 3}$$$$\\mu $$FR"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "torque",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over 3}$$$$\\mu $$FR"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5ak88g7",
    "question": "<p>If force $$\\overrightarrow F  = 3\\widehat i + 4\\widehat j - 2\\widehat k$$ acts on a particle position vector $$2\\widehat i + \\widehat j + 2\\widehat k$$ then, the torque about the origin will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3\\widehat i + 4\\widehat j - 2\\widehat k$$",
      "$$ - 10\\widehat i + 10\\widehat j + 5\\widehat k$$",
      "$$10\\widehat i + 5\\widehat j - 10\\widehat k$$",
      "$$10\\widehat i + \\widehat j - 5\\widehat k$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "torque",
    "solution": "$$ - 10\\widehat i + 10\\widehat j + 5\\widehat k$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rhk51x",
    "question": "<p>The torque of a force $$5 \\hat{i}+3 \\hat{j}-7 \\hat{k}$$ about the origin is $$\\tau$$. If the force acts on a particle whose position vector is $$2 i+2 j+k$$, then the value of $$\\tau$$ will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$11 \\hat{i}+19 \\hat{j}-4 \\hat{k}$$",
      "$$-11 \\hat{i}+9 \\hat{j}-16 \\hat{k}$$",
      "$$-17 \\hat{i}+19 \\hat{j}-4 \\hat{k}$$",
      "$$17 \\hat{i}+9 \\hat{j}+16 \\hat{k}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "torque",
    "solution": "$$-17 \\hat{i}+19 \\hat{j}-4 \\hat{k}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscp2nwn",
    "question": "<p>A heavy iron bar of weight $$12 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ is having its one end on the ground and the other on the shoulder of a man. The rod makes an angle $$60^{\\circ}$$ with the horizontal, the weight experienced by the man is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3 \\mathrm{~kg}$$\n",
      "$$6 \\mathrm{~kg}$$\n",
      "$$6 \\sqrt{3} \\mathrm{~kg}$$\n",
      "$$12 \\mathrm{~kg}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "rotational-motion",
    "topic": "torque",
    "solution": "$$6 \\mathrm{~kg}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "XI6gmRSfBGISa2EP",
    "question": "In forced oscillation of a particle the amplitude is maximum for a frequency $${\\omega _1}$$ of the force while the energy is maximum for a frequency $${\\omega _2}$$ of the force; then ",
    "options": [
      "$${\\omega _1} &lt; {\\omega _2}$$ when damping is small and $${\\omega _1} &gt; {\\omega _2}$$ when damping is large",
      "$${\\omega _1} &gt; {\\omega _2}$$  ",
      "$${\\omega _1} = {\\omega _2}$$ ",
      "$${\\omega _1} &lt; {\\omega _2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "forced,-damped-oscillations-and-resonance",
    "solution": "$${\\omega _1} = {\\omega _2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "B7GUvm9882JuXuow",
    "question": "If a simple pendulum has significant amplitude (up to a factor of $$1/e$$ of original ) only in the period between $$t = 0s\\,\\,to\\,\\,t = \\tau \\,s,$$ then $$\\tau \\,$$ may be called the average life of the pendulum When the spherical bob of the pendulum suffers a retardation (due to viscous drag) proportional to its velocity with $$b$$ as the constant of proportionality, the average life time of the pendulum is (assuming damping is small) in seconds : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{0.693} \\over b}$$ ",
      "$$b$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over b}$$ ",
      "$${2 \\over b}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "forced,-damped-oscillations-and-resonance",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over b}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "VgQ1HInwgYLBv8GP",
    "question": "The amplitude of a damped oscillator decreases to $$0.9$$ times its original magnitude in $$5s$$. In another $$10s$$ it will decrease to $$\\alpha $$  times its original magnitude, where $$\\alpha $$ equals ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.7$$ ",
      "$$0.81$$ ",
      "$$0.729$$ ",
      "$$0.6$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "forced,-damped-oscillations-and-resonance",
    "solution": "$$0.729$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ceMdTgOe0w5MurlETAo8s",
    "question": "A block of mass 0.1 kg is connected to an elastic spring of spring constant 640 Nm<sup>−1</sup> and oscillates in a damping medium of damping constant 10<sup>−2</sup>  kg s<sup>−1</sup> . The system dissipates its energy gradually. The  time taken for its mechanical energy of vibration to drop to half of its initial value, is closest to :",
    "options": [
      "2 s",
      "3.5 s",
      "5 s",
      "7 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "forced,-damped-oscillations-and-resonance",
    "solution": "7 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "xMJeEMmsuWemlT9ZvztNR",
    "question": "A closed organ pipe has a fundamental frequency of 1.5 kHz. The number of overtones that can be distinctly heard by a person with this organ pipe will be (Assume that the highest frequency a person can hear is 20,000 Hz)",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "7",
      "6",
      "5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "forced,-damped-oscillations-and-resonance",
    "solution": "7"
  },
  {
    "id": "TwVP2ZUg0hlMZaoFyMbOb",
    "question": "A simple pendulum of length 1 m is oscillating with an angular frequency 10 rad/s. The support of the pendulum starts oscillating up and down with a small angular frequency of 1 rad/s and an amplitude of 10<sup>–2</sup> m. The relative change in the angular frequency of the pendulum is best given by :",
    "options": [
      "1 rad/s",
      "10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> rad/s",
      "10<sup>$$-$$1</sup> rad/s",
      "10<sup>$$-$$5</sup> rad/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "forced,-damped-oscillations-and-resonance",
    "solution": "10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> rad/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "WOoBlt8ETS13tJULYdraT",
    "question": "A damped harmonic oscillator has a frequency\nof 5 oscillations per second. The amplitude\ndrops to half its value for every 10 oscillations.\nThe time it will take to drop to\n1/1000 of the original amplitude is close to :-",
    "options": [
      "100 s",
      "10 s",
      "20 s",
      "50 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "forced,-damped-oscillations-and-resonance",
    "solution": "20 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "DvgRFow7lD0kFK2GSn18hoxe66ijvzt49s0",
    "question": "The displacement of a damped harmonic\noscillator is given by<br/>\nx(t ) = e<sup>–0.1t </sup>cos (10$$\\pi $$t + f).<br/> Here t is in seconds.\nThe time taken for its amplitude of vibration to\ndrop to half of its initial value is close to :",
    "options": [
      "27 s",
      "13 s",
      "7 s",
      "4 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "forced,-damped-oscillations-and-resonance",
    "solution": "7 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "tomYJrsUOb2nA6jVXp1kmipm6wr",
    "question": "Amplitude of a mass-spring system, which is executing simple harmonic motion decreases with time. If mass = 500g, Decay constant = 20 g/s then how much time is required for the amplitude of the system to drop to drop to half of its initial value? (ln 2 = 0.693)",
    "options": [
      "17.32 s",
      "34.65 s",
      "0.034 s",
      "15.01 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "forced,-damped-oscillations-and-resonance",
    "solution": "34.65 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "zz3ADWesFzGXe3V28Q1kmkayv27",
    "question": "A block of mass 1 kg attached to a spring is made to oscillate with an initial amplitude of 12 cm. After 2 minutes the amplitude decreases to 6 cm. Determine the value of the damping constant for this motion . (take ln 2 = 0.693)",
    "options": [
      "0.69 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>2</sup> kg s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "3.3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>2</sup> kg s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "1.16 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> kg s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "5.7 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> kg s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "forced,-damped-oscillations-and-resonance",
    "solution": "1.16 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup> kg s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "U23891NbmcviFxD9",
    "question": "If a spring has time period $$T,$$ and is cut into $$n$$ equal parts, then the time period of each part will be ",
    "options": [
      "$$T\\sqrt n $$ ",
      "$$T/\\sqrt n $$ ",
      "$$nT$$ ",
      "$$T$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$T/\\sqrt n $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "4nLFC4HQ4tyheKRV",
    "question": "In a simple harmonic oscillator, at the mean position ",
    "options": [
      "kinetic energy is minimum, potential energy is maximum ",
      "both kinetic and potential energies are maximum ",
      "kinetic energy is maximum, potential energy is minimum ",
      "both kinetic and potential energies are minimum. "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "kinetic energy is maximum, potential energy is minimum "
  },
  {
    "id": "8prRwQnTYiNrCcsA",
    "question": "The displacement of particle varies according to the relation \n<br/>$$x=4$$$$\\left( {\\cos \\,\\pi t + \\sin \\,\\pi t} \\right).$$ The amplitude of the particle is ",
    "options": [
      "$$-4$$ ",
      "$$4$$ ",
      "$$4\\sqrt 2 $$ ",
      "$$8$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$4\\sqrt 2 $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "nj1E14ufjeMxKVxU",
    "question": "A body executes simple harmonic motion. The potential energy $$(P.E),$$ the kinetic energy $$(K.E)$$ and total energy $$(T.E)$$ are measured as a function of displacement $$x.$$ Which of the following statements is true ? ",
    "options": [
      "$$K.E$$ is maximum when $$x=0$$  ",
      "$$T.E$$ is zero when $$x=0$$ ",
      "$$K.E$$ is maximum when $$x$$ is maximum ",
      "$$P.E$$ is maximum when $$x=0$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$K.E$$ is maximum when $$x=0$$  "
  },
  {
    "id": "06Xs52fuhsUOl4iW",
    "question": "The total energy of particle, executing simple harmonic motion is ",
    "options": [
      "independent of $$x$$ ",
      "$$ \\propto \\,{x^2}$$ ",
      "$$ \\propto \\,x$$ ",
      "$$ \\propto \\,{x^{1/2}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "independent of $$x$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "UyF3fOCwppXJBgLo",
    "question": "The function $${\\sin ^2}\\left( {\\omega t} \\right)$$ represents",
    "options": [
      "a periodic, but not $$SHM$$ with a period $${\\pi  \\over \\omega }$$ ",
      "a periodic, but not $$SHM$$ with a period $${{2\\pi } \\over \\omega }$$  ",
      "a $$SHM$$ with a period $${\\pi  \\over \\omega }$$ ",
      "a $$SHM$$ with a period $${{2\\pi } \\over \\omega }$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "a periodic, but not $$SHM$$ with a period $${\\pi  \\over \\omega }$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "SbAnufkqtDJhxdk1",
    "question": "Two simple harmonic motions are represented by the equations $${y_1} = 0.1\\,\\sin \\left( {100\\pi t + {\\pi  \\over 3}} \\right)$$ and $${y_2} = 0.1\\,\\cos \\,\\pi t.$$ The phase difference of the velocity of particle $$1$$ with respect to the velocity of particle $$2$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$${\\pi  \\over 3}$$ ",
      "$${{ - \\pi } \\over 6}$$ ",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 6}$$ ",
      "$${{ - \\pi } \\over 3}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${{ - \\pi } \\over 6}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "6uyRBI1wBMOJBn9Y",
    "question": "If a simple harmonic motion is represented by $${{{d^2}x} \\over {d{t^2}}} + \\alpha x = 0.$$ its time period is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{2\\pi } \\over {\\sqrt \\alpha  }}$$ ",
      "$${{2\\pi } \\over \\alpha }$$ ",
      "$$2\\pi \\sqrt \\alpha  $$ ",
      "$$2\\pi \\alpha $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${{2\\pi } \\over {\\sqrt \\alpha  }}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "CtaC83vmguYf3d6j",
    "question": "A coin is placed on a horizontal platform which undergoes vertical simple harmonic motoin of angular frequency $$\\omega .$$ The amplitude of oscillation is gradually increased. The coin will leave contact with the platform for the first time ",
    "options": [
      "at the mean position of the platform ",
      "for an amplitude of $${g \\over {{\\omega ^2}}}$$ ",
      "For an amplitude of $${{{g^2}} \\over {{\\omega ^2}}}$$ ",
      "at the height position of the platform "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "for an amplitude of $${g \\over {{\\omega ^2}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "J8uRzrAhyPfJjsch",
    "question": "The maximum velocity of a particle, executing simple harmonic motion with an amplitude $$7$$ $$mm,$$ is $$4.4$$ $$m/s.$$ The period of oscillation is ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.01$$ $$s$$ ",
      "$$10$$ $$s$$ ",
      "$$0.1$$ $$s$$ ",
      "$$100$$ $$s$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$0.01$$ $$s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "ebtUyonKOJW3vNQj",
    "question": "Starting from the origin a body oscillates simple harmonically with a period of $$2$$ $$s.$$ After what time will its kinetic energy be $$75\\% $$ of the total energy? ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 6}s$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 4}s$$",
      "$${1 \\over 3}s$$",
      "$${1 \\over 12}s$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 6}s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "pByDQlRirgmfmwsq",
    "question": "A particle of mass $$m$$ executes simple harmonic motion with amplitude a and frequency $$v.$$ The average kinetic energy during its motion from the position of equilibrium to the end is ",
    "options": [
      "$$2{\\pi ^2}\\,m{a^2}{v^2}$$  ",
      "$${\\pi ^2}\\,m{a^2}{v^2}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 4}\\,m{a^2}{v^2}$$ ",
      "$$4{\\pi ^2}m{a^2}{v^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${\\pi ^2}\\,m{a^2}{v^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "LzZpukGgNRPtGq8G",
    "question": "A point mass oscillates along the $$x$$-axis according to the law $$x = {x_0}\\,\\cos \\left( {\\omega t - \\pi /4} \\right).$$ If the acceleration of the particle is written as $$a = A\\,\\cos \\left( {\\omega t + \\delta } \\right),$$ then ",
    "options": [
      "$$A = {x_0}{\\omega ^2},\\,\\,\\delta  = 3\\pi /4$$ ",
      "$$A = {x_0},\\,\\,\\delta  =  - \\pi /4$$ ",
      "$$A = {x_0}{\\omega ^2},\\,\\,\\delta  = \\pi /4$$ ",
      "$$A = {x_0}{\\omega ^2},\\,\\,\\delta  =  - \\pi /4$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$A = {x_0}{\\omega ^2},\\,\\,\\delta  = 3\\pi /4$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "2PhZcY8YjfpiVK8t",
    "question": "The displacement of an object attached to a spring and executing simple harmonic motion is given by $$x = 2 \\times {10^{ - 2}}$$ $$cos$$ $$\\pi t$$ metre. The time at which the maximum speed first occurs is",
    "options": [
      "$$0.25$$ $$s$$ ",
      "$$0.5$$ $$s$$",
      "$$0.75$$ $$s$$ ",
      "$$0.125$$ $$s$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$0.5$$ $$s$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "62HlH0BFHZTEnXmT",
    "question": "If $$x,$$ $$v$$ and $$a$$ denote the displacement, the velocity and the acceleration of a particle executing simple harmonic motion of time period $$T,$$ then, which of the following does not change with time? ",
    "options": [
      "$$aT/x$$ ",
      "$$aT + 2\\pi v$$ ",
      "$$aT/v$$ ",
      "$${a^2}{T^2} + 4{\\pi ^2}{v^2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$aT/x$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "nc8I9HTKAlvVNXMY",
    "question": "A mass $$M,$$ attached to a horizontal spring, executes $$S.H.M.$$ with amplitude $${A_1}.$$ When the mass $$M$$ passes through its mean position then a smaller mass $$m$$ is placed over it and both of them move together with amplitude $${A_2}.$$ The ratio of $$\\left( {{{{A_1}} \\over {{A_2}}}} \\right)$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{M + m} \\over M}$$ ",
      "$${\\left( {{M \\over {M + m}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ ",
      "$${\\left( {{{M + m} \\over M}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ ",
      "$${M \\over {M + m}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${\\left( {{{M + m} \\over M}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "YgHkasDCKsJtSxFH",
    "question": "Two particles are executing simple harmonic motion of the same amplitude $$A$$ and frequency $$\\omega $$ along the $$x$$-axis. Their mean position is separated by distance $${X_0}\\left( {{X_0} &gt; A} \\right)$$. If the maximum separation between them is $$\\left( {{X_0} + A} \\right),$$ the phase difference between their motion is: ",
    "options": [
      "$${\\pi  \\over 3}$$ ",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 4}$$ ",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 6}$$ ",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${\\pi  \\over 3}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "cFCwAnr5uP5w4PPM",
    "question": "A particle moves with simple harmonic motion in a straight line. In first $$\\tau s,$$ after starting from rest it travels a distance $$a,$$ and in next $$\\tau s$$ it travels $$2a,$$ in same direction, then:",
    "options": [
      "amplitude of motion  is $$3a$$ ",
      "time period of oscillations is $$8\\tau $$ ",
      "amplitude of motion is $$4a$$ ",
      "time period of oscillations is $$6\\tau $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "time period of oscillations is $$6\\tau $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "jejAjmwC6yYZiJYj",
    "question": "A particle performs simple harmonic motion with amplitude $$A.$$ Its speed is trebled at the instant that it is at a distance $${{2A} \\over 3}$$ from equilibrium position. The new amplitude of the motion is: ",
    "options": [
      "$$A\\sqrt 3 $$ ",
      "$${{7A} \\over 3}$$ ",
      "$${A \\over 3}\\sqrt {41} $$ ",
      "$$3A$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${{7A} \\over 3}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "4aY9Zg26IPzekAJj8MjXe",
    "question": "In an engine the piston undergoes vertical simple harmonic motion with amplitude 7 cm. A washer rests on top of the piston and moves with it. The motor speed is slowly increased. The frequency of the piston at which the washer no longer stays in contact with the piston, is close to :\n",
    "options": [
      "0.1 Hz ",
      "1.2 Hz ",
      "0.7 Hz ",
      "1.9 Hz "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "1.9 Hz "
  },
  {
    "id": "q0JavxzwOukBQqLiO4Uvl",
    "question": "Two particles are performing simple harmonic motion in a straight line about\nthe same equilibrium point. The amplitude and time period for both particles are same and equal to A and <i>I</i>, respectively. At time t = 0 one particle has \ndisplacement A while the other one has displacement $${{ - A} \\over 2}$$ and they are  moving towards each other. If they cross each other at time t, then t is :",
    "options": [
      "$${T \\over 6}$$ ",
      "$${5T \\over 6}$$",
      "$${T \\over 3}$$",
      "$${T \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${T \\over 6}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "J0ztRZyOpDhCkCo5Py6tj",
    "question": "A 1 kg block attached to a spring vibrates with a frequency of 1 Hz on a frictionless horizontal table. Two springs identical to the original spring are attached in parallel to an 8 kg block placed on the same table. So, the frequency of vibration of the 8 kg block is :\n",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 4}Hz$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {2\\sqrt 2 }}Hz$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}Hz$$",
      "$$2$$ $$Hz$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}Hz$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "eAYBP42rGLjuQR2SS2H9g",
    "question": "The ratio of maximum acceleration to maximum velocity in a simple harmonic motion is 10 s<sup>−1</sup> . At, t = 0 the displacement is 5 m. What is the maximum acceleration ? The initial phase is $${\\pi  \\over 4}$$.",
    "options": [
      "500 m/s<sup>2</sup> ",
      "500 $$\\sqrt 2 m/$$ s<sup>2</sup> ",
      "750 m/s<sup>2</sup> ",
      "750 $$\\sqrt 2 $$m / s<sup>2</sup> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "500 $$\\sqrt 2 m/$$ s<sup>2</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "CTJxDgKJxL1pyelJYoyhf",
    "question": "A particle executes simple harmonic motion and is located at x = a, b and c at times t<sub>0</sub>, 2t<sub>0</sub> and 3t<sub>0</sub> respectively.  The freqquency of the oscillation is : ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {2\\,\\pi \\,{t_0}}}{\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{a + c} \\over {2b}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over {2\\,\\pi \\,{t_0}}}{\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{a + b} \\over {2c}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over {2\\,\\pi \\,{t_0}}}{\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{2a + 3c} \\over b}} \\right)$$",
      "$${1 \\over {2\\,\\pi \\,{t_0}}}{\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{a + 2b} \\over {3c}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {2\\,\\pi \\,{t_0}}}{\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{a + c} \\over {2b}}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "SsY8ijRyGV2Y3ETBy1GQ3",
    "question": "Two simple harmonic motions, as shown below, are at right angles. They are combined to form Lissajous figures. \n<br/>x(t) = A sin (at + $$\\delta $$)\n<br/>y(t) = B sin (bt)\n<br/><br/>Identify the <b>correct</b>  match below.",
    "options": [
      "<b>Parameters</b> &nbsp;&nbsp;A $$ \\ne $$ B, a = b; $$\\delta $$ = 0;\n<br><b>Curve</b> &nbsp;&nbsp; Parabola",
      "<b>Parameters</b> &nbsp;&nbsp; A = B, a = b; $$\\delta $$ = $${\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle \\pi $}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}$$\n<br><b>Curve</b> &nbsp;&nbsp; Line",
      "<b>Parameters</b> &nbsp;&nbsp; A $$ \\ne $$ B, a = b; $$\\delta $$ = $${\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle \\pi $}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}$$\n<br><b>Curve</b> &nbsp;&nbsp; Ellipse",
      "<b>Parameters</b> &nbsp;&nbsp; A = B,  a = 2b; $$\\delta $$ = $${\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle \\pi $}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}$$\n<br><b>Curve</b> &nbsp;&nbsp; Circle "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "<b>Parameters</b> &nbsp;&nbsp; A $$ \\ne $$ B, a = b; $$\\delta $$ = $${\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle \\pi $}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}$$\n<br><b>Curve</b> &nbsp;&nbsp; Ellipse"
  },
  {
    "id": "h9jlYSnorP6W5PIDbR1TC",
    "question": "A particle is executing simple harmonic motion (SHM) of amplitude A, along the x-axis, about x = 0. When its potential Energy (PE) equals kinetic energy (KE), the position of the particle will be : ",
    "options": [
      "$${A \\over 2}$$",
      "$${A \\over {2\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$${A \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${A \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "BIB7dgP8SnMAN9yyLiocZ",
    "question": "A simple harmonic motion is represented by :\n<br/><br/>y = 5 (sin 3 $$\\pi $$ t + $$\\sqrt 3 $$ cos 3 $$\\pi $$t) cm\n<br/><br/>The amplitude and time period of the motion are : ",
    "options": [
      "10 cm, $${3 \\over 2}$$ s",
      "5 cm, $${2 \\over 3}$$ s",
      "5 cm, $${3 \\over 2}$$ s",
      "10 cm, $${2 \\over 3}$$ s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "10 cm, $${2 \\over 3}$$ s"
  },
  {
    "id": "v2ptj6ziRkQiRpQdcytDD",
    "question": "A particle undergoing simple harmonic motion has time dependent displacement given by x(t) = Asin$${{\\pi t} \\over {90}}$$. The ratio of kinetic to potential energy of this particle at t = 210 s will be: ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 9}$$",
      "3",
      "2",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "3"
  },
  {
    "id": "cm46ByyrxvFyOpZp5rXol",
    "question": "A particle executes simple harmonic motion with an amplitude of 5 cm. When the particle is at 4 cm from the mean position, the magnitude of its velocity in SI units is equal to that of its acceleration. Then, its periodic time in seconds is - ",
    "options": [
      "$${{4\\pi } \\over 3}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 8}\\pi $$",
      "$${7 \\over 3}\\pi $$",
      "$${{8\\pi } \\over 3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${{8\\pi } \\over 3}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "F5IDR67uID3EyumOBp7k9k2k5hgtxa6",
    "question": "A simple pendulum is being used to determine\nth value of gravitational acceleration g at a\ncertain place. Th length of the pendulum is\n25.0 cm and a stop watch with 1s resolution\nmeasures the time taken for 40 oscillations to\nbe 50 s. The accuracy in g is :",
    "options": [
      "4.40%",
      "3.40%",
      "2.40%",
      "5.40%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "4.40%"
  },
  {
    "id": "b287D16YoPT48A5Ui71klrnt483",
    "question": "When a particle executes SHM, the nature of graphical representation of velocity as a function of displacement is :",
    "options": [
      "circular",
      "straight line",
      "parabolic",
      "elliptical"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "elliptical"
  },
  {
    "id": "5nvIqbcRtSrVqlqPO91klt2xeyn",
    "question": "Y = A sin($$\\omega$$t + $$\\phi$$<sub>0</sub>) is the time-displacement equation of a SHM. At t = 0 the displacement of the particle is $$Y = {A \\over 2}$$ and it is moving along negative x-direction. Then the initial phase angle $$\\phi$$<sub>0</sub> will be:",
    "options": [
      "$${{5\\pi } \\over 6}$$",
      "$${{\\pi } \\over 3}$$",
      "$${{2\\pi } \\over 3}$$",
      "$${{\\pi } \\over 6}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${{5\\pi } \\over 6}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "z3Q9KUwuSIlVdPQJO01klune0zd",
    "question": "A particle executes S.H.M., the graph of velocity as a function of displacement is :",
    "options": [
      "a parabola",
      "a helix",
      "an ellipse",
      "a circle"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "an ellipse"
  },
  {
    "id": "9I5Qk79S5teMX13cDS1kmj25mzo",
    "question": "For what value of displacement the kinetic energy and potential energy of a simple harmonic oscillation become equal ?",
    "options": [
      "x = $${A \\over 2}$$",
      "x = $$\\pm$$ A",
      "x = $$\\pm$$ $${A \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "x = 0"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "x = $$\\pm$$ $${A \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "AAufQa38qwmRel8etd1kmlhlvfe",
    "question": "The time period of a simple pendulum is given by $$T = 2\\pi \\sqrt {{l \\over g}} $$. The measured value of the length of pendulum is 10 cm known to a 1mm accuracy. The time for 200 oscillations of the pendulum is found to be 100 second using a clock of 1s resolution. The percentage accuracy in the determination of 'g' using this pendulum is 'x'. The value of 'x' to be nearest integer is :-",
    "options": [
      "2%",
      "3%",
      "5%",
      "4%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "3%"
  },
  {
    "id": "FsHhtR64PT7qW01aGE1kmlw7pej",
    "question": "The function of time representing a simple harmonic motion with a period of $${\\pi  \\over \\omega }$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "cos($$\\omega$$t) + cos(2$$\\omega$$t) + cos(3$$\\omega$$t)",
      "sin<sup>2</sup>($$\\omega$$t)",
      "sin($$\\omega$$t) + cos($$\\omega$$t)",
      "3cos$$\\left( {{\\pi  \\over 4} - 2\\omega t} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "3cos$$\\left( {{\\pi  \\over 4} - 2\\omega t} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqc9uhv",
    "question": "A particle is making simple harmonic motion along the X-axis. If at a distances x<sub>1</sub> and x<sub>2</sub> from the mean position the velocities of the particle are v<sub>1</sub> and v<sub>2</sub> respectively. The time period of its oscillation is given as :",
    "options": [
      "$$T = 2\\pi \\sqrt {{{x_2^2 + x_1^2} \\over {v_1^2 - v_2^2}}} $$",
      "$$T = 2\\pi \\sqrt {{{x_2^2 + x_1^2} \\over {v_1^2 + v_2^2}}} $$",
      "$$T = 2\\pi \\sqrt {{{x_2^2 - x_1^2} \\over {v_1^2 + v_2^2}}} $$",
      "$$T = 2\\pi \\sqrt {{{x_2^2 - x_1^2} \\over {v_1^2 - v_2^2}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$T = 2\\pi \\sqrt {{{x_2^2 - x_1^2} \\over {v_1^2 - v_2^2}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw6gaab",
    "question": "In a simple harmonic oscillation, what fraction of total mechanical energy is in the form of kinetic energy, when the particle is midway between mean and extreme position.",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${3 \\over 4}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 3}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krywgvzm",
    "question": "A particle starts executing simple harmonic motion (SHM) of amplitude 'a' and total energy E. At any instant, its kinetic energy is $${{3E} \\over 4}$$ then its displacement 'y' is given by :",
    "options": [
      "y = a",
      "$$y = {a \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$$y = {{a\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}$$",
      "$$y = {a \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$y = {a \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks0katmf",
    "question": "An object of mass 0.5 kg is executing simple harmonic motion. It amplitude is 5 cm and time period (T) is 0.2 s. What will be the potential energy of the object at an instant $$t = {T \\over 4}s$$ starting from mean position. Assume that the initial phase of the oscillation is zero.",
    "options": [
      "0.62 J",
      "6.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$3</sup> J",
      "1.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> J",
      "6.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "0.62 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjpuusx",
    "question": "For a body executing S.H.M. :<br/><br/>(1) Potential energy is always equal to its K.E.<br/><br/>(2) Average potential and kinetic energy over any given time interval are always equal.<br/><br/>(3) Sum of the kinetic and potential energy at any point of time is constant.<br/><br/>(4) Average K.E. in one time period is equal to average potential energy in one time period.<br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate option from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(3) and (4)",
      "only (3)",
      "(2) and (3)",
      "only (2)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "(3) and (4)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l54v46ak",
    "question": "<p>The motion of a simple pendulum executing S.H.M. is represented by the following equation.</p>\n<p>$$y = A\\sin (\\pi t + \\phi )$$, where time is measured in second. The length of pendulum is</p>",
    "options": [
      "97.23 cm",
      "25.3 cm",
      "99.4 cm",
      "406.1 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "99.4 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l568jzrd",
    "question": "<p>Motion of a particle in x-y plane is described by a set of following equations $$x = 4\\sin \\left( {{\\pi  \\over 2} - \\omega t} \\right)\\,m$$ and $$y = 4\\sin (\\omega t)\\,m$$. The path of the particle will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "circular",
      "helical",
      "parabolic",
      "elliptical"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "circular"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56uvlyh",
    "question": "<p>The equation of a particle executing simple harmonic motion is given by $$x = \\sin \\pi \\left( {t + {1 \\over 3}} \\right)m$$. At t = 1s, the speed of particle will be</p>\n<p>(Given : $$\\pi$$ = 3.14)</p>",
    "options": [
      "0 cm s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "157 cm s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "272 cm s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "314 cm s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "157 cm s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gmqiah",
    "question": "<p>When a particle executes Simple Hormonic Motion, the nature of graph of velocity as a function of displacement will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Circular",
      "Elliptical",
      "Sinusoidal",
      "Straight line"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "Elliptical"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpm3li8",
    "question": "<p>The maximum potential energy of a block executing simple harmonic motion is $$25 \\mathrm{~J}$$. A is amplitude of oscillation. At $$\\mathrm{A / 2}$$, the kinetic energy of the block is</p>",
    "options": [
      "9.75 J",
      "37.5 J",
      "18.75 J",
      "12.5 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "18.75 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtxfpwr",
    "question": "<p>A particle executes simple harmonic motion between $$x=-A$$ and $$x=+A$$. If time taken by particle to go from $$x=0$$ to $$\\frac{A}{2}$$ is 2 s; then time taken by particle in going from $$x=\\frac{A}{2}$$ to A is</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 s",
      "1.5 s",
      "3 s",
      "2 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "4 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgny52r8",
    "question": " In a linear Simple Harmonic Motion (SHM)\n<br/><br/>\n(A) Restoring force is directly proportional to the displacement.\n<br/><br/>\n(B) The acceleration and displacement are opposite in direction.\n<br/><br/>\n(C) The velocity is maximum at mean position.\n<br/><br/>\n(D) The acceleration is minimum at extreme points.\n<br/><br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below:",
    "options": [
      "${\\text {(A), (B) and (D) only }}$",
      "(C) and (D) only",
      "(A), (B) and (C) Only",
      "(A), (C) and (D) only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "(A), (B) and (C) Only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp0iu9i",
    "question": "<p>A particle executes SHM of amplitude A. The distance from the mean position when its's kinetic energy becomes equal to its potential energy is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} A$$",
      "$$\\frac{1}{2} A$$",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~A}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt{2 A}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{2}} A$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrgy9ww",
    "question": "<p>A particle is executing simple harmonic motion (SHM). The ratio of potential energy and kinetic energy of the particle when its displacement is half of its amplitude will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 1",
      "1 : 4",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "1 : 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgxxnshu",
    "question": "<p>A particle executes S.H.M. of amplitude A along x-axis. At t = 0, the position of the particle is $$x=\\frac{A}{2}$$ and it moves along positive x-axis. The displacement of particle in time t is $$x = A\\sin (wt + \\delta )$$, then the value of $$\\delta$$ will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{3}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\pi}{6}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\pi}{6}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbl5lz1",
    "question": "A simple pendulum of length $1 \\mathrm{~m}$ has a wooden bob of mass $1 \\mathrm{~kg}$. It is struck by a bullet of mass $10^{-2} \\mathrm{~kg}$ moving with a speed of $2 \\times 10^2 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$. The bullet gets embedded into the bob. The height to which the bob rises before swinging back is. (use $\\mathrm{g}=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^2$ )",
    "options": [
      "$0.20 \\mathrm{~m}$",
      "$0.40 \\mathrm{~m}$",
      "$0.30 \\mathrm{~m}$",
      "$0.35 \\mathrm{~m}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$0.20 \\mathrm{~m}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscoytpx",
    "question": "<p>A ball suspended by a thread swings in a vertical plane so that its magnitude of acceleration in the extreme position and lowest position are equal. The angle $$(\\theta)$$ of thread deflection in the extreme position will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$2 \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$2 \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{5}}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$\\tan ^{-1}(\\sqrt{2})$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$2 \\tan ^{-1}\\left(\\frac{1}{2}\\right)$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v4o88",
    "question": "<p>A simple pendulum doing small oscillations at a place $$R$$ height above earth surface has time period of $$T_1=4 \\mathrm{~s}$$. $$\\mathrm{T}_2$$ would be it's time period if it is brought to a point which is at a height $$2 \\mathrm{R}$$ from earth surface. Choose the correct relation [$$\\mathrm{R}=$$ radius of earth] :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3 \\mathrm{~T}_1=2 \\mathrm{~T}_2$$\n",
      "$$\\mathrm{T}_1=\\mathrm{T}_2$$\n",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~T}_1=3 \\mathrm{~T}_2$$\n",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~T}_1=\\mathrm{T}_2$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "solution": "$$3 \\mathrm{~T}_1=2 \\mathrm{~T}_2$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "MFDKspc0MnNCPOLv",
    "question": "A child swinging on a swing in sitting position, stands up, then the time period of the swing will ",
    "options": [
      "increase ",
      "decrease ",
      "remains same ",
      "increases of the child is long and decreases if the child is short "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "decrease "
  },
  {
    "id": "w8ha9w1H1yXKnYQh",
    "question": "A mass $$M$$ is suspended from a spring of negligible mass. The spring is pulled a little and then released so that the mass executes $$SHM$$ of time period $$T.$$ If the mass is increased by $$m.$$ the time period becomes $${{5T} \\over 3}$$. Then the ratio of $${{m} \\over M}$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 5}$$ ",
      "$${25 \\over 9}$$",
      "$${16 \\over 9}$$",
      "$${5 \\over 3}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$${16 \\over 9}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "WcNVakC4ImT5qVL7",
    "question": "Two particles $$A$$ and $$B$$ of equal masses are suspended from two massless springs  of spring of spring constant $${k_1}$$ and $${k_2}$$, respectively. If the maximum velocities, during oscillation, are equal, the ratio of amplitude of $$A$$ and $$B$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{k_1}} \\over {{k_2}}}} $$ ",
      "$${{{{k_2}} \\over {{k_1}}}}$$ ",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{k_2}} \\over {{k_1}}}} $$ ",
      "$${{{{k_1}} \\over {{k_2}}}}$$  "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{{k_2}} \\over {{k_1}}}} $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "sbsnGQLplnIDSD1j",
    "question": "The length of a simple pendulum executing simple harmonic motion is increased by $$21\\% $$. The percentage increase in the time period of the pendulum of increased length is ",
    "options": [
      "$$11\\% $$",
      "$$21\\% $$ ",
      "$$42\\% $$",
      "$$10\\% $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$10\\% $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "65Tec9CL2BozjP1E",
    "question": "The bob of a simple pendulum executes simple harmonic motion in water with a period $$t,$$ while the period of oscillation of the bob is $${t_0}$$ in air. Neglecting frictional force of water and given that the density of the bob is $$\\left( {4/3} \\right) \\times 1000\\,\\,kg/{m^3}.$$ What relationship between $$t$$ and $${t_0}$$  is true ",
    "options": [
      "$$t = 2{t_0}$$ ",
      "$$t = {t_0}/2$$ ",
      "$$t = {t_0}$$ ",
      "$$t = 4{t_0}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$t = 2{t_0}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "jbXo9c9iN9BAcsPy",
    "question": "A particle at the end of a spring executes $$S.H.M$$ with a period $${t_1}$$. While the corresponding period for another spring is $${t_2}$$. If the period of oscillation with the two springs in series is $$T$$ then",
    "options": [
      "$${T^{ - 1}} = t_1^{ - 1} + t_2^{ - 1}$$ ",
      "$${T^2} = t_1^2 + t_2^2$$ ",
      "$$T = {t_1} + {t_2}$$ ",
      "$${T^{ - 2}} = t_1^{ - 2} + t_2^{ - 2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$${T^2} = t_1^2 + t_2^2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "DwvQomzRTsQjLmej",
    "question": "A particle of mass $$m$$ is attached to a spring (of spring constant $$k$$) and has a natural angular frequency $${\\omega _0}.$$ An external force $$F(t)$$ proportional to $$\\cos \\,\\omega t\\left( {\\omega  \\ne {\\omega _0}} \\right)$$ is applied to the oscillator. The time displacement of the oscillator will be proportional to ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {m\\left( {\\omega _0^2 + {\\omega ^2}} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {m\\left( {\\omega _0^2 - {\\omega ^2}} \\right)}}$$ ",
      "$${m \\over {\\omega _0^2 - {\\omega ^2}}}$$ ",
      "$${m \\over {\\omega _0^2 + {\\omega ^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {m\\left( {\\omega _0^2 - {\\omega ^2}} \\right)}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "YeqfjfzgZ2NMPf7Q",
    "question": "The bob of a simple pendulum is a spherical hollow ball filled with water. A plugged hole near the bottom of the oscillating bob gets suddenly unplugged. During observation, till water is coming out, the time period of oscillation would ",
    "options": [
      "first decrease and then increase to the original value",
      "first increase and then decrease to the original value",
      "increase towards a saturation value",
      "remain unchanged "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "first increase and then decrease to the original value"
  },
  {
    "id": "2bzyhJzXtz4R5ytc",
    "question": "An ideal gas enclosed in a vertical cylindrical container supports a freely moving piston of mass $$M.$$ The piston and the cylinder have equal cross sectional area $$A$$. When the piston is in equilibrium, the volume of the gas is $${V_0}$$ and its pressure is $${P_0}.$$ The piston is slightly displaced from the equilibrium position and released,. Assuming that the system is completely isolated from its surrounding, the piston executes a simple harmonic motion with frquency",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\,{{A\\gamma {P_0}} \\over {{V_0}M}}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\,{{{V_0}M{P_0}} \\over {{A^2}\\gamma }}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\,\\sqrt {{{A\\gamma {P_0}} \\over {{V_0}M}}} $$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\,\\sqrt {{{M{V_0}} \\over {A\\gamma {P_0}}}} $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\,\\sqrt {{{A\\gamma {P_0}} \\over {{V_0}M}}} $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "c0bxKdhVGVrfsYLY",
    "question": "A pendulum made of a uniform wire of cross sectional area $$A$$ has time period $$T.$$ When an additional mass $$M$$ is added to its bob, the time period changes to $${T_{M.}}$$ If the Young's modulus of the material of the wire is $$Y$$ then $${1 \\over Y}$$ is equal to : \n<br/>($$g=$$ $$gravitational$$ $$acceleration$$)",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[ {1 - {{\\left( {{{{T_M}} \\over T}} \\right)}^2}} \\right]{A \\over {Mg}}$$ ",
      "$$\\left[ {1 - {{\\left( {{T \\over {{T_M}}}} \\right)}^2}} \\right]{A \\over {Mg}}$$ ",
      "$$\\left[ {{{\\left( {{{{T_M}} \\over T}} \\right)}^2} - 1} \\right]{A \\over {Mg}}$$ ",
      "$$\\left[ {{{\\left( {{{{T_M}} \\over T}} \\right)}^2} - 1} \\right]{{Mg} \\over A}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$\\left[ {{{\\left( {{{{T_M}} \\over T}} \\right)}^2} - 1} \\right]{A \\over {Mg}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "0biZwoHVNUIxBTRk",
    "question": "The period of oscillation of a simple pendulum is $$T = 2\\pi \\sqrt {{L \\over g}} $$.  Measured value of L is 20.0 cm known to 1 mm accuracy and time for 100 oscillations of the pendulum is found to be 90 s using wrist watch of 1 s resolution. The accuracy in the determination of g is:",
    "options": [
      "1 %",
      "5 %",
      "2 %",
      "3 %"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "3 %"
  },
  {
    "id": "nac8kY5q9RGKZP0u",
    "question": "A silver atom in a solid oscillates in simple harmonic motion in some direction with a frequency of 10<sup>12</sup>/sec. What is the force constant of the bonds connecting one atom with the other? (Mole wt. of silver = 108 and Avogadro number = 6.02 × 10<sup>23</sup> gm mole<sup>–1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "5.5 N/m",
      "6.4 N/m",
      "7.1 N/m",
      "2.2 N/m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "7.1 N/m"
  },
  {
    "id": "wIrfCSO0LoC6EEX0BUqZP",
    "question": "An oscillator of mass M is at rest in its equilibrium position in a potential \n<br/>V = $${1 \\over 2}$$ k(x $$-$$ X)<sup>2</sup>.  A particle of mass m comes from right with speed u and collides completely inelastically with M and sticks to it.  This process repeats every time the oscillator crosses its equilibrium position. The amplitude of oscillations after 13 collisions is : (M = 10, m = 5,  u = 1,  k = 1)",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}$$",
      "$${3 \\over {\\sqrt 5 }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "hwSXkF7lcurZVhTMigBzk",
    "question": "A cylindrical plastic bottle of negligible mass is filled with 310 ml of water and left floating in a pond with still water. If pressed downward slightly and released, it starts performing simple harmonic motion at angular frequency $$\\omega $$. If the radius of the bottle is 2.5 cm then $$\\omega $$ is close to – (density of water = 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup>). ",
    "options": [
      "2.50 rad s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "3.75 rad s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "5.00 rad s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "7.90 rad s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "7.90 rad s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "R70yewfdGLHeUwBVHXqNz",
    "question": "The mass and the diameter of a planet are three times the respective values for the Earth. The period of oscillation of simple pendulum on the Earth is 2 s. The period of oscillation of the same pendulum on the planet would be : \n",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}$$ s",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$ s",
      "$${2 \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$ s",
      "$$2\\sqrt 3 $$ s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$2\\sqrt 3 $$ s"
  },
  {
    "id": "CEgJFbJzD7arRv9ZZwXQl",
    "question": "A pendulum is executing simple harmonic motion and its maximum kinetic energy is K<sub>1</sub>. If the length of the pendulum is doubled and it performs simple harmonic motion with the same amplitude as in the first case, its maximum kinetic energy is K<sub>2</sub>. Then : ",
    "options": [
      "$${K_2}$$ = $${{{K_1}} \\over 2}$$",
      "K<sub>2</sub> = 2K<sub>1</sub>",
      "K<sub>2</sub> = K<sub>1</sub>",
      "K<sub>2</sub> = $${{{K_1}} \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "K<sub>2</sub> = 2K<sub>1</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "BYsxQYSbAykOPe28jcSIQ",
    "question": "A rod of mass 'M' and length '2L' is suspended at its middle by a wire. It exhibits torsional oscillations; If two masses each of 'm' are attached at distance 'L/2' from its centre on both sides, it reduces the oscillation frequency by 20%. The value of radio m/M is close to : ",
    "options": [
      "0.77",
      "0.57",
      "0.37",
      "0.17"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "0.37"
  },
  {
    "id": "T22xjk5EZvVaBxf9n77k9k2k5kupnnb",
    "question": "A spring mass system (mass m, spring\nconstant k and natural length $$l$$) rest in\nequilibrium on a horizontal disc. The free end\nof the spring is fixed at the centre of the disc.\nIf the disc together with spring mass system,\nrotates about it's axis with an angular velocity\n$$\\omega $$, (k $$ \\gg m{\\omega ^2}$$) the relative change in the length\nof the spring is best given by the option :",
    "options": [
      "$${{m{\\omega ^2}} \\over {3k}}$$",
      "$${{m{\\omega ^2}} \\over k}$$",
      "$${{2m{\\omega ^2}} \\over k}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{2 \\over 3}} \\left( {{{m{\\omega ^2}} \\over k}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$${{m{\\omega ^2}} \\over k}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "38P6BbDb1DA1trTd3vjgy2xukf3qtlip",
    "question": "A block of mass m attached to a massless spring is performing oscillatory motion of amplitude ‘A’ on\na frictionless horizontal plane. If half of the mass of the block breaks off when it is passing through\nits equilibrium point, the amplitude of oscillation for the remaining system become fA. The value of\nf is :",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "xEV6aw10Ry8j2kpRUljgy2xukg0bbj8f",
    "question": "When a particle of mass m is attached to a vertical spring of spring constant k and released, its\nmotion is described by <br/>y(t) = y<sub>0</sub>\nsin<sup>2</sup> $$\\omega $$t, where 'y' is measured from the lower end of unstretched\nspring. Then $$\\omega $$ is:\n",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{g \\over {{y_0}}}} $$",
      "$${1 \\over 2}\\sqrt {{g \\over {{y_0}}}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{2g} \\over {{y_0}}}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{g \\over {2{y_0}}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{g \\over {2{y_0}}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "u7GYMMt9l9aVfRHUS61klrnvm02",
    "question": "The period of oscillation of a simple pendulum is $$T = 2\\pi \\sqrt {{L \\over g}} $$. Measured value of 'L' is 1.0 m from meter scale having a minimum division of 1 mm and time of one complete oscillation is 1.95 s measured from stopwatch of 0.01 s resolution. The percentage error in the determination of 'g' will be :",
    "options": [
      "1.30%",
      "1.33%",
      "1.13%",
      "1.03%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "1.13%"
  },
  {
    "id": "e8YRS1dC8UJySCKeTk1klry90x0",
    "question": "If the time period of a two meter long simple pendulum is 2s, the acceleration due to gravity at the place where pendulum is executing S.H.M. is :",
    "options": [
      "16 m/s<sup>2</sup>",
      "2$$\\pi$$<sup>2</sup><sup></sup> ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "$$\\pi$$<sup>2</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "9.8 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "2$$\\pi$$<sup>2</sup><sup></sup> ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "hD12lNb0C5ziDINBjA1klthpg5z",
    "question": "Assume that a tunnel is dug along a chord of the earth, at a perpendicular distance (R/2) from the earth's centre, where 'R' is the radius of the Earth. The wall of the tunnel is frictionless. If a particle is released in this tunnel, it will execute a simple harmonic motion with a time period :",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\pi \\sqrt {{R \\over g}} $$",
      "$${g \\over {2\\pi R}}$$",
      "$${{2\\pi R} \\over g}$$",
      "$${1 \\over {2\\pi }}\\sqrt {{g \\over R}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$2\\pi \\sqrt {{R \\over g}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZCo7nN4rxMmJbPzPGs1kltin1hk",
    "question": "If two similar springs each of spring constant K<sub>1</sub> are joined in series, the new spring constant and time period would be changed by a factor :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 2},2\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$${1 \\over 4},2\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$${1 \\over 2},\\sqrt 2 $$",
      "$${1 \\over 4},\\sqrt 2 $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2},\\sqrt 2 $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "fRNuoiDVSnesqdH7At1klunj0s9",
    "question": "Given below are two statements :<br/><br/>Statement I : A second's pendulum has a time period of 1 second.<br/><br/>Statement II : It takes precisely one second to move between the two extreme positions.<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "rCX9fIpzCJjNkEfGtf1kmhntg12",
    "question": "Time period of a simple pendulum is T inside a lift when the lift is stationary. If the lift moves upwards with an acceleration g/2, the time period of pendulum will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt 3 T$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{2 \\over 3}} T$$",
      "$${T \\over {\\sqrt 3 }}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{3 \\over 2}} T$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{2 \\over 3}} T$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "mp5rBNVEt1QwcsVSFr1kmkapnhb",
    "question": "Two particles A and B of equal masses are suspended from two massless springs of spring constants K<sub>1</sub> and K<sub>2</sub> respectively. If the maximum velocities during oscillations are equal, the ratio of the amplitude of A and B is",
    "options": [
      "$${{{K_1}} \\over {{K_2}}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{K_1}} \\over {{K_2}}}} $$",
      "$${{{K_2}} \\over {{K_1}}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{K_2}} \\over {{K_1}}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{{K_2}} \\over {{K_1}}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsvn5pi",
    "question": "T<sub>0</sub> is the time period of a simple pendulum at a place. if the length of the pendulum is reduced to $${1 \\over {16}}$$ times of its initial value, the modified time period is :",
    "options": [
      "4 T<sub>0</sub>",
      "$${1 \\over {4}}$$ T<sub>0</sub>",
      "T<sub>0</sub>",
      "8$$\\pi$$ T<sub>0</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over {4}}$$ T<sub>0</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjobzfj",
    "question": "A bob of mass 'm' suspended by a thread of length l undergoes simple harmonic oscillations with time period T. If the bob is immersed in a liquid that has density $${1 \\over 4}$$ times that of the bob and the length of the thread is increased by 1/3<sup>rd</sup> of the original length, then the time period of the simple harmonic oscillations will be :-",
    "options": [
      "T",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$T",
      "$${3 \\over 4}$$T",
      "$${4 \\over 3}$$T"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$${4 \\over 3}$$T"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57q9zaw",
    "question": "<p>The displacement of simple harmonic oscillator after 3 seconds starting from its mean position is equal to half of its amplitude. The time period of harmonic motion is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "6 s",
      "8 s",
      "12 s",
      "36 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "36 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58bke0g",
    "question": "<p>Time period of a simple pendulum in a stationary lift is 'T'. If the lift accelerates with $${g \\over 6}$$ vertically upwards then the time period will be :</p>\n<p>(Where g = acceleration due to gravity)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{6 \\over 5}} T$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{5 \\over 6}} T$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{6 \\over 7}} T$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{7 \\over 6}} T$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{6 \\over 7}} T$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbmix6",
    "question": "<p>Two massless springs with spring constants 2 k and 9 k, carry 50 g and 100 g masses at their free ends. These two masses oscillate vertically such that their maximum velocities are equal. Then, the ratio of their respective amplitudes will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 2",
      "3 : 2",
      "3 : 1",
      "2 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "3 : 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6nrcg6d",
    "question": "<p>Assume there are two identical simple pendulum clocks. Clock - 1 is placed on the earth and Clock - 2 is placed on a space station located at a height h above the earth surface. Clock - 1 and Clock - 2 operate at time periods 4 s and 6 s respectively. Then the value of h is -</p>\n<p>(consider radius of earth $$R_{E}=6400 \\mathrm{~km}$$ and $$\\mathrm{g}$$ on earth $$10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "1200 km",
      "1600 km",
      "3200 km",
      "4800 km"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "3200 km"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p4qe4d",
    "question": "<p>The time period of oscillation of a simple pendulum of length L suspended from the roof of a vehicle, which moves without friction down an inclined plane of inclination $$\\alpha$$, is given by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2 \\pi \\sqrt{\\mathrm{L} /(\\mathrm{g} \\cos \\alpha)}$$",
      "$$2 \\pi \\sqrt{\\mathrm{L} /(\\mathrm{g} \\sin \\alpha)}$$",
      "$$2 \\pi \\sqrt{\\mathrm{L} / \\mathrm{g}}$$",
      "$$2 \\pi \\sqrt{\\mathrm{L} /(\\mathrm{g} \\tan \\alpha)}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$2 \\pi \\sqrt{\\mathrm{L} /(\\mathrm{g} \\cos \\alpha)}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduh9rsm",
    "question": "<p>T is the time period of simple pendulum on the earth's surface. Its time period becomes $$x$$ T when taken to a height R (equal to earth's radius) above the earth's surface. Then, the value of $$x$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "$$\\frac{1}{2}$$",
      "2",
      "$$\\frac{1}{4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsflxsi0",
    "question": "<p>The bob of a pendulum was released from a horizontal position. The length of the pendulum is $$10 \\mathrm{~m}$$. If it dissipates $$10 \\%$$ of its initial energy against air resistance, the speed with which the bob arrives at the lowest point is:</p>\n<p>[Use, $$\\mathrm{g}: 10 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-2}$$]</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$5 \\sqrt{6} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$5 \\sqrt{5} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$2 \\sqrt{5} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$\n",
      "$$6 \\sqrt{5} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "simple-harmonic-motion",
    "topic": "some-systems-of-executing-shm",
    "solution": "$$6 \\sqrt{5} \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "vFMPNzyqwdwRNs7q",
    "question": "Identify the pair whose dimensions are equal",
    "options": [
      "torque and work",
      "stress and energy",
      "force and stress",
      "force and work"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "torque and work"
  },
  {
    "id": "07Fb9a0w1SWCOyMV",
    "question": "Dimensions of $${1 \\over {{\\mu _0}{\\varepsilon _0}}}$$, where symbols have their usual meaning, are",
    "options": [
      "[ L<sup>-1</sup>T ]",
      "[ L<sup>-2</sup>T<sup>2</sup> ]",
      "[ L<sup>2</sup>T<sup>-2</sup> ]",
      "[ LT<sup>-1</sup> ]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "[ L<sup>2</sup>T<sup>-2</sup> ]"
  },
  {
    "id": "02536sILFKVDSkVh",
    "question": "The physical quantities not having same dimensions are",
    "options": [
      "torque and work",
      "momentum and Planck's constant",
      "stress and Young's modulus",
      "speed and $${\\left( {{\\mu _0}{\\varepsilon _0}} \\right)^{ - 1/2}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "momentum and Planck's constant"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvCcEFmK67vPwsNI",
    "question": "Which one of the following represents the correct dimensions of the coefficient of viscosity?",
    "options": [
      "ML<sup>-1</sup>T<sup>-1</sup>",
      "MLT<sup>-1</sup>",
      "ML<sup>-1</sup>T<sup>-2</sup>",
      "ML<sup>-2</sup>T<sup>-2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "ML<sup>-1</sup>T<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "IBkMPPxNIloJY8cD",
    "question": "Out of the following pair, which one does NOT have identical dimensions is",
    "options": [
      "angular momentum and Planck's constant",
      "impulse and momentum",
      "moment of inertia and moment of a force",
      "work and torque"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "moment of inertia and moment of a force"
  },
  {
    "id": "vKN4F98zXejlgqUZ",
    "question": "The dimension of magnetic field in M, L, T and C (coulomb) is given as",
    "options": [
      "MLT<sup>-1</sup>C<sup>-1</sup>",
      "MT<sup>2</sup>C<sup>-2</sup>",
      "MT<sup>-1</sup>C<sup>-1</sup>",
      "MT<sup>-2</sup>C<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "MT<sup>-1</sup>C<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "JsYfxzWCG2nBVfIp",
    "question": "Let [$${\\varepsilon _0}$$] denote the dimensional formula of the permittivity of vacuum. If M = mass, L = length, T = time\nand A = electric current, then:",
    "options": [
      "$${\\varepsilon _0} = \\left[ {{M^{ - 1}}{L^{ - 3}}{T^2}A} \\right]$$",
      "$${\\varepsilon _0} = $$$$\\left[ {{M^{ - 1}}{L^{ - 3}}{T^4}{A^2}} \\right]$$",
      "$${\\varepsilon _0} = \\left[ {{M^1}{L^2}{T^1}{A^2}} \\right]$$",
      "$${\\varepsilon _0} = \\left[ {{M^1}{L^2}{T^1}A} \\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$${\\varepsilon _0} = $$$$\\left[ {{M^{ - 1}}{L^{ - 3}}{T^4}{A^2}} \\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "a0Oc15SkQSAm3RCpyzXhr",
    "question": "In the following ‘I’ refers to current and other symbols have their usual meaning.\nChoose the option that corresponds to the <sup></sup>dimensions of electrical conductivity :",
    "options": [
      "ML<sup>$$-$$3</sup> T<sup>$$-$$3</sup> I2",
      "M<sup>$$-$$1</sup> L<sup>3</sup> T<sup>3</sup> I",
      "M<sup>$$-$$1</sup> L<sup>$$-$$3</sup> T<sup>3</sup> I<sup>2</sup> ",
      "M<sup>$$-$$1</sup>  L<sup>$$-$$3</sup> T<sup>3</sup> I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "M<sup>$$-$$1</sup> L<sup>$$-$$3</sup> T<sup>3</sup> I<sup>2</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "eRl9cqE9A6KmAZfB9BBZI",
    "question": "Time (T), velocity (C) and angular momentum (h) are chosen as fundamentalquantities instead of mass, length and time. In terms of these, the dimensions of mass would be :\n",
    "options": [
      "[M] = [T<sup>$$-$$1</sup> C<sup>$$-$$2</sup> h]",
      "[M] = [T<sup>$$-$$1</sup> C<sup>2</sup> h]",
      "[M] = [T<sup>$$-$$1</sup> C<sup>$$-$$2</sup> h<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]",
      "[M] = [T C<sup>$$-$$2</sup> h]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "[M] = [T<sup>$$-$$1</sup> C<sup>$$-$$2</sup> h]"
  },
  {
    "id": "2lYPc9yvA2f6HHSJvpQTT",
    "question": "The characteristic distance at which quantum gravitational effects are significant, the Planck length, can be determined from a suitable combination of the fundamental physical constants G, h and c. <br/><br/>Which of the following correctly gives the Planck length ? ",
    "options": [
      "G $$\\hbar $$<sup>2</sup> c<sup>3</sup>",
      "G<sup>2</sup> $$\\hbar $$ c",
      "$${G^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}}}{\\hbar ^2}c$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{G\\hbar } \\over {{c^3}}}} \\right)^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$${\\left( {{{G\\hbar } \\over {{c^3}}}} \\right)^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "YjHRHYhwFh2vTu0gJtLrN",
    "question": "If speed (V), acceleration (A) and force (F) are considered as fundamental units, the dimension of Young,s modulus will be: ",
    "options": [
      "V<sup>$$-$$2</sup>A<sup>2</sup>F<sup>2</sup>",
      "V<sup>$$-$$4</sup>A<sup>$$-$$2</sup>F",
      "V<sup>$$-$$4</sup>A<sup>2</sup>F",
      "V<sup>$$-$$2</sup>A<sup>2</sup>F<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "V<sup>$$-$$4</sup>A<sup>2</sup>F"
  },
  {
    "id": "TSlvOuUar7yzKEyuix3rsa0w2w9jx3p37sc",
    "question": "Which of the following combinations has the dimension of electrical resistance ($$ \\in $$<sub>0 </sub>is the permittivity of\nvacuum and $$\\mu $$<sub>0</sub> is the permeability of vacuum)?",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{ \\in _0}} \\over {{\\mu _0}}}} $$",
      "$${{{{ \\in _0}} \\over {{\\mu _0}}}}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{\\mu _0}} \\over {{ \\in _0}}}} $$",
      "$${{{{\\mu _0}} \\over {{ \\in _0}}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{{\\mu _0}} \\over {{ \\in _0}}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "IkxrAnrmblHnX3kEXK3rsa0w2w9jwz162jd",
    "question": "In the formula X = 5YZ<sup>2</sup>\n, X and Z have dimensions of capacitance and magnetic field, respectively. What are\nthe dimensions of Y in SI units?",
    "options": [
      "[M<sup>–3</sup>L<sup>–2</sup>T<sup>8</sup>A<sup>4</sup>]",
      "[M<sup>–2</sup>L<sup>–2</sup>T<sup>6</sup>A<sup>3</sup>]",
      "[M<sup>–1</sup>L<sup>–2</sup>T<sup>4</sup>A<sup>2</sup>]",
      "[M<sup>–2</sup>L<sup>0</sup> T<sup>–4</sup>A<sup>–2</sup>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "[M<sup>–3</sup>L<sup>–2</sup>T<sup>8</sup>A<sup>4</sup>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "0DIhSkOruKebYWI5WN7Ko",
    "question": "If surface tension (S), Moment of inertia (I) and\nPlanck's constant (h), were to be taken as the\nfundamental units, the dimensional formula for\nlinear momentum would be :-",
    "options": [
      "S<sup>1/2</sup>I<sup>1/2</sup>h<sup>0</sup>",
      "S<sup>3/2</sup>I<sup>1/2</sup>h<sup>0</sup>",
      "S<sup>1/2</sup>I<sup>1/2</sup>h<sup>-1</sup>",
      "S<sup>1/2</sup>I<sup>3/2</sup>h<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "S<sup>1/2</sup>I<sup>1/2</sup>h<sup>0</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "8DDJsTM9iQCh6lkfIOp6z",
    "question": "In SI units, the dimensions of $$\\sqrt {{{{ \\in _0}} \\over {{\\mu _0}}}} $$ is :",
    "options": [
      "A<sup>–1</sup> TML<sup>3</sup>",
      "A<sup>2</sup>T<sup>3</sup>M<sup>–1</sup>L<sup>–2</sup>",
      "AT<sup>–3</sup>ML<sup>3/2</sup>",
      "AT<sup>2</sup>M<sup>–1</sup>L<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "A<sup>2</sup>T<sup>3</sup>M<sup>–1</sup>L<sup>–2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "IRnlgTEFHaETDtX47bLV4",
    "question": "Let $$\\ell $$, r, C and V represent inductance, resistance, capacitance and voltage, respectively. The dimension of $${\\ell  \\over {rCV}}$$ in SI units will be : ",
    "options": [
      "[A<sup>–1</sup>]",
      "[LTA]",
      "[LA<sup>–2</sup>]",
      "[LT<sup>2</sup>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "[A<sup>–1</sup>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "At9P01Is6s69OyEoECX4d",
    "question": "The force of interaction between two atoms is given by F = $$\\alpha $$$$\\beta $$exp $$\\left( { - {{{x^2}} \\over {\\alpha kt}}} \\right)$$;  where x is the distance, k is the Boltzmann constant and T is temperature and $$\\alpha $$ and $$\\beta $$ are two constants. The dimension of $$\\beta $$ is :",
    "options": [
      "M<sup>2</sup>L<sup>2</sup>T<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "M<sup>2</sup>LT<sup>$$-$$4</sup>",
      "MLT<sup>$$-$$4</sup>",
      "M<sup>0</sup>L<sup>2</sup>LT<sup>$$-$$4</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "M<sup>2</sup>LT<sup>$$-$$4</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "f9L3qCp6iK7QkgvEWnmj6",
    "question": "Expression for time in terms of G(universal gravitional constant), h (Planck constant) and c (speed of light) is proportional to : ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{{h{c^5}} \\over G}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{{c^3}} \\over {Gh}}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{Gh} \\over {{c^5}}}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{Gh} \\over {{c^3}}}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{Gh} \\over {{c^5}}}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "VvLRXRNWzR6zCBsBJt7k9k2k5gvtufp",
    "question": "The dimension of stopping potential V<sub>0</sub> in photoelectric effect in units of Planck's constant 'h', speed of light 'c' and Gravitational constant 'G' and ampere A is :",
    "options": [
      "h<sup>1/3</sup> G<sup>2/3</sup> c<sup>1/3</sup> A<sup>–1</sup>",
      "h<sup>0</sup> c<sup>5</sup> G<sup>-1</sup> A<sup>-1</sup>",
      "h<sup>2/3</sup> c<sup>5/3</sup> G<sup>1/3</sup> A<sup>–1</sup>",
      "h<sup>2</sup> G<sup>3/2</sup> c<sup>1/3</sup> A<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "h<sup>0</sup> c<sup>5</sup> G<sup>-1</sup> A<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "GziM0gxsRQMxENruUgjgy2xukfl1yz9k",
    "question": "The quantities x = $${1 \\over {\\sqrt {{\\mu _0}{\\varepsilon _0}} }}$$, y = $${E \\over B}$$ and z = $${l \\over {CR}}$$ are\n<br/>defined where C-capacitance, R-Resistance,\nl-length, E-Electric field, B-magnetic field and\n$${{\\varepsilon _0}}$$, $${{\\mu _0}}$$, - free space permittivity and permeability\nrespectively. Then :",
    "options": [
      "Only y and z have the same dimension",
      "x, y and z have the same dimension",
      "Only x and y have the same dimension",
      "Only x and z have the same dimension"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "x, y and z have the same dimension"
  },
  {
    "id": "7xGT51VK2ieW0N0ftKjgy2xukfamk105",
    "question": "A quantity x is given by $$\\left( {{{IF{v^2}} \\over {W{L^4}}}} \\right)$$ in terms of moment of inertia I, force F, velocity v, work W and\nLength L. The dimensional formula for x is same as that of :\n",
    "options": [
      "Coefficient of viscosity",
      "Force constant",
      "Energy density",
      "Planck's constant"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "Energy density"
  },
  {
    "id": "tKdPgxYEygdJoj7jfFjgy2xukf6j18rx",
    "question": "Dimensional formula for thermal conductivity is (here K denotes the temperature):",
    "options": [
      "MLT<sup>–3</sup>K<sup>–1</sup>",
      "MLT<sup>–2</sup>K<sup>–2</sup>",
      "MLT<sup>–2</sup>K",
      "MLT<sup>–3</sup>K"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "MLT<sup>–3</sup>K<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Bhfm22BXwbX94LoLY9jgy2xukf3rah8p",
    "question": "Amount of solar energy received on the earth’s surface per unit area per unit time is defined a solar\nconstant. Dimension of solar constant is :",
    "options": [
      "MLT<sup>–2</sup>",
      "ML<sup>0</sup>T<sup>–3</sup> ",
      "M<sup>2</sup>L<sup>0</sup>T<sup>–1</sup>",
      "ML<sup>2</sup>T<sup>–2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "ML<sup>0</sup>T<sup>–3</sup> "
  },
  {
    "id": "nS9LaEzHUKxeuFS3z1jgy2xukexsdb2t",
    "question": "If momentum (P), area (A) and time (T) are\ntaken to be the fundamental quantities then the\ndimensional formula for energy is",
    "options": [
      "[P<sup>2</sup>AT<sup>–2</sup>]",
      "$$\\left[ {{P^{{1 \\over 2}}}A{T^{ - 1}}} \\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[ {P{A^{{1 \\over 2}}}{T^{ - 1}}} \\right]$$",
      "[PA<sup>–1</sup>T<sup>–2</sup>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\left[ {P{A^{{1 \\over 2}}}{T^{ - 1}}} \\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "n5mZ89v3oYDnfYyg0Ujgy2xukev18nyc",
    "question": "If speed V, area A and force F are chosen as\nfundamental units, then the dimension of\nYoung’s modulus will be",
    "options": [
      "FA<sup>–1</sup>V<sup>0</sup>",
      "FA<sup>2</sup>V<sup>–1</sup>",
      "FA<sup>2</sup>V<sup>–2</sup>",
      "FA<sup>2</sup>V<sup>–3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "FA<sup>–1</sup>V<sup>0</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "qPVBPF82REXPyKsffg7k9k2k5i6hb7m",
    "question": "A quantity f is given by $$f = \\sqrt {{{h{c^5}} \\over G}} $$ where c is\nspeed of light, G universal gravitational\nconstant and h is the Planck's constant.\nDimension of f is that of :",
    "options": [
      "Energy",
      "Momentum",
      "Area",
      "Volume"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "Energy"
  },
  {
    "id": "xEjU6Vvvmxsi4oBcxp7k9k2k5farxr8",
    "question": "The dimension of $${{{B^2}} \\over {2{\\mu _0}}}$$, where B is magnetic field and $${{\\mu _0}}$$\n is the magnetic permeability of vacuum,\nis :",
    "options": [
      "ML<sup>2</sup>T<sup>–2</sup>",
      "MLT<sup>–2</sup>",
      "ML<sup>-1</sup>T<sup>–2</sup>",
      "ML<sup>2</sup>T<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "ML<sup>-1</sup>T<sup>–2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "wkrPtWXp8dheOeww7O1klri6brz",
    "question": "The work done by a gas molecule in an isolated system is <br/><br/>given by, $$W = \\alpha {\\beta ^2}{e^{ - {{{x^2}} \\over {\\alpha kT}}}}$$, where x is the displacement, k is the Boltzmann constant and T is the temperature. $$\\alpha$$ and $$\\beta$$ are constants. Then the dimensions of $$\\beta$$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$[{M^0}L{T^0}]$$",
      "$$[M{L^2}{T^{ - 2}}]$$",
      "$$[ML{T^{ - 2}}]$$",
      "$$[{M^2}L{T^2}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$[ML{T^{ - 2}}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "uInD6uieRdDlLVE1Vj1klrx8pev",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II :<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>h (Planck's constant)</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>$$[ML{T^{ - 1}}]$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>E (kinetic energy)</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>$$[M{L^2}{T^{ - 1}}]$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>V (electric potential)</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>$$[M{L^2}{T^{ - 2}}]$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>P (linear momentum)</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>$$[M{L^2}{I^{ - 1}}{T^{ - 3}}]$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (i)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (i), (b) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (iii)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (i)",
      "(a) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (c) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (d) $$ \\to $$ (i)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "(a) $$ \\to $$ (ii), (b) $$ \\to $$ (iii), (c) $$ \\to $$ (iv), (d) $$ \\to $$ (i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "NTDwUXVnzYf9Vp17zd1klt344f5",
    "question": "If e is the electronic charge, c is the speed of light in free space and h is Planck's constant, the quantity $${1 \\over {4\\pi {\\varepsilon _0}}}{{|e{|^2}} \\over {hc}}$$ has dimensions of :",
    "options": [
      "$$[ML{T^{ - 1}}]$$",
      "$$[ML{T^0}]$$",
      "$$[{M^0}{L^0}{T^0}]$$",
      "$$[L{C^{ - 1}}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$[{M^0}{L^0}{T^0}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Wgp580uhw4Gc7CC3Si1kltil3pw",
    "question": "In a typical combustion engine the workdone by a gas molecule is given by $$W = {\\alpha ^2}\\beta {e^{{{ - \\beta {x^2}} \\over {kT}}}}$$, where x is the displacement, k is the Boltzmann constant and T is the temperature. If $$\\alpha$$ and $$\\beta$$ are constants, dimensions of $$\\alpha$$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$[{M^0}L{T^0}]$$",
      "$$[ML{T^{ - 1}}]$$",
      "$$[ML{T^{ - 2}}]$$",
      "$$[{M^2}L{T^{ - 2}}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$[{M^0}L{T^0}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "11GkXBqmyuMqTqOwvf1kluld119",
    "question": "If 'C' and 'V' represent capacity and voltage respectively then what are the dimensions of $$\\lambda$$ where C/V = $$\\lambda$$ ?",
    "options": [
      "$$[{M^{ - 3}}{L^{ - 4}}{I^3}{T^7}]$$",
      "$$[{M^{ - 2}}{L^{ - 3}}{I^2}{T^6}]$$",
      "$$[{M^{ - 2}}{L^{ - 4}}{I^3}{T^7}]$$",
      "$$[{M^{ - 1}}{L^{ - 3}}{I^{ - 2}}{T^{ - 7}}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$[{M^{ - 2}}{L^{ - 4}}{I^3}{T^7}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqco49l",
    "question": "If time (t), velocity (v), and angular momentum (l) are taken as the fundamental units. Then the dimension of mass (m) in terms of t, v and l is :",
    "options": [
      "$$[{t^{ - 1}}{v^1}{l^{ - 2}}]$$",
      "$$[{t^1}{v^2}{l^{ - 1}}]$$",
      "$$[{t^{ - 2}}{v^{ - 1}}{l^1}]$$",
      "$$[{t^{ - 1}}{v^{ - 2}}{l^1}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$[{t^{ - 1}}{v^{ - 2}}{l^1}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krw9mhlm",
    "question": "The force is given in terms of time t and displacement x by the equation <br/><br/>F = A cos Bx + C sin Dt<br/><br/>The dimensional formula of $${{AD} \\over B}$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$$[{M^0}L{T^{ - 1}}]$$",
      "$$[M{L^2}{T^{ - 3}}]$$",
      "$$[{M^1}{L^1}{T^{ - 2}}]$$",
      "$$[{M^2}{L^2}{T^{ - 3}}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$[M{L^2}{T^{ - 3}}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktafapj6",
    "question": "If E, L, M and G denote the quantities as energy, angular momentum, mass and constant of gravitation respectively, then the dimensions of P in the formula P = EL<sup>2</sup>M<sup>$$-$$5</sup>G<sup>$$-$$2</sup> are : ",
    "options": [
      "[M<sup>0</sup> L<sup>1</sup> T<sup>0</sup>]",
      "[M<sup>$$-$$1</sup> L<sup>$$-$$1</sup> T<sup>2</sup>]",
      "[M<sup>1</sup> L<sup>1</sup> T<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]",
      "[M<sup>0</sup> L<sup>0</sup> T<sup>0</sup>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "[M<sup>0</sup> L<sup>0</sup> T<sup>0</sup>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktdyiybr",
    "question": "Which of the following is not a dimensionless quantity?",
    "options": [
      "Relative magnetic permeability ($$\\mu$$<sub>r</sub>)",
      "Power factor",
      "Permeability of free space ($$\\mu$$<sub>0</sub>)",
      "Quality factor"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "Permeability of free space ($$\\mu$$<sub>0</sub>)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfmwreu",
    "question": "If force (F), length (L) and time (T) are taken as the fundamental quantities. Then what will be the dimension of density :",
    "options": [
      "[FL<sup>$$-$$4</sup>T<sup>2</sup>]",
      "[FL<sup>$$-$$3</sup>T<sup>2</sup>]",
      "[FL<sup>$$-$$5</sup>T<sup>2</sup>]",
      "[FL<sup>$$-$$3</sup>T<sup>3</sup>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "[FL<sup>$$-$$4</sup>T<sup>2</sup>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth4i2zc",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>Torque</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>MLT$$^{ - 1}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>Impulse</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>MT$$^{ - 2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>Tension</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>ML$$^{ 2}$$T$$^{ - 2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>Surface Tension</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>MLT$$^{ - 2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the option given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(i), (b)-(iii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(iv), (c)-(i), (d)-(ii)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(i), (c)-(iv), (d)-(ii)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kth50gxo",
    "question": "Which of the following equations is dimensionally incorrect?<br/><br/>Where t = time, h = height, s = surface tension, $$\\theta$$ = angle, $$\\rho$$ = density, a, r = radius, g = acceleration due to gravity, v = volume, p = pressure, W = work done, T = torque, $$\\in$$ = permittivity, E = electric field, J = current density, L = length.",
    "options": [
      "$$v = {{\\pi p{a^4}} \\over {8\\eta L}}$$",
      "$$h = {{2s\\cos \\theta } \\over {\\rho rg}}$$",
      "$$J =  \\in {{\\partial E} \\over {\\partial t}}$$",
      "$$W = \\Gamma \\theta $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$v = {{\\pi p{a^4}} \\over {8\\eta L}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjoqnm5",
    "question": "If velocity [V], time [T] and force [F] are chosen as the base quantities, the dimensions of the mass will be :",
    "options": [
      "[FT<sup>$$-$$1</sup> V<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]",
      "[FTV<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]",
      "[FT<sup>2</sup> V]",
      "[FVT<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "[FTV<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56ucya7",
    "question": "<p>The SI unit of a physical quantity is pascal-second. The dimensional formula of this quantity will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "[ML<sup>$$-$$1</sup>T<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]",
      "[ML<sup>$$-$$1</sup>T<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]",
      "[ML<sup>2</sup>T<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]",
      "[M<sup>$$-$$1</sup>L<sup>3</sup>T<sup>0</sup>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "[ML<sup>$$-$$1</sup>T<sup>$$-$$1</sup>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58b9vrj",
    "question": "<p>An expression for a dimensionless quantity P is given by $$P = {\\alpha  \\over \\beta }{\\log _e}\\left( {{{kt} \\over {\\beta x}}} \\right)$$; where $$\\alpha$$ and $$\\beta$$ are constants, x is distance; k is Boltzmann constant and t is the temperature. Then the dimensions of $$\\alpha$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "[M<sup>0</sup> L<sup>$$-$$1</sup> T<sup>0</sup>]",
      "[M L<sup>0</sup> T<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]",
      "[M L T<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]",
      "[M L<sup>2</sup> T<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "[M L T<sup>$$-$$2</sup>]"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58h9trw",
    "question": "<p>The dimension of mutual inductance is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$[M{L^2}{T^{ - 2}}{A^{ - 1}}]$$",
      "$$[M{L^2}{T^{ - 3}}{A^{ - 1}}]$$",
      "$$[M{L^2}{T^{ - 2}}{A^{ - 2}}]$$",
      "$$[M{L^2}{T^{ - 3}}{A^{ - 2}}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$[M{L^2}{T^{ - 2}}{A^{ - 2}}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bbdwo9",
    "question": "<p>Identify the pair of physical quantities that have same dimensions:</p>",
    "options": [
      "velocity gradient and decay constant",
      "Wien's constant and Stefan constant",
      "angular frequency and angular momentum",
      "wave number and Avogadro number"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "velocity gradient and decay constant"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c2rikj",
    "question": "<p>Identify the pair of physical quantities which have different dimensions:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Wave number and Rydberg's constant",
      "Stress and Coefficient of elasticity",
      "Coercivity and Magnetisation",
      "Specific heat capacity and Latent heat"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "Specific heat capacity and Latent heat"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dxrj4z",
    "question": "<p>If momentum [P], area $$[\\mathrm{A}]$$ and time $$[\\mathrm{T}]$$ are taken as fundamental quantities, then the dimensional formula for coefficient of viscosity is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{P} \\,\\mathrm{A}^{-1} \\mathrm{~T}^{0}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{P} \\,\\mathrm{A}\\mathrm{~T}^{-1}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{P}\\,\\mathrm{A}^{-1} \\mathrm{~T}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{P} \\,\\mathrm{A}^{-1} \\mathrm{~T}^{-1}\\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{P} \\,\\mathrm{A}^{-1} \\mathrm{~T}^{0}\\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6km9t7o",
    "question": "<p>An expression of energy density is given by $$u=\\frac{\\alpha}{\\beta} \\sin \\left(\\frac{\\alpha x}{k t}\\right)$$, where $$\\alpha, \\beta$$ are constants, $$x$$ is displacement, $$k$$ is Boltzmann constant and t is the temperature. The dimensions of $$\\beta$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^{2} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2} \\theta^{-1}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^{0} \\mathrm{~L}^{2} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^{0} \\mathrm{~L}^{0} \\mathrm{~T}^{0}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^{0} \\mathrm{~L}^{2} \\mathrm{~T}^{0}\\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^{0} \\mathrm{~L}^{2} \\mathrm{~T}^{0}\\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6m9lzq0",
    "question": "<p>The dimensions of $$\\left(\\frac{\\mathrm{B}^{2}}{\\mu_{0}}\\right)$$ will be :</p>\n<p>(if $$\\mu_{0}$$ : permeability of free space and $$B$$ : magnetic field)</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}\\, \\mathrm{L}^2 \\,\\mathrm{T}^{-2}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\,\\mathrm{L} \\,\\mathrm{T}^{-2}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\,\\mathrm{L}^{-1} \\,\\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\,\\mathrm{L}^{2} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2} \\mathrm{~A}^{-1}\\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\,\\mathrm{L}^{-1} \\,\\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6npvqpp",
    "question": "<p>Consider the efficiency of carnot's engine is given by $$\\eta=\\frac{\\alpha \\beta}{\\sin \\theta} \\log_e \\frac{\\beta x}{k T}$$, where $$\\alpha$$ and $$\\beta$$ are constants. If T is temperature, k is Boltzmann constant, $$\\theta$$ is angular displacement and x has the dimensions of length. Then, choose the incorrect option :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Dimensions of $$\\beta$$ is same as that of force.",
      "Dimensions of $$\\alpha^{-1} x$$ is same as that of energy.",
      "Dimensions of $$\\eta^{-1} \\sin \\theta$$ is same as that of $$\\alpha \\beta$$.",
      "Dimensions of $$\\alpha$$ is same as that of $$\\beta$$."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "Dimensions of $$\\alpha$$ is same as that of $$\\beta$$."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p3y0nm",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : One is labelled as Assertion (A) and other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : Time period of oscillation of a liquid drop depends on surface tension (S), if density of the liquid is $$\\rho$$ and radius of the drop is r, then $$\\mathrm{T}=\\mathrm{K} \\sqrt{\\rho \\mathrm{r}^{3} / \\mathrm{S}^{3 / 2}}$$ is dimensionally correct, where K is dimensionless.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : Using dimensional analysis we get R.H.S. having different dimension than that of time period.</p>\n<p>In the light of above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are true but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "(A) is false but (R) is true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldnwsfpv",
    "question": "<p>If the velocity of light $$\\mathrm{c}$$, universal gravitational constant $$\\mathrm{G}$$ and Planck's constant $$\\mathrm{h}$$ are chosen as fundamental quantities. The dimensions of mass in the new system is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{h}^{1} \\mathrm{c}^{1} \\mathrm{G}^{-1}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{h}^{-1 / 2} \\mathrm{c}^{1 / 2} \\mathrm{G}^{1 / 2}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{h}^{1 / 2} \\mathrm{c}^{1 / 2} \\mathrm{G}^{-1 / 2}\\right]$$",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{h}^{1 / 2} \\mathrm{c}^{-1 / 2} \\mathrm{G}^{1}\\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{h}^{1 / 2} \\mathrm{c}^{1 / 2} \\mathrm{G}^{-1 / 2}\\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldo74ikz",
    "question": "Match List <b>I</b> with List <b>II</b><br/><br/>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\" colspan=\"2\"> LIST I </th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\" colspan=\"2\"> LIST II </th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Angular momentum</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^{2} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Torque</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^{-2} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Stress</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^{2} \\mathrm{~T}^{-1}\\right]$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Pressure gradient</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^{-1} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below: ",
    "options": [
      "A - I, B - IV, C - III, D - II",
      "A - III, B - I, C - IV, D - II",
      "A - IV, B - II, C - I, D - III",
      "A - II, B - III, C - IV, D - I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "A - III, B - I, C - IV, D - II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lds9liqj",
    "question": "<p>The equation of a circle is given by $$x^2+y^2=a^2$$, where a is the radius. If the equation is modified to change the origin other than (0, 0), then find out the correct dimensions of A and B in a new equation : $${(x - At)^2} + {\\left( {y - {t \\over B}} \\right)^2} = {a^2}$$. The dimensions of t is given as $$[\\mathrm{T^{-1}]}$$.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{A=[L^{-1}T^{-1}],B=[LT^{-1}]}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{A=[L^{-1}T^{-1}],B=[LT]}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{A=[LT],B=[L^{-1}T^{-1}]}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{A=[L^{-1}T],B=[LT^{-1}]}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{A=[LT],B=[L^{-1}T^{-1}]}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsp679n",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II :</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 614px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 47px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 199px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 316px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List I (Physical Quantity)</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List II (Dimensional Formula)</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Pressure gradient</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^{\\circ} \\mathrm{L}^{2} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Energy density</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^{1} \\mathrm{L}^{-1} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Electric Field</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^{1} \\mathrm{L}^{-2} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Latent heat</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^{1} \\mathrm{~L}^{1} \\mathrm{~T}^{-3} \\mathrm{~A}^{-1}\\right]$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "A-III, B-II, C-IV, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldtyxe4z",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 669px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 249px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Young's Modulus (Y)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[ML^{-1}T^{-1}]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Co-efficient of Viscosity ($$\\eta$$)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[ML^2T^{-1}]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Planck's Constant (h)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[ML^{-1}T^{-2}]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Work function ($$\\varphi $$)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[ML^2T^{-2}]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-III, C-IV, D-I",
      "A-I, B-II, C-III, D-IV",
      "A-I, B-III, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldyef9zw",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 668px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 50px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 248px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 45px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 325px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List-I<br/></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List-II<br/></th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Planck's constant (h)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[{M^1}\\,{L^2}\\,{T^{ - 2}}]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Stopping potential (Vs)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[{M^1}\\,{L^1}\\,{T^{ - 1}}]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Work function ($$\\phi$$)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[{M^1}\\,{L^2}\\,{T^{ - 1}}]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Momentum (p)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[{M^1}\\,{L^2}\\,{T^{ - 3}}\\,{A^{ - 1}}]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-III, C-IV, D-II",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-III, D-I",
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnyfjcm",
    "question": "The speed of a wave produced in water is given by $v=\\lambda^{a} g^{b} \\rho^{c}$. Where $\\lambda, g$ and $\\rho$ are wavelength of wave, acceleration due to gravity and density of water respectively. The values of $a, b$ and $c$ respectively, are :",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{1}{2}, 0, \\frac{1}{2}$",
      "$1,1,0$",
      "$1,-1,0$",
      "$\\frac{1}{2}, \\frac{1}{2}, 0$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$\\frac{1}{2}, \\frac{1}{2}, 0$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgoyia4x",
    "question": "<p>In the equation $$\\left[X+\\frac{a}{Y^{2}}\\right][Y-b]=\\mathrm{R} T, X$$ is pressure, $$Y$$ is volume, $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is universal gas constant and $$T$$ is temperature. The physical quantity equivalent to the ratio $$\\frac{a}{b}$$ is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Impulse",
      "Energy",
      "Pressure gradient",
      "Coefficient of viscosity"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "Energy"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsx9rki",
    "question": "<p>If force (F), velocity (V) and time (T) are considered as fundamental physical quantity, then dimensional formula of density will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{FV}^{-2} \\mathrm{~T}^{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{FV}^{4} \\mathrm{~T}^{-6}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{F}^{2} \\mathrm{~V}^{-2} \\mathrm{~T}^{6}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{FV}^{-4} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{FV}^{-4} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh00yauq",
    "question": "<p>Dimension of $$\\frac{1}{\\mu_{0} \\in_{0}}$$ should be equal to</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{T}^{2} / \\mathrm{L}^{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{T} / \\mathrm{L}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{L}^{2} / \\mathrm{T}^{2}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{L} / \\mathrm{T}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{L}^{2} / \\mathrm{T}^{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbknus1",
    "question": "The dimensional formula of angular impulse is :",
    "options": [
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$",
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^{-2} \\mathrm{~T}^{-1}\\right]$",
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-1}\\right]$",
      "$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L} \\mathrm{T}^{-1}\\right]$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-1}\\right]$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsc3tnnj",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement (I) : Planck's constant and angular momentum have same dimensions.</p>\n<p>Statement (II) : Linear momentum and moment of force have same dimensions.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd5ibjj",
    "question": "<p>Consider two physical quantities $$A$$ and $$B$$ related to each other as $$E=\\frac{B-x^2}{A t}$$ where $$E, x$$ and $$t$$ have dimensions of energy, length and time respectively. The dimension of $$A B$$ is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$L^{-2} M^1 T^0$$\n",
      "$$L^2 M^{-1} T^1$$\n",
      "$$L^0 M^{-1} T^1$$\n",
      "$$L^{-2} M^{-1} T^1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$L^2 M^{-1} T^1$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse6mdlu",
    "question": "<p>A force is represented by $$F=a x^2+b t^{\\frac{1}{2}}$$</p>\n<p>where $$x=$$ distance and $$t=$$ time. The dimensions of $$b^2 / a$$ are:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-3}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^3 \\mathrm{~T}^{-3}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[M L T^{-2}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[M L^{-1} T^{-1}\\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^3 \\mathrm{~T}^{-3}\\right]$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg6udgl",
    "question": "<p>If mass is written as $$m=k \\mathrm{c}^{\\mathrm{P}} G^{-1 / 2} h^{1 / 2}$$ then the value of $$P$$ will be : (Constants have their usual meaning with $k a$ dimensionless constant)</p>",
    "options": [
      "1/3",
      "$$-$$1/3",
      "1/2",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "1/2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgdjves",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 687px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 70px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 245px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 94px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 278px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(A)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Coefficient of viscosity</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(I)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(B)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Surface tension</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(II)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-1}\\right]$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(C)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Angular momentum</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(III)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^{-1} \\mathrm{~T}^{-1}\\right]$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(D)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Rotational kinetic energy</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">(IV)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\left[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^0 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(III)\n",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(II), (C)-(III), (D)-(IV)\n",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)\n",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)"
  },
  {
    "id": "luxwd2ms",
    "question": "<p>The de-Broglie wavelength associated with a particle of mass $$m$$ and energy $$E$$ is $$h / \\sqrt{2 m E}$$. The dimensional formula for Planck's constant is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^2 \\mathrm{~L}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^{-1} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-1}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{MLT}^{-2}\\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-1}\\right]$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "luy9clxz",
    "question": "<p>The dimensional formula of latent heat is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^{\\mathrm{0}} \\mathrm{LT}^{-2}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{MLT}^{-2}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^0 \\mathrm{~L}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$\n",
      "$$\\left[\\mathrm{ML}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$\\left[\\mathrm{M}^0 \\mathrm{~L}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}\\right]$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxm6r",
    "question": "<p>The equation of stationary wave is :</p>\n<p>$$y=2 \\mathrm{a} \\sin \\left(\\frac{2 \\pi \\mathrm{nt}}{\\lambda}\\right) \\cos \\left(\\frac{2 \\pi x}{\\lambda}\\right) \\text {. }$$</p>\n<p>Which of the following is NOT correct :</p>",
    "options": [
      "The dimensions of $$\\mathrm{nt}$$ is [L]\n",
      "The dimensions of $$n$$ is $$[\\mathrm{LT}^{-1}]$$\n",
      "The dimensions of $$x$$ is [L]\n",
      "The dimensions of $$n / \\lambda$$ is [T]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "The dimensions of $$n / \\lambda$$ is [T]"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2es2kt",
    "question": "<p>Applying the principle of homogeneity of dimensions, determine which one is correct,\nwhere $$T$$ is time period, $$G$$ is gravitational constant, $$M$$ is mass, $$r$$ is radius of orbit.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$T^2=\\frac{4 \\pi^2 r}{G M^2}$$\n",
      "$$T^2=4 \\pi^2 r^3$$\n",
      "$$T^2=\\frac{4 \\pi^2 r^3}{G M}$$\n",
      "$$T^2=\\frac{4 \\pi^2 r^2}{G M}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$T^2=\\frac{4 \\pi^2 r^3}{G M}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3ve84f",
    "question": "<p>If $$\\epsilon_{\\mathrm{o}}$$ is the permittivity of free space and $$\\mathrm{E}$$ is the electric field, then $$\\epsilon_{\\mathrm{o}} \\mathrm{E}^2$$ has the dimensions :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^{-1} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}]$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}]$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{M}^{\\mathrm{0}} \\mathrm{L}^{-2} \\mathrm{TA}]$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{M}^{-1} \\mathrm{~L}^{-3} \\mathrm{~T}^4 \\mathrm{~A}^2]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$[\\mathrm{M} \\mathrm{L}^{-1} \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}]$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s20rh",
    "question": "<p>What is the dimensional formula of $$a b^{-1}$$ in the equation $$\\left(\\mathrm{P}+\\frac{\\mathrm{a}}{\\mathrm{V}^2}\\right)(\\mathrm{V}-\\mathrm{b})=\\mathrm{RT}$$, where letters have their usual meaning.</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$[\\mathrm{M}^6 \\mathrm{~L}^7 \\mathrm{~T}^4]$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{M}^{-1} \\mathrm{~L}^5 \\mathrm{~T}^3]$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{M}^0 \\mathrm{~L}^3 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}]$$\n",
      "$$[\\mathrm{ML}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$[\\mathrm{ML}^2 \\mathrm{~T}^{-2}]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57i1o",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 690px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 239px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 75px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 301px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Torque</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\left[M^1 L^1 T^{-2} A^{-2}\\right]<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.\t</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Magnetic field</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\left[L^2 A^1\\right]<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Magnetic moment</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\left[M^1 T^{-2} A^{-1}\\right]<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Permeability of free space</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$<br/>\\left[M^1 L^2 T^{-2}\\right]<br/>$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-I, B-III, C-II, D-IV\n",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-III, D-I\n",
      "A-III, B-I, C-II, D-IV\n",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "dimensions-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "A-IV, B-III, C-II, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "bG5J7nFuAXdARcvv",
    "question": "A body of mass m = 3.513 kg is moving along the x-axis with a speed of 5.00 ms<sup>−1</sup>. The magnitude of its momentum is recorded as",
    "options": [
      "17.6 kg ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "17.565 kg ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "17.56 kg ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "17.57 kg ms<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "17.6 kg ms<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "QJ0Wnabg6uWRis74",
    "question": "The respective number of significant figures for the numbers 23.023, 0.0003 and 2.1 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>–3</sup> are",
    "options": [
      "5, 1, 2",
      "5, 1, 5",
      "5, 5, 2",
      "4, 4, 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "5, 1, 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1WO1uKabShEMiYbW",
    "question": "Resistance of a given wire is obtained by measuring the current flowing in it and the voltage difference\napplied across it. If the percentage errors in the measurement of the current and the voltage difference\nare 3% each, then error in the value of resistance of the wire is",
    "options": [
      "6 %",
      "zero",
      "1 %",
      "3 %"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "6 %"
  },
  {
    "id": "rNK6NSjY2AtVlzUW",
    "question": "A student measures the time period of 100 oscillations of a simple pendulum four times. The data set is 90 s, 91 s, 95 s and 92 s. If the minimum division in the measuring clock is 1 s, then the reported mean time should be :",
    "options": [
      "92 $$ \\pm $$ 1.8 s",
      "92 $$ \\pm $$ 3 s",
      "92 $$ \\pm $$ 2 s",
      "92 $$ \\pm $$ 5.0 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "92 $$ \\pm $$ 2 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "WIwmkYyfbaRmEFOZ",
    "question": "The following observations were taken for determining surface tension T of water by capillary method:<br/>\ndiameter of capillary, D = 1.25 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup> m<br/>\nrise of water, h = 1.45 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>-2</sup>m<br/>\nUsing g = 9.80 m/s<sup>2</sup> and the simplified relation T = $${{rhg} \\over 2} \\times {10^3}N/m$$,  the possible error in surface tension is closest to :",
    "options": [
      "10 %",
      "0.15 % ",
      "1.5 %",
      "2.4 %"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "1.5 %"
  },
  {
    "id": "48SnUPA0bQRSXeluiylbq",
    "question": "A physical quantity P is described by the relation\n<br/><br/>P = a$$^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}}$$ b<sup>2</sup> c<sup>3</sup> d<sup>$$-$$4</sup>\n<br/><br/>If the relative errors in the measurement of a, b, c and d respectively, are 2%, 1%, 3% and 5%, then the relative error in P will be : ",
    "options": [
      "8%",
      "12%",
      "32%",
      "25%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "32%"
  },
  {
    "id": "JZRIaTnHbyjwerrd",
    "question": "The density of a material in the shape of a cube is determined by measuring three sides of the cube and its\nmass. If the relative errors in measuring the mass and length are respectively 1.5% and 1%, the maximum\nerror in determining the density is:",
    "options": [
      "6%",
      "2.5%",
      "3.5%",
      "4.5%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "4.5%"
  },
  {
    "id": "uNKq0YRE3wVHutE4Kphwd",
    "question": "The relative error  in the determination of the surface area of sphere is $$\\alpha $$. Then the relative error in the determination of its volume is :",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 2}\\alpha $$",
      "$${2 \\over 3}\\alpha $$",
      "$${5 \\over 2}\\alpha $$",
      "$$\\alpha $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 2}\\alpha $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "84Jq5pG4lgm5EKEka4Knz",
    "question": "The percentage errors in quantities P, Q, R and S are 0.5%, 1%, 3% and 1.5% respectively in the measurement of a physical quantity A = $${{{P^3}{Q^2}} \\over {\\sqrt R S}}.$$\n<br/><br/>The maximum percentage error in the value of A will be :",
    "options": [
      "6.0%",
      "7.5%",
      "8.5%",
      "6.5%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "6.5%"
  },
  {
    "id": "stgRK8lBApemvKm4g3YKp",
    "question": "The relative uncertainly in the period of a satellite orbiting around the earth is 10<sup>-2</sup>. If the relative uncertainty in the radius of the orbit is negligible, the relative uncertainty in the mass of the earth is : ",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup>",
      "6 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "2 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>$$-$$2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "59uIoYKOVAjaPOyoFRGtx",
    "question": "In a simple pendulum experiment for\ndetermination of acceleration due to gravity (g),\ntime taken for 20 oscillations is measured by\nusing a watch of 1 second least count. The\nmean value of time taken comes out to be\n30 s. The length of pendulum is measured by\nusing a meter scale of least count 1 mm and the\nvalue obtained is 55.0 cm. The percentage\nerror in the determination of g is close to :-",
    "options": [
      "0.2%",
      "3.5%",
      "0.7%",
      "6.8%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "6.8%"
  },
  {
    "id": "0b1VEhxv1KQTfukGKZBi0",
    "question": "The area of a square is 5.29 cm<sup>2</sup>. The area of\n7 such squares taking into account the\nsignificant figures is :-",
    "options": [
      "37.0 cm<sup>2</sup>",
      "37 cm<sup>2</sup>",
      "37.030 cm<sup>2</sup>",
      "37.03 cm<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "37.0 cm<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "O96L41Np317XvIrPuQQIp",
    "question": "In the density measurement of a cube, the mass and\nedge length are measured as (10.00 ± 0.10) kg and\n(0.10 ± 0.01) m, respectively. The error in the\nmeasurement of density is :",
    "options": [
      "0.01 kg/m<sup>3</sup>",
      "0.10 kg/m<sup>3</sup>",
      "0.31 kg/m<sup>3</sup>",
      "0.07 kg/m<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "0.31 kg/m<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "l3NOPR5ufPBk0BNChP3fB",
    "question": "The diameter and height of a cylinder are measured by a meter scale to be 12.6 $$ \\pm $$ 0.1 cm and 34.2 $$ \\pm $$ 0.1 cm, respectively. What will be the value of its volume in appropriate significant figures ? ",
    "options": [
      "4264.4 $$ \\pm $$ 81.0 cm<sup>3</sup>",
      "4264 $$ \\pm $$ 81 cm<sup>3</sup>\n",
      "4300 $$ \\pm $$ 80 cm<sup>3</sup>\n",
      "4260 $$ \\pm $$ 80 cm<sup>3</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "4260 $$ \\pm $$ 80 cm<sup>3</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "fLULH050rO7T9paNTwB92",
    "question": "A copper wire is stretched to make it 0.5% longer. The percentage change in its electrical resistance if its volume remains unchanged is : ",
    "options": [
      "2.0 %",
      "2.5 %",
      "1.0 %",
      "0.5 %"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "1.0 %"
  },
  {
    "id": "3gXwrUFQAXIKxIvf1I7k9k2k5lcx8s4",
    "question": "For the four sets of three measured physical\nquantities as given below. Which of the\nfollowing options is correct ?\n<br/>(i) A<sub>1</sub> = 24.36, B<sub>1</sub> = 0.0724, C<sub>1</sub> = 256.2\n<br/>(ii) A<sub>2</sub> = 24.44, B<sub>2</sub> = 16.082, C<sub>2</sub> = 240.2\n<br/>(iii) A<sub>3</sub> = 25.2, B<sub>3</sub> = 19.2812, C<sub>3</sub> = 236.183\n<br/>(iv) A<sub>4</sub> = 25, B<sub>4</sub> = 236.191, C<sub>4</sub> = 19.5",
    "options": [
      "A<sub>1</sub> + B<sub>1</sub> + C<sub>1</sub> = A<sub>2</sub> + B<sub>2</sub> + C<sub>2</sub> = A<sub>3</sub> + B<sub>3</sub> + C<sub>3</sub>\n= A<sub>4</sub> + B<sub>4</sub> + C<sub>4</sub>",
      "A<sub>4</sub> + B<sub>4</sub> + C<sub>4</sub> $$ &lt; $$ A<sub>1</sub> + B<sub>1</sub> + C<sub>1</sub> $$ &lt; $$ A<sub>3</sub> + B<sub>3</sub> + C<sub>3</sub>\n$$ &lt; $$ A<sub>2</sub> + B<sub>2</sub> + C<sub>2</sub>",
      "A<sub>4</sub> + B<sub>4</sub> + C<sub>4</sub> $$ &lt; $$ A<sub>1</sub> + B<sub>1</sub> + C<sub>1</sub> = A<sub>2</sub> + B<sub>2</sub> + C<sub>2</sub>\n= A<sub>3</sub> + B<sub>3</sub> + C<sub>3</sub>",
      "A<sub>4</sub> + B<sub>4</sub> + C<sub>4</sub> $$ &gt; $$ A<sub>3</sub> + B<sub>3</sub> + C<sub>3</sub> = A<sub>2</sub> + B<sub>2</sub> + C<sub>2</sub> $$ &gt; $$\nA<sub>1</sub> + B<sub>1</sub> + C<sub>1</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "A<sub>4</sub> + B<sub>4</sub> + C<sub>4</sub> $$ &gt; $$ A<sub>3</sub> + B<sub>3</sub> + C<sub>3</sub> = A<sub>2</sub> + B<sub>2</sub> + C<sub>2</sub> $$ &gt; $$\nA<sub>1</sub> + B<sub>1</sub> + C<sub>1</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "056s5ywj58ztHQUNRLjgy2xukfg6crhx",
    "question": "A physical quantity z depends on four\nobservables <br/>a, b, c and d, as z = $${{{a^2}{b^{{2 \\over 3}}}} \\over {\\sqrt c {d^3}}}$$. The\npercentages of error in the measurement of a,\nb, c and d are 2%, 1.5%, 4% and 2.5%\nrespectively. The percentage of error in z is :",
    "options": [
      "13.5 %",
      "14.5%",
      "16.5%",
      "12.25%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "14.5%"
  },
  {
    "id": "6KPZcoU8UJSSsYtZXq1kmipb8hp",
    "question": "In order to determine the Young's Modulus of a wire of radius 0.2 cm (measured using a scale of least count = 0.001 cm) and length 1m (measured using a scale of least count = 1 mm), a weight of mass 1 kg (measured using a scale of least count = 1 g) was hanged to get the elongation of 0.5 cm (measured using a scale of least count 0.001 cm). What will be the fractional error in the value of Young's Modulus determined by this experiment?",
    "options": [
      "0.14%",
      "9%",
      "1.4%",
      "0.9%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "1.4%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks18vtz1",
    "question": "A physical quantity 'y' is represented by the formula $$y = {m^2}{r^{ - 4}}{g^x}{l^{ - {3 \\over 2}}}$$<br/><br/>If the percentage errors found in y, m, r, l and g are 18, 1, 0.5, 4 and p respectively, then find the value of x and p.",
    "options": [
      "5 and $$\\pm$$2",
      "4 and $$\\pm$$3",
      "$${{16} \\over 3}$$ and $$ \\pm {3 \\over 2}$$",
      "8 and $$\\pm$$ 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "$${{16} \\over 3}$$ and $$ \\pm {3 \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktbrll2z",
    "question": "If the length of the pendulum in pendulum clock increases by 0.1%, then the error in time per day is :",
    "options": [
      "86.4 s",
      "4.32 s",
      "43.2 s",
      "8.64 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "43.2 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktmo4lfv",
    "question": "A student determined Young's Modulus of elasticity using the formula $$Y = {{Mg{L^3}} \\over {4b{d^3}\\delta }}$$. The value of g is taken to be 9.8 m/s<sup>2</sup>, without any significant error, his observation are as following.<br/><br/><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;width:100%}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">Physical<br/>Quantity</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Least count of the</span><br/><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">Equipment used</span><br/><span style=\"font-weight:bold\">for measurement</span></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"><br/>Observed value</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">Mass (M)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">1 g</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">2 kg</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">Length of bar (L)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">1 mm</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">1 m</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">Breadth of bar (b)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">0.1 mm</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">4 cm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">Thickness of bar (d)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">0.01 mm</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">0.4 cm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">Depression ($$\\delta $$)</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">0.01 mm</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">5 mm</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>Then the fractional error in the measurement of Y is :",
    "options": [
      "0.0083",
      "0.0155",
      "0.155",
      "0.083"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "0.0155"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57ph8j3",
    "question": "<p>A silver wire has a mass (0.6 $$\\pm$$ 0.006) g, radius (0.5 $$\\pm$$ 0.005) mm and length (4 $$\\pm$$ 0.04) cm. The maximum percentage error in the measurement of its density will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4%",
      "3%",
      "6%",
      "7%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "4%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5ak50l1",
    "question": "<p>If $$Z = {{{A^2}{B^3}} \\over {{C^4}}}$$, then the relative error in Z will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\Delta A} \\over A} + {{\\Delta B} \\over B} + {{\\Delta C} \\over C}$$",
      "$${{2\\Delta A} \\over A} + {{3\\Delta B} \\over B} - {{4\\Delta C} \\over C}$$",
      "$${{2\\Delta A} \\over A} + {{3\\Delta B} \\over B} + {{4\\Delta C} \\over C}$$",
      "$${{\\Delta A} \\over A} + {{\\Delta B} \\over B} - {{\\Delta C} \\over C}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "$${{2\\Delta A} \\over A} + {{3\\Delta B} \\over B} + {{4\\Delta C} \\over C}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f5b6sd",
    "question": "<p>The maximum error in the measurement of resistance, current and time for which current flows in an electrical circuit are $$1 \\%, 2 \\%$$ and $$3 \\%$$ respectively. The\nmaximum percentage error in the detection of the dissipated heat will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "4",
      "6",
      "8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "8"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jepz9i",
    "question": "<p>A torque meter is calibrated to reference standards of mass, length and time each with $$5 \\%$$ accuracy. After calibration, the measured torque with this torque meter will have net accuracy of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "15%",
      "25%",
      "75%",
      "5%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "25%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq2s5sc",
    "question": "<p>A body of mass $$(5 \\pm 0.5) ~\\mathrm{kg}$$ is moving with a velocity of $$(20 \\pm 0.4) ~\\mathrm{m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. Its kinetic energy will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$(1000 \\pm 140) ~\\mathrm{J}$$",
      "$$(500 \\pm 0.14) ~\\mathrm{J}$$",
      "$$(1000 \\pm 0.14) ~\\mathrm{J}$$",
      "$$(500 \\pm 140) ~\\mathrm{J}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "$$(1000 \\pm 140) ~\\mathrm{J}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgxwqesk",
    "question": "<p>A physical quantity P is given as</p>\n<p>$$P = {{{a^2}{b^3}} \\over {c\\sqrt d }}$$<?p>\n<p>The percentage error in the measurement of a, b, c and d are 1%, 2%, 3% and 4% respectively. The percentage error in the measurement of quantity P will be</p></p>",
    "options": [
      "12%",
      "13%",
      "16%",
      "14%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "13%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh01bfcp",
    "question": "<p>A cylindrical wire of mass $$(0.4 \\pm 0.01) \\mathrm{g}$$ has length $$(8 \\pm 0.04) \\mathrm{cm}$$ and radius $$(6 \\pm 0.03) \\mathrm{mm}$$. The maximum error in its density will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "1%",
      "5%",
      "4%",
      "3.5%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "4%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh25ck1e",
    "question": "<p>Two resistances are given as $$\\mathrm{R}_{1}=(10 \\pm 0.5) \\Omega$$ and $$\\mathrm{R}_{2}=(15 \\pm 0.5) \\Omega$$. The percentage error in the measurement of equivalent resistance when they are connected in parallel is -</p>",
    "options": [
      "2.33",
      "5.33",
      "4.33",
      "6.33"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "4.33"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsampttb",
    "question": "Match <b>List - I</b> with <b>List - II</b>.\n<br/><br/><style>\n  table {\n    width: 100%;\n    border-collapse: collapse;\n  }\n  table, th, td {\n    border: 1px solid black;\n  }\n  th, td {\n    padding: 10px;\n    text-align: center;\n  }\n  th {\n    background-color: blue;\ncolor: white;\n  }\n</style><table>\n<tr>\n<th>List I (Number)</th>\n<th>List II (Significant figure)</th>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(A) 1001</td>\n<td>(I) 3</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(B) 010.1</td>\n<td>(II) 4</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(C) 100.100</td>\n<td>(III) 5</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(D) 0.0010010</td>\n<td>(IV) 6</td>\n</tr>\n</table><br/>\nChoose the correct answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(A)-(II), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(III)",
      "(A)-(IV), (B)-(III), (C)-(I), (D)-(II)",
      "(A)-(I), (B)-(II), (C)-(III), (D)-(IV)",
      "(A)-(III), (B)-(IV), (C)-(II), (D)-(I)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "(A)-(II), (B)-(I), (C)-(IV), (D)-(III)"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbl30sw",
    "question": "The radius $(\\mathrm{r})$, length $(l)$ and resistance $(\\mathrm{R})$ of a metal wire was measured in the laboratory as<br/><br/>\n$$\n\\begin{aligned}\n&amp; \\mathrm{r}=(0.35 \\pm 0.05) ~\\mathrm{cm} \\\\\\\\\n&amp; \\mathrm{R}=(100 \\pm 10) ~\\mathrm{ohm} \\\\\\\\\n&amp; l=(15 \\pm 0.2)~ \\mathrm{cm}\n\\end{aligned}\n$$\n<br/><br/>\nThe percentage error in resistivity of the material of the wire is :",
    "options": [
      "$37.3 \\%$",
      "$25.6 \\%$",
      "$35.6 \\%$",
      "$39.9 \\%$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "$39.9 \\%$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd69lms",
    "question": "<p>The measured value of the length of a simple pendulum is $$20 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ with $$2 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ accuracy. The time for 50 oscillations was measured to be 40 seconds with 1 second resolution. From these measurements, the accuracy in the measurement of acceleration due to gravity is $$\\mathrm{N} \\%$$. The value of $$\\mathrm{N}$$ is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "6",
      "5",
      "4",
      "8"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "6"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse6k1yn",
    "question": "<p>If the percentage errors in measuring the length and the diameter of a wire are $$0.1 \\%$$ each. The percentage error in measuring its resistance will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.144%",
      "0.2%",
      "0.1%",
      "0.3%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "0.3%"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf0z1zf",
    "question": "<p>The resistance $$R=\\frac{V}{I}$$ where $$\\mathrm{V}=(200 \\pm 5) \\mathrm{V}$$ and $$I=(20 \\pm 0.2) \\mathrm{A}$$, the percentage error in the measurement of $$\\mathrm{R}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "5.5%",
      "3%",
      "7%",
      "3.5%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "3.5%"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsfljjt0",
    "question": "<p>A physical quantity $$Q$$ is found to depend on quantities $$a, b, c$$ by the relation $$Q=\\frac{a^4 b^3}{c^2}$$. The percentage error in $$a, b$$ and $$c$$ are $$3 \\%, 4 \\%$$ and $$5 \\%$$ respectively. Then, the percentage error in $$Q$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "43%",
      "34%",
      "66%",
      "14%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "34%"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3kd9",
    "question": "<p>Time periods of oscillation of the same simple pendulum measured using four different measuring clocks were recorded as $$4.62 \\mathrm{~s}, 4.632 \\mathrm{~s}, 4.6 \\mathrm{~s}$$ and $$4.64 \\mathrm{~s}$$. The arithmetic mean of these readings in correct significant figure is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "5 s",
      "4.6 s",
      "4.62 s",
      "4.623 s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "4.6 s"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc58eba",
    "question": "<p>To find the spring constant $$(k)$$ of a spring experimentally, a student commits $$2 \\%$$ positive error in the measurement of time and $$1 \\%$$ negative error in measurement of mass. The percentage error in determining value of $$k$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "5%",
      "3%",
      "1%",
      "4%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "errors-in-measurements",
    "solution": "5%"
  },
  {
    "id": "uLzo7Sy9GBkyVoh0",
    "question": "An experiment is performed to find the refractive index of glass using a travelling microscope. In this experiment distances are measured by ",
    "options": [
      "a vernier scale provided on the microscope ",
      "a standard laboratory scale ",
      "a meter scale provided on the microscope ",
      "a screw gauge provided on the microscope "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "a vernier scale provided on the microscope "
  },
  {
    "id": "D2kSpusVKhN8Jqi8",
    "question": "Two full turns of the circular scale of a screw gauge cover a distance of 1 mm on its main scale. The\ntotal number of divisions on the circular scale is 50. Further, it is found that the screw gauge has a\nzero error of − 0.03 mm while measuring the diameter of a thin wire, a student notes the main scale\nreading of 3 mm and the number of circular scale divisions in line with the main scale as 35. The\ndiameter of the wire is",
    "options": [
      "3.32 mm",
      "3.73 mm",
      "3.67 mm",
      "3.38 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "3.38 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "4fUgumz5cFmHGhk4",
    "question": "A screw gauge gives the following reading when used to measure the diameter of a wire.\n<br/>Main scale reading : 0 mm\n<br/>Circular scale reading : 52 divisions\n<br/>Given that 1 mm on main scale corresponds to 100 divisions of the circular scale.\n<br/>The diameter of wire from the above date is:",
    "options": [
      "0.052 cm",
      "0.026 cm",
      "0.005 cm",
      "0.52 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "0.052 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1RspF8Uv4G4qH6Kv",
    "question": "A student measured the length of a rod and wrote it as 3.50 cm. Which instrument did he use to measure it?",
    "options": [
      "A screw gauge having 100 divisions in the circular scale and pitch as 1 mm.",
      "A screw gauge having 50 divisions in the circular scale and pitch as 1 mm.",
      "A meter scale.",
      "A vernier calliper where the 10 divisions in vernier scale matches with 9 division in main scale and main scale has 10 divisions in 1 cm."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "A vernier calliper where the 10 divisions in vernier scale matches with 9 division in main scale and main scale has 10 divisions in 1 cm."
  },
  {
    "id": "qFVR1FZqI7vpo6pR",
    "question": "A screw gauge with a pitch of 0.5 mm and a circular scale with 50 divisions is used to measure the\nthickness of a thin sheet of Aluminium. Before starting the measurement, it is found that when the two jaws of the screw gauge are brought in contact, the 45<sup>th</sup> division coincides with the main scale line and that the zero of the main scale is barely visible. What is the thickness of the sheet if the main scale reading is 0.5 mm and the 25<sup>th</sup> division coincides with the main scale line?",
    "options": [
      "0.70 mm",
      "0.50 mm",
      "0.75 mm",
      "0.80 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "0.80 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "eUDUw7QfIrCcbSehxHRGi",
    "question": "In a screw gauge, $$5$$ complete rotations of the screw cause it to move a linear distance of $$0.25$$ $$cm.$$ There are $$100$$ circular scale divisions. The thickness of a wire measured by this screw gauge gives a reading of $$4$$ main scale divisions and $$30$$ circular scale divisions. Assuming negligible zero error, the thickness of the wire is :  ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.4300$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$0.2150$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$0.3150$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$0.0430$$ $$cm$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "$$0.2150$$ $$cm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "EeeYQYM6s7ZhsevyDL8yA",
    "question": "The pitch and the number of divisions,  on the circular scale, for a given screw gauge are 0.5 mm and 100 respectively. When the screw gauge is fully tightened without any object, the zero of its circular scale lies 3 divisions below the mean line. \n<br/><br/>The readings of the main scale and the circular scale, for a thin sheet, are 5.5 mm and 48 respectively, the thickness of this sheet is : ",
    "options": [
      "5.755 mm",
      "5.950 mm",
      "5.725 mm",
      "5.740 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "5.725 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "otkYB2HhzhwOhdNuVlhWd",
    "question": "The least count of the main scale of a screw gauge is 1 mm. The minimum number of divisions on its circular scale required to measure 5 $$\\mu $$m diameter of a wire is :",
    "options": [
      "500",
      "100",
      "200",
      "50"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "200"
  },
  {
    "id": "pBXPJNBq2nU9jnQ5ZUjgy2xukfrmfcis",
    "question": "A screw gauge has 50 divisions on its circular scale. The circular scale is 4 units ahead of the\npitch scale marking, prior to use. Upon one complete rotation of the circular scale, a displacement of 0.5mm is noticed on the pitch scale. The nature of zero error involved and the least\ncount of the screw gauge, are respectively :",
    "options": [
      "Positive, 0.1 mm",
      "Positive, 0.1 $$\\mu $$m",
      "Positive, 10 $$\\mu $$m",
      "Negative, 2 $$\\mu $$m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "Positive, 10 $$\\mu $$m"
  },
  {
    "id": "HFfm172sKwYUOE6oamjgy2xukf13vwnp",
    "question": "Using screw gauge of pitch 0.1 cm and\n50 divisions on its circular scale, the thickness\nof an object is measured. It should correctly be\nrecorded as",
    "options": [
      "2.123 cm",
      "2.124 cm",
      "2.125 cm",
      "2.121 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "2.124 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "6WWz6qZQoCqr8VSj8e7k9k2k5i8h2b8",
    "question": "If the screw on a screw-gauge is given six\nrotations, it moves by 3 mm on the main scale.\nIf there are 50 divisions on the circular scale\nthe least count of the screw gauge is :",
    "options": [
      "0.001 mm",
      "0.01 cm",
      "0.02 mm",
      "0.001 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "0.001 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "sg6pDegJuwhS7hd4v81klry7esc",
    "question": "The pitch of the screw gauge is 1 mm and there are 100 divisions on the circular scale. When nothing is put in between the jaws, the zero of the circular scale lies 8 divisions below the reference line. When a wire is placed between the jaws, the first linear scale division is clearly visible while 72<sup>nd</sup> division on circular scale coincides with the reference line. The radius of the wire is :",
    "options": [
      "1.80 mm",
      "0.90 mm",
      "0.82 mm",
      "1.64 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "0.82 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kryxq3eh",
    "question": "Assertion A : If in five complete rotations of the circular scale, the distance travelled on main scale of the screw gauge is 5 mm and there are 50 total divisions on circular scale, then least count is 0.001 cm.<br/><br/>Reason R :<br/><br/>Least Count = $${{Pitch} \\over {Total\\,divisions\\,on\\,circular\\,scale}}$$<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "A is not correct but R is correct.",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is the correct explanation of A.",
      "A is correct but R is not correct.",
      "Both A and R are correct and R is NOT the correct explanation of A."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "A is not correct but R is correct."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktaeq1a8",
    "question": "In a Screw Gauge, fifth division of the circular scale coincides with the reference line when the ratchet is closed. There are 50 divisions on the circular scale, and the main scale moves by 0.5 mm on a complete rotation. For a particular observation the reading on the main scale is 5 mm and the 20<sup>th</sup> division of the circular scale coincides with reference line. Calculate the true reading.",
    "options": [
      "5.00 mm",
      "5.25 mm",
      "5.15 mm",
      "5.20 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "5.15 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gnbulf",
    "question": "<p>A screw gauge of pitch $$0.5 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ is used to measure the diameter of uniform wire of length $$6.8 \\mathrm{~cm}$$, the main scale reading is $$1.5 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ and circular scale reading is 7 . The calculated curved surface area of wire to appropriate significant figures is :</p>\n<p>[Screw gauge has 50 divisions on its circular scale]</p>",
    "options": [
      "6.8 cm<sup>2</sup>",
      "3.4 cm<sup>2</sup>",
      "3.9 cm<sup>2</sup>",
      "2.4 cm<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "3.4 cm<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3veax2",
    "question": "<p>There are 100 divisions on the circular scale of a screw gauge of pitch $$1 \\mathrm{~mm}$$. With no measuring quantity in between the jaws, the zero of the circular scale lies 5 divisions below the reference line. The diameter of a wire is then measured using this screw gauge. It is found that 4 linear scale divisions are clearly visible while 60 divisions on circular scale coincide with the reference line. The diameter of the wire is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4.65 mm",
      "4.60 mm",
      "4.55 mm",
      "3.35 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "4.55 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc57o02",
    "question": "<p>While measuring diameter of wire using screw gauge the following readings were noted. Main scale reading is $$1 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ and circular scale reading is equal to 42 divisions. Pitch of screw gauge is $$1 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ and it has 100 divisions on circular scale. The diameter of the wire is $$\\frac{x}{50} \\mathrm{~mm}$$. The value of $$x$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "42",
      "71",
      "21",
      "142"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "screw-gauge",
    "solution": "71"
  },
  {
    "id": "tft0pdC6aros3ZqbvgjF4",
    "question": "The density of a material in SI units is 128 kg m<sup>–3</sup>\n. In certain units in which the unit of length is 25 cm and the unit of mass is 50 g, the numerical value of density of the material is -",
    "options": [
      "40",
      "640",
      "16",
      "410"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "unit-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "40"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktdypm6s",
    "question": "If E and H represents the intensity of electric field and magnetising field respectively, then the unit of E/H will be :",
    "options": [
      "ohm",
      "mho",
      "joule",
      "newton"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "unit-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "ohm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfmmmj4",
    "question": "Match List - I with List - II.<br/><br/><table>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - I</th>\n<th></th>\n<th>List - II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td>(a)</td>\n<td>$${R_H}$$ (Rydberg constant)</td>\n<td>(i)</td>\n<td>$$kg\\,{m^{ - 1}}{s^{ - 1}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(b)</td>\n<td>h (Planck's constant)</td>\n<td>(ii)</td>\n<td>$$kg\\,{m^2}{s^{ - 1}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(c)</td>\n<td>$${\\mu _B}$$ (Magnetic field energy density)</td>\n<td>(iii)</td>\n<td>$$\\,{m^{ - 1}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td>(d)</td>\n<td>$$\\eta $$ (coefficient of viscocity)</td>\n<td>(iv)</td>\n<td>$$kg\\,{m^{ - 1}}{s^{ - 2}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/><br/>Choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :",
    "options": [
      "(a)-(ii), (b)-(iii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(i)",
      "(a)-(iv), (b)-(ii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iii)",
      "(a)-(iii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(i), (d)-(iv)"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "unit-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "(a)-(iii), (b)-(ii), (c)-(iv), (d)-(i)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55jlw84",
    "question": "<p>Velocity (v) and acceleration (a) in two systems of units 1 and 2 are related as $${v_2} = {n \\over {{m^2}}}{v_1}$$ and $${a_2} = {{{a_1}} \\over {mn}}$$ respectively. Here m and n are constants. The relations for distance and time in two systems respectively are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${{{n^3}} \\over {{m^3}}}{L_1} = {L_2}$$ and $${{{n^2}} \\over m}{T_1} = {T_2}$$",
      "$${L_1} = {{{n^4}} \\over {{m^2}}}{L_2}$$ and $${T_1} = {{{n^2}} \\over m}{T_2}$$",
      "$${L_1} = {{{n^2}} \\over m}{L_2}$$ and $${T_1} = {{{n^4}} \\over {{m^2}}}{T_2}$$",
      "$${{{n^2}} \\over m}{L_1} = {L_2}$$ and $${{{n^4}} \\over {{m^2}}}{T_1} = {T_2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "unit-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$${{{n^3}} \\over {{m^3}}}{L_1} = {L_2}$$ and $${{{n^2}} \\over m}{T_1} = {T_2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rggomm",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II.</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 294px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 40px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 107px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 40px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 107px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">List II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Torque</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Nms$$^{ - 1}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Stress</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">J kg$$^{ - 1}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Latent Heat</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Nm</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Power</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Nm$$^{ - 2}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-III, B-II, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I",
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "unit-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "A-III, B-IV, C-II, D-I"
  },
  {
    "id": "ldqutld6",
    "question": "<p>Match List <b>I</b> with List <b>II</b>:</p>\n<style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\">\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\" colspan=\"2\"> List I </th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\" colspan=\"2\"> List II </th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Torque</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\mathrm{kg} \\mathrm{m}^{-1} \\mathrm{~s}^{-2}$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Energy density</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\mathrm{kg} \\,\\mathrm{ms}^{-1}$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Pressure gradient</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\mathrm{kg}\\, \\mathrm{m}^{-2} \\mathrm{~s}^{-2}$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Impulse</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$\\mathrm{kg} \\,\\mathrm{m}^{2} \\mathrm{~s}^{-2}$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table><br/>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      " A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II",
      " A-IV, B-I, C-II, D-III",
      " A-I, B-IV, C-III, D-II",
      "A-IV, B-III, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "unit-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": " A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrh5r8m",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-c3ow{border-color:inherit;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-7btt{border-color:inherit;font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0pky{border-color:inherit;text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 554px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 159px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 52px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 295px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-7btt\">LIST II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Spring constant</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[T^{-1}]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Angular speed</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[MT^{-2}]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Angular momentum</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[ML^2]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">Moment of inertia</td>\n<td class=\"tg-c3ow\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0pky\">$$\\mathrm{[ML^2T^{-1}]}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-IV, B-I, C-III, D-II",
      "A-II, B-III, C-I, D-IV",
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-I, B-III, C-II, D-IV"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "unit-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgux3l91",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statements I : Astronomical unit (Au), Parsec (Pc) and Light year (ly) are units for measuring astronomical distances.</p>\n<p>Statements II : $$\\mathrm{Au} &lt; \\mathrm{Parsec} (\\mathrm{Pc}) &lt; \\mathrm{ly}$$</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statements I and Statements II are incorrect.",
      "Both Statements I and Statements II are correct,",
      "Statements I is incorrect but Statements II is correct.",
      "Statements I is correct but Statements II is incorrect."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "unit-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "Statements I is correct but Statements II is incorrect."
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyr0x6i",
    "question": "<p>Match List I with List II</p>\n<p><style type=\"text/css\">\n.tg  {border-collapse:collapse;border-spacing:0;}\n.tg td{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg th{border-color:black;border-style:solid;border-width:1px;font-family:Arial, sans-serif;font-size:14px;\n  font-weight:normal;overflow:hidden;padding:10px 5px;word-break:normal;}\n.tg .tg-baqh{text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-amwm{font-weight:bold;text-align:center;vertical-align:top}\n.tg .tg-0lax{text-align:left;vertical-align:top}\n</style>\n<table class=\"tg\" style=\"undefined;table-layout: fixed; width: 625px\">\n<colgroup>\n<col style=\"width: 46px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 267px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 48px\"/>\n<col style=\"width: 264px\"/>\n</colgroup>\n<thead>\n<tr>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST I</th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\"></th>\n<th class=\"tg-amwm\">LIST II</th>\n</tr>\n</thead>\n<tbody>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">A.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Torque</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">I.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{ML^{-2}T^{-2}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">B.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Stress</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">II.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{ML^2T^{-2}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">C.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Pressure gradient</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">III.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{ML^{-1}T^{-1}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n<tr>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">D.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">Coefficient of viscosity</td>\n<td class=\"tg-baqh\">IV.</td>\n<td class=\"tg-0lax\">$$\\mathrm{ML^{-1}T^{-2}}$$</td>\n</tr>\n</tbody>\n</table></p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below:</p>",
    "options": [
      "A-II, B-I, C-IV, D-III",
      "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III",
      "A-IV, B-II, C-III, D-I",
      "A-III, B-IV, C-I, D-II"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "unit-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "A-II, B-IV, C-I, D-III"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gs2xe",
    "question": "<p>In an expression $$a \\times 10^b$$ :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$a$$ is order of magnitude for $$b \\leq 5$$\n",
      "$$b$$ is order of magnitude for $$a \\leq 5$$\n",
      "$$b$$ is order of magnitude for $$a \\geq 5$$\n",
      "$$b$$ is order of magnitude for $$5< a \\leq 10$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "unit-of-physical-quantities",
    "solution": "$$b$$ is order of magnitude for $$a \\leq 5$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "JoNKAFlxCRfBlO7M",
    "question": "In an experiment the angles are required to be measured using an instrument, 29 divisions of the\nmain scale exactly coincide with the 30 divisions of the vernier scale. If the smallest division of the\nmain scale is half-a degree(=$$0.5^\\circ $$), then the least count of the instrument is:",
    "options": [
      "one minute",
      "half minute",
      "one degree",
      "half degree"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "one minute"
  },
  {
    "id": "F4htSzUIYbnF9CrQ",
    "question": "A spectrometer gives the following reading when used to measure the angle of a prism.\n<br/>Main scale reading: 58.5 degree\n<br/>Vernier scale reading : 09 divisions\n<br/>Given that 1 division on main scale corresponds to 0.5 degree. Total divisions on the vernier scale is 30 and match with 29 divisions of the main scale. The angle of the prism from the above data",
    "options": [
      "58.59 degree",
      "58.77 degree",
      "58.65 degree",
      "59 degree"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "58.65 degree"
  },
  {
    "id": "LsWAOacRx13cxoyErzjgy2xukev16eea",
    "question": "The least count of the main scale of a vernier\ncallipers is 1 mm. Its vernier scale is divided\ninto 10 divisions and coincide with 9 divisions\nof the main scale. When jaws are touching\neach other, the 7<sup>th</sup> division of vernier scale\ncoincides with a division of main scale and the\nzero of vernier scale is lying right side of the\nzero of main scale. When this vernier is used to\nmeasure length of a cylinder the zero of the\nvernier scale between 3.1 cm and 3.2 cm and\n4<sup>th</sup> VSD coincides with a main scale division.\nThe length of the cylinder is : (VSD is vernier\nscale division)",
    "options": [
      "3.21 cm",
      "2.99 cm",
      "3.07 cm",
      "3.2 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "3.07 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "o6iiZQFUF9rs3b8ppijgy2xukg0hx007",
    "question": "A student measuring the diameter of a pencil of circular cross-section with the help of a vernier\nscale records the following four readings 5.50 mm, 5.55 mm, 5.45 mm, 5.65 mm. The average of\nthese four readings is 5.5375 mm and the standard deviation of the data is 0.07395 mm. The\naverage diameter<br/> of the pencil should therefore be recorded as :",
    "options": [
      "(5.54 $$ \\pm $$ 0.07) mm",
      "(5.5375 $$ \\pm $$ 0.0740) mm",
      "(5.5375 $$ \\pm $$ 0.0739) mm",
      "(5.538 $$ \\pm $$ 0.074) mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "(5.54 $$ \\pm $$ 0.07) mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "8oWgSj3ol8wvZBUCQv1kmhp1qex",
    "question": "One main scale division of a vernier callipers is 'a' cm and n<sup>th</sup> division of the vernier scale coincide with (n $$-$$ 1)<sup>th</sup> division of the main scale. The least count of the callipers in mm is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{10a} \\over n}$$",
      "$${{10na} \\over {(n - 1)}}$$",
      "$$\\left( {{{n - 1} \\over {10n}}} \\right)a$$",
      "$${{10a} \\over {(n - 1)}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "$${{10a} \\over n}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "aHLoWQMEVWbods0LBY1kmj3p1zj",
    "question": "The vernier scale used for measurement has a positive zero error of 0.2 mm. If while taking a measurement it was noted that '0' on the vernier scale lies between 8.5 cm and 8.6 cm, vernier coincidence is 6, then the correct value of measurement is ___________ cm. (least count = 0.01 cm)",
    "options": [
      "8.58 cm",
      "8.54 cm",
      "8.56 cm",
      "8.36 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "8.54 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w1uvmj",
    "question": "<p>If n main scale divisions coincide with (n + 1) vernier scale divisions. The least count of vernier callipers, when each centimetre on the main scale is divided into five equal parts, will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${2 \\over {n + 1}}$$ mm",
      "$${5 \\over {n + 1}}$$ mm",
      "$${1 \\over {2n}}$$ mm",
      "$${1 \\over {5n}}$$ mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "$${2 \\over {n + 1}}$$ mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i0avr8",
    "question": "<p>In a Vernier Calipers, 10 divisions of Vernier scale is equal to the 9 divisions of main scale. When both jaws of Vernier calipers touch each other, the zero of the Vernier scale is shifted to the left of zero of the main scale and $$4^{\\text {th }}$$ Vernier scale division exactly coincides with the main scale reading. One main scale division is equal to $$1 \\mathrm{~mm}$$. While measuring diameter of a spherical body, the body is held between two jaws. It is now observed that zero of the Vernier scale lies between 30 and 31 divisions of main scale reading and $$6^{\\text {th }}$$ Vernier scale division exactly coincides with the main scale reading. The diameter of the spherical body will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3.02 cm",
      "3.06 cm",
      "3.10 cm",
      "3.20 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "3.10 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p5jrba",
    "question": "<p>A travelling microscope has 20 divisions per $$\\mathrm{cm}$$ on the main scale while its vernier scale has total 50 divisions and 25 vernier scale divisions are equal to 24 main scale divisions, what is the least count of the travelling microscope?</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.001 cm",
      "0.002 mm",
      "0.002 cm",
      "0.005 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "0.002 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvs0iis",
    "question": "<p>In an experiment with vernier callipers of least count $$0.1 \\mathrm{~mm}$$, when two jaws are joined together the zero of vernier scale lies right to the zero of the main scale and 6th division of vernier scale coincides with the main scale division. While measuring the diameter of a spherical bob, the zero of vernier scale lies in between $$3.2 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ and $$3.3 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ marks, and 4th division of vernier scale coincides with the main scale division. The diameter of bob is measured as</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3 .18 \\mathrm{~cm}$$",
      "$$3.22 \\mathrm{~cm}$$",
      "$$3.26 \\mathrm{~cm}$$",
      "$$3.25 \\mathrm{~cm}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "$$3 .18 \\mathrm{~cm}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbkltkk",
    "question": "10 divisions on the main scale of a Vernier calliper coincide with 11 divisions on the Vernier scale. If each division on the main scale is of 5 units, the least count of the instrument is :",
    "options": [
      "$\\frac{5}{11}$",
      "$\\frac{10}{11}$",
      "$\\frac{50}{11}$",
      "$\\frac{1}{2}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "$\\frac{5}{11}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscoxnio",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A) and the other is labelled as Reason (R).</p>\n<p>Assertion (A) : In Vernier calliper if positive zero error exists, then while taking measurements, the reading taken will be more than the actual reading.</p>\n<p>Reason (R) : The zero error in Vernier Calliper might have happened due to manufacturing defect or due to rough handling.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation of (A)",
      "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)",
      "(A) is true but (R) is false",
      "(A) is false but (R) is true"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg5fkiq",
    "question": "<p>If 50 Vernier divisions are equal to 49 main scale divisions of a traveling microscope and one smallest reading of main scale is $$0.5 \\mathrm{~mm}$$, the Vernier constant of traveling microscope is</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.01 mm",
      "0.01 cm",
      "0.1 mm",
      "0.1 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "0.01 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "luyita15",
    "question": "<p>One main scale division of a vernier caliper is equal to $$\\mathrm{m}$$ units. If $$\\mathrm{n}^{\\text {th }}$$ division of main scale coincides with $$(n+1)^{\\text {th }}$$ division of vernier scale, the least count of the vernier caliper is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{(\\mathrm{n}+1)}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{m}{(n+1)}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{n}{(n+1)}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{m}}{\\mathrm{n}(\\mathrm{n}+1)}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{m}{(n+1)}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3vefs7",
    "question": "<p>Least count of a vernier caliper is $$\\frac{1}{20 \\mathrm{~N}} \\mathrm{~cm}$$. The value of one division on the main scale is $$1 \\mathrm{~mm}$$. Then the number of divisions of main scale that coincide with $$\\mathrm{N}$$ divisions of vernier scale is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left(\\frac{2 \\mathrm{~N}-1}{2 \\mathrm{~N}}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{2 \\mathrm{~N}-1}{20 \\mathrm{~N}}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$(2 \\mathrm{~N}-1)$$\n",
      "$$\\left(\\frac{2 \\mathrm{~N}-1}{2}\\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "$$\\left(\\frac{2 \\mathrm{~N}-1}{2}\\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv5gs1aw",
    "question": "<p>The diameter of a sphere is measured using a vernier caliper whose 9 divisions of main scale are equal to 10 divisions of vernier scale. The shortest division on the main scale is equal to $$1 \\mathrm{~mm}$$. The main scale reading is $$2 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ and second division of vernier scale coincides with a division on main scale. If mass of the sphere is 8.635 $$\\mathrm{g}$$, the density of the sphere is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$2.2 \\mathrm{~g} / \\mathrm{cm}^3$$\n",
      "$$2.0 \\mathrm{~g} / \\mathrm{cm}^3$$\n",
      "$$1.7 \\mathrm{~g} / \\mathrm{cm}^3$$\n",
      "$$2.5 \\mathrm{~g} / \\mathrm{cm}^3$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "$$2.0 \\mathrm{~g} / \\mathrm{cm}^3$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s214v",
    "question": "<p>A vernier callipers has 20 divisions on the vernier scale, which coincides with $$19^{\\text {th }}$$ division on the main scale. The least count of the instrument is $$0.1 \\mathrm{~mm}$$. One main scale division is equal to ________ mm.</p>",
    "options": [
      "5",
      "2",
      "1",
      "0.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb295cr",
    "question": "<p>In a vernier calliper, when both jaws touch each other, zero of the vernier scale shifts towards left and its $$4^{\\text {th }}$$ division coincides exactly with a certain division on main scale. If 50 vernier scale divisions equal to 49 main scale divisions and zero error in the instrument is $$0.04 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ then how many main scale divisions are there in $$1 \\mathrm{~cm}$$ ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "5",
      "40",
      "10",
      "20"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "20"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29ekd",
    "question": "<p>In finding out refractive index of glass slab the following observations were made through travelling microscope 50 vernier scale division $$=49 \\mathrm{~MSD} ; 20$$ divisions on main scale in each $$\\mathrm{cm}$$</p>\n<p>For mark on paper</p>\n<p>$$\\text { MSR }=8.45 \\mathrm{~cm}, \\mathrm{VC}=26$$</p>\n<p>For mark on paper seen through slab</p>\n<p>$$\\mathrm{MSR}=7.12 \\mathrm{~cm}, \\mathrm{VC}=41$$</p>\n<p>For powder particle on the top surface of the glass slab</p>\n<p>$$\\text { MSR }=4.05 \\mathrm{~cm}, \\mathrm{VC}=1$$</p>\n<p>(MSR $$=$$ Main Scale Reading, VC = Vernier Coincidence)</p>\n<p>Refractive index of the glass slab is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.52",
      "1.35",
      "1.24",
      "1.42"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "units-and-measurements",
    "topic": "vernier-calipers",
    "solution": "1.42"
  },
  {
    "id": "9kfKtUC7KzYG4UTz",
    "question": "If $$\\overrightarrow A  \\times \\overrightarrow B  = \\overrightarrow B  \\times \\overrightarrow A $$, then the angle beetween A and B is",
    "options": [
      "$${\\pi  \\over 2}$$",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 3}$$",
      "$$\\pi $$",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "dot-product-and-cross-product",
    "solution": "$$\\pi $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "7g32uuGIUcoOXdWvhezer",
    "question": "Let $$\\overrightarrow A $$ = $$\\left( {\\widehat i + \\widehat j} \\right)$$ and, $$\\overrightarrow B  = \\left( {2\\widehat i - \\widehat j} \\right).$$ The magnitude of a coplanar vector $$\\overrightarrow C $$ such that $$\\overrightarrow A .\\overrightarrow C  = \\overrightarrow B .\\overrightarrow C  = \\overrightarrow A .\\overrightarrow B ,$$ is given by :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{{10} \\over 9}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{5} \\over 9}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{20} \\over 9}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{{9} \\over 12}} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "dot-product-and-cross-product",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{{5} \\over 9}} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "2aRURYbihz8VTEEdARJYe",
    "question": "Let $$\\left| {\\mathop {{A_1}}\\limits^ \\to  } \\right| = 3$$,  $$\\left| {\\mathop {{A_2}}\\limits^ \\to  } \\right| = 5$$ and $$\\left| {\\mathop {{A_1}}\\limits^ \\to   + \\mathop {{A_2}}\\limits^ \\to  } \\right| = 5$$. The\nvalue of $$\\left( {2\\mathop {{A_1}}\\limits^ \\to   + 3\\mathop {{A_2}}\\limits^ \\to  } \\right)\\left( {3\\mathop {{A_1}}\\limits^ \\to   - \\mathop {2{A_2}}\\limits^ \\to  } \\right)$$\nis :-",
    "options": [
      "–118.5",
      "–112.5",
      "–99.5",
      "–106.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "dot-product-and-cross-product",
    "solution": "–118.5"
  },
  {
    "id": "ditCSzGW4WhUWtlFQ71krpnfxmb",
    "question": "If $$\\overrightarrow A $$ and $$\\overrightarrow B $$ are two vectors satisfying the relation $$\\overrightarrow A $$ . $$\\overrightarrow B $$ = $$\\left| {\\overrightarrow A  \\times \\overrightarrow B } \\right|$$. Then the value of $$\\left| {\\overrightarrow A  - \\overrightarrow B } \\right|$$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt {{A^2} + {B^2} + \\sqrt 2 AB} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{A^2} + {B^2}} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{A^2} + {B^2} - \\sqrt 2 AB} $$",
      "$$\\sqrt {{A^2} + {B^2} + 2AB} $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "dot-product-and-cross-product",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt {{A^2} + {B^2} - \\sqrt 2 AB} $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5ak67ib",
    "question": "<p>$$\\overrightarrow A $$ is a vector quantity such that $$|\\overrightarrow A |$$ = non-zero constant. Which of the following expression is true for $$\\overrightarrow A $$ ?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\overrightarrow A \\,.\\,\\overrightarrow A  = 0$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow A  \\times \\overrightarrow A  < 0$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow A  \\times \\overrightarrow A  = 0$$",
      "$$\\overrightarrow A  \\times \\overrightarrow A  > 0$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "dot-product-and-cross-product",
    "solution": "$$\\overrightarrow A  \\times \\overrightarrow A  = 0$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldwrrpm6",
    "question": "<p>If two vectors $$\\overrightarrow P  = \\widehat i + 2m\\widehat j + m\\widehat k$$ and $$\\overrightarrow Q  = 4\\widehat i - 2\\widehat j + m\\widehat k$$ are perpendicular to each other. Then, the value of m will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$-1$$",
      "3",
      "1",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "dot-product-and-cross-product",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "3nnVXmxYp9y1YCWxEFd0V",
    "question": "Two vectors $$\\overrightarrow A $$ and $$\\overrightarrow B $$ have equal magnitudes. The magnitude  of $$\\left( {\\overrightarrow A  + \\overrightarrow B } \\right)$$ is 'n' times the magnitude of $$\\left( {\\overrightarrow A  - \\overrightarrow B } \\right)$$ . The angle between $${\\overrightarrow A }$$ and $${\\overrightarrow B }$$ is -",
    "options": [
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left[ {{{n - 1} \\over {n + 1}}} \\right]$$",
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left[ {{{{n^2} - 1} \\over {{n^2} + 1}}} \\right]$$",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left[ {{{{n^2} - 1} \\over {{n^2} + 1}}} \\right]$$",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left[ {{{n - 1} \\over {n + 1}}} \\right]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-arithmetic",
    "solution": "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left[ {{{{n^2} - 1} \\over {{n^2} + 1}}} \\right]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqdgwra",
    "question": "Two vectors $${\\overrightarrow P }$$ and $${\\overrightarrow Q }$$ have equal magnitudes. If the magnitude of $${\\overrightarrow P  + \\overrightarrow Q }$$ is n times the magnitude of $${\\overrightarrow P  - \\overrightarrow Q }$$, then angle between $${\\overrightarrow P }$$ and $${\\overrightarrow Q }$$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{n - 1} \\over {n + 1}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{n - 1} \\over {n + 1}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{{n^2} - 1} \\over {{n^2} + 1}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{{n^2} - 1} \\over {{n^2} + 1}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-arithmetic",
    "solution": "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{{n^2} - 1} \\over {{n^2} + 1}}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krwalshv",
    "question": "Two vectors $$\\overrightarrow X $$ and $$\\overrightarrow Y $$ have equal magnitude. The magnitude of ($$\\overrightarrow X $$ $$-$$ $$\\overrightarrow Y $$) is n times the magnitude of ($$\\overrightarrow X $$ + $$\\overrightarrow Y $$). The angle between $$\\overrightarrow X $$ and $$\\overrightarrow Y $$ is :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{ - {n^2} - 1} \\over {{n^2} - 1}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{{n^2} - 1} \\over { - {n^2} - 1}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{{n^2} + 1} \\over { - {n^2} - 1}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{{n^2} + 1} \\over {{n^2} - 1}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-arithmetic",
    "solution": "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{{{n^2} - 1} \\over { - {n^2} - 1}}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjncsc4",
    "question": "Statement I :<br/><br/>Two forces $$\\left( {\\overrightarrow P  + \\overrightarrow Q } \\right)$$ and $$\\left( {\\overrightarrow P  - \\overrightarrow Q } \\right)$$ where $$\\overrightarrow P  \\bot \\overrightarrow Q $$, when act at an angle $$\\theta$$<sub>1</sub> to each other, the magnitude of their resultant is $$\\sqrt {3({P^2} + {Q^2})} $$, when they act at an angle $$\\theta$$<sub>2</sub>, the magnitude of their resultant becomes $$\\sqrt {2({P^2} + {Q^2})} $$. This is possible only when $${\\theta _1} &lt; {\\theta _2}$$.<br/><br/>Statement II :<br/><br/>In the situation given above.<br/><br/>$$\\theta$$<sub>1</sub> = 60$$^\\circ$$ and $$\\theta$$<sub>2</sub> = 90$$^\\circ$$<br/><br/>In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below :-",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-arithmetic",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l547i59w",
    "question": "<p>Two vectors $$\\overrightarrow A $$ and $$\\overrightarrow B $$ have equal magnitudes. If magnitude of $$\\overrightarrow A $$ + $$\\overrightarrow B $$ is equal to two times the magnitude of $$\\overrightarrow A $$ $$-$$ $$\\overrightarrow B $$, then the angle between $$\\overrightarrow A $$ and $$\\overrightarrow B $$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{3 \\over 5}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{1 \\over 3}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{3 \\over 5}} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{1 \\over 3}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-arithmetic",
    "solution": "$${\\cos ^{ - 1}}\\left( {{3 \\over 5}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5ak77sx",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following relations is true for two unit vector $$\\widehat A$$ and $$\\widehat B$$ making an angle $$\\theta$$ to each other?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$|\\widehat A + \\widehat B| = |\\widehat A - \\widehat B|\\tan {\\theta  \\over 2}$$",
      "$$|\\widehat A - \\widehat B| = |\\widehat A + \\widehat B|\\tan {\\theta  \\over 2}$$",
      "$$|\\widehat A + \\widehat B| = |\\widehat A - \\widehat B|cos{\\theta  \\over 2}$$",
      "$$|\\widehat A - \\widehat B| = |\\widehat A + \\widehat B|\\cos {\\theta  \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-arithmetic",
    "solution": "$$|\\widehat A - \\widehat B| = |\\widehat A + \\widehat B|\\tan {\\theta  \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgsx8o8b",
    "question": "<p>When vector $$\\vec{A}=2 \\hat{i}+3 \\hat{j}+2 \\hat{k}$$ is subtracted from vector $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}$$, it gives a vector\n\nequal to $$2 \\hat{j}$$. Then the magnitude of vector $$\\overrightarrow{\\mathrm{B}}$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "$$\\sqrt{33}$$",
      "$$\\sqrt6$$",
      "$$\\sqrt5$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-arithmetic",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt{33}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh018ywo",
    "question": "<p>Two forces having magnitude $$A$$ and $$\\frac{A}{2}$$ are perpendicular to each other. The magnitude of their resultant is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{5 A}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{5} A}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{5} A}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{5} A^{2}}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-arithmetic",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\sqrt{5} A}{2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd5t0u4",
    "question": "<p>If two vectors $$\\vec{A}$$ and $$\\vec{B}$$ having equal magnitude $$R$$ are inclined at angle $$\\theta$$, then</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$|\\vec{A}+\\vec{B}|=2 R \\cos \\left(\\frac{\\theta}{2}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$|\\vec{A}-\\vec{B}|=2 R \\cos \\left(\\frac{\\theta}{2}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$|\\vec{A}-\\vec{B}|=\\sqrt{2} R \\sin \\left(\\frac{\\theta}{2}\\right)$$\n",
      "$$|\\vec{A}+\\vec{B}|=2 R \\sin \\left(\\frac{\\theta}{2}\\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-arithmetic",
    "solution": "$$|\\vec{A}+\\vec{B}|=2 R \\cos \\left(\\frac{\\theta}{2}\\right)$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3whh",
    "question": "<p>The angle between vector $$\\vec{Q}$$ and the resultant of $$(2 \\vec{Q}+2 \\vec{P})$$ and $$(2 \\vec{Q}-2 \\vec{P})$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\n\\tan ^{-1}(\\mathrm{P} / \\mathrm{Q})\n$$",
      "0$$^\\circ$$",
      "$$\n\\tan ^{-1} \\frac{(2 \\vec{Q}-2 \\vec{P})}{2 \\vec{Q}+2 \\vec{P}}\n$$",
      "$$\n\\tan ^{-1}(2 Q / \\mathrm{P})\n$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-arithmetic",
    "solution": "0$$^\\circ$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krstql6h",
    "question": "What will be the projection of vector $$\\overrightarrow A  = \\widehat i + \\widehat j + \\widehat k$$ on vector $$\\overrightarrow B  = \\widehat i + \\widehat j$$ ?",
    "options": [
      "$$\\sqrt 2 (\\widehat i + \\widehat j + \\widehat k)$$",
      "$$(\\widehat i + \\widehat j)$$",
      "$$\\sqrt 2 (\\widehat i + \\widehat j)$$",
      "$$2(\\widehat i + \\widehat j + \\widehat k)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-projections",
    "solution": "$$(\\widehat i + \\widehat j)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgnyee6z",
    "question": "A vector in $x-y$ plane makes an angle of $30^{\\circ}$ with $y$-axis. The magnitude of $\\mathrm{y}$-component of vector is $2 \\sqrt{3}$. The magnitude of $x$-component of the vector will be :",
    "options": [
      "$\\sqrt{3}$",
      "2",
      "6",
      "$\\frac{1}{\\sqrt{3}}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "vector-algebra",
    "topic": "vector-projections",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "34o3vyAYO4XWHFTn",
    "question": "If $${I_0}$$ is the intensity of the principal maximum in the single slit diffraction pattern, then what will be its intensity when the slit width is doubled? ",
    "options": [
      "$$4{I_0}$$ ",
      "$$2{I_0}$$",
      "$${{{I_0}} \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$${I_0}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "$${I_0}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "2ASuUseYGDAEVSEj",
    "question": "Two point white dots are $$1$$ $$mm$$ apart on a black paper. They are viewed by eye of pupil diameter $$3$$ $$mm.$$ Approximately, what is the maximum distance at which these dots can be resolved by the eye? [ Take wavelength of light $$=500$$ $$nm$$ ] ",
    "options": [
      "$$1m$$ ",
      "$$5m$$",
      "$$3m$$ ",
      "$$6m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "$$5m$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "IxkapcQL8kDuPGeo",
    "question": "Assuming human pupil to have a radius of $$0.25$$ $$cm$$ and a comfortable viewing distance of $$25$$ $$cm$$, the minimum separation between two objects that human eye can resolve at $$500$$ $$nm$$ wavelength is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$100\\,\\mu m$$ ",
      "$$300\\,\\mu m$$",
      "$$1\\,\\mu m$$",
      "$$30\\,\\mu m$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "$$30\\,\\mu m$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "cZHI27nfer4g9uw5",
    "question": "The box of a pin hole camera, of length $$L,$$ has a hole of radius a. It is assumed that when the hole is illuminated by a parallel beam of light of wavelength $$\\lambda $$ the spread of the spot (obtained on the opposite wall of the camera) is the sum of its geometrical spread and the spread due to diffraction. The spot would then have its minimum size (say $${b_{\\min }}$$) when : ",
    "options": [
      "$$a = \\sqrt {\\lambda L} \\,$$ and $${b_{\\min }} = \\sqrt {4\\lambda L} $$ ",
      "$$a = {{{\\lambda ^2}} \\over L}$$ and  $${b_{\\min }} = \\sqrt {4\\lambda L} $$ ",
      "$$a = {{{\\lambda ^2}} \\over L}$$ and $${b_{\\min }} = \\left( {{{2{\\lambda ^2}} \\over L}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$a = \\sqrt {\\lambda L} $$ and $${b_{\\min }} = \\left( {{{2{\\lambda ^2}} \\over L}} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "$$a = \\sqrt {\\lambda L} \\,$$ and $${b_{\\min }} = \\sqrt {4\\lambda L} $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Rr7Bp9D3FCCCY7M5EKLB1",
    "question": "Two stars are 10 light years away from the earth. They are seen through a telescope of objective diameter 30 cm. The wavelength of light is 600 nm. To see the stars just resolved by the telescope, the minimum distance between them should be (1 light year = 9.46 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>15</sup> m) of the order of :",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>6</sup> km",
      "10<sup>8</sup> km",
      "10<sup>11</sup> km",
      "10<sup>10</sup> km"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "10<sup>8</sup> km"
  },
  {
    "id": "FlHY9DnXSIJmV3RquNC0T",
    "question": "A single slit of width b is illuminated by a coherent monochromatic light of wavelength  $$\\lambda $$. If the second and fourthminima in the diffraction pattern at a distance 1 m from the slit are at 3 cm and 6 cm respectively from the central maximum, what is the width of the central maximum ? (i.e. distance between first minimum on either side of the central maximum)\n",
    "options": [
      "1.5 cm",
      "3.0 cm",
      "4.5 cm",
      "6.0 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "3.0 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "ROMfLpNsRNhcjrwcrj95H",
    "question": "A single slit of width 0.1 mm is illuminated by a parallel beam of light of wavelength 6000 $$\\mathop A\\limits^ \\circ  $$ and diffraction bands are observed on a screen 0.5 m from the slit. The distance of the third dark band from the central bright band is :\n",
    "options": [
      "3 mm",
      "9 mm",
      "4.5 mm",
      "1.5 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "9 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "4HCQyTodJiBcYhU5",
    "question": "The angular width of the central maximum in a single slit diffraction pattern is 60°. The width of the slit is\n1 $$\\mu $$m. The slit is illuminated by monochromatic plane waves. If another slit of same width is made near it,\nYoung’s fringes can be observed on a screen placed at a distance 50 cm from the slits. If the observed\nfringe width is 1 cm, what is slit separation distance?\n(i.e. distance between the centres of each slit.)",
    "options": [
      "100 $$\\mu $$m",
      "25 $$\\mu $$m",
      "50 $$\\mu $$m",
      "75 $$\\mu $$m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "25 $$\\mu $$m"
  },
  {
    "id": "AHA5xDf0UYBUcU6mFTSFc",
    "question": "In a double-slit experiment, green light (5303$$\\mathop A\\limits^ \\circ  $$) falls on a double slit having a separation of 19.44 $$\\mu $$m and awidht of 4.05 $$\\mu $$m. The number of bright fringes between the first and the second diffraction minima is : ",
    "options": [
      "04",
      "05",
      "10",
      "09"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "05"
  },
  {
    "id": "PC1GVA6bsiet0U8DtSF11",
    "question": "Calculate the limit of resolution of a telescope\nobjective having a diameter of 200 cm, if it has\nto detect light of wavelength 500 nm coming\nfrom a star :-",
    "options": [
      "610 × 10<sup>–9</sup> radian",
      "457.5 × 10<sup>–9</sup> radian",
      "305 × 10<sup>–9</sup> radian",
      "152.5 × 10<sup>–9</sup> radian"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "305 × 10<sup>–9</sup> radian"
  },
  {
    "id": "sfjqKLesBT3iL5sftnuFC",
    "question": "Diameter of the objective lens of a telescope is\n250 cm. For light of wavelength 600nm.\ncoming from a distant object, the limit of\nresolution of the telescope is close to :-",
    "options": [
      "3.0 × 10<sup>–7</sup> rad",
      "4.5 × 10<sup>–7</sup> rad",
      "1.5 × 10<sup>–7</sup> rad",
      "2.0 × 10<sup>–7</sup> rad"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "3.0 × 10<sup>–7</sup> rad"
  },
  {
    "id": "nXeKhIlD362CvHTfHw3rsa0w2w9jx3gy4fs",
    "question": "The value of numerical aperature of the objective lens of a microscope is 1.25. If light of wavelength 5000 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$\nis used, the minimum separation between two points, to be seen as distinct, will be :",
    "options": [
      "0.12 $$\\mu $$m",
      "0.38 $$\\mu $$m",
      "0.24 $$\\mu $$m",
      "0.48 $$\\mu $$m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "0.24 $$\\mu $$m"
  },
  {
    "id": "Csx5R69ZLsfyE4nkiW7k9k2k5dr2rrv",
    "question": "Visible light of wavelength 6000 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-8</sup> cm falls normally on a single slit and produces a diffraction pattern. It is found that the second diffraction minimum is at 60<sup>o</sup> from the central maximum. If the first minimum is produced at $$\\theta $$<sub>1</sub>, then $$\\theta $$<sub>1</sub>, is close to :",
    "options": [
      "45<sup>o</sup>",
      "30<sup>o</sup>",
      "25<sup>o</sup>",
      "20<sup>o</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "25<sup>o</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "SrNQK9wS3AmWrLIZ9e1klt2g8bl",
    "question": "Consider the diffraction pattern obtained from the sunlight incident on a pinhole of diameter 0.1 $$\\mu$$m. If the diameter of the pinhole is slightly increased, it will affect the diffraction pattern such that:",
    "options": [
      "its size increases, but intensity decreases",
      "its size increases, and intensity increases",
      "its size decreases, but intensity increases",
      "its sizes decreases, and intensity decreases"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "its size decreases, but intensity increases"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqazd2m",
    "question": "With what speed should a galaxy move outward with respect to earth so that the sodium-D line at wavelength 5890 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$ is observed at 5896 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$ ?",
    "options": [
      "306 km/sec",
      "322 km/sec",
      "296 km/sec",
      "336 km/sec"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "306 km/sec"
  },
  {
    "id": "lgny7rsq",
    "question": " A single slit of width $a$ is illuminated by a monochromatic light of wavelength $600 \\mathrm{~nm}$. The value of ' $a$ ' for which first minimum appears at $\\theta=30^{\\circ}$ on the screen will be :",
    "options": [
      "${3} \\mu \\mathrm{m}$",
      "$0.6 \\mu \\mathrm{m}$",
      "$1.8 \\mu \\mathrm{m}$",
      "$1.2 \\mu \\mathrm{m}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "$1.2 \\mu \\mathrm{m}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsamz14j",
    "question": "A microwave of wavelength $2.0 \\mathrm{~cm}$ falls normally on a slit of width $4.0 \\mathrm{~cm}$. The angular spread of the central maxima of the diffraction pattern obtained on a screen $1.5 \\mathrm{~m}$ away from the slit, will be :",
    "options": [
      "$60^{\\circ}$",
      "$45^{\\circ}$",
      "$15^{\\circ}$",
      "$30^{\\circ}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "$60^{\\circ}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lsbkrtgp",
    "question": "A monochromatic light of wavelength $6000 ~\\mathring{A}$ is incident on the single slit of width $0.01 \\mathrm{~mm}$. If the diffraction pattern is formed at the focus of the convex lens of focal length $20 \\mathrm{~cm}$, the linear width of the central maximum is :",
    "options": [
      "$12 \\mathrm{~mm}$",
      "$24 \\mathrm{~mm}$",
      "$60 \\mathrm{~mm}$",
      "$120 \\mathrm{~mm}$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "$24 \\mathrm{~mm}$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsgd1frq",
    "question": "<p>The diffraction pattern of a light of wavelength $$400 \\mathrm{~nm}$$ diffracting from a slit of width $$0.2 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ is focused on the focal plane of a convex lens of focal length $$100 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. The width of the $$1^{\\text {st }}$$ secondary maxima will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 mm",
      "0.2 mm",
      "0.02 mm",
      "2 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "2 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s210z",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : When the white light passed through a prism, the red light bends lesser than yellow and violet.</p>\n<p>Statement II : The refractive indices are different for different wavelengths in dispersive medium. In the light of the above statements, chose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false\n",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true\n",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "diffraction-and-doppler-effect-of-light",
    "solution": "Both Statement I and Statement II are true\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "vlIKj7ws7yJTw3xe",
    "question": "To demonstrate the phenomenon of interference, we require two sources which emit radiation ",
    "options": [
      "of nearly the same frequency ",
      "of the same frequency ",
      "of different wavelengths ",
      "of the same frequency and having a definite phase relationship "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "of the same frequency and having a definite phase relationship "
  },
  {
    "id": "ZROTrKy2l6oWIgmx",
    "question": "The maximum number of possible interference maxima for slit-separation equal to twice the wavelength in Young's double-slit experiment, is :",
    "options": [
      "three ",
      "five ",
      "infinite",
      "zero "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "five "
  },
  {
    "id": "sx0tgfZu2WFPrY2N",
    "question": "A Young's double slit experiment uses a monochromatic  source. The shape of the interference fringes formed on a screen is ",
    "options": [
      "circle ",
      "hyperbola ",
      "parabola ",
      "straight line "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "straight line "
  },
  {
    "id": "Ueq6sUXqmqWK1s43",
    "question": "In a Young's double slit experiment the intensity at a point where the path difference is $${\\lambda  \\over 6}$$ ( $$\\lambda $$ being the wavelength of light used ) is $$I$$. If $${I_0}$$ denotes the maximum intensity, $${I \\over {{I_0}}}$$ is equal to ",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over 4}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "$${{\\sqrt 3 } \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over 4}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "NuenoqunK5W1Y0RB",
    "question": "A mixture of light, consisting of wavelength $$590$$ $$nm$$ and an unknown wavelength, illuminates Young's double slit and gives rise to two overlapping interference patterns on the screen. The central maximum of both lights coincide. Further, it is observed that the third bright fringe of known light coincides with the $$4$$th bright fringe of the unknown light. From this data, the wavelength of the unknown light is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$885.0$$ $$nm$$ ",
      "$$442.5$$ $$nm$$ ",
      "$$776.8$$ $$nm$$ ",
      "$$393.4$$ $$nm$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "$$442.5$$ $$nm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "NcocnCNiO5P0g9Ap",
    "question": "An initially parallel cylindrical beam travels in a medium of refractive index $$\\mu \\left( I \\right) = {\\mu _0} + {\\mu _2}\\,I,$$ where $${\\mu _0}$$ and $${\\mu _2}$$ are positive constants and $$I$$ is the intensity of the light beam. The intensity of the beam is decreasing with increasing radius.\n<p>The initial shape of the wavefront of the beam is </p>",
    "options": [
      "convex ",
      "concave ",
      "convex near the axis and concave near the periphery ",
      "planar "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "planar "
  },
  {
    "id": "41nFUyg1gLt7zYHA",
    "question": "This question has a paragraph followed by two statements,  Statement $$-1$$ and Statement $$-2$$. Of the given four alternatives after the statements, choose the one that describes the statements. \n<p>A thin air film is formed by putting the convex surface of a plane-convex lens over a plane glass plane. With monochromatic light, this film gives an interference pattern due to light, reflected from the top (convex) surface and the bottom (glass plate) surface of the film.</p>\n<p><b>Statement - $$1$$ : </b> When light reflects from the air-glass plate interface, the reflected wave suffers a phase change of $$\\pi .$$ \n<br/><br><b>Statement - $$2$$ : </b> The center of the interference pattern is dark.</br></p> ",
    "options": [
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is the correct explanation of Statement - $$1$$",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is not the correct explanation of Statement - $$1$$",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is false, Statement - $$2$$ is true",
      "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is false."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "Statement - $$1$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is true, Statement - $$2$$ is not the correct explanation of Statement - $$1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "bM1DfyCupRYOOnIF",
    "question": "In Young's double slit experiment , one of the slit is wider than other, so that amplitude of the light from one slit is double of that from other slit. If $${{\\rm I}_m}$$ be the maximum intensity, the resultant intensity $${\\rm I}$$ when they interfere at phase difference $$\\phi $$ is given by : ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{I_m}} \\over 9}\\left( {4 + 5\\cos \\,\\phi } \\right)$$ ",
      "$${{{I_m}} \\over 3}\\left( {1 + 2{{\\cos }^2}\\,{\\phi  \\over 2}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${{{I_m}} \\over 3}\\left( {1 + 4{{\\cos }^2}\\,{\\phi  \\over 2}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${{{I_m}} \\over 9}\\left( {1 + 8{{\\cos }^2}\\,{\\phi  \\over 2}} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "$${{{I_m}} \\over 9}\\left( {1 + 8{{\\cos }^2}\\,{\\phi  \\over 2}} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "zAAqcmyvG6YRPqcB",
    "question": "On a hot summer night, the refractive index of air  is smallest near the ground and increases with height from  the ground. When a light beam is directed horizontally, the Huygens' principle leads us to conclude that as it travels, the light beam : ",
    "options": [
      "bends down wards ",
      "bends upwards ",
      "becomes narrower ",
      "goes horizontally without any deflection "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "bends upwards "
  },
  {
    "id": "m0vQxMmAet79BdaAt0tTA",
    "question": "In Young’s double slit experiment, the distance between slits and the screen is\n1.0 m and monochromatic light of 600 nm is being used. A person standing near the slits is looking at the fringe pattern. When the separation between the slits is varied, the interference pattern disappears for a particular distance d<sub>0</sub> between the slits. If the angular resolution of the eye is $$({{{1}} \\over {60}})^o$$, the value of d<sub>0</sub>  is close to : ",
    "options": [
      "1 mm",
      "2 mm",
      "4 mm",
      "3 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "2 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "ywYvyxqzjdSH85eM",
    "question": "In a Young’s double slit experiment, slits are separated by 0.5 mm, and the screen is placed 150 cm away.\nA beam of light consisting of two wavelengths, 650 nm and 520 nm, is used to obtain interference fringes\non the screen. The least distance from the common central maximum to the point where the bright fringes\ndue to both the wavelengths coincide is ",
    "options": [
      "15.6 mm",
      "1.56 mm",
      "7.8 mm",
      "9.75 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "7.8 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "eeDo4ihIyAS0heSwgnqad",
    "question": "Light of wavelength $$550$$ $$nm$$ falls normally on a slit of width $$22.0 \\times {10^{ - 5}}$$ $$cm.$$ The angular position of the second minima from the central maximum will (in radians) :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\pi  \\over {12}}$$",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 8}$$",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 6}$$",
      "$${\\pi  \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "$${\\pi  \\over 6}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "X8AicXrqXVxNzWN9zo3rsa0w2w9jx3g17vi",
    "question": "In a double slit experiment, when a thin film of thickness t having refractive index $$\\mu $$. is introduced in front of\none of the slits, the maximum at the centre of the fringe pattern shifts by one fringe width. The value of t is\n($$\\lambda $$ is the wavelength of the light used) :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\lambda  \\over {2\\left( {\\mu  - 1} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${\\lambda  \\over {\\left( {2\\mu  - 1} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${{2\\lambda } \\over {\\left( {\\mu  - 1} \\right)}}$$",
      "$${\\lambda  \\over {\\left( {\\mu  - 1} \\right)}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "$${\\lambda  \\over {\\left( {\\mu  - 1} \\right)}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "cMQDMvy7MGwBNyEUPb3rsa0w2w9jwzizoxm",
    "question": "In a Young's double slit experiment, the ratio of the slit's width is 4 : 1. The ratio of the intensity of maxima to minima, close to the central fringe on the screen, will be : ",
    "options": [
      "25 : 9",
      "4 : 1",
      "$${\\left( {\\sqrt 3  + 1} \\right)^4}:16$$",
      "9 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "9 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "N1qPaQ0qVDbCnDfqFbPgc",
    "question": "In an interference experiment the ratio of amplitudes of coherent waves is $${{{a_1}} \\over {{a_2}}} = {1 \\over 3}$$ . The\nratio of maximum and minimum intensities of\nfringes will be :",
    "options": [
      "2",
      "4",
      "18",
      "9"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "hhozgMiNRGW3rI6di0OCa",
    "question": "In a Young’s double slit experiment with slit separation 0.1 mm, one observes a bright fringe at angle  $${1 \\over {40}}$$ by  using light of wavelength $$\\lambda $$<sub>1</sub>.  When the light of wavelength $$\\lambda $$<sub>2</sub> is used a bright fringe is seen at the same angle in the same set up. Given that $$\\lambda $$<sub>1</sub> and $$\\lambda $$<sub>2</sub> are in visible range (380 nm to 740 nm), their values are -",
    "options": [
      "400 nm, 500 nm",
      "625 nm, 500 nm",
      "380 nm, 500 nm",
      "380 nm, 525 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "625 nm, 500 nm"
  },
  {
    "id": "9zilMx6VVSkhrOIjJyRHZ",
    "question": "In a Young's double slit experiment, the slits are placed 0.320 mm apart. Light of wavelength $$\\lambda $$ = 500 nm is incident on the slits. The total number of bright fringes that are observed in the angular range $$-$$ 30<sup>o</sup>$$ \\le $$$$\\theta $$$$ \\le $$30<sup>o</sup> is : ",
    "options": [
      "640",
      "320",
      "321",
      "641"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "641"
  },
  {
    "id": "utwI9W3XjMSPDNOsoHkgf",
    "question": "Two coherent sources produce waves of different intensities which interfere. After interference, the ratio of the maximum intensity to the minimum intensity is 16. The intensity of the waves are in the ratio : ",
    "options": [
      "16 : 9",
      "25 : 9",
      "4 : 1",
      "5 : 3"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "25 : 9"
  },
  {
    "id": "Y94QrvvNLVtJyW62ysQKm",
    "question": "In a Young's double slit experiment, the path difference, at a certain point on the screen, between two interfering waves is $${1 \\over 8}$$ th of wavelength. The ratio of the intensity at this point to that at the centre of a bright fringe is close to : \n",
    "options": [
      "0.94",
      "0.85",
      "0.74",
      "0.80"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "0.85"
  },
  {
    "id": "td8owo16ioRFFI54fijgy2xukf3vpbie",
    "question": "Two light waves having the same wavelength $$\\lambda $$ in vacuum are in phase initially. Then the first wave\ntravels a path L<sub>1</sub>\n through a medium of refractive index n<sub>1</sub>\n while the second wave travels a path of length\nL<sub>2</sub>\n through a medium of refractive index n<sub>2</sub>\n. After this the phase difference between the two waves is :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2\\pi } \\over \\lambda }\\left( {{n_1}{L_1} - {n_2}{L_2}} \\right)$$",
      "$${{2\\pi } \\over \\lambda }\\left( {{n_2}{L_1} - {n_1}{L_2}} \\right)$$",
      "$${{2\\pi } \\over \\lambda }\\left( {{{{L_1}} \\over {{n_1}}} - {{{L_2}} \\over {{n_2}}}} \\right)$$",
      "$${{2\\pi } \\over \\lambda }\\left( {{{{L_2}} \\over {{n_1}}} - {{{L_1}} \\over {{n_2}}}} \\right)$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "$${{2\\pi } \\over \\lambda }\\left( {{n_1}{L_1} - {n_2}{L_2}} \\right)$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "JJ4KnW2ZTOpF1oOhu4jgy2xukf24k8fe",
    "question": "In a Young’s double slit experiment, light of\n500 nm is used to produce an interference\npattern. When the distance between the slits\nis 0.05 mm, the angular width (in degree) of\nthe fringes formed on the distance screen is\nclose to",
    "options": [
      "0.17<sup>o</sup>",
      "1.7<sup>o</sup>",
      "0.57<sup>o</sup>",
      "0.07<sup>o</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "0.57<sup>o</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "Shbmi2dFOIbjr1aB5ljgy2xukexrn8tt",
    "question": "In a Young’s double slit experiment, 16 fringes\nare observed in a certain segment of the\nscreen when light of a wavelength 700 nm is\nused. If the wavelength of light is changed to\n400 nm, the number of fringes observed in the\nsame segment of the screen would be",
    "options": [
      "28",
      "24",
      "30",
      "18"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "28"
  },
  {
    "id": "5Q1mNCgne4SjAJqDZ6jgy2xukeuzv008",
    "question": "Interference fringes are observed on a screen\nby illuminating two thin slits 1 mm apart with a\nlight source ($$\\lambda $$ = 632.8 nm). The distance\nbetween the screen and the slits is 100 cm. If\na bright fringe is observed on a screen at a\ndistance of 1.27 mm from the central bright\nfringe, then the path difference between the\nwaves, which are reaching this point from the\nslits is close is",
    "options": [
      "1.27 $$\\mu $$m",
      "2.05 $$\\mu $$m",
      "2.87 nm",
      "2 nm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "1.27 $$\\mu $$m"
  },
  {
    "id": "jauORrExyOhtks9IK97k9k2k5hgkl5e",
    "question": "In a double slit experiment, at a certain point\non the screen the path difference between the\ntwo interfering waves is $${1 \\over 8}$$th of a wavelength.\nThe ratio of the intensity of light at that point\nto that at the centre of a bright fringe is :",
    "options": [
      "0.853",
      "0.568",
      "0.672",
      "0.760"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "0.853"
  },
  {
    "id": "ixUmVK4IM0Aajyr8bq7k9k2k5f7n16m",
    "question": "In a Young's double slit experiment, the separation between the slits is 0.15 mm. in the experiment,\na source of light of wavelengh 589 nm is used and the interference pattern is observed on a\nscreen kept 1.5 m away. The separation between the successive bright fringes on the screen is :",
    "options": [
      "4.9 mm",
      "5.9 mm",
      "6.9 mm",
      "3.9 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "5.9 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "Ii4WSgqHd3E6E5KLo51klrhlhir",
    "question": "In a Young's double slit experiment, the width of the one of the slit is three times the other slit. The amplitude of the light coming from a slit is proportional to the slit-width. Find the ratio of the maximum to the minimum intensity in the interference pattern.",
    "options": [
      "4 : 1",
      "2 : 1",
      "1 : 4",
      "3 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "4 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "wqtXW6qVvLyQxz4YJ01klrndy3u",
    "question": "If the source of light used in a Young's double slit experiment is changed from red to violet :",
    "options": [
      "the fringes will become brighter.",
      "the intensity of minima will increase.",
      "consecutive fringe lines will come closer.",
      "the central bright fringe will become a dark fringe."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "consecutive fringe lines will come closer."
  },
  {
    "id": "ifYqznrVJ6WtWCARcV1klrxgdv7",
    "question": "Two coherent light sources having intensity in the ratio 2x produce an interference pattern. The ratio $${{{I_{\\max }} - {I_{\\min }}} \\over {{I_{\\max }} + {I_{\\min }}}}$$ will be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2\\sqrt {2x} } \\over {2x + 1}}$$",
      "$${{2\\sqrt {2x} } \\over {x + 1}}$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt {2x} } \\over {x + 1}}$$",
      "$${{\\sqrt {2x} } \\over {2x + 1}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "$${{2\\sqrt {2x} } \\over {2x + 1}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "tyjRf3yNoegzrT6hNR1klthmn6b",
    "question": "In a Young's double slit experiment two slits are separated by 2 mm and the screen is placed one meter away. When a light of wavelength 500 nm is used, the fringe separation will be :",
    "options": [
      "0.50 mm",
      "0.25 mm",
      "1 mm",
      "0.75 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "0.25 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "qSQMmHfdQwXFYprfHX1kmkr9bz7",
    "question": "In Young's double slit arrangement, slits are separated by a gap of 0.5 mm, and the screen is placed at a distance of 0.5 m from them. The distance between the first and the third bright fringe formed when the slits are illuminated by a monochromatic light of 5890 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$ is :-",
    "options": [
      "1178 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$9</sup> m",
      "1178 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> m",
      "1178 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$12</sup> m",
      "5890 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$7</sup> m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "1178 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>$$-$$6</sup> m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krull889",
    "question": "In the Young's double slit experiment, the distance between the slits varies in time as <br/>d(t) = d<sub>0</sub> + a<sub>0</sub> sin$$\\omega$$t; where d<sub>0</sub>, $$\\omega$$ and a<sub>0</sub> are constants. The difference between the largest fringe width and the smallest fringe width obtained over time is given as :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2\\lambda D({d_0})} \\over {(d_0^2 - a_0^2)}}$$",
      "$${{2\\lambda D{a_0}} \\over {(d_0^2 - a_0^2)}}$$",
      "$${{\\lambda D} \\over {d_0^2}}{a_0}$$",
      "$${{\\lambda D} \\over {{d_0} + {a_0}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "$${{2\\lambda D{a_0}} \\over {(d_0^2 - a_0^2)}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1kryvl2jd",
    "question": "In Young's double slit experiment, if the source of light changes from orange to blue then :",
    "options": [
      "the central bright fringe will become a dark fringe.",
      "the distance between consecutive fringes will decrease.",
      "the distance between consecutive fringes will increases.",
      "the intensity of the minima will increase."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "the distance between consecutive fringes will decrease."
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktfnfm48",
    "question": "The light waves from two coherent sources have same intensity I<sub>1</sub> = I<sub>2</sub> = I<sub>0</sub>. In interference pattern the intensity of light at minima is zero. What will be the intensity of light at maxima?",
    "options": [
      "I<sub>0</sub>",
      "2 I<sub>0</sub>",
      "5 I<sub>0</sub>",
      "4 I<sub>0</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "4 I<sub>0</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l547rrx9",
    "question": "<p>Using Young's double slit experiment, a monochromatic light of wavelength 5000 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$ produces fringes of fringe width 0.5 mm. If another monochromatic light of wavelength 6000 $$\\mathop A\\limits^o $$ is used and the separation between the slits is doubled, then the new fringe width will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.5 mm",
      "1.0 mm",
      "0.6 mm",
      "0.3 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "0.3 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l55kjyi5",
    "question": "<p>In Young's double slit experiment performed using a monochromatic light of wavelength $$\\lambda$$, when a glass plate ($$\\mu$$ = 1.5) of thickness x$$\\lambda$$ is introduced in the path of the one of the interfering beams, the intensity at the position where the central maximum occurred previously remains unchanged. The value of x will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "2",
      "1.5",
      "0.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l58i4rff",
    "question": "<p>For a specific wavelength 670 nm of light coming from a galaxy moving with velocity v, the observed wavelength is 670.7 nm. The value of v is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "3 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "3.13 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "4.48 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "3.13 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>5</sup> ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59p9sm6",
    "question": "<p>The interference pattern is obtained with two coherent light sources of intensity ratio 4 : 1. And the ratio $${{{I_{\\max }} + {I_{\\min }}} \\over {{I_{\\max }} - {I_{\\min }}}}$$ is $${5 \\over x}$$. Then, the value of x will be equal to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3",
      "4",
      "2",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5aksul5",
    "question": "<p>The two light beams having intensities I and 9I interfere to produce a fringe pattern on a screen. The phase difference between the beams is $$\\pi$$/2 at point P and $$\\pi$$ at point Q. Then the difference between the resultant intensities at P and Q will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 I",
      "6 I",
      "5 I",
      "7 I"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "6 I"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5bc8xqz",
    "question": "<p>Two light beams of intensities in the ratio of 9 : 4 are allowed to interfere. The ratio of the intensity of maxima and minima will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 : 3",
      "16 : 81",
      "25 : 169",
      "25 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "25 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w33tt4",
    "question": "<p>Find the ratio of maximum intensity to the minimum intensity in the interference pattern if the widths of the two slits in Young's experiment are in the ratio of 9 : 16. (Assuming intensity of light is directly proportional to the width of slits)</p>",
    "options": [
      "3 : 4",
      "4 : 3",
      "7 : 1",
      "49 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "49 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6gk37fd",
    "question": "<p>In Young's double slit experiment, the fringe width is $$12 \\mathrm{~mm}$$. If the entire arrangement is placed in water of refractive index $$\\frac{4}{3}$$, then the fringe width becomes (in mm):</p>",
    "options": [
      "16",
      "9",
      "48",
      "12"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "9"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6knn062",
    "question": "<p>Two coherent sources of light interfere. The intensity ratio of two sources is $$1: 4$$. For this interference pattern if the value of $$\\frac{I_{\\max }+I_{\\min }}{I_{\\max }-I_{\\min }}$$ is equal to $$\\frac{2 \\alpha+1}{\\beta+3}$$, then $$\\frac{\\alpha}{\\beta}$$ will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.5",
      "2",
      "0.5",
      "1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lduh83d8",
    "question": "<p>In Young's double slits experiment, the position of 5$$\\mathrm{^{th}}$$ bright fringe from the central maximum is 5 cm. The distance between slits and screen is 1 m and wavelength of used monochromatic light is 600 nm. The separation between the slits is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "60 $$\\mu$$m",
      "48 $$\\mu$$m",
      "36 $$\\mu$$m",
      "12 $$\\mu$$m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "60 $$\\mu$$m"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgp058hb",
    "question": "<p>In a Young's double slits experiment, the ratio of amplitude of light coming from slits is $$2: 1$$. The ratio of the maximum to minimum intensity in the interference pattern is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "25 : 9",
      "9 : 1",
      "9 : 4",
      "2 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "9 : 1"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvrsf71",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of intensities at two points $$\\mathrm{P}$$ and $$\\mathrm{Q}$$ on the screen in a Young's double slit experiment where phase difference between two waves of same amplitude are $$\\pi / 3$$ and $$\\pi / 2$$, respectively are</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 : 3",
      "1 : 3",
      "3 : 1",
      "3 : 2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "3 : 2"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqx612",
    "question": "<p>The width of fringe is $$2 \\mathrm{~mm}$$ on the screen in a double slits experiment for the light of wavelength of $$400 \\mathrm{~nm}$$. The width of the fringe for the light of wavelength 600 $$\\mathrm{nm}$$ will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "4 mm",
      "1.33 mm",
      "2 mm",
      "3 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "3 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsflzlxu",
    "question": "<p>In Young's double slit experiment, light from two identical sources are superimposing on a screen. The path difference between the two lights reaching at a point on the screen is $$7 \\lambda / 4$$. The ratio of intensity of fringe at this point with respect to the maximum intensity of the fringe is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{1}{2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{3}{4}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{3}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{1}{4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{1}{2}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv2er9hk",
    "question": "<p>The width of one of the two slits in a Young's double slit experiment is 4 times that of the other slit. The ratio of the maximum of the minimum intensity in the interference pattern is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$1: 1$$\n",
      "$$4: 1$$\n",
      "$$16: 1$$\n",
      "$$9: 1$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "$$9: 1$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv7v3wga",
    "question": "<p>Light emerges out of a convex lens when a source of light kept at its focus. The shape of wavefront of the light is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "cylindrical\n",
      "spherical\n",
      "plane\n",
      "both spherical and cylindrical"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "huygens-principle-and-interference-of-light",
    "solution": "plane\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "429FQrFTdPwRfLj4",
    "question": "The angle of incidence at which reflected light is totally polarized for reflection from air to glass (refractive index $$n$$) is :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( {1/n} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( {1/n} \\right)$$",
      "$${\\sin ^{ - 1}}\\left( n \\right)$$ ",
      "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( n \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "$${\\tan ^{ - 1}}\\left( n \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "BijlamTgHjsVK0so",
    "question": "When an unpolarized light of intensity $${{I_0}}$$ is incident on a polarizing sheet, the intensity of the light which does not get transmitted is ",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 4}\\,{I_0}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}\\,{I_0}$$",
      "$${I_0}$$ ",
      "zero "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 2}\\,{I_0}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "opyZi55h8LkfaBuD",
    "question": "A beam of unpolarised light of intensity $${{\\rm I}_0}$$ is passed through a polaroid $$A$$ and then through another polaroid $$B$$ which is oriented so that its principal plane makes an angle of $${45^ \\circ }$$ relative to that of $$A$$. The intensity of the emergent light is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{\\rm I}_0}$$ ",
      "$${{{I_0}} \\over 2}$$",
      "$${{{I_0}} \\over 4}$$",
      "$${{{I_0}} \\over 8}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "$${{{I_0}} \\over 4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "cF3Og2dZYyNaQHOp",
    "question": "Two beams, $$A$$ and $$B$$, of plane polarized light with mutually perpendicular planes of polarization are seen through a polaroid.  From the position when the beam $$A$$ has maximum intensity (and beam $$B$$ has zero intensity), a rotation of polaroid through $${30^ \\circ }$$ makes the two beams appear equally bright. If the initial intensities of the two beams are $${{\\rm I}_A}$$ and $${{\\rm I}_B}$$ respectively, then $${{{{\\rm I}_A}} \\over {{{\\rm I}_B}}}$$ equals: ",
    "options": [
      "$$3$$ ",
      "$${3 \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$$1$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 3}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 3}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "OTlN14Qj26fOGxTe",
    "question": "Unpolarized light of intensity I passes through an ideal polarizer A. Another identical polarizer B is placed\nbehind A. The intensity of light beyond B is found to be I/2. Now another identical polarizer C is placed between A and B. The intensity beyond B is now found to be I/8. The angle between polarizer A and C is :",
    "options": [
      "60<sup>o</sup>",
      "30<sup>o</sup>",
      "45<sup>o</sup>",
      "0<sup>o</sup> "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "45<sup>o</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "DAHnVbQ5G4tV6YSLA12PQ",
    "question": "Unpolarized light of intensity I is incident on a system of two polarizers,  A followed by B. The intensity of emergent light is I/2. If a third polarizer C is placed between A and B, the intensity of emergent light is reduced to I/3. The angle between the polarizers A and C is $$\\theta $$. Then : ",
    "options": [
      "cos$$\\theta $$ = $${\\left( {{2 \\over 3}} \\right)^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}}}$$",
      "cos$$\\theta $$ = $${\\left( {{2 \\over 3}} \\right)^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 4$}}}}$$",
      "cos$$\\theta $$ = $${\\left( {{1 \\over 3}} \\right)^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 2$}}}}$$",
      "cos$$\\theta $$ = $${\\left( {{1 \\over 3}} \\right)^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 4$}}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "cos$$\\theta $$ = $${\\left( {{2 \\over 3}} \\right)^{{\\raise0.5ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 1$}\n\\kern-0.1em/\\kern-0.15em\n\\lower0.25ex\\hbox{$\\scriptstyle 4$}}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "fXCvbuLCsyc8HhHoud3rsa0w2w9jx7f30rl",
    "question": "A system of three polarizers P<sub>1</sub>, P<sub>2</sub>, P<sub>3</sub> is set up such that the pass axis of P<sub>3</sub> is crossed with respect to that of P<sub>1</sub>.\nThe pass axis of P<sub>2</sub> is inclined at 60<sup>o</sup> to the pass axis of P<sub>3</sub>. When a beam of unpolarized light of intensity I0 is\nincident on P<sub>1</sub>, the intensity of light transmitted by the three polarizers is I. The ratio ($${{{I_0}} \\over I}$$) equals (nearly) :\n",
    "options": [
      "10.67",
      "5.33",
      "16.00",
      "1.80"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "10.67"
  },
  {
    "id": "od7DMOyW8iCwUSlRJr7k9k2k5dgop7u",
    "question": "A polarizer - analyser set is adjusted such that the intensity of light coming out of the analyser is just 10% of the original intensity. Assuming that the polarizer - analyser set does not absorb any light, the angle by which the analyser need to be rotated further to reduce the output intensity to be\nzero, is :",
    "options": [
      "71.6<sup>o</sup>",
      "90<sup>o</sup>",
      "18.4<sup>o</sup>",
      "45<sup>o</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "18.4<sup>o</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "DEXb1H9n6UDZQ0mPfNjgy2xuketzmue8",
    "question": "A beam of plane polarised light of large<br/> cross-sectional area and uniform intensity<br/> of 3.3 Wm<sup>-2</sup> falls normally on a<br/> polariser (cross sectional area 3 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-4</sup> m<sup>2</sup>) which <br/>rotates about its axis with an angular speed<br/> of 31.4 rad/s. The energy of light passing through<br/> the polariser per revolution, is close to :",
    "options": [
      "1.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-5</sup> J",
      "1.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-4</sup> J",
      "1.5 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-4</sup> J",
      "5.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-4</sup> J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "1.0 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>-4</sup> J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l59pbrj3",
    "question": "<p>A light whose electric field vectors are completely removed by using a good polaroid, allowed to incident on the surface of the prism at Brewster's angle. Choose the most suitable option for the phenomenon related to the prism.</p>",
    "options": [
      "Reflected and refracted rays will be perpendicular to each other.",
      "Wave will propagate along the surface of prism.",
      "No refraction, and there will be total reflection of light.",
      "No reflection, and there will be total transmission of light."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "No reflection, and there will be total transmission of light."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6rh2eia",
    "question": "<p>An unpolarised light beam of intensity $$2 I_{0}$$ is passed through a polaroid P and then through another polaroid Q which is oriented in such a way that its passing axis makes an angle of $$30^{\\circ}$$ relative to that of P. The intensity of the emergent light is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{I}_{0}}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{I}_{0}}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3 I_{0}}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{3 \\mathrm{I}_{0}}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{3 I_{0}}{4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldoex374",
    "question": "<p>'$$n$$' polarizing sheets are arranged such that each makes an angle $$45^{\\circ}$$ with the preceeding sheet. An unpolarized light of intensity I is incident into this arrangement. The output intensity is found to be $$I / 64$$. The value of $$n$$ will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "5",
      "3",
      "6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "6"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldpkgq0o",
    "question": "<p>Two polaroide $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$ are placed in such a way that the pass-axis of polaroids are perpendicular to each other. Now, another polaroid $$\\mathrm{C}$$ is placed between $$\\mathrm{A}$$ and $$\\mathrm{B}$$ bisecting angle between them. If intensity of unpolarized light is $$\\mathrm{I}_{0}$$ then intensity of transmitted light after passing through polaroid $$\\mathrm{B}$$ will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{I_{0}}{4}$$",
      "$$\\frac{I_{0}}{8}$$",
      "Zero",
      "$$\\frac{I_{0}}{2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{I_{0}}{8}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldycy2fs",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements :</p>\n<p>Statement I : If the Brewster's angle for the light propagating from air to glass is $$\\mathrm{\\theta_B}$$, then the Brewster's angle for the light propagating from glass to air is $$\\frac{\\pi}{2}-\\theta_B$$</p>\n<p>Statement II : The Brewster's angle for the light propagating from glass to air is $${\\tan ^{ - 1}}({\\mu _\\mathrm{g}})$$ where $$\\mathrm{\\mu_g}$$ is the refractive index of glass.</p>\n<p>In the light of the above statements, choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are false",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are true",
      "Statement I is false but Statement II is true",
      "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "Statement I is true but Statement II is false"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscpjas0",
    "question": "<p>When a polaroid sheet is rotated between two crossed polaroids then the transmitted light intensity will be maximum for a rotation of :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$90^\\circ$$",
      "$$30^\\circ$$",
      "$$45^\\circ$$",
      "$$60^\\circ$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "$$45^\\circ$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd79z39",
    "question": "<p>When unpolarized light is incident at an angle of $$60^{\\circ}$$ on a transparent medium from air, the reflected ray is completely polarized. The angle of refraction in the medium is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$60^{\\circ}$$",
      "$$90^{\\circ}$$",
      "$$30^{\\circ}$$",
      "$$45^{\\circ}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "$$30^{\\circ}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lsg61008",
    "question": "<p>A beam of unpolarised light of intensity $$I_0$$ is passed through a polaroid $$A$$ and then through another polaroid $$B$$ which is oriented so that its principal plane makes an angle of $$45^{\\circ}$$ relative to that of $$A$$. The intensity of emergent light is:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$I_0 / 2$$\n",
      "$$I_0 / 8$$\n",
      "$$I_0 / 4$$\n",
      "$$I_0$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "wave-optics",
    "topic": "polarisation",
    "solution": "$$I_0 / 4$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "9xfFS0a6p88PwPh5",
    "question": "Tube $$A$$ has bolt ends open while tube $$B$$ has one end closed, otherwise they are identical. The ratio of fundamental frequency of tube $$A$$ and $$B$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$1:2$$ ",
      "$$1:4$$ ",
      "$$2:1$$ ",
      "$$4:1$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$2:1$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "QeZ5VRytU04iZT3c",
    "question": "length of a string tied to two rigid supports is $$40$$ $$cm$$. Maximum length (wavelength in $$cm$$) of a stationary wave produced on it is ",
    "options": [
      "$$20$$ ",
      "$$80$$ ",
      "$$40$$ ",
      "$$120$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$80$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Kn7AWK9rxGnehYwl",
    "question": "When temperature increases, the frequency of a tuning fork ",
    "options": [
      "increases ",
      "decreases ",
      "remains same ",
      "increases or decreases depending on the material "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "decreases "
  },
  {
    "id": "dk49USPnjKhi6cd9",
    "question": "The displacement $$y$$ of a wave travelling in the $$x$$-direction is given by \n$$$y = {10^{ - 4}}\\,\\sin \\left( {600t - 2x + {\\pi  \\over 3}} \\right)\\,\\,metres$$$\n<br/>where $$x$$ is expressed in metres and $$t$$ in seconds. The speed of the wave - motion, in $$m{s^{ - 1}}$$, is ",
    "options": [
      "$$300$$ ",
      "$$600$$ ",
      "$$1200$$ ",
      "$$200$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$300$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "yM7OAgWEzhC9oe3k",
    "question": "The displacement $$y$$ of a particle in a medium can be expressed as, $$y = {10^{ - 6}}\\,\\sin $$ $$\\left( {100t + 20x + {\\pi  \\over 4}} \\right)$$ $$m$$ where $$t$$ is in second and $$x$$ in meter. The speed of the wave is \n",
    "options": [
      "$$20\\,\\,m/s$$ ",
      "$$5\\,m/s$$ ",
      "$$2000\\,m/s$$",
      "$$5\\,\\pi \\,m/s$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$5\\,m/s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "fCvli4kKhHJGaEzV",
    "question": "A sound absorber attenuates the sound level by $$20$$ $$dB$$. The intensity decreases by a factor of ",
    "options": [
      "$$100$$ ",
      "$$1000$$ ",
      "$$10000$$ ",
      "$$10$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$100$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "bGozeOvzUYEFkAPs",
    "question": "A wave travelling along the $$x$$-axis is described by the equation $$y(x, t)=0.005$$ $$\\cos \\,\\left( {\\alpha \\,x - \\beta t} \\right).$$ If the wavelength and the time period of the wave are $$0.08$$ $$m$$ and $$2.0s$$, respectively, then $$\\alpha $$ and $$\\beta $$ in appropriate units are ",
    "options": [
      "$$\\alpha  = 25.00\\pi ,\\,\\beta  = \\pi $$ ",
      "$$\\alpha  = {{0.08} \\over \\pi },\\,\\beta  = {{2.0} \\over \\pi }$$ ",
      "$$\\alpha  = {{0.04} \\over \\pi },\\,\\beta  = {{1.0} \\over \\pi }$$ ",
      "$$\\alpha  = 12.50\\pi ,\\,\\beta  = {\\pi  \\over {2.0}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\alpha  = 25.00\\pi ,\\,\\beta  = \\pi $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "OmrGAtsrjTlUkdvp",
    "question": "The equation of a wave on a string of linear mass density $$0.04\\,\\,kg\\,{m^{ - 1}}$$ is given by \n$$$y = 0.02\\left( m \\right)\\,\\sin \\left[ {2\\pi \\left( {{t \\over {0.04\\left( s \\right)}} - {x \\over {0.50\\left( m \\right)}}} \\right)} \\right].$$$\n<p>The tension in the string is</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$4.0N$$ ",
      "$$12.5$$ $$N$$ ",
      "$$0.5$$ $$N$$ ",
      "$$6.25$$ $$N$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$6.25$$ $$N$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "zuTeLygZRWONONIV",
    "question": "The transverse displacement $$y(x, t)$$ of a wave on a string is given by $$y\\left( {x,t} \\right) = {e^{ - \\left( {a{x^2} + b{t^2} + 2\\sqrt {ab} \\,xt} \\right)}}.$$ This represents $$a:$$ ",
    "options": [
      "wave moving in  $$-x$$  direction with speed $$\\sqrt {{b \\over a}} $$ ",
      "standing wave of frequency $$\\sqrt b $$ ",
      "standing wave of frequency $${1 \\over {\\sqrt b }}$$ ",
      "wave moving in $$+x$$ direction speed $$\\sqrt {{a \\over b}} $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "wave moving in  $$-x$$  direction with speed $$\\sqrt {{b \\over a}} $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "qFw7NC5XFLugusBz",
    "question": "A cylindrical tube, open at both ends, has a fundamental frequency, $$f,$$ in air. The tube is dipped vertically in water so that half of it is in water. The fundamental frequency of the air-column is now : ",
    "options": [
      "$$f$$ ",
      "$$f/2$$ ",
      "$$3/4$$ ",
      "$$2f$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$f$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "hQq5s6CvCiT8jEcd",
    "question": "A sonometer wire of length $$1.5$$ $$m$$  is made of steel. The tension in it produces an elastic strain of $$1\\% $$. What is the fundamental frequency of steel if density and elasticity of steel are $$7.7 \\times {10^3}\\,kg/{m^3}$$ and $$2.2 \\times {10^{11}}\\,N/{m^2}$$ respectively ? ",
    "options": [
      "$$188.5$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$178.2$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$200.5$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$770$$ $$Hz$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$178.2$$ $$Hz$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "6O1HbsZMKLGfi32x",
    "question": "A uniform string of length $$20$$ $$m$$ is suspended from a rigid support. A short wave pulse is introduced at its lowest end. It starts moving up the string. The time taken to reach the supports is : \n<br/>(take $${\\,\\,g = 10m{s^{ - 2}}}$$ )",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\sqrt 2 s$$ ",
      "$$2\\pi \\sqrt 2 s$$ ",
      "$$2\\pi \\sqrt 2 s$$ ",
      "$$2$$ $$s$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$2\\sqrt 2 s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "DsXUQa82lLgbJ7xBa7AO9",
    "question": "In an experiment to determine the period of a simple pendulum of length 1 m, it is attached to different spherical bobs of radii r<sub>1</sub>\n and r<sub>2</sub> . The two spherical bobs have uniform mass distribution. If the relative difference in the periods, is found to be\n5×10<sup>−4</sup>  s, the difference in radii, $$\\left| {} \\right.$$r<sub>1</sub> $$-$$ r<sub>2</sub> $$\\left| {} \\right.$$ is best given by :",
    "options": [
      "1 cm ",
      "0.05 cm",
      "0.5 cm",
      "0.01 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "0.05 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "HdBSQqW96bmmlXvGPra8p",
    "question": "A standing wave is formed by the superposition of two waves travelling in\nopposite directions. The transverse displacement is given by\n<br/><br/>y(x, t) = 0.5 sin $$\\left( {{{5\\pi } \\over 4}x} \\right)\\,$$ cos(200 $$\\pi $$t).\n<br/><br/>What is the speed of the travelling wave moving in the positive x direction ?\n<br/><br/>(x and t are in meter and second, respectively.)",
    "options": [
      "160 m/s",
      "90 m/s",
      "180 m/s",
      "120 m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "160 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "hDSwe4zz1mcwvD0MbthSZ",
    "question": "The end correction of a resonance column is 1 cm. If the shortest length resonating with the tunning fork is 10 cm,  the next resonating length should be : ",
    "options": [
      "28 cm",
      "32 cm",
      "36 cm",
      "40 c"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "32 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "B9xnNpMaJ5UPp6lIpimJT",
    "question": "5 beats / econd are heard when a tuning fork is sounded with a sonometer wire under tension, when the length of the sonometer wire is either 0.95 m or 1 m. The frequency of the fork will be : ",
    "options": [
      "195 Hz",
      "150 Hz",
      "300 Hz",
      "251 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "195 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "bErMi1ftWwu3xRhj6kKR8",
    "question": "A tuning fork vibrates with frequency $$256$$ $$Hz$$ and gives one beat per second with the third normal mode of vibration of an open pipe. What is the length of the pipe ? (Speed of sound in air is $$340\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$)",
    "options": [
      "$$220$$ $$cm$$",
      "$$190$$ $$cm$$",
      "$$180$$ $$cm$$",
      "$$200$$ $$cm$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$200$$ $$cm$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "CMBFz9IyO51LtRUL",
    "question": "A granite rod of 60 cm length is clamped at its middle point and is set into longitudinal vibrations. The\ndensity of granite is 2.7 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup> kg/m<sup>3</sup> and its Young’s modulus is 9.27 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>10</sup> Pa. What will be the fundamental frequency of the longitudinal vibrations ?",
    "options": [
      "7.5 kHz",
      "5 kHz",
      "2.5 kHz",
      "10 kHz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "5 kHz"
  },
  {
    "id": "ishxRlvOA3XL98ow4g1KA",
    "question": "A heavy ball of mass M is suspendeed from the ceiling of a car by a light string of mass m (m &lt; &lt; M). When the car is at rest, the speed of transverse waves in the string is 60 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. When the car has acceleration a, the wave-speed increases to 60.5 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>. The value of a, in terms of gravitational acceleration g, is closest to : ",
    "options": [
      "$${g \\over {30}}$$",
      "$${g \\over 5}$$",
      "$${g \\over 10}$$",
      "$${g \\over 20}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$${g \\over 5}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "NvTjG9c3TSiLaGrvlNUf9",
    "question": "A string of length 1 m and mass 5 g is fixed at both ends. The tension in the string is 8.0 N. The string is set into vibration using an external vibrator of frequency 100 Hz. The separation between successive nodes on the string is close to -\n",
    "options": [
      "16.6 cm",
      "10.0 cm",
      "20.0 cm",
      "33.3 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "20.0 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "BYmFhNw4xdzmbhiLZpkm8",
    "question": "Equation of travelling wave on a stretched string of linear density 5 g/m is y = 0.03 sin(450 t – 9x) where distance and time are measured in SI units. The tension in the string is : ",
    "options": [
      "10 N",
      "7.5 N",
      "5 N",
      "12.5 N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "12.5 N"
  },
  {
    "id": "H61a7txwgKg17fypuWvj8",
    "question": "A travelling harmonic wave is represented by the equation y(x,t) = 10<sup>–3</sup>sin (50t + 2x), where, x and y are in mater and t is in seconds. Which of the following is a correct statement about the wave ? ",
    "options": [
      "The wave is propagating along the positive x-axis with speed 100 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "The wave is propagating along the positive x-axis with speed 25 ms<sup>–1</sup>\n",
      "The wave is propagating along the negative x-axis with speed 25 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "The wave is propagating along the negative x-axis with speed 100 ms<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "The wave is propagating along the negative x-axis with speed 25 ms<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "SR6QkQKvEU37EApJ9Zw53",
    "question": "The pressure wave, P = 0.01 sin [1000t – 3x] Nm<sup>–2</sup>,\ncorresponds to the sound produced by a vibrating blade\non a day when atmospheric temperature is 0°C. On\nsome other day, when temperature is T, the speed of\nsound produced by the same blade and at the same\nfrequency is found to be 336 ms<sup>–1</sup> . Approximate value\nof T is",
    "options": [
      "12°C",
      "15°C",
      "4°C",
      "11°C"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "4°C"
  },
  {
    "id": "EGhlHU9UoLuqxFE6E63rsa0w2w9jx7i5dk8",
    "question": "A small speaker delivers 2 W of audio output. At what distance from the speaker will one detect 120 dB\nintensity sound ? [Given reference intensity of sound as 10<sup>–12</sup> W/m<sup>2</sup>\n]",
    "options": [
      "20 cm",
      "10 cm",
      "40 cm",
      "30 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "40 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "K67KN8aXxmZ0aVS0LNjgy2xukff4m7wg",
    "question": "Assume that the displacement(s) of air is\nproportional to the pressure difference ($$\\Delta $$p)\ncreated by a sound wave. Displacement (s)\nfurther depends on the speed of sound (v),\ndensity of air ($$\\rho $$) and the frequency (f). If\n$$\\Delta $$p ~ 10 Pa, v ~ 300 m/s, $$\\rho $$ ~ 1 kg/m<sup>3</sup> and f ~ 1000 Hz,\nthen s will be of the order of (take the\nmultiplicative constant to be 1) :",
    "options": [
      "1 mm",
      "$${3 \\over {100}}$$ mm",
      "10 mm",
      "$${1 \\over {10}}$$ mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over {100}}$$ mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "UVhA9cbd0cmeABRTkWjgy2xukf237ezt",
    "question": "A uniform thin rope of length 12 m and mass 6 kg hangs vertically from a rigid support and a block\nof mass 2 kg is attached to its free end. A transverse short wavetrain of wavelength 6 cm is\nproduced at the lower end of the rope. What is the wavelength of the wavetrain (in cm) when it\nreaches the top of the rope ?",
    "options": [
      "12",
      "3",
      "9",
      "6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "12"
  },
  {
    "id": "B0Jecr48H1IJRiCs1Xjgy2xukev0j9v4",
    "question": "Two identical strings X and Z made of same\nmaterial have tension T<sub>X</sub> and T<sub>Z</sub> in them. If their\nfundamental frequencies are 450 Hz and\n300 Hz, respectively, then the ratio T<sub>X</sub>/T<sub>Z</sub> is\n",
    "options": [
      "2.25",
      "0.44",
      "1.25",
      "1.5"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "2.25"
  },
  {
    "id": "APAConvaEa3JPbTzze7k9k2k5hgyp97",
    "question": "A transverse wave travels on a taut steel wire\nwith a velocity of v when tension in it is\n2.06 × 10<sup>4</sup> N. When the tension is changed to\nT, the velocity changed to v/2. The value of T\nis close to :",
    "options": [
      "30.5 × 10<sup>4</sup> N",
      "2.50 × 10<sup>4</sup> N",
      "10.2 × 10<sup>2</sup> N",
      "5.15 × 10<sup>3</sup> N"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "5.15 × 10<sup>3</sup> N"
  },
  {
    "id": "VzV2m7NC9fsU8uYnup7k9k2k5dkt9w7",
    "question": "Speed of a transverse wave on a straight wire (mass 6.0 g, length 60 cm and area of cross-section 1.0 mm<sup>2</sup>) is 90 ms<sup>-1</sup>. If the Young's modulus of wire is 16 $$ \\times $$ 10<sup>11</sup> Nm<sup>-2</sup>, the extension of wire over its natural length is :",
    "options": [
      "0.03 mm",
      "0.04 mm",
      "0.02 mm",
      "0.01 mm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "0.03 mm"
  },
  {
    "id": "IedRVvf4ePGbKxJOmkjgy2xukeu3qoi4",
    "question": "For a transverse wave travelling along a straight line, the distance between two peaks (crests) is 5 m, while the distance between one crest and one trough is 1.5 m. The possible wavelengths (in m) of the are :\n",
    "options": [
      "1, 3, 5, .....",
      "$${1 \\over 1},{1 \\over 3},{1 \\over 5},$$ .....",
      "1, 2, 3, .....",
      "$${1 \\over 2},{1 \\over 4},{1 \\over 6},$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 1},{1 \\over 3},{1 \\over 5},$$ ....."
  },
  {
    "id": "SrsXOTYkGXmH4jH1a01klro19wm",
    "question": "Which of the following equations represents a travelling wave?",
    "options": [
      "y = Ae<sup>x</sup>cos($$\\omega$$t $$-$$ $$\\theta$$)",
      "y = Ae<sup>$$-$$x<sup>2</sup></sup>(vt + $$\\theta$$)",
      "y = A sin (15x $$-$$ 2t)",
      "y = A sinx cos$$\\omega$$t"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "y = A sin (15x $$-$$ 2t)"
  },
  {
    "id": "MP7OCgdzOAK4bfZ4Vj1kmk7usxc",
    "question": "A sound wave of frequency 245 Hz travels with the speed of 300 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup> along the positive x-axis. Each point of the wave moves to and from through a total distance of 6 cm. What will be the mathematical expression of this travelling wave?",
    "options": [
      "Y(x, t) = 0.03 [ sin 5.1x $$-$$ (0.2 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup>)t ]",
      "Y(x, t) = 0.03 [ sin 5.1x $$-$$ (1.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup>)t ]",
      "Y(x, t) = 0.06 [ sin 5.1x $$-$$ (1.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup>)t ]",
      "Y(x, t) = 0.06 [ sin 0.8x $$-$$ (0.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup>)t ]"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "Y(x, t) = 0.03 [ sin 5.1x $$-$$ (1.5 $$\\times$$ 10<sup>3</sup>)t ]"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l547mvg0",
    "question": "<p>A longitudinal wave is represented by $$x = 10\\sin 2\\pi \\left( {nt - {x \\over \\lambda }} \\right)$$ cm. The maximum particle velocity will be four times the wave velocity if the determined value of wavelength is equal to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2$$\\pi$$",
      "5$$\\pi$$",
      "$$\\pi$$",
      "$${{5\\pi } \\over 2}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "5$$\\pi$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56vbh22",
    "question": "<p>If a wave gets refracted into a denser medium, then which of the following is true?</p>",
    "options": [
      "wavelength, speed and frequency decreases.",
      "wavelength increases, sped decreases and frequency remains constant.",
      "wavelength and speed decreases but frequency remains constant.",
      "wavelength, speed and frequency increases."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "wavelength and speed decreases but frequency remains constant."
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5w2qtor",
    "question": "<p>Which of the following equations correctly represents a travelling wave having wavelength $$\\lambda$$ = 4.0 cm, frequency v = 100 Hz and travelling in positive x-axis direction?</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$y = A\\sin [(0.50\\,\\pi \\,c{m^{ - 1}})x - (100\\,\\pi \\,{s^{ - 1}})t]$$",
      "$$y = A\\sin \\,\\,2\\pi [(0.25\\,\\,c{m^{ - 1}})x - (50\\,{s^{ - 1}})t]$$",
      "$$y = A\\sin \\left[ {\\left( {{{2\\pi } \\over 4}\\,c{m^{ - 1}}} \\right)x - \\left( {{{2\\pi } \\over {100}}\\,{s^{ - 1}}} \\right)t} \\right]$$",
      "$$y = A\\sin \\,\\pi [(0.5\\,\\,c{m^{ - 1}})x - (200\\,\\,{s^{ - 1}})t]$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$y = A\\sin \\,\\pi [(0.5\\,\\,c{m^{ - 1}})x - (200\\,\\,{s^{ - 1}})t]$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6i179pu",
    "question": "<p>A transverse wave is represented by $$y=2 \\sin (\\omega t-k x)\\, \\mathrm{cm}$$. The value of wavelength (in $$\\mathrm{cm}$$) for which the wave velocity becomes equal to the maximum particle velocity, will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4$$\\pi$$",
      "2$$\\pi$$",
      "$$\\pi$$",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "4$$\\pi$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6ma0qrt",
    "question": "<p>In the wave equation</p>\n<p>$$\ny=0.5 \\sin \\frac{2 \\pi}{\\lambda}(400 \\mathrm{t}-x) \\,\\mathrm{m}\n$$</p>\n<p>the velocity of the wave will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "200 m/s",
      "200$$\\sqrt2$$ m/s",
      "400 m/s",
      "400$$\\sqrt2$$ m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "400 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldofk8r1",
    "question": "<p>A steel wire with mass per unit length $$7.0 \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~kg} \\mathrm{~m}^{-1}$$ is under tension of $$70 \\mathrm{~N}$$. The speed of transverse waves in the wire will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$50 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$100 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$",
      "$$200 \\pi\\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$100 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldye5kc3",
    "question": "<p>A travelling wave is described by the equation</p>\n<p>$$y(x,t) = [0.05\\sin (8x - 4t)]$$ m</p>\n<p>The velocity of the wave is : [all the quantities are in SI unit]</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\mathrm{4~ms^{-1}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{2~ms^{-1}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{8~ms^{-1}}$$",
      "$$\\mathrm{0.5~ms^{-1}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\mathrm{0.5~ms^{-1}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgvrlanb",
    "question": "<p>For a periodic motion represented by the equation</p>\n<p>$$y=\\sin \\omega \\mathrm{t}+\\cos \\omega \\mathrm{t}$$</p>\n<p>the amplitude of the motion is</p>",
    "options": [
      "1",
      "$$\\sqrt2$$",
      "0.5",
      "2"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "$$\\sqrt2$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lse6e2vu",
    "question": "<p>The fundamental frequency of a closed organ pipe is equal to the first overtone frequency of an open organ pipe. If length of the open pipe is $$60 \\mathrm{~cm}$$, the length of the closed pipe will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "15 cm",
      "60 cm",
      "45 cm",
      "30 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "15 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv3ve49a",
    "question": "<p>A plane progressive wave is given by $$y=2 \\cos 2 \\pi(330 \\mathrm{t}-x) \\mathrm{m}$$. The frequency of the wave is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "660 Hz",
      "340 Hz",
      "330 Hz",
      "165 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "basic-of-waves-and-progressive-waves",
    "solution": "330 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "4MofO2vKfhMQ6Pth",
    "question": "An observer moves towards a stationary source of sound, with a velocity one-fifth of the velocity of sound. What is the percentage increase in the apparent frequency ? ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.5\\% $$ ",
      "zero ",
      "$$20\\% $$ ",
      "$$5\\% $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "$$20\\% $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "SiKOIADsyZ9cP2gD",
    "question": "A whistle producing sound waves of frequencies $$9500$$ $$Hz$$ and above is approaching a stationary person with speed $$v$$ $$m{s^{ - 1}}.$$ The velocity of sound in air is $$300\\,m{s^{ - 1}}.$$ If the person can hear frequencies upto a maximum of $$10,000$$ $$HZ,$$ the maximum value of $$v$$ upto which he can hear whistle is ",
    "options": [
      "$$15\\sqrt 2 \\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$ ",
      "$${{15} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$ ",
      "$$15\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$ ",
      "$$30\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "$$15\\,\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "MYrgUrSyS9emm9QI",
    "question": "A motor cycle starts from rest and accelerates along a straight path at $$2m/{s^2}.$$ At the starting point of the motor cycle there is a stationary electric siren. How far has the motor cycle gone when the driver hears the frequency of the siren at $$94\\% $$ of its value when the motor cycle was at rest? (Speed of sound $$ = 330\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$) ",
    "options": [
      "$$98$$ $$m$$ ",
      "$$147$$ $$m$$ ",
      "$$196\\,m$$ ",
      "$$49$$ $$m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "$$98$$ $$m$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "OExRi6Lu6uVj7AJu",
    "question": "A train is moving on a straight track with speed $$20\\,m{s^{ - 1}}.$$ It is blowing its whistle at the frequency of $$1000$$ $$Hz$$. The percentage change in the frequency heard by a person standing near the track as the train passes him is (speed of sound $$ = 320\\,m{s^{ - 1}}$$) close to : ",
    "options": [
      "$$18\\% $$ ",
      "$$24\\% $$",
      "$$6\\% $$",
      "$$12\\% $$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "$$12\\% $$"
  },
  {
    "id": "60X1nzX2V8xmSQS3CmPfZ",
    "question": "Two engines pass each other moving in opposite directions with uniform speed of 30 m/s. One of them is blowing a whistle of frequency 540 Hz. Calculate the\nfrequency heard by driver of second engine before they pass each other. Speed of sound is 330 m/sec :",
    "options": [
      "450 Hz ",
      "540 Hz",
      "648 Hz",
      "270 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "648 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "bsRPs9UNc7doIecsOnarW",
    "question": "A toy-car, blowing its horn, is moving with a steady speed of 5 m/s, away from a wall. An observer, towards whom the toy car is moving, is able to hear 5 beats per second. If the velocity of sound in air is 340 m/s, the frequency of the horn of the toy car is close to :\n",
    "options": [
      "680 Hz",
      "510 Hz",
      "340 Hz",
      "170 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "170 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "2KcecQ7w09psggxN",
    "question": "An observer is moving with half the speed of light towards a stationary microwave source emitting waves\nat frequency 10 GHz. What is the frequency of the microwave measured by the observer? (speed of light =\n3 ×10<sup>8</sup> ms<sup>–1</sup>) ",
    "options": [
      "15.3 GHz",
      "10.1 GHz",
      "12.1 GHz",
      "17.3 GHz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "17.3 GHz"
  },
  {
    "id": "BVOU7UdVCNvscWtoYT6jT",
    "question": "Two sitar strings,  A and B, playing the note 'Dha' are slightly out of tune and produce beats of frequency 5 Hz. The tension of the string B s slightly increased and the beat frequency is found to decrease by 3Hz. If the frequency of A is 425 Hz, the original frequency of B is : ",
    "options": [
      "430 Hz",
      "420 Hz",
      "428 Hz",
      "422 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "420 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "SpUIuJrk4YBMGww1p4Iko",
    "question": "A musician using an open flute of length 50 cm producess second harmonic sound waves. A person runs towards the musician from another end of hall at  a speed of 10 km/h. If the wave speed is 330 m/s, the frequency heard by the running person shall be close to : ",
    "options": [
      "666 Hz",
      "753 Hz",
      "500 Hz",
      "333 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "666 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "ECXQtYbodUIg95yuaHdt1",
    "question": "A train moves towards a stationary observer with speed 34 m/s. The train sounds a whistle and its frequency registered by the observer is ƒ<sub>1</sub>. If the speed of the train is reduced to 17 m/s, the frequency registered is ƒ<sub>2</sub>. If speed of sound is 340 m/s, then the ratio ƒ<sub>1</sub>/ƒ<sub>2</sub> is - ",
    "options": [
      "19/18",
      "20/19",
      "21/20",
      "18/17"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "19/18"
  },
  {
    "id": "l25sS5PIYF23EuyYXSlOP",
    "question": "Two cars A and B are moving away from each\nother in opposite directions. Both the cars are\nmoving with a speed of 20 ms<sup>–1</sup> with respect\nto the ground. If an observer in car A detects\na frequency 2000 Hz of the sound coming from\ncar B, what is the natural frequency of the sound\nsource in car B ?<br/>\n(speed of sound in air = 340 ms<sup>–1</sup>) :-",
    "options": [
      "2300 Hz",
      "2060 Hz",
      "2250 Hz",
      "2150 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "2250 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "i5pnbyKL1RZWoPSsSe18hoxe66ijvztf4yl",
    "question": "A stationary source emits sound waves of\nfrequency 500 Hz. Two observers moving\nalong a line passing through the source detect\nsound to be of frequencies 480 Hz and 530 Hz.\nTheir respective speeds are, in ms–1,\n(Given speed of sound = 300 m/s)",
    "options": [
      "12, 18",
      "16, 14",
      "12, 16",
      "8, 18"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "12, 18"
  },
  {
    "id": "oFaY37SfwT0dHIv9g43rsa0w2w9jwzj67bh",
    "question": "A source of sound S is moving with a velocity of 50 m/s towards a stationary observer. The observer\nmeasures the frequency of the source as 1000 Hz. What will be the apparent frequency of the source when it\nis moving away from the observer after crossing him? (Take velocity of sound in air is 350 m/s)",
    "options": [
      "750 Hz",
      "857 Hz",
      "807 Hz",
      "1143 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "750 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "jFjezGAIX0ffZW5UK93rsa0w2w9jx3sa7hv",
    "question": "A submarine (A) travelling at 18 km/hr is being chased along the line of its velocity by another submarine\n(B) travelling at 27 km/hr. B sends a sonar signal of 500 Hz to detect A and receives a reflected sound of\nfrequency $$\\upsilon $$. The value of $$\\upsilon $$ is close to: (Speed of sound in water =1500 ms<sup>–1</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "507 Hz",
      "502 Hz",
      "499 Hz",
      "504 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "502 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "l48AhpYxhb8JRSAuT53rsa0w2w9jx7gevqh",
    "question": "Two sources of sound S<sub>1</sub> and S<sub>2</sub> produce sound waves of same frequency 660 Hz. A listener is moving from\nsource S<sub>1</sub> towards S<sub>2</sub> with a constant speed u m/s and he hears 10 beats/s. The velocity of sound is 330 m/s.\nThen, u equals : ",
    "options": [
      "10.0 m/s",
      "5.5 m/s",
      "15.0 m/s",
      "2.5 m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "2.5 m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "jxwkx4ONjuEghsZq9tjgy2xukfl34vez",
    "question": "A driver in a car, approaching a vertical wall\nnotices that the frequency of his car horn, has\nchanged from 440 Hz to 480 Hz, when it gets\nreflected from the wall. If the speed of sound in\nair is 345 m/s, then the speed of the car is :",
    "options": [
      "36 km/hr",
      "54 km/hr",
      "24 km/hr",
      "18 km/hr"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "54 km/hr"
  },
  {
    "id": "SnKKcB2x4K79oGV17g7k9k2k5f7qel2",
    "question": "A stationary observer receives sound from two identical tuning forks, one of which approaches\nand the other one recedes with the same speed (much less than the speed of sound). The\nobserver hears 2 beats/sec. The oscillation frequency of each tuning fork is v<sub>0</sub>\n = 1400 Hz and the\nvelocity of sound in air is 350 m/s. The speed of each tuning fork is close to :",
    "options": [
      "1 m/s",
      "$${1 \\over 8}$$ m/s",
      "$${1 \\over 4}$$ m/s",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$ m/s"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 4}$$ m/s"
  },
  {
    "id": "hHz0hj0lEMSO0UBsvujgy2xukfahqmr0",
    "question": "The driver of a bus approaching a big wall notices that the frequency of his bus's horn changes\nfrom 420 Hz to 490 Hz when he hears it after it gets reflected from the wall. Find the speed of the\nbus if speed of the sound is 330 ms<sup>–1</sup>.",
    "options": [
      "91 kmh<sup>–1</sup>",
      "81 kmh<sup>–1</sup>",
      "61 kmh<sup>–1</sup>",
      "71 kmh<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "91 kmh<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l57qc1t6",
    "question": "<p>An observer moves towards a stationary source of sound with a velocity equal to one-fifth of the velocity of sound. The percentage change in the frequency will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "20%",
      "10%",
      "5%",
      "0%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "20%"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldspadeh",
    "question": "<p>A person observes two moving trains, 'A' reaching the station and 'B' leaving the station with equal speed of $$30 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. If both trains emit sounds with frequency $$300 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$, (Speed of sound: $$330 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$) approximate difference of frequencies heard by the person will be:</p>",
    "options": [
      "10 Hz",
      "55 Hz",
      "80 Hz",
      "33 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "55 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgswkwfl",
    "question": "<p>A car P travelling at $$20 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ sounds its horn at a frequency of $$400 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$. Another car $$\\mathrm{Q}$$ is travelling behind the first car in the same direction with a velocity $$40 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$.\n\nThe frequency heard by the passenger of the car $$\\mathrm{Q}$$ is approximately [Take, velocity of sound $$=360 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ ]</p>",
    "options": [
      "485 Hz",
      "514 Hz",
      "421 Hz",
      "471 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "421 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lh017qcw",
    "question": "<p>The engine of a train moving with speed $$10 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ towards a platform sounds a whistle at frequency $$400 \\mathrm{~Hz}$$. The frequency heard by a passenger inside the train is: (neglect air speed. Speed of sound in air $$=330 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "200 Hz",
      "412 Hz",
      "400 Hz",
      "388 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "doppler-effect",
    "solution": "400 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "9Ich0KInX8771D3Q",
    "question": "A wave $$y=a$$ $$\\sin \\left( {\\omega t - kx} \\right)$$ on a string meets with another wave producing a node at $$x=0.$$ Then the equation of the unknown wave is ",
    "options": [
      "$$y = a\\,\\sin \\,\\left( {\\omega t + kx} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$y =  - a\\,\\sin \\,\\left( {\\omega t + kx} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$y = a\\,\\sin \\,\\left( {\\omega t - kx} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$y =  - a\\,\\sin \\,\\left( {\\omega t - kx} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "$$y =  - a\\,\\sin \\,\\left( {\\omega t + kx} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "pvjyp3ZHeVkb48LJ",
    "question": "A tuning fork arrangement (pair) produces $$4$$ beats/sec with one fork of frequency $$288$$ $$cps.$$ A little wax is placed on the unknown fork and it then produces $$2$$ beats/sec. The frequency of the unknown fork is ",
    "options": [
      "$$286$$ $$cps$$ ",
      "$$292$$ $$cps$$ ",
      "$$294$$ $$cps$$ ",
      "$$288$$ $$cps$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "$$292$$ $$cps$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "pLQ7IRnOZQeVfyYK",
    "question": "A tuning fork of known frequency $$256$$ $$Hz$$ makes $$5$$ beats per second with the vibrating string of a piano. The beat frequency decreases to $$2$$ beats per second when the tension in the piano string is slightly increased. The frequency of the piano string before increasing the tension was ",
    "options": [
      "$$256 + 2Hz$$ ",
      "$$256 - 2Hz$$ ",
      "$$256 - 5Hz$$ ",
      "$$256 + 5Hz$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "$$256 - 5Hz$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "QsfC42VBdLAKECVD",
    "question": "A metal wire of linear mass density of $$9.8$$ $$g/m$$ is stretched with a tension of $$10$$ $$kg$$-$$wt$$ between two rigid supports $$1$$ metre apart. The wire passes at its middle point between the poles of a permanent magnet, and it vibrates in resonance when carrying an alternating current of frequency $$n.$$ The frequency $$n$$ of the alternating source is  ",
    "options": [
      "$$50$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$100$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$200$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$25$$ $$Hz$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "$$50$$ $$Hz$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "R72cAxAJntbMHhze",
    "question": "When two tuning forks (fork $$1$$ and fork $$2$$) are sounded simultaneously, $$4$$ beats per second are heated. Now, some tape is attached on the prong of the fork $$2.$$ When the tuning forks are sounded again, $$6$$ beats per second are heard. If the frequency of fork $$1$$ is $$200$$ $$Hz$$, then what was the original frequency of fork $$2$$ ? ",
    "options": [
      "$$202$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$200$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$204$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$196$$ $$Hz$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "$$196$$ $$Hz$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "BOo8T7fZF1xCgKO3",
    "question": "A string is stretched between fixed points separated by $$75.0$$ $$cm.$$ It is observed to have resonant frequencies of $$420$$ $$Hz$$ and $$315$$ $$Hz$$. There are no other resonant frequencies between these two. Then, the lowest resonant frequency for this string is ",
    "options": [
      "$$105$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$1.05$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$1050$$ $$Hz$$ ",
      "$$10.5$$ $$Hz$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "$$105$$ $$Hz$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "JrmC9oOmB9ar6zq3",
    "question": "While measuring the speed of sound by performing a resonance column experiment, a student gets the first resonance condition at a column length of $$18$$ $$cm$$ during winter. Repeating the same experiment during summer, she measures the column length to be $$x$$ $$cm$$ for the second resonance. Then ",
    "options": [
      "$$18 &gt; x$$ ",
      "$$x &gt; 54$$",
      "$$54 &gt; x &gt; 36$$ ",
      "$$36 &gt; x &gt; 18$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "$$x &gt; 54$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "fEk2e829UwWupmJ5",
    "question": "Three sound waves of equal amplitudes have frequencies $$\\left( {v - 1} \\right),\\,v,\\,\\left( {v + 1} \\right).$$ They superpose to give beats. The number of beats produced per second will be :",
    "options": [
      "$$3$$",
      "$$2$$ ",
      "$$1$$ ",
      "$$4$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "$$2$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "cnyozyez95rIrvz7",
    "question": "A pipe of length $$85$$ $$cm$$ is closed from one end. Find the number of possible natural oscillations of air column in the pipe whose frequencies lie below $$1250$$ $$Hz$$. The velocity of sound in air is $$340$$ $$m/s$$. ",
    "options": [
      "$$12$$ ",
      "$$8$$ ",
      "$$6$$ ",
      "$$4$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "$$6$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "rTKNtTaUgcoKrODk",
    "question": "A pipe open at both ends has a fundamental frequency $$f$$ in air. The pipe is dipped vertically in water so that half of it is in water. The fundamental frequency of the air column is now : ",
    "options": [
      "$$2f$$ ",
      "$$f$$ ",
      "$${f \\over 2}$$ ",
      "$${3f \\over 4}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "$$f$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "4clTZBYdW9mQhKJbri3rsa0w2w9jx7h05fo",
    "question": "A tuning fork of frequency 480 Hz is used in an experiment for measuring speed of sound (v) in air\nby resonance tube method. Resonance is observed to occur at two successive lengths of the air column,\nl<sub>1</sub> = 30 cm and l<sub>2</sub> = 70 cm. Then, v is equal to -\n",
    "options": [
      "338 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "384 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "379 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "332 ms<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "384 ms<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "dDpBFrPerkbjbOX4uj3AN",
    "question": "A string 2.0 m long and fixed at its ends is\ndriven by a 240 Hz vibrator. The string vibrates\nin its third harmonic mode. The speed of the\nwave and its fundamental frequency is :-",
    "options": [
      "180m/s, 80 Hz",
      "180m/s, 120 Hz",
      "320m/s, 120 Hz",
      "320m/s, 80 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "320m/s, 80 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "MnhNQRDhUTsaArZEjsflg",
    "question": "A string is clamped at both the ends and it is\nvibrating in its 4th harmonic. The equation of the\nstationary wave is Y = 0.3 sin(0.157x) cos(200pt).\nThe length of the string is : (All quantities are\nin SI units.)",
    "options": [
      "60 m",
      "20 m",
      "80 m",
      "40 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "80 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "8db4RgUWh6H8WZ7RsBLsv",
    "question": "A resonance tube is old and has jagged end. It is still used in the laboratory to determine velocity of sound in air. A tuning fork of frequency 512 Hz produces first resonance when the tube is filled with water to a mark 11 cm below a reference mark, near the open end of the tube. The experiment is repeated with another fork of frequency 256 Hz which produces first resonance when water reaches a mark 27 cm below the reference mark. The velocity of sound in air, obtained in the experiment, is close to : ",
    "options": [
      "335 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "328 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "341 ms<sup>–1</sup>",
      "322 ms<sup>–1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "328 ms<sup>–1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "v0ZzHvZpHuNn1LTcyH7k9k2k5imbtht",
    "question": "Three harmonic waves having equal frequency\n$$\\nu $$ and same intensity $${I_0}$$, have phase angles 0, $${\\pi  \\over 4}$$ and $$ - {\\pi  \\over 4}$$ respectively. When they are\nsuperimposed the intensity of the resultant wave\nis close to :",
    "options": [
      "5.8 I<sub>0</sub>",
      "3 I<sub>0</sub>",
      "0.2 I<sub>0</sub>",
      "I<sub>0</sub>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "5.8 I<sub>0</sub>"
  },
  {
    "id": "IZxmnnFa29NVFrr8Kw7k9k2k5kukxcz",
    "question": "A wire of length L and mass per unit length\n6.0 × 10<sup>–3</sup> kgm<sup>–1</sup> is put under tension of\n540 N. Two consecutive frequencies that it\nresonates at are : 420 Hz and 490 Hz. Then L\nin meters is :",
    "options": [
      "5.1 m",
      "2.1 m",
      "1.1 m",
      "8.1 m"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "2.1 m"
  },
  {
    "id": "s0OKiThrw7Ybc7Wqljjgy2xukfg7w1tf",
    "question": "In a resonance tube experiment when the tube\nis filled with water up to a height of 17.0 cm\nfrom bottom, it resonates with a given tuning\nfork. When the water level is raised the next\nresonance with the same tuning fork occurs at\na height of 24.5 cm. If the velocity of sound in\nair is 330 m/s, the tuning fork frequency is :",
    "options": [
      "2200 Hz",
      "3300 Hz",
      "1100 Hz",
      "550 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "2200 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "UcGyT2yc2Dc0vbsolj1klryf526",
    "question": "A student is performing the experiment of resonance column. The diameter of the column tube is 6 cm. The frequency of the tuning fork is 504 Hz. Speed of the sound at the given temperature is 336 m/s. The zero of the metre scale coincides with the top end of the resonance column tube. The reading of the water level in the column when the first resonance occurs is :",
    "options": [
      "13 cm",
      "18.4 cm",
      "16.6 cm",
      "14.8 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "14.8 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "0zXuZhUDKLmKtGvzuf1klunfw2z",
    "question": "A tuning fork A of unknown frequency produces 5 beats/s with a fork of known frequency 340 Hz. When fork A is filed, the beat frequency decreases to 2 beats/s. What is the frequency of fork A?",
    "options": [
      "335 Hz",
      "345 Hz",
      "338 Hz",
      "342 Hz"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "335 Hz"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l56a1cwz",
    "question": "<p>The velocity of sound in a gas, in which two wavelengths 4.08 m and 4.16 m produce 40 beats in 12s, will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "282.8 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "175.5 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "353.6 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "707.2 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "707.2 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c3wc9l",
    "question": "<p>The equations of two waves are given by :</p>\n<p>y<sub>1</sub> = 5 sin 2$$\\pi$$(x - vt) cm</p>\n<p>y<sub>2</sub> = 3 sin 2$$\\pi$$(x $$-$$ vt + 1.5) cm</p>\n<p>These waves are simultaneously passing through a string. The amplitude of the resulting wave is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 cm",
      "4 cm",
      "5.8 cm",
      "8 cm"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "waves",
    "topic": "superposition-and-reflection-of-waves",
    "solution": "2 cm"
  },
  {
    "id": "kdj7FKu9ut7VhCZO",
    "question": "A ball whose kinetic energy E, is projected at an angle of $$45^\\circ $$ to the horizontal. The kinetic energy of the ball at the highest point of its height will be",
    "options": [
      "E",
      "$${E \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$",
      "$${E \\over 2}$$",
      "zero"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$${E \\over 2}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "dciWqKRInJedFcSE",
    "question": "If a body looses half of its velocity on penetrating $$3$$ $$cm$$ in a wooden block, then how much will it penetrate more before coming to rest?",
    "options": [
      "$$1$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$2$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$3$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$4$$ $$cm$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$1$$ $$cm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "slG1cirAyiL5Igxz",
    "question": "A wire suspended vertically from one of its ends is stretched by attaching a weight of $$200N$$ to the lower end. The weight stretches the wire by $$1$$ $$mm.$$ Then the elastic energy stored in the wire is ",
    "options": [
      "$$0.2$$ $$J$$ ",
      "$$10$$ $$J$$ ",
      "$$20$$ $$J$$ ",
      "$$0.1$$ $$J$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$0.1$$ $$J$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "mor1tIL395NgGm6o",
    "question": "A particle moves in a straight line with retardation proportional to its displacement. Its loss of kinetic energy for any displacement $$x$$ is proportional to ",
    "options": [
      "$$x$$ ",
      "$${e^x}$$ ",
      "$${x^2}$$ ",
      "$${\\log _e}x$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$${x^2}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "E06vjkbrljlbse8g",
    "question": "A uniform chain of length $$2$$ $$m$$ is kept on a table such that a length of $$60$$ $$cm$$ hangs freely from the edge of  the table. The total mass of the chain is $$4$$ $$kg.$$ What is the work done in pulling the entire chain on the table? ",
    "options": [
      "$$12$$ $$J$$ ",
      "$$3.6$$  $$J$$ ",
      "$$7.2$$ $$J$$ ",
      "$$1200$$ $$J$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$3.6$$  $$J$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "WXGbxhl2cLFb0XzO",
    "question": "A particle is acted upon by a force of constant magnitude which is always perpendicular to the velocity of the particle, the motion of the particles takes place in a plane. It follows that ",
    "options": [
      "its kinetic energy is constant ",
      "is acceleration is constant ",
      "its velocity is constant ",
      "it moves in a straight line "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "its kinetic energy is constant "
  },
  {
    "id": "IFRAJQhvbCb0V715",
    "question": "A bullet fired into a fixed target loses half of its velocity after penetrating $$3$$ $$cm.$$ How much further it will penetrate before coming to rest assuming that it faces constant resistance to motion? ",
    "options": [
      "$$2.0$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$3.0$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$1.0$$ $$cm$$ ",
      "$$1.5$$ $$cm$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$1.0$$ $$cm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "k6wzlGYB11QeZqO3",
    "question": "The upper half of an inclined plane with inclination $$\\phi $$ is perfectly smooth while the lower half is rough. A body starting from rest at the top will again come to rest at the bottom if the coefficient of friction for the lower half is given by ",
    "options": [
      "$$2\\,\\cos \\,\\,\\phi $$ ",
      "$$2\\,sin\\,\\,\\phi $$ ",
      "$$\\,\\tan \\,\\,\\phi $$ ",
      "$$2\\,\\tan \\,\\,\\phi $$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$2\\,\\tan \\,\\,\\phi $$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "N1FwfMlH6cr2lPTl",
    "question": "A  spherical ball of mass $$20$$ $$kg$$ is stationary at the top of a hill of height $$100$$ $$m$$. It rolls down a smooth surface to the ground, then climbs up another hill of height $$30$$ $$m$$ and finally rolls down to a horizontal base at a height of $$20$$ $$m$$ above the ground. The velocity attained by the ball is ",
    "options": [
      "$$20$$ $$m/s$$ ",
      "$$40$$ $$m/s$$ ",
      "$$10\\sqrt {30} \\,\\,\\,m/s$$ ",
      "$$10\\,\\,m/s$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$40$$ $$m/s$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "8TUAunhq3xPQ0rm0",
    "question": "A mass of $$M$$ $$kg$$ is suspended by a weightless string. The horizontal force that is required to displace it until the string makes an angle of $${45^ \\circ }$$ with the initial vertical direction is ",
    "options": [
      "$$Mg\\left( {\\sqrt 2  + 1} \\right)$$ ",
      "$$Mg\\sqrt 2 $$ ",
      "$${{Mg} \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "$$Mg\\left( {\\sqrt 2  - 1} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$Mg\\left( {\\sqrt 2  - 1} \\right)$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "usA64o7LZ73SyIrB",
    "question": "A ball of mass $$0.2$$ $$kg$$ is thrown vertically upwards by applying a force by hand. If the hand moves $$0.2$$ $$m$$ while applying the force and the ball goes upto $$2$$ $$m$$ height further, find the magnitude of the force. (consider $$g = 10\\,m/{s^2}$$).",
    "options": [
      "$$4N$$ ",
      "$$16$$ $$N$$ ",
      "$$20$$ $$N$$ ",
      "$$22$$ $$N$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$22$$ $$N$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "UD5n3M6kkE7ZAY2I",
    "question": "A particle of mass $$100g$$ is thrown vertically upwards with a speed of $$5$$ $$m/s$$. The work done by the force of gravity during the time the particle goes up is ",
    "options": [
      "$$-0.5J$$ ",
      "$$-1.25J$$ ",
      "$$1.25J$$ ",
      "$$0.5J$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$-1.25J$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "YUsFXpo3NaZrN29x",
    "question": "The potential energy of a $$1$$ $$kg$$ particle free to move along the $$x$$-axis is given by $$V\\left( x \\right) = \\left( {{{{x^4}} \\over 4} - {{{x^2}} \\over 2}} \\right)J$$.\n<p>The total mechanical energy of the particle is $$2J.$$ Then, the maximum speed (in $$m/s$$) is </p>",
    "options": [
      "$${3 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "$${\\sqrt 2 }$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ ",
      "$$2$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$${3 \\over {\\sqrt 2 }}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "fikBwNmY84OD7I2h",
    "question": "A particle is projected at $$60^\\circ $$ to the horizontal with a kinetic energy K. The kinetic energy at the\nhighest point is",
    "options": [
      "K/2",
      "K",
      "Zero",
      "K/4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "K/4"
  },
  {
    "id": "cykLCXddi80lGcXx",
    "question": "A $$2$$ $$kg$$ block slides on a horizontal floor with a speed of $$4m/s.$$ It strikes a uncompressed spring, and compress it till the block is motionless. The kinetic friction force is $$15N$$ and spring constant is $$10, 000$$ $$N/m.$$ The spring compresses by ",
    "options": [
      "$$8.5cm$$ ",
      "$$5.5cm$$ ",
      "$$2.5cm$$ ",
      "$$11.0cm$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$5.5cm$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "VEKmSiNkuXyahSLy",
    "question": "An athlete in the olympic games covers a distance of $$100$$ $$m$$ in $$10$$ $$s.$$ His kinetic energy can be estimated to be in the range",
    "options": [
      "$$200J-500J$$ ",
      "$$2 \\times {10^5}J - 3 \\times {10^5}J$$ ",
      "$$20,000J - 50,000J$$ ",
      "$$2,000J - 5,000J$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$2,000J - 5,000J$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "uWhjPEbP9mZUUT5B",
    "question": "The potential energy function for the force between two atoms in a diatomic molecule is approximately given by $$U\\left( x \\right) = {a \\over {{x^{12}}}} - {b \\over {{x^6}}},$$ where $$a$$ and $$b$$ are constants and $$x$$ is the distance between the atoms. If the dissociation energy of the molecule is $$D = \\left[ {U\\left( {x = \\infty } \\right) - {U_{at\\,\\,equilibrium}}} \\right],\\,\\,D$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$${{{b^2}} \\over {2a}}$$ ",
      "$${{{b^2}} \\over {12a}}$$ ",
      "$${{{b^2}} \\over {4a}}$$",
      "$${{{b^2}} \\over {6a}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$${{{b^2}} \\over {4a}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "KY02Pg1xJZ6d8kDg",
    "question": "This question has Statement $$1$$ and Statement $$2.$$ Of the four choices given after the Statements, choose the one that best describes the two Statements. \n<br/><br/><p>If two springs $${S_1}$$ and $${S_2}$$ of force constants $${k_1}$$ and $${k_2}$$, respectively, are stretched by the same force, it is found that more work is done on spring $${S_1}$$ than on spring $${S_2}$$.\n<br/><br/><b>STATEMENT 1:</b> If stretched by the same amount work done on $${S_1}$$, Work done on $${S_1}$$ is more than $${S_2}$$\n<br/><b>STATEMENT 2:</b> $${k_1} &lt; {k_2}$$</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement 1 is false, Statement 2 is true ",
      "Statement 1 is true, Statement 2 is false",
      "Statement 1 is true, Statement 2 is true, Statement 2 is the correct explanation for Statement 1",
      "Statement 1 is true, Statement 2 is true, Statement 2 is not the correct explanation for Statement 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "Statement 1 is false, Statement 2 is true "
  },
  {
    "id": "kEGfJEfrcCXU58yX",
    "question": "A person trying to lose weight by burning fat lifts a mass of $$10$$ $$kg$$ upto a height of $$1$$ $$m$$ $$1000$$ times. Assume that the potential energy lost each time he lowers the mass  is dissipated.  How much fat will he use up considering the work done only when the weight is lifted up? Fat supplies $$3.8 \\times {10^7}J$$ of energy per $$kg$$ which is converted to mechanical energy with a $$20\\% $$  efficiency rate. Take $$g = 9.8\\,m{s^{ - 2}}$$ :",
    "options": [
      "$$9.89 \\times {10^{ - 3}}\\,\\,kg$$ ",
      "$$12.89 \\times {10^{ - 3}}\\,kg$$ ",
      "$$2.45 \\times {10^{ - 3}}\\,\\,kg$$ ",
      "$$6.45 \\times {10^{ - 3}}\\,\\,kg$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$12.89 \\times {10^{ - 3}}\\,kg$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "y1q1Cv23VTPqHYK4",
    "question": "A body of mass m = 10<sup>–2</sup> kg is moving in a medium and experiences a frictional force F = –kv<sup>2</sup>. Its initial speed is v<sub>0</sub> = 10 ms<sup>–1</sup>. If, after 10 s, its energy is $${1 \\over 8}mv_0^2$$, the value of k will be: ",
    "options": [
      "10<sup>-1</sup> kg m<sup>-1</sup> s<sup>-1</sup>",
      "10<sup>-3</sup> kg m<sup>-1</sup>",
      "10<sup>-3</sup> kg s<sup>-1</sup>",
      "10<sup>-4</sup> kg m<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "10<sup>-4</sup> kg m<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "uJ5k3O0S7r7e3uvy",
    "question": "A time dependent force F = 6t acts on a particle of mass 1 kg. If the particle starts from rest, the work done\nby the force during the first 1 sec. will be:",
    "options": [
      "18 J ",
      "4.5 J ",
      "22 J ",
      "9 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "4.5 J "
  },
  {
    "id": "C4qcuKUAna4e6RlkuWtgW",
    "question": "An object is dropped from a height h from the ground. Every time it hits the ground it looses 50% of its kinetic energy. The total distance covered as t $$ \\to $$ $$\\infty $$ is :",
    "options": [
      "3h",
      "$$\\infty $$",
      "$${5 \\over 3}$$h",
      "$${8 \\over 3}$$h"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "3h"
  },
  {
    "id": "nQBrRdrD6Jc5VGZS",
    "question": "A particle is moving in a circular path of radius $$a$$ under the action of an attractive potential $$U =  - {k \\over {2{r^2}}}$$ Its total energy is:",
    "options": [
      "$$ - {3 \\over 2}{k \\over {{a^2}}}$$ ",
      "Zero",
      "$$ - {k \\over {4{a^2}}}$$ ",
      "$$ {k \\over {2{a^2}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "Zero"
  },
  {
    "id": "XE1KidIvUZJDR05xGBii4",
    "question": "Two particles of the same mass m are moving in circular orbits because of force, given by $$F\\left( r \\right) = {{ - 16} \\over r} - {r^3}$$\n<br/><br/>The first particle is at a distance r = 1, and the second, at r = 4. The best estimate for the ratio of kinetic energies of the first and the second particle is closest to : ",
    "options": [
      "$$6 \\times {10^{ - 2}}$$",
      "$$3 \\times {10^{ - 3}}$$",
      "$${10^{ - 1}}$$",
      "$$6 \\times {10^{  2}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$6 \\times {10^{ - 2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "3uxZwzJ2S5Rygx7z1OOL6",
    "question": "A force acts on a 2 kg object so that its position is given as a function of time as x = 3t<sup>2</sup> + 5. What is the work done by this force in first 5 seconds ? ",
    "options": [
      "850 J",
      "950 J",
      "875 J",
      "900 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "900 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "moa8dmyYInAJFicbkaXoD",
    "question": "A particle which is experiencing a force, given by $$\\overrightarrow F  = 3\\widehat i - 12\\widehat j,$$ undergoes a displacement of $$\\overrightarrow d  = 4\\overrightarrow i $$ particle had a kinetic energy of 3 J at the beginning of the displacement, what is its kinetic energy at the end of the displacement ? \n",
    "options": [
      "9 J",
      "10 J",
      "12 J",
      "15 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "15 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "3GgNSfzUmHCgcT4Ul4jgy2xukfrny787",
    "question": "If the potential energy between two molecules is given by\n<br/>U = $$ - {A \\over {{r^6}}} + {B \\over {{r^{12}}}}$$,\n<br/>then at equilibrium,\nseparation between molecules, and the potential energy are :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left( {{{2B} \\over A}} \\right)^{1/6}}$$, $$ - {{{A^2}} \\over {4B}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{2B} \\over A}} \\right)^{1/6}}, - {{{A^2}} \\over {2B}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{B \\over A}} \\right)^{1/6}},0$$",
      "$${\\left( {{B \\over {2A}}} \\right)^{1/6}}, - {{{A^2}} \\over {2B}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$${\\left( {{{2B} \\over A}} \\right)^{1/6}}$$, $$ - {{{A^2}} \\over {4B}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "O47owIXADRkp0jLqr41kmj171d8",
    "question": "A boy is rolling a 0.5 kg ball on the frictionless floor with the speed of 20 ms<sup>-1</sup>. The ball gets deflected by an obstacle on the way. After deflection it moves with 5% of its initial kinetic energy. What is the speed of the ball now?",
    "options": [
      "14.41 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "19.0 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "4.47 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "1.00 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "4.47 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktjpowmd",
    "question": "A block moving horizontally on a smooth surface with a speed of 40 m/s splits into two parts with masses in the ratio of 1 : 2. If the smaller part moves at 60 m/s in the same direction, then the fractional change in kinetic energy is :-",
    "options": [
      "$${{1 \\over 3}}$$",
      "$${{2 \\over 3}}$$",
      "$${{1 \\over 8}}$$",
      "$${{1 \\over 4}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$${{1 \\over 8}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5476l4l",
    "question": "<p>A particle of mass 500 gm is moving in a straight line with velocity v = b x<sup>5/2</sup>. The work done by the net force during its displacement from x = 0 to x = 4 m is : (Take b = 0.25 m<sup>$$-$$3/2</sup> s<sup>$$-$$1</sup>).</p>",
    "options": [
      "2 J",
      "4 J",
      "8 J",
      "16 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "16 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6dxxjk3",
    "question": "<p>A body of mass $$0.5 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ travels on straight line path with velocity $$v=\\left(3 x^{2}+4\\right) \\mathrm{m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. The net workdone by the force during its displacement from $$x=0$$ to $$x=2 \\mathrm{~m}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "64 J",
      "60 J",
      "120 J",
      "128 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "60 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6f57pk1",
    "question": "<p>A bag of sand of mass 9.8 kg is suspended by a rope. A bullet of 200 g travelling with speed 10 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup> gets embedded in it, then loss of kinetic energy will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4.9 J",
      "9.8 J",
      "14.7 J",
      "19.6 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "9.8 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6p45uh5",
    "question": "<p>A ball is projected with kinetic energy E, at an angle of $$60^{\\circ}$$ to the horizontal. The kinetic energy of this ball at the highest point of its flight will become :</p>",
    "options": [
      "Zero",
      "$$\\frac{E}{2}$$",
      "$$\\frac{E}{4}$$",
      "E"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{E}{4}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsojq5f",
    "question": "<p>A stone is projected at angle $$30^{\\circ}$$ to the horizontal. The ratio of kinetic energy of the stone at point of projection to its kinetic energy at the highest point of flight will be -</p>",
    "options": [
      "1 : 4",
      "1 : 2",
      "4 : 3",
      "4 : 1"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "4 : 3"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq2uj1c",
    "question": "<p>Two bodies are having kinetic energies in the ratio 16 : 9. If they have same linear momentum, the ratio of their masses respectively is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$3: 4$$",
      "$$4: 3$$",
      "$$9: 16$$",
      "$$16: 9$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$9: 16$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgrh1w3m",
    "question": "<p>Given below are two statements:</p>\n<p>Statement I : A truck and a car moving with same kinetic energy are brought to rest by applying breaks which provide equal retarding forces. Both come to rest in equal distance.</p>\n<p>Statement II : A car moving towards east takes a turn and moves towards north, the speed remains unchanged. The acceleration of the car is zero.</p>\n<p>In the light of given statements, choose the most appropriate answer from the options given below</p>",
    "options": [
      "Statement I is incorrect but Statement II is correct.",
      "Statement $$\\mathrm{I}$$ is correct but Statement II is incorrect.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are correct.",
      "Both Statement I and Statement II are incorrect."
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "Statement $$\\mathrm{I}$$ is correct but Statement II is incorrect."
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lscpdeey",
    "question": "<p>A bullet is fired into a fixed target looses one third of its velocity after travelling $$4 \\mathrm{~cm}$$. It penetrates further $$\\mathrm{D} \\times 10^{-3} \\mathrm{~m}$$ before coming to rest. The value of $$\\mathrm{D}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "23",
      "32",
      "42",
      "52"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "32"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1whjx",
    "question": "<p>The potential energy function (in $$J$$ ) of a particle in a region of space is given as $$U=\\left(2 x^2+3 y^3+2 z\\right)$$. Here $$x, y$$ and $$z$$ are in meter. The magnitude of $$x$$-component of force (in $$N$$ ) acting on the particle at point $$P(1,2,3) \\mathrm{m}$$ is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "4",
      "2",
      "8",
      "6"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "4"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv0vxlra",
    "question": "<p>If a rubber ball falls from a height $$h$$ and rebounds upto the height of $$h / 2$$. The percentage loss of total energy of the initial system as well as velocity ball before it strikes the ground, respectively, are :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$50 \\%, \\sqrt{2 \\mathrm{gh}}$$\n",
      "$$50 \\%, \\sqrt{\\mathrm{gh}}$$\n",
      "$$50 \\%, \\sqrt{\\frac{\\text { gh }}{2}}$$\n",
      "$$40 \\%, \\sqrt{2 \\mathrm{gh}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$50 \\%, \\sqrt{2 \\mathrm{gh}}$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvb29egr",
    "question": "<p>When kinetic energy of a body becomes 36 times of its original value, the percentage increase in the momentum of the body will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "60%",
      "500%",
      "6%",
      "600%"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "500%"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc586c4",
    "question": "<p>A bullet of mass $$50 \\mathrm{~g}$$ is fired with a speed $$100 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$ on a plywood and emerges with $$40 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}$$. The percentage loss of kinetic energy is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$44 \\%$$\n",
      "$$16 \\%$$\n",
      "$$84 \\%$$\n",
      "$$32 \\%$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "$$84 \\%$$\n"
  },
  {
    "id": "lvc5837p",
    "question": "<p>Four particles $$A, B, C, D$$ of mass $$\\frac{m}{2}, m, 2 m, 4 m$$, have same momentum, respectively. The particle with maximum kinetic energy is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "B",
      "C",
      "D",
      "A"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "energy",
    "solution": "A"
  },
  {
    "id": "snApUKYYNFM6rlsV",
    "question": "A body is moved along a straight line by a machine delivering a constant power. The distance moved by the body in time $$'t'$$ is proportional to ",
    "options": [
      "$${t^{3/4}}$$ ",
      "$${t^{3/2}}$$",
      "$${t^{1/4}}$$",
      "$${t^{1/2}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "$${t^{3/2}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "Y3CQEw8N0K3fp45s",
    "question": "A body of mass $$' m ',$$ acceleration uniformly from rest to $$'{v_1}'$$ in time $${T}$$. The instantaneous power delivered to the body as a function of time is given by",
    "options": [
      "$${{m{v_1}{t^2}} \\over {{T}}}$$ ",
      "$${{mv_1^2t} \\over {T^2}}$$ ",
      "$${{m{v_1}t} \\over {{T}}}$$ ",
      "$${{mv_1^2t} \\over {{T}}}$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "$${{mv_1^2t} \\over {T^2}}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Myw55b51DroWYrEJ",
    "question": "A body of mass $$m$$ is accelerated uniformly from rest to a speed $$v$$ in a time $$T.$$ The instantaneous power delivered to the body as a function of time is given by ",
    "options": [
      "$${{m{v^2}} \\over {{T^2}}}.{t^2}$$ ",
      "$${{m{v^2}} \\over {{T^2}}}.t$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}{{m{v^2}} \\over {{T^2}}}.{t^2}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}{{m{v^2}} \\over {{T^2}}}.t$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "$${{m{v^2}} \\over {{T^2}}}.t$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "NdfqSU4oZXegcvY0up9KF",
    "question": "A car of weight W is on an inclined road that rises by 100 m over a distance of 1 km\nand applies a constant frictional force $${W \\over 20}$$ on the car. While moving uphill on the road at a speed of 10 ms<sup>−1</sup>, the car needs power P. If it needs power $${p \\over 2}$$ while moving downhill at speed v then value of $$\\upsilon $$ is :",
    "options": [
      "20 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "15 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "10 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>",
      "5 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "15 ms<sup>$$-$$1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "iNdJxfqhO7oytfXaS9uIX",
    "question": "A particle of mass M is moving in a circle of fixed radius R in such a way that its centripetal acceleration at time t is given by n<sup>2</sup> R t<sup>2</sup> where n is a constant. The power delivered to the particle by the force acting on it, is :",
    "options": [
      "M n<sup>2</sup> R<sup>2</sup> t",
      "M n R<sup>2</sup> t",
      "M n R<sup>2</sup> t<sup>2</sup>",
      "$${1 \\over 2}$$ M n<sup>2</sup> R<sup>2</sup> t<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "M n<sup>2</sup> R<sup>2</sup> t"
  },
  {
    "id": "ixRSOh2PSaBUBL6v437k9k2k5dgg4fj",
    "question": "A 60 HP electric motor lifts an elevator having a maximum total load capacity of 2000 kg. If the frictional force on the elevator is 4000 N, the speed of the elevator at full load is close to : <br/>(1 HP = 746 W, g = 10 ms<sup>-2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "1.5 ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "1.7 ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "2.0 ms<sup>-1</sup>",
      "1.9 ms<sup>-1</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "1.9 ms<sup>-1</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "rgQmR27Xkry0uATPBi7k9k2k5f7e86q",
    "question": "An elevator in a building can carry a maximum of 10 persons, with the average mass of each\nperson being 68 kg, The mass of the elevator itself is 920 kg and it moves with a constant speed\nof 3 m/s. The frictional force opposing the motion is 6000 N. If the elevator is moving up with its\nfull capacity, the power delivered by the motor to the elevator (g = 10 m/s<sup>2</sup>) must be at least :",
    "options": [
      "48000 W",
      "62360 W",
      "56300 W",
      "66000 W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "66000 W"
  },
  {
    "id": "vr8ojlJgMPfgGFa8TV1kmlho355",
    "question": "A constant power delivering machine has towed a box, which was initially at rest, along a horizontal straight line. The distance moved by the box in time 't' is proportional to :-",
    "options": [
      "t<sup>2/3</sup>",
      "t<sup>3/2</sup>",
      "t",
      "t<sup>1/2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "t<sup>3/2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krqd8z4h",
    "question": "A body at rest is moved along a horizontal straight line by a machine delivering a constant power. The distance moved by the body in time 't' is proportional to :",
    "options": [
      "$${t^{{3 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${t^{{1 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${t^{{1 \\over 4}}}$$",
      "$${t^{{3 \\over 4}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "$${t^{{3 \\over 2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ks1943x1",
    "question": "An automobile of mass 'm' accelerates starting from origin and initially at rest, while the engine supplies constant power P. The position is given as a function of time by :",
    "options": [
      "$${\\left( {{{9P} \\over {8m}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}{t^{{3 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{8P} \\over {9m}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}{t^{{2 \\over 3}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{9m} \\over {8P}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}{t^{{3 \\over 2}}}$$",
      "$${\\left( {{{8P} \\over {9m}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}{t^{{3 \\over 2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "$${\\left( {{{8P} \\over {9m}}} \\right)^{{1 \\over 2}}}{t^{{3 \\over 2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l6jevuii",
    "question": "<p>Sand is being dropped from a stationary dropper at a rate of $$0.5 \\,\\mathrm{kgs}^{-1}$$ on a conveyor belt moving with a velocity of $$5 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$. The power needed to keep the belt moving with the same velocity will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "1.25 W",
      "2.5 W",
      "6.25 W",
      "12.5 W"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "12.5 W"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgq2tf2b",
    "question": "<p>The ratio of powers of two motors is $$\\frac{3 \\sqrt{x}}{\\sqrt{x}+1}$$, that are capable of raising $$300 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ water in 5 minutes and $$50 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ water in 2 minutes respectively from a well of $$100 \\mathrm{~m}$$ deep. The value of $$x$$ will be</p>",
    "options": [
      "16",
      "4",
      "2",
      "2.4"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "16"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsd7mk0c",
    "question": "<p>A body of mass $$2 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ begins to move under the action of a time dependent force given by $$\\vec{F}=\\left(6 t \\hat{i}+6 t^2 \\hat{j}\\right) N$$. The power developed by the force at the time $$t$$ is given by:</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\left(3 t^3+6 t^5\\right) W$$\n",
      "$$\\left(9 t^5+6 t^3\\right) W$$\n",
      "$$\\left(6 t^4+9 t^5\\right) W$$\n",
      "$$\\left(9 t^3+6 t^5\\right) W$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "$$\\left(9 t^3+6 t^5\\right) W$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "lv9s20qb",
    "question": "<p>A body is moving unidirectionally under the influence of a constant power source. Its displacement in time t is proportional to :</p>",
    "options": [
      "t<sup>2/3</sup>",
      "t<sup>3/2</sup>",
      "t",
      "t<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "power",
    "solution": "t<sup>3/2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "yPW3Q3i4SocLyGVy",
    "question": "A spring of force constant $$800$$ $$N/m$$ has an extension of $$5$$ $$cm.$$ The work done in extending it from $$5$$ $$cm$$ to $$15$$ $$cm$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$16J$$ ",
      "$$8J$$ ",
      "$$32J$$ ",
      "$$24J$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "$$8J$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "LPEk2w5DjjNtUsdy",
    "question": "A spring of spring constant $$5 \\times {10^3}\\,N/m$$ is stretched initially by $$5$$ $$cm$$ from the unstretched position. Then the work required to stretch it further by another $$5$$ $$cm$$ is ",
    "options": [
      "$$12.50$$ $$N$$-$$m$$ ",
      "$$18.75$$ $$N$$-$$m$$ ",
      "$$25.00$$ $$N$$-$$m$$ ",
      "$$625$$ $$N$$-$$m$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "$$18.75$$ $$N$$-$$m$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "5XDwclBfifQsjnml",
    "question": "A force $$\\overrightarrow F  = \\left( {5\\overrightarrow i  + 3\\overrightarrow j  + 2\\overrightarrow k } \\right)N$$ is applied over a particle which displaces it from its origin to the point $$\\overrightarrow r  = \\left( {2\\overrightarrow i  - \\overrightarrow j } \\right)m.$$ The work done on the particle in joules is ",
    "options": [
      "$$+10$$",
      "$$+7$$",
      "$$-7$$",
      "$$+13$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "$$+7$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "M83DLNrq3KVL75D3",
    "question": "When a rubber-band is stretched by a distance $$x$$, it exerts restoring force of magnitude $$F = ax + b{x^2}$$ where $$a$$ and $$b$$ are constants. The work done in stretching the unstretched rubber-band by $$L$$ is : ",
    "options": [
      "$$a{L^2} + b{L^3}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}\\left( {a{L^2} + b{L^3}} \\right)$$ ",
      "$${{a{L^2}} \\over 2} + {{b{L^3}} \\over 3}$$ ",
      "$${1 \\over 2}\\left( {{{a{L^2}} \\over 2} + {{b{L^3}} \\over 3}} \\right)$$ "
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "$${{a{L^2}} \\over 2} + {{b{L^3}} \\over 3}$$ "
  },
  {
    "id": "Qyl0DPTtmSRlKUjMmxCnJ",
    "question": "A body of mass m starts moving from rest along x-axis so that its velocity varies as $$\\upsilon  = a\\sqrt s $$ where a is a constant and s is the distance covered by the body. The total work done by all the forces acting on the body in the first t seconds after the start of the motion is :",
    "options": [
      "$${1 \\over 8}\\,$$ m a<sup>4</sup> t<sup>2</sup>",
      "8 m a<sup>4</sup> t<sup>2</sup>",
      "4 m a<sup>4</sup> t<sup>2</sup>",
      "$${1 \\over 4}\\,$$ m a<sup>4</sup> t<sup>2</sup>"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "$${1 \\over 8}\\,$$ m a<sup>4</sup> t<sup>2</sup>"
  },
  {
    "id": "dTeBzFNTsV1tfh1F4RZ9l",
    "question": "A uniform cable of mass 'M' and length 'L' is\nplaced on a horizontal surface such that its (1/n)<sup>th</sup>\npart is hanging below the edge of the\nsurface. To lift the hanging part of the cable upto\nthe surface, the work done should be :",
    "options": [
      "$${{2MgL} \\over {{n^2}}}$$",
      "nMgL",
      "$${{MgL} \\over {2{n^2}}}$$",
      "$${{MgL} \\over {{n^2}}}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "$${{MgL} \\over {2{n^2}}}$$"
  },
  {
    "id": "ZjHmqNwNiJbLX81qPwjgy2xukfahetcu",
    "question": "A person pushes a box on a rough horizontal plateform surface. He applies a force of 200 N over a\ndistance of 15 m. Thereafter, he gets progressively tired and his applied force reduces linearly with\ndistance to 100 N. The total distance through which the box has been moved is 30 m. What is the\nwork done by the person during the total movement of the box?",
    "options": [
      "5690 J",
      "5250 J",
      "2780 J",
      "3280 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "5250 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1krsu3bwl",
    "question": "A porter lifts a heavy suitcase of mass 80 kg and at the destination lowers it down by a distance of 80 cm with a constant velocity. Calculate the work done by the porter in lowering the suitcase.<br/><br/>(take g = 9.8 ms<sup>$$-$$2</sup>)",
    "options": [
      "+627.2 J",
      "$$-$$62720.0 J",
      "$$-$$627.2 J",
      "784.0 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "$$-$$627.2 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ktmn70rw",
    "question": "A body of mass 'm' dropped from a height 'h' reaches the ground with a speed of 0.8$$\\sqrt {gh} $$. The value of workdone by the air-friction is :",
    "options": [
      "$$-$$0.68 mgh",
      "mgh",
      "1.64 mgh",
      "0.64 mgh"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 0,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "$$-$$0.68 mgh"
  },
  {
    "id": "1l5c3r2k8",
    "question": "<p>A particle experiences a variable force $$\\overrightarrow F  = \\left( {4x\\widehat i + 3{y^2}\\widehat j} \\right)$$ in a horizontal x-y plane. Assume distance in meters and force is newton. If the particle moves from point (1, 2) to point (2, 3) in the x-y plane, then Kinetic Energy changes by :</p>",
    "options": [
      "50.0 J",
      "12.5 J",
      "25.0 J",
      "0 J"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "25.0 J"
  },
  {
    "id": "1ldsa408f",
    "question": "<p>Identify the correct statements from the following :</p>\n<p>A. Work done by a man in lifting a bucket out of a well by means of a rope tied to the bucket is negative.</p>\n<p>B. Work done by gravitational force in lifting a bucket out of a well by a rope tied to the bucket is negative.</p>\n<p>C. Work done by friction on a body sliding down an inclined plane is positive.</p>\n<p>D. Work done by an applied force on a body moving on a rough horizontal plane with uniform velocity is zero.</p>\n<p>E. Work done by the air resistance on an oscillating pendulum is negative.</p>\n<p>Choose the correct answer from the options given below :</p>",
    "options": [
      "A and C only",
      "B and D only",
      "B, D and E only",
      "B and E only"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "B and E only"
  },
  {
    "id": "1lgyqdov2",
    "question": "<p>A bullet of mass $$0.1 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ moving horizontally with speed $$400 \\mathrm{~ms}^{-1}$$ hits a wooden block of mass $$3.9 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ kept on a horizontal rough surface. The bullet gets embedded into the block and moves $$20 \\mathrm{~m}$$ before coming to rest. The coefficient of friction between the block and the surface is __________.</p>\n<p>(Given $$g=10 \\mathrm{~m} / \\mathrm{s}^{2}$$ )</p>",
    "options": [
      "0.65",
      "0.25",
      "0.50",
      "0.90"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 1,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "0.25"
  },
  {
    "id": "jaoe38c1lsf1fzjr",
    "question": "<p>A block of mass $$100 \\mathrm{~kg}$$ slides over a distance of $$10 \\mathrm{~m}$$ on a horizontal surface. If the co-efficient of friction between the surfaces is 0.4, then the work done against friction $$(\\operatorname{in} J$$) is :</p>",
    "options": [
      "3900",
      "4500",
      "4200",
      "4000"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 3,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "4000"
  },
  {
    "id": "luyit9wg",
    "question": "<p>A particle of mass $$m$$ moves on a straight line with its velocity increasing with distance according to the equation $$v=\\alpha \\sqrt{x}$$, where $$\\alpha$$ is a constant. The total work done by all the forces applied on the particle during its displacement from $$x=0$$ to $$x=\\mathrm{d}$$, will be :</p>",
    "options": [
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{m}}{2 \\alpha^2 \\mathrm{~d}}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{md}}{2 \\alpha^2}$$\n",
      "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{m} \\alpha^2 \\mathrm{~d}}{2}$$\n",
      "$$2 \\mathrm{~m} \\alpha^2 \\mathrm{~d}$$"
    ],
    "answerIndex": 2,
    "chapter": "work-power-and-energy",
    "topic": "work",
    "solution": "$$\\frac{\\mathrm{m} \\alpha^2 \\mathrm{~d}}{2}$$\n"
  }
]